<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35925788</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2326-5108</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>20</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Season>Jul-Aug</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Health security</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Health Secur</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Infectious Disease Underreporting Is Predicted by Country-Level Preparedness, Politics, and Pathogen Severity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>331</StartPage><EndPage>338</EndPage><MedlinePgn>331-338</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1089/hs.2021.0197</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Underreporting of infectious diseases is a pervasive challenge in public health that has emerged as a central issue in characterizing the dynamics of the COVID-19 pandemic. Infectious diseases are underreported for a range of reasons, including mild or asymptomatic infections, weak public health infrastructure, and government censorship. In this study, we investigated factors associated with cross-country and cross-pathogen variation in reporting. We performed a literature search to collect estimates of empirical reporting rates, calculated as the number of cases reported divided by the estimated number of true cases. This literature search yielded a dataset of reporting rates for 32 pathogens, representing 52 countries. We combined epidemiological and social science theory to identify factors specific to pathogens, country health systems, and politics that could influence empirical reporting rates. We performed generalized linear regression to test the relationship between the pathogen- and country-specific factors that we hypothesized could influence reporting rates, and the reporting rate estimates that we collected in our literature search. Pathogen- and country-specific factors were predictive of reporting rates. Deadlier pathogens and sexually transmitted diseases were more likely to be reported. Country epidemic preparedness was positively associated with reporting completeness, while countries with high levels of media bias in favor of incumbent governments were less likely to report infectious disease cases. Underreporting is a complex phenomenon that is driven by factors specific to pathogens, country health systems, and politics. In this study, we identified specific and measurable components of these broader factors that influence pathogen- and country-specific reporting rates and used model selection techniques to build a model that can guide efforts to diagnose, characterize, and reduce underreporting. Furthermore, this model can characterize uncertainty and correct for bias in reported infectious disease statistics, particularly when outbreak-specific empirical estimates of underreporting are unavailable. More precise estimates can inform control policies and improve the accuracy of infectious disease models.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meadows</LastName><ForeName>Amanda J</ForeName><Initials>AJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Amanda J. Meadows, PhD, is a Data Scientist/Modeler, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oppenheim</LastName><ForeName>Ben</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ben Oppenheim, PhD, MA, MSc, is Vice President of Product, Policy, and Partnerships, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Guerrero</LastName><ForeName>Jaclyn</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Jaclyn Guerrero, MPH, is an Advisor, Epidemiology Products, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ash</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Benjamin Ash, MS, is Manager of NRT Data, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Badker</LastName><ForeName>Rinette</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Rinette Badker, MSc, is a Senior Epidemic Analyst, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lam</LastName><ForeName>Cathine K</ForeName><Initials>CK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Cathine K. Lam, ACAS, is a Data Scientist/Actuary, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pardee</LastName><ForeName>Chris</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Chris Pardee, MS, is Senior Manager of Data Acquisition, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ngoon</LastName><ForeName>Christopher</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Christopher Ngoon, MS, is a Senior Data Analyst, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Savage</LastName><ForeName>Patrick T</ForeName><Initials>PT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Patrick T. Savage is a Data Quality Analyst, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sridharan</LastName><ForeName>Vikram</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Vikram Sridharan, MS, is a Senior Data Scientist and Technical Product Manager, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madhav</LastName><ForeName>Nita K</ForeName><Initials>NK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nita K. Madhav, MSPH, is Chief Executive Officer, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stephenson</LastName><ForeName>Nicole</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nicole Stephenson, DVM, MPVM, PhD, is Senior Director of Data Science and Modeling, Metabiota, San Francisco, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Health Secur</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101654694</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2326-5094</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Communicable Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011057" MajorTopicYN="N">Politics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infectious disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health preparedness/response</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Reporting bias</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Underreporting</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>52</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35925788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10818036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/hs.2021.0197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Gibbons CL, Mangen M-JJ, Plass D, et al. ; Burden of Communicable Diseases in Europe consortium. Measuring underreporting and under-ascertainment in infectious disease datasets: a comparison of methods. BMC Public Health. 2014;14:147.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4015559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24517715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Undurraga EA, Halasa YA, Shepard DS. Use of expansion factors to estimate the burden of dengue in Southeast Asia: a systematic analysis. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2013;7(2):e2056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3578761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23437407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyle TJ, Glynn MK, Groseclose SL. Completeness of notifiable infectious disease reporting in the United States: an analytical literature review. Am J Epidemiol. 2002;155(9):866-874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11978592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalziel BD, Lau MSY, Tiffany A, et al. Unreported cases in the 2014-2016 Ebola epidemic: spatiotemporal variation, and implications for estimating transmission. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2018;12(1):e0006161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5806896</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29357363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamado KM, Streftaris G, Zachary S. Modelling under-reporting in epidemics. J Math Biol. 2014;69(3):737-765.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23942791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silk BJ, Berkelman RL. A review of strategies for enhancing the completeness of notifiable disease reporting: J Public Health Manag Pract. 2005;11(3):191-200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15829831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan EH, Brewer TF, Madoff LC, et al. Global capacity for emerging infectious disease detection. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2010;107(50):21701-21706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3003006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21115835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oppenheim B, Gallivan M, Madhav NK, et al. Assessing global preparedness for the next pandemic: development and application of an Epidemic Preparedness Index. BMJ Glob Health. 2019;4(1):e001157.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6352812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30775006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coppedge M, Gerring J, Knutsen CH, et al. V-Dem Dataset. 2020. 10.23696/VDEMDS20</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.23696/VDEMDS20</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee ST, Kim HS. Nation branding in the COVID-19 era: South Korea's pandemic public diplomacy. Place Brand Public Dipl. 2021;17(4):382-396.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Wike R, Fetterolf J, Mordecai M.. 
U.S. image plummets internationally as most say country has handled Coronavirus badly. Pew Research Center. Published September 15, 2020. Accessed June
23, 2022. https://www.pewresearch.org/global/2020/09/15/us-image-plummets-internationally-as-most-say-country-has-handled-coronavirus-badly/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Oppenheim B, Serhiyenko V, Guerrero J, et al. 
System for determining public sentiment towards pathogens. US 2019 370 834A1, 2019. Patent pending. Accessed July
29, 2022. https://patents.google.com/patent/US20190370834A1/en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Worsnop CZ. Concealing disease: trade and travel barriers and the timeliness of outbreak reporting. Int Stud Perspect. 2019;20(4):344-372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7149472</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38626279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Guriev S, Treisman D. How Modern Dictators Survive: An Informational Theory of the New Authoritarianism. NBER working paper series No. 21136. Cambridge, MA: National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER); 2015. Accessed June
23, 2022. https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w21136/w21136.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Barto&#x144; K. MuMIn: Multi-Model Inference. R package version 1.46.0. 2022. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=MuMIn</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Maechler M, Rousseeuw P, Croux C, et al. 
robustbase: Basic Robust Statistics R package version 0.95-0 2022. http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=robustbase</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rechel B, McKee M. The effects of dictatorship on health: the case of Turkmenistan. BMC Med. 2007;5:21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1948003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17663794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsevat DG, Wiesenfeld HC, Parks C, Peipert JF. Sexually transmitted diseases and infertility. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2017;216(1):1-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5193130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28007229</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oppenheim B, Guerrero J, Euren J, et al. Quantifying preparedness for emerging infectious diseases: a new methodology to assess health security at the subnational level in African countries. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;101(suppl 1):S266.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>