<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">33963235</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Tracking the time course of reproduction number and lockdown's effect on human behaviour during SARS-CoV-2 epidemic: nonparametric estimation.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>9772</StartPage><MedlinePgn>9772</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">9772</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-021-89014-9</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Understanding the SARS-CoV-2 dynamics has been subject of intense research in the last months. In particular, accurate modeling of lockdown effects on human behaviour and epidemic evolution is a key issue in order e.g. to inform health-care decisions on emergency management. In this regard, the compartmental and spatial models so far proposed use parametric descriptions of the contact rate, often assuming a time-invariant effect of the lockdown. In this paper we show that these assumptions may lead to erroneous evaluations on the ongoing pandemic. Thus, we develop a new class of nonparametric compartmental models able to describe how the impact of the lockdown varies in time. Our estimation strategy does not require significant Bayes prior information and exploits regularization theory. Hospitalized data are mapped into an infinite-dimensional space, hence obtaining a function which takes into account also how social distancing measures and people's growing awareness of infection's risk evolves as time progresses. This also permits to reconstruct a continuous-time profile of SARS-CoV-2 reproduction number with a resolution never reached before in the literature. When applied to data collected in Lombardy, the most affected Italian region, our model illustrates how people behaviour changed during the restrictions and its importance to contain the epidemic. Results also indicate that, at the end of the lockdown, around [Formula: see text] of people in Lombardy and [Formula: see text] in Italy was affected by SARS-CoV-2, with the fatality rate being 1.14%. Then, we discuss how the situation evolved after the end of the lockdown showing that the reproduction number dangerously increased in the summer, due to holiday relax, reaching values larger than one on August 1, 2020. Finally, we also document how Italy faced the second wave of infection in the last part of 2020. Since several countries still observe a growing epidemic and others could be subject to other waves, the proposed reproduction number tracking methodology can be of great help to health care authorities to prevent SARS-CoV-2 diffusion or to assess the impact of lockdown restrictions on human behaviour to contain the spread.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pillonetto</LastName><ForeName>G</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Information Engineering, University of Padova, Padova, Italy. giapi@dei.unipd.it.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bisiacco</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Information Engineering, University of Padova, Padova, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pal&#xf9;</LastName><ForeName>G</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6310-5147</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Molecular Medicine, Professor Emeritus, University of Padova, Padova, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Member of the Scientific Technical Committee, Italian Ministry of Health, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cobelli</LastName><ForeName>C</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Member of Consiglio Superiore di Sanit&#xe0;, Italian Ministry of Health, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dipartimento di Salute della Donna e del Bambino, Professor Emeritus, University of Padova, Padova, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001499" MajorTopicYN="N">Bayes Theorem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003140" MajorTopicYN="N">Communicable Disease Control</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062665" MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiological Monitoring</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007558" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Italy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000085762" MajorTopicYN="N">Physical Distancing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012621" MajorTopicYN="N">Seasons</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013997" MajorTopicYN="N">Time Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Authors have no competing interests as defined by Nature Research, or other interests that might be perceived to influence the results and/or discussion reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33963235</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8105401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-89014-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-021-89014-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zhou F, Yu T, Du R, Fan G, Liu Z, Xiang J, Wang Y, Song B, Gu X, Guan L, Wei Y, Li H, Wu X, Xu J, Tu S, Zhang Y, Chen H, Cao B. Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with covid-19 in wuhan, china: a retrospective cohort study. The Lancet. 2020;395:1054&#x2013;1062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32171076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) outbreak in china: summary of a report of 72314 cases from the chinese center for disease control and prevention. JAMA. 2020;323:1239&#x2013;1242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guan W, Ni Z, Hu Y, Liang W, Ou C, He J, Liu L, Shan H, Lei C, Hui DSC, Du B, Li L, Zeng G, Yuen K, Chen R, Tang C, Wang T, Chen P, Xiang J, Li S, Wang J, Liang Z, Peng Y, Wei L, Liu Y, Hu Y, Peng P, Wang J, Liu J, Chen Z, Li G, Zheng Z, Qiu S, Luo J, Ye C, Zhu S, Zhong N. Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China. New England J. Med. 2020;382(18):1708&#x2013;1720.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7092819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32109013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velavan TP, Meyer CG. The covid-19 epidemic. Trop. Med. Int. Health. 2020;25:278&#x2013;280.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7169770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32052514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wittkowski, K. M. The first three months of the covid-19 epidemic: Epidemiological evidence for two separate strains of sars-cov-2 viruses spreading and implications for prevention strategies. <i>medRxiv</i>, 2020. 10.1101/2020.03.28.20036715.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lavezzo, E., Franchin, E. &amp; Ciavarella E. Suppression of a sars-cov-2 outbreak in the italian municipality of Vo&#x2019;. <i>Nature</i>, (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7618354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32604404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertozzi A, Franco E, Mohler G, Short MB, Sledge D. The challenges of modeling and forecasting the spread of covid-19. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2020;117(29):16732&#x2013;16738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7382213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32616574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kernack WO, McKendrick AG. A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics. Proc. Royal Soc. Lond. Ser. A. 1927;115(772):700&#x2013;721.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samanta S, Chattopadhyay J. Effect of awareness program in disease outbreak: a slow fast dynamics. Appl. Math. Comput. 2014;237:98&#x2013;109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu D, Lin Q, Chiu APY, He D. Effects of reactive social distancing on the 1918 influenza pandemic. PloS one. 2017;12(7):6872&#x2013;6877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5507503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28704460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Funk S, Gilad E, Watkins C, Jansen V. The spread of awareness and its impact on epidemic outbreaks. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2009;106(16):6872&#x2013;6877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2672559</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19332788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kiss IZ, Cassell J, Recker M, Simon PL. The impact of information transmission on epidemic outbreaks. Math. Biosci. 2010;225(1):1&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19948177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buonomo B, d&#x2019;Onofrio A, Lacitignola D. Global stability of an sir epidemic model with information dependent vaccination. Math. Biosci. 2008;216(1):9&#x2013;16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18725233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casella, F. Can the covid-19 epidemic be controlled on the basis of daily test reports? <i>arXiv</i>, (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Qianying, Zhao Shi, Gao Daozhou, Lou Yijun, Yang Shu, Musa Salihu S, Wang Maggie H, Cai Yongli, Wang Weiming, Yang Lin, He Daihai. A conceptual model for the coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) outbreak in wuhan, china with individual reaction and governmental action. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 2020;93:211&#x2013;216.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32145465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anastassopoulou C, Russo L, Tsakris A, Siettos C. Data-based analysis, modelling and forecasting of the covid-19 outbreak. PLoS. 2020;15:e0230405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7108749</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32231374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weitz, Joshua S. <i>et al.</i> Modeling shield immunity to reduce covid-19 epidemic spread. <i>Nature Medicine</i> (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8272982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32382154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Xia C, Chen Z, Chen G. Epidemic propagation with positive and negative preventive information in multiplex networks. IEEE Trans. Cybern. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31940584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giordano, G. <i>et al.</i> Modelling the covid-19 epidemic and implementation of population-wide interventions in Italy. <i>Nat. Med.</i> 1&#x2013;6 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7175834</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32322102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gumel AB, Ruan S, Day T, Watmough J, Brauer F, van den Driessche P, Gabrielson D, Bowman C, Alexander ME, Ardal S, Wu J, Sahai BM. Modelling strategies for controlling sars outbreak. Proc. R. Soc. Lond. 2004;271:2223&#x2013;2232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1691853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15539347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mari L, Casagrandi R, Bertuzzo E, Rinaldo A, Gatto M. Floquet theory for seasonal environmental forcing of spatially explicit waterborne epidemics. Theor. Ecol. 2014;7(4):351&#x2013;365.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isham V, Mollison D, Trapman P, Riley S, Eames K. Five challenges for spatial epidemic models. Epidemics. 2015;10(3):68&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4383807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25843387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertuzzo E, Casagrandi R, Gatto M, Rodriguez-Iturbe I, Rinaldo A. On spatially explicit models of cholera epidemics. J. Royal Soc. Interface. 2010;7:321&#x2013;333.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2842613</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19605400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mari L, Casagrandi R, Bertuzzo E, Rinaldo A, Gatto M. Conditions for transient epidemics of waterborne disease in spatially explicit systems. Royal Soc. Open Sci. 2019;6(5):181517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6549988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31218018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Exeter, D. J., Adams, B., O&#x2019;Sullivan, D. &amp; Gahegan, M. Spatially explicit models for exploring covid-19 lockdown strategies. <i>Trans. GIS</i> 1&#x2013;34 (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7283721</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32837240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gatto M, Bertuzzo E, Mari L, Miccoli S, Carraro L, Casagrandi R, Rinaldo A. Spread and dynamics of the covid-19 epidemic in italy: effects of emergency containment measures. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2020;117(19):10484&#x2013;10491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7229754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32327608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeling MJ, Eames KT. Networks and epidemic models. J. Royal Soc. Interface. 2005;2(4):295&#x2013;307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1578276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16849187</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastor-Satorras, R., Castellano, C., Van Mieghem, P. &amp; Vespignani, A. Epidemic processes in complex networks. <i>Rev. Modern Phys.</i><b>87</b>(925), (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pellis L, Ball F, Bansal S, Eames K, House T, Isham V, Trapman P. Eight challenges for network epidemic model. Epidemics. 2015;10:58&#x2013;62.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25843385</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaxman, S., Mishra, S., Gandy, A., Unwin, H., Coupland, H., Mellan, T., Zhu, H., Berah, T., Eaton, J., Guzman, P., Schmit, N., Callizo, L. Imperial College COVID-19 Response Team, C.&#xa0;Whittaker, P.&#xa0;Winskill, X.&#xa0;Xi, A.&#xa0;Ghani, C.&#xa0;Donnelly, S.&#xa0;Riley, L.&#xa0;Okell, M.&#xa0;Vollmer, N.&#xa0;Ferguson, and S.&#xa0;Bhatt. Estimating the number of infections and the impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions on COVID-19 in European countries. <i>Nature</i>, (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Teunis P. Different epidemic curves for severe acute respiratory syndrome reveal similar impacts of control measures. Am. J. Epidemiol. 2004;160(6):509&#x2013;516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7110200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15353409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministero della Salute (Italian Ministry&#xa0;of Health). Covid-19 data. https://github.com/pcm-dpc/COVID-19, (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertero M. Linear inverse and ill-posed problems. Adv. Electron. Electron Phys. 1989;75:1&#x2013;120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pillonetto, G., Dinuzzo, F., Chen, T., De Nicolao, G. &amp; Ljung, L. Kernel methods in system identification, machine learning and function estimation: A survey. <i>Automatica</i><b>50</b>, (2014).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisiacco, M. &amp; Pillonetto, G. On the mathematical foundations of stable RKHSs. <i>Automatica</i> (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poggio T, Girosi F. Networks for approximation and learning. Proc. IEEE. 1990;78:1481&#x2013;1497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sch&#xf6;lkopf, B. &amp; Smola, A. J. <i>Learning with Kernels: Support Vector Machines, Regularization, Optimization, and Beyond</i>. (Adaptive Computation and Machine Learning). MIT Press, (2001).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilks WR, Richardson S, Spiegelhalter DJ. Markov chain Monte Carlo in Practice. London: Chapman and Hall; 1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valenti, L., Bergna, A., Pelusi, S., Facciotti, F., Lai, A., Tarkowski, M., Berzuini, A., Caprioli, F., Santoro, L., Baselli, G., Della Ventura, C., Erba, E., Bosari, S., Galli, M., Zehender, G. &amp; Prati, D. Sars-cov-2 seroprevalence trends in healthy blood donors during the covid-19 milan outbreak. <i>medRxiv</i>, (2020). 10.1101/2020.05.11.20098442.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>La&#xa0;Stampa&#xa0;(Italian newspaper). Coronavirus, Castiglione d&#x2019;Adda is a case study: 70<mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:math> of blood donors tested positive. https://www.lastampa.it/topnews/primo-piano/2020/04/02/news, (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>La&#xa0;Repubblica&#xa0;(Italian newspaper). Coronavirus, antibodies in more than 1.4 million of italian people. https://www.repubblica.it/cronaca/2020/08/03/news, (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Long, Q. &amp; Tang, X. et al. Clinical and immunological assessment of asymptomatic sars-cov-2 infections. <i>Nat. Med.</i>, (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32555424</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaynes ET. On the rationale of maximum-entropy methods. Proc. IEEE. 1982;70:939&#x2013;952.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papoulis A, Pillai SU. Probability of random variables and stochastic processes. New York: McGraw Hill; 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plebani, M., Padoan, A., Fedeli, U., Schievano, E., Vecchiato, E., Lippi, G., Lo Cascio, G., Porru, S. &amp; Pal&#xf9;, G. Sars-cov-2 serosurvey in health care workers of the veneto region. <i>Clin. Chem. Lab. Med. (CCLM)</i>, (2020).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32845861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krammer F, Simon V. Serology assays to manage covid-19. Science. 2020;368(6495):1060&#x2013;1061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32414781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johns Hopkins&#xa0;Center for Health&#xa0;Security. Serology testing for covid-19. https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/resources/COVID-19/COVID-19-fact-sheets, (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mallapaty, S. How deadly is the coronavirus? scientists are close to an answer. https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-01738-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32546810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saccomani MP, Audoly S, D&#x2019;Angio&#x2019; L. Parameter identifiability of nonlinear systems: the role of initial conditions. Automatica. 2003;39(4):619&#x2013;632.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aronszajn N. Theory of reproducing kernels. Trans. Am. Math. Soc. 1950;68:337&#x2013;404.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergman, S. <i>The Kernel Function and Conformal Mapping</i> (Mathematical Surveys and Monographs, AMS, 1950).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cucker F, Smale S. On the mathematical foundations of learning. Bullet. Am. Math. Soc. 2001;39:1&#x2013;49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pillonetto G, De Nicolao G. A new kernel-based approach for linear system identification. Automatica. 2010;46(1):81&#x2013;93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasmussen CE, Williams CKI. Gaussian processes for machine learning. Cambridge: The MIT Press; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pillonetto G. Solutions of nonlinear control and estimation problems in reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces: Existence and numerical determination. Automatica. 2008;44(8):2135&#x2013;2141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pillonetto G, Saccomani MP. Input estimation in nonlinear dynamic systems using differential algebra concepts. Automatica. 2006;42:2117&#x2013;2129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kass RE, Raftery AE. Bayes factors. J. Am. Statist. Assoc. 1995;90:773&#x2013;795.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>