<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">27744095</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2018</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1878-0067</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>17</Volume><PubDate><Year>2016</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Epidemics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Epidemics</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Estimating infectious disease transmission distances using the overall distribution of cases.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>10</StartPage><EndPage>18</EndPage><MedlinePgn>10-18</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.epidem.2016.10.001</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S1755-4365(16)30031-7</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The average spatial distance between transmission-linked cases is a fundamental property of infectious disease dispersal. However, the distance between a case and their infector is rarely measurable. Contact-tracing investigations are resource intensive or even impossible, particularly when only a subset of cases are detected. Here, we developed an approach that uses onset dates, the generation time distribution and location information to estimate the mean transmission distance. We tested our method using outbreak simulations. We then applied it to the 2001 foot-and-mouth outbreak in Cumbria, UK, and compared our results to contact-tracing activities. In simulations with a true mean distance of 106m, the average mean distance estimated was 109m when cases were fully observed (95% range of 71-142). Estimates remained consistent with the true mean distance when only five percent of cases were observed, (average estimate of 128m, 95% range 87-165). Estimates were robust to spatial heterogeneity in the underlying population. We estimated that both the mean and the standard deviation of the transmission distance during the 2001 foot-and-mouth outbreak was 8.9km (95% CI: 8.4km-9.7km). Contact-tracing activities found similar values of 6.3km (5.2km-7.4km) and 11.2km (9.5km-12.8km), respectively. We were also able to capture the drop in mean transmission distance over the course of the outbreak. Our approach is applicable across diseases, robust to under-reporting and can inform interventions and surveillance.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2016 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Salje</LastName><ForeName>Henrik</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, USA; Mathematical Modeling of Infectious Diseases Unit, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France; CNRS, URA3012, Paris 75015, France; Center of Bioinformatics, Biostatistics and Integrative Biology, Institut Pasteur, Paris 75015, France. Electronic address: hsalje@jhu.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cummings</LastName><ForeName>Derek A T</ForeName><Initials>DAT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, USA; Mathematical Modeling of Infectious Diseases Unit, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France; Department of Biology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA; Emerging Pathogens Institute, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lessler</LastName><ForeName>Justin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, USA; Department of Biology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI102939</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2016</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Epidemics</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101484711</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1878-0067</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016358" MajorTopicYN="N">Contact Tracing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018562" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Transmission, Infectious</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005536" MajorTopicYN="N">Foot-and-Mouth Disease</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006113" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United Kingdom</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Foot-and-mouth disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infectious disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Outbreaks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Transmission distance</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2016</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2016</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2016</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2016</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2018</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2016</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2017</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27744095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS822992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5159225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2016.10.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S1755-4365(16)30031-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Assiri A, McGeer A, Perl TM, Price CS, Rabeeah, Al AA, Cummings DAT, Alabdullatif ZN, Assad M, Almulhim A, Makhdoom H, Madani H, Alhakeem R, Al-Tawfiq JA, Cotten M, Watson SJ, Kellam P, Zumla AI, Memish ZA KSA MERS-CoV Investigation Team. Hospital outbreak of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus. N Engl J Med. 2013;369:407&#x2013;416. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1306742.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1306742</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4029105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23782161</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhoomiboonchoo P, Gibbons RV, Huang A, Yoon I-K, Buddhari D, Nisalak A, Chansatiporn N, Thipayamongkolgul M, Kalanarooj S, Endy T, Rothman AL, Srikiatkhachorn A, Green S, Mammen MP, Cummings DA, Salje H. The spatial dynamics of dengue virus in Kamphaeng Phet, Thailand. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2014;8:e3138. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0003138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003138</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4161352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25211127</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bovet P, Benhamou S. Spatial analysis of animals&#x2019; movements using a correlated random walk model. Journal of Theoretical Biology. 1988;131:419&#x2013;433. doi: 10.1016/S0022-5193(88)80038-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0022-5193(88)80038-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cleveland WS, Grosse E, Shyu WM. Local regression models. Statistical models in S 1992</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Codling EA, Plank MJ, Benhamou S. Random walk models in biology. J R Soc Interface. 2008;5:813&#x2013;834. doi: 10.1098/rsif.2008.0014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsif.2008.0014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2504494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18426776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cotten M, Watson SJ, Kellam P, Rabeeah, Al AA, Makhdoom HQ, Assiri A, Al-Tawfiq JA, Alhakeem RF, Madani H, AlRabiah FA, Hajjar SA, Al-nassir WN, Albarrak A, Flemban H, Balkhy HH, Alsubaie S, Palser AL, Gall A, Bashford-Rogers R, Rambaut A, Zumla AI, Memish ZA. Transmission and evolution of the Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus in Saudi Arabia: a descriptive genomic study. The Lancet. 2013;382:1993&#x2013;2002. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61887-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61887-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3898949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24055451</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies G. The foot and mouth disease (FMD) epidemic in the United Kingdom 2001. Comparative immunology. 2002;25:331&#x2013;343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12365809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faye O, Bo&#xeb;lle P-Y, Heleze E, Faye O, Loucoubar C, Magassouba N, Soropogui B, Keita S, Gakou T, Bah EHI, Koivogui L, Sall AA, Cauchemez S. Chains of transmission and control of Ebola virus disease in Conakry, Guinea, in 2014: an observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2015;15:320&#x2013;326. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(14)71075-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(14)71075-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4373532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25619149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson NM, Donnelly CA, Anderson RM. The foot-and-mouth epidemic in Great Britain: pattern of spread and impact of interventions. Science. 2001a;292:1155&#x2013;1160. doi: 10.1126/science.1061020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1061020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11303090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferguson NM, Donnelly CA, Anderson RM. Transmission intensity and impact of control policies on the foot and mouth epidemic in Great Britain. Nature. 2001b;413:542&#x2013;548. doi: 10.1038/35097116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/35097116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11586365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grabowski MK, Lessler J, Redd AD, Kagaayi J, Laeyendecker O, Ndyanabo A, Nelson MI, Cummings DAT, Bwanika JB, Mueller AC, Reynolds SJ, Munshaw S, Ray SC, Lutalo T, Manucci J, Tobian AAR, Chang LW, Beyrer C, Jennings JM, Nalugoda F, Serwadda D, Wawer MJ, Quinn TC, Gray RH, Gray RH. The Role of Viral Introductions in Sustaining Community-Based HIV Epidemics in Rural Uganda: Evidence from Spatial Clustering, Phylogenetics, and Egocentric Transmission Models. PLoS Med. 2014;11:e1001610&#x2013;e1001610. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1001610.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3942316</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24595023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haydon DT, Chase-Topping M, Shaw DJ, Matthews L, Friar JK, Wilesmith J, Woolhouse MEJ. The construction and analysis of epidemic trees with reference to the 2001 UK foot-and-mouth outbreak. Proc Biol Sci. 2003;270:121&#x2013;127. doi: 10.1098/rspb.2002.2191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rspb.2002.2191</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1691228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12590749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iles JC, Raghwani J, Harrison GLA, Pepin J, Djoko CF, Tamoufe U, LeBreton M, Schneider BS, Fair JN, Tshala FM, Kayembe PK, Muyembe JJ, Edidi-Basepeo S, Wolfe ND, Simmonds P, Klenerman P, Pybus OG. Phylogeography and epidemic history of hepatitis C virus genotype 4 in Africa. Virology. 2014:464&#x2013;465. 233&#x2013;243. doi: 10.1016/j.virol.2014.07.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2014.07.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4162651</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25105489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kareiva PM, Shigesada N. Analyzing Insect Movement as a Correlated Random Walk. Oecologia. 1983;56:234&#x2013;238.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28310199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeling MJ, Brooks SP, Gilligan CA. Using conservation of pattern to estimate spatial parameters from a single snapshot. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2004;101:9155&#x2013;9160. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0400335101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.0400335101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC428489</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15184669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeling MJ, Woolhouse ME, Shaw DJ, Matthews L, Chase-Topping M, Haydon DT, Cornell SJ, Kappey J, Wilesmith J, Grenfell BT. Dynamics of the 2001 UK foot and mouth epidemic: stochastic dispersal in a heterogeneous landscape. Science. 2001;294:813&#x2013;817. doi: 10.1126/science.1065973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1065973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11679661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin H, Shin S, Blaya JA, Zhang Z, Cegielski P, Contreras C, Asencios L, Bonilla C, Bayona J, Paciorek CJ, Cohen T. Assessing spatiotemporal patterns of multidrug-resistant and drug-sensitive tuberculosis in a South American setting. Epidemiol Infect. 2011;139:1784&#x2013;1793. doi: 10.1017/S0950268810002797.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268810002797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3153578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21205434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mat&#xe9;rn B. Lecture Notes in Statistics. Vol. 36. Springer; 1986. Spatial variation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison AC, Getis A, Santiago M, Rigau-Perez JG, Reiter P. Exploratory space-time analysis of reported dengue cases during an outbreak in Florida, Puerto Rico 1991-1992. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 1998;58:287&#x2013;298.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9546405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathan R, Muller-Landau H. Spatial patterns of seed dispersal, their determinants and consequences for recruitment. Trends Ecol Evol (Amst) 2000;15:278&#x2013;285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10856948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neri FM, Cook AR, Gibson GJ, Gottwald TR, Gilligan CA. Bayesian analysis for inference of an emerging epidemic: citrus canker in urban landscapes. PLoS Comput Biol. 2014;10:e1003587&#x2013;e1003587. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003587.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003587</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3998883</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24762851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H. Time variations in the generation time of an infectious disease: implications for sampling to appropriately quantify transmission potential. Math Biosci Eng. 2010;7:851&#x2013;869.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21077712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pybus OG, Suchard MA, Lemey P, Bernardin FJ, Rambaut A, Crawford FW, Gray RR, Arinaminpathy N, Stramer SL, Busch MP, Delwart EL. Unifying the spatial epidemiology and molecular evolution of emerging epidemics. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2012;109:15066&#x2013;15071. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1206598109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1206598109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3443149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22927414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabaa MA, Klungthong C, Yoon I-K, Holmes EC, Chinnawirotpisan P, Thaisomboonsuk B, Srikiatkhachorn A, Rothman AL, Tannitisupawong D, Aldstadt J, Nisalak A, Mammen MP, Gibbons RV, Endy TP, Fansiri T, Scott TW, Jarman RG. Frequent in-migration and highly focal transmission of dengue viruses among children in Kamphaeng Phet, Thailand. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2013;7:e1990. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0001990.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3547850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23350000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabaa MA, Ty Hang VT, Wills B, Farrar J, Simmons CP, Holmes EC. Phylogeography of recently emerged DENV-2 in southern Viet Nam. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2010;4:e766. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0000766.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2910671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20668540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salje H, Cauchemez S, Theresa Alera M, Rodriguez-Barraquer I, Thaisomboonsuk B, Srikiatkhachorn A, Lago CB, Villa D, Klungthong C, Tac-An IA, Fernandez S, Velasco JM, Roque VG, Nisalak A, Macareo LR, Levy JW, Cummings D, Yoon I-K. Reconstruction of 60 years of chikungunya epidemiology in the Philippines demonstrates episodic and focal transmission. J Infect Dis. 2015 doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiv470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiv470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4721913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26410592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salje H, Lessler J, Endy TP, Curriero FC, Gibbons RV, Nisalak A, Nimmannitya S, Kalayanarooj S, Jarman RG, Thomas SJ, Burke DS, Cummings DAT. Revealing the microscale spatial signature of dengue transmission and immunity in an urban population. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2012;109:9535&#x2013;9538. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1120621109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1120621109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3386131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22645364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stack JC, Welch JD, Ferrari MJ, Shapiro BU, Grenfell BT. Protocols for sampling viral sequences to study epidemic dynamics. J R Soc Interface. 2010;7:1119&#x2013;1127. doi: 10.1098/rsif.2009.0530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsif.2009.0530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2880085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20147314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ster IC, Ferguson NM. Transmission parameters of the 2001 foot and mouth epidemic in Great Britain. PLoS ONE 2007</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1876810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17551582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Teunis P. Different epidemic curves for severe acute respiratory syndrome reveal similar impacts of control measures. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2004;160:509&#x2013;516. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwh255.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kwh255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7110200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15353409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>