<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">33376449</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1369-7412</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>82</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2020</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society. Series B, Statistical methodology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J R Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multiply robust causal inference with double-negative control adjustment for categorical unmeasured confounding.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>521</StartPage><EndPage>540</EndPage><MedlinePgn>521-540</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/rssb.12361</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Unmeasured confounding is a threat to causal inference in observational studies. In recent years, the use of negative controls to mitigate unmeasured confounding has gained increasing recognition and popularity. Negative controls have a long-standing tradition in laboratory sciences and epidemiology to rule out non-causal explanations, although they have been used primarily for bias detection. Recently, Miao and colleagues have described sufficient conditions under which a pair of negative control exposure and outcome variables can be used to identify non-parametrically the average treatment effect (ATE) from observational data subject to uncontrolled confounding. We establish non-parametric identification of the ATE under weaker conditions in the case of categorical unmeasured confounding and negative control variables. We also provide a general semiparametric framework for obtaining inferences about the ATE while leveraging information about a possibly large number of measured covariates. In particular, we derive the semiparametric efficiency bound in the non-parametric model, and we propose multiply robust and locally efficient estimators when non-parametric estimation may not be feasible. We assess the finite sample performance of our methods in extensive simulation studies. Finally, we illustrate our methods with an application to the post-licensure surveillance of vaccine safety among children.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shi</LastName><ForeName>Xu</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miao</LastName><ForeName>Wang</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Peking University, Beijing, People's Republic of China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nelson</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer C</ForeName><Initials>JC</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Kaiser Permanente Washington Health Research Institute, Seattle, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tchetgen</LastName><ForeName>Eric J Tchetgen</ForeName><Initials>EJT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AG065276</GrantID><Acronym>AG</Acronym><Agency>NIA NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI104459</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI127271</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2020</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J R Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100890344</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1369-7412</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Causal inference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Negative control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Semiparametric inference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Unmeasured confounding</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2020</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33376449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1655073</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7768794</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/rssb.12361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Athey S and Wager S (2017) Efficient policy learning Preprint arXiv:1702.02896 Graduate School of Business, Stanford University, Stanford.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bang H and Robins JM (2005) Doubly robust estimation in missing data and causal inference models. Biometrics, 61, 962&#x2013;973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16401269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bickel PJ, Klaassen C, Ritov Y and Wellner J (1993) Efficient and Adaptive Inference in Semiparametric Models, vol. 2 Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng G and Huang JZ (2010) Bootstrap consistency for general semiparametric M-estimation. Ann. Statist, 38, 2884&#x2013;2915.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chernozhukov V, Escanciano JC, Ichimura H, Newey WK and Robins JM (2016) Locally robust semiparametric estimation Preprint arXiv:1608.00033 Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi Y, Taylor J and Tibshirani R (2017) Selecting the number of principal components: estimation of the true rank of a noisy matrix. Ann. Statist, 45, 2590&#x2013;2617.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davey Smith G (2008) Assessing intrauterine influences on offspring health outcomes: can epidemiological studies yield robust findings? Basic Clin. Pharmcol. Toxicol, 102, 245&#x2013;256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18226080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davey Smith G (2012) Negative control exposures in epidemiologic studies: Comments on &#x201c;Negative controls: a tool for detecting confounding and bias in observational studies&#x201d;. Epidemiology, 23, 350&#x2013;351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22317815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flanders WD, Klein M, Darrow LA, Strickland MJ, Sarnat SE, Sarnat JA, Waller LA, Winquist A and Tolbert PE (2011) A method for detection of residual confounding in time-series and other observational studies. Epidemiology, 22, 59&#x2013;67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3743227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21068669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flanders WD, Strickland MJ and Klein M (2017) A new method for partial correction of residual confounding in time-series and other observational studies. Am. J. Epidem, 185, 941&#x2013;949.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28430842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagnon-Bartsch JA and Speed TP (2012) Using control genes to correct for unwanted variation in microarray data. Biostatistics, 13, 539&#x2013;552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3577104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22101192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glass DJ (2014) Experimental Design for Biologists. Cold Spring Harbor: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G&#xf3;mez P, Lacruz B and Pruneda RE (2008) Generalized inverse computation based on an orthogonal decomposition methodology In Advances in Mathematical and Statistical Modeling, pp. 305&#x2013;315. New York: Springer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson LA, Jackson ML, Nelson JC, Neuzil KM and Weiss NS (2005) Evidence of bias in estimates of influenza vaccine effectiveness in seniors. Int. J. Epidem, 35, 337&#x2013;344.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16368725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>James M (1978) The generalised inverse. Math. Gaz, 62, 109&#x2013;114.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuroki M and Pearl J (2014) Measurement bias and effect restoration in causal inference. Biometrika, 101, 423&#x2013;437.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lipsitch M, Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ and Cohen T (2010) Negative controls: a tool for detecting confounding and bias in observational studies. Epidemiology, 21, 383&#x2013;388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3053408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20335814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lipsitch M, Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ and Cohen T (2012) Negative control exposures in epidemiologic studies (author reply). Epidemiology, 23, 351&#x2013;352.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22317815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miao W, Geng Z and Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ (2018) Identifying causal effects with proxy variables of an unmeasured confounder. Biometrika, 105, 987&#x2013;993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7746017</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33343006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miao W, Shi X and Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ (2019) A confounding bridge approach for double negative control inference on causal effects
Preprint. Guanghua School of Management, Peking University, Beijing:  (Available from https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.04945.)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miao W and Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ (2017) Bias attenuation and identification of causal effects with multiple negative controls. Am. J. Epidem, 185, 950&#x2013;953.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5430936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28430847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelson JC, Yu O, Dominguez-Islas CP, Cook AJ, Peterson D, Greene SK, Yih WK, Daley MF, Jacobsen SJ, Klein NP, Weintraub ES, Broder KR and Jackson LA (2013) Adapting group sequential methods to observational postlicensure vaccine safety surveillance: results of a pentavalent combination DTaP-IPV-Hib vaccine safety study. Am. J. Epidem, 177, 131&#x2013;141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23292957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newey WK (1990) Semiparametric efficiency bounds. J. Appl. Econmetr, 5, 99&#x2013;135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogburn EL and VanderWeele TJ (2012) On the nondifferential misclassification of a binary confounder. Epidemiology, 23, 433&#x2013;439.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3365922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22450692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson TS and Robins JM (2013) Single world intervention graphs (SWIGs): a unification of the counterfactual and graphical approaches to causality Working Paper, p. 128 Center for the Statistics and the Social Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM (1986) A new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with a sustained exposure period&#x2014;application to control of the healthy worker survivor effect. Math. Modllng, 7, 1393&#x2013;1512.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM (1994) Correcting for non-compliance in randomized trials using structural nested mean models. Communs Statist. Theory Meth, 23, 2379&#x2013;2412.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM (2000) Robust estimation in sequentially ignorable missing data and causal inference models. Proc. Baysn Statist. Sci. Sect. Am. Statist. Ass, 6&#x2013;10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM and Rotnitzky A (2001) Comment on &#x201c;Inference for semiparametric models: some questions and an answer&#x201d; by P. J. Bickel and J. Kwon. Statist. Sin, 11, 920&#x2013;936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM, Rotnitzky A and Zhao LP (1994) Estimation of regression coefficients when some regressors are not always observed. J. Am. Statist. Ass, 89, 846&#x2013;866.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR (1989) The role of known effects in observational studies. Biometrics, 45, 557&#x2013;569.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR (1992) Detecting bias with confidence in observational studies. Biometrika, 79, 367&#x2013;374.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rotnitzky A, Robins J and Babino L (2017) On the multiply robust estimation of the mean of the g-functional Preprint arXiv:1705.08582 Di Tella University, Buenos Aires.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scharfstein DO, Rotnitzky A and Robins JM (1999) Adjusting for nonignorable drop-out using semiparametric nonresponse models. J. Am. Statist. Ass, 94, 1096&#x2013;1120.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuemie MJ, Ryan PB, DuMouchel W, Suchard MA and Madigan D (2014) Interpreting observational studies: why empirical calibration is needed to correct p-values. Statist. Med, 33, 209&#x2013;218.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4285234</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23900808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sofer T, Richardson DB, Colicino E, Schwartz J and Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ (2016) On negative outcome control of unobserved confounding as a generalization of difference-in-differences. Statist. Sci, 31, 348&#x2013;361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5322866</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28239233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tan Z (2006) A distributional approach for causal inference using propensity scores. J. Am. Statist. Ass, 101, 1619&#x2013;1637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ (2013) The control outcome calibration approach for causal inference with unobserved confounding. Am. J. Epidem, 179, 633&#x2013;640.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3927977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24363326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ and Shpitser I (2012) Semiparametric theory for causal mediation analysis: efficiency bounds, multiple robustness, and sensitivity analysis. Ann. Statist, 40, 1816&#x2013;1845.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4710381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26770002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsiatis A (2007) Semiparametric Theory and Missing Data. New York: Springer Science and Business Media.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van der Laan MJ and Robins JM (2003) Unified Methods for Censored Longitudinal Data and Causality. New York: Springer Science and Business Media.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van der Laan MJ and Rose S (2011) Targeted Learning: Causal Inference for Observational and Experimental Data. New York: Springer Science and Business Media.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van der Vaart AW (1998) Asymptotic Statistics, vol. 3 New York: Cambridge University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vansteelandt S, VanderWeele TJ, Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ and Robins JM (2008) Multiply robust inference for statistical interactions. J. Am. Statist. Ass, 103, 1693&#x2013;1704.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3097121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21603124</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L and Tchetgen Tchetgen E (2018) Bounded, efficient and multiply robust estimation of average treatment effects using instrumental variables. J. R. Statist. Soc. B, 80, 531&#x2013;550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6051728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30034269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang J, Zhao Q, Hastie T and Owen AB (2017) Confounder adjustment in multiple hypothesis testing. Ann. Statist, 45, 1863&#x2013;1894.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6706069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31439967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss NS (2002) Can the &#x201c;specificity&#x201d; of an association be rehabilitated as a basis for supporting a causal hypothesis? Epidemiology, 13, 6&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11805580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>