<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">32995829</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2020</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>medRxiv : the preprint server for health sciences</Title><ISOAbbreviation>medRxiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>EXTENDING THE SUSCEPTIBLE-EXPOSED-INFECTED-REMOVED(SEIR) MODEL TO HANDLE THE HIGH FALSE NEGATIVE RATE AND SYMPTOM-BASED ADMINISTRATION OF COVID-19 DIAGNOSTIC TESTS: SEIR-fansy.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">2020.09.24.20200238</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1101/2020.09.24.20200238</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The false negative rate of the diagnostic RT-PCR test for SARS-CoV-2 has been reported to be substantially high. Due to limited availability of testing, only a non-random subset of the population can get tested. Hence, the reported test counts are subject to a large degree of selection bias. We consider an extension of the Susceptible-Exposed-Infected-Removed (SEIR) model under both selection bias and misclassification. We derive closed form expression for the basic reproduction number under such data anomalies using the next generation matrix method. We conduct extensive simulation studies to quantify the effect of misclassification and selection on the resultant estimation and prediction of future case counts. Finally we apply the methods to reported case-death-recovery count data from India, a nation with more than 5 million cases reported over the last seven months. We show that correcting for misclassification and selection can lead to more accurate prediction of case-counts (and death counts) using the observed data as a beta tester. The model also provides an estimate of undetected infections and thus an under-reporting factor. For India, the estimated under-reporting factor for cases is around 21 and for deaths is around 6. We develop an R-package (SEIRfansy) for broader dissemination of the methods.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhaduri</LastName><ForeName>Ritwik</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Indian Statistical Institute Kolkata, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kundu</LastName><ForeName>Ritoban</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Purkayastha</LastName><ForeName>Soumik</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kleinsasser</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beesley</LastName><ForeName>Lauren J</ForeName><Initials>LJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mukherjee</LastName><ForeName>Bhramar</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics and Epidemiology, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P30 CA046592</GrantID><Acronym>CA</Acronym><Agency>NCI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2020</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>medRxiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101767986</NlmUniqueID></MedlineJournalInfo><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="UpdateIn"><RefSource>Stat Med. 2022 Jun 15;41(13):2317-2337. doi: 10.1002/sim.9357.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">35224743</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><CoiStatement>Conflict of Interest. Nothing to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32995829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7523173</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2020.09.24.20200238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2020.09.24.20200238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ai Tao, Yang Zhenlu, Hou Hongyan, Zhan Chenao, Chen Chong, Lv Wenzhi, Tao Qian, Sun Ziyong, and Xia Liming. Correlation of chest ct and rt-pcr testing in coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) in china: a report of 1014 cases. Radiology, page 200642, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7233399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32101510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arevalo-Rodriguez Ingrid, Buitrago-Garcia Diana, Simancas-Racines Daniel, Zambrano-Achig Paula, Campo Rosa del, Ciapponi Agustin, Sued Omar, Martinez-Garcia Laura, Rutjes Anne, Low Nicola, et al. False-negative results of initial rt-pcr assays for covid-19: a systematic review. medRxiv, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7728293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33301459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Babu N. Percentage of people with antibodies high, shows delhi serological survey. The Hindu, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai Yan, Yao Lingsheng, Wei Tao, Tian Fei, Jin Dong-Yan, Chen Lijuan, and Wang Meiyun. Presumed asymptomatic carrier transmission of covid-19. Jama, 323(14):1406&#x2013;1407, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7042844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32083643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beesley Lauren J and Mukherjee Bhramar. Statistical inference for association studies using electronic health records: handling both selection bias and outcome misclassification. medRxiv, 2019. doi: 10.1101/2019.12.26.19015859 URL https://www.medrxiv.org/content/early/2019/12/30/2019.12.26.19015859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2019.12.26.19015859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33179768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burstyn Igor, Goldstein Neal D, and Gustafson Paul. Towards reduction in bias in epidemic curves due to outcome misclassification through bayesian analysis of time-series of laboratory test results: Case study of covid-19 in alberta, canada and philadelphia, usa. BMC Medical Research Methodology, 20:1&#x2013;10, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7275354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32505172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>IHME COVID, Murray Christopher JL, et al. Forecasting covid-19 impact on hospital bed-days, icu-days, ventilator-days and deaths by us state in the next 4 months. MedRxiv, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dempsey Walter. The hypothesis of testing: Paradoxes arising out of reported coronavirus case-counts. arXiv preprint arXiv:200510425, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaxman Seth, Mishra Swapnil, Gandy Axel, Juliette H Unwin T, Mellan Thomas A, Coupland Helen, Whittaker Charles, Harrison Zhu, Tresnia Berah, Eaton Jeffrey W, et al. Estimating the effects of non-pharmaceutical interventions on covid-19 in europe. Nature, pages 1&#x2013;5, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32512579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffith Gareth, Morris Tim T, Tudball Matt, Herbert Annie, Mancano Giulia, Pike Lindsey, Sharp Gemma C, Palmer Tom M, Smith George Davey, Tilling Kate, et al. Collider bias undermines our understanding of covid-19 disease risk and severity. medRxiv, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7665028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33184277</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamer Davidson H. Vaccinology: An essential guide, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao Xingjie, Cheng Shanshan, Wu Degang, Wu Tangchun, Lin Xihong, and Wang Chaolong. Reconstruction of the full transmission dynamics of covid-19 in wuhan. Nature, pages 1&#x2013;5, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32674112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kermack William Ogilvy and McKendrick Anderson G. A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics. Proceedings of the royal society of london. Series A, Containing papers of a mathematical and physical character, 115(772):700&#x2013;721, 1927.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kucirka Lauren M, Lauer Stephen A, Laeyendecker Oliver, Boon Denali, and Lessler Justin. Variation in false-negative rate of reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction-based sars-cov-2 tests by time since exposure. Annals of Internal Medicine, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7240870</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32422057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauer Stephen A and Grantz Kyra H. bi Qifang, jones forrest k, zheng qulu, meredith hannah r, azman andrew s, reich nicholas g, and lessler justin. 2020.&#x201c;the incubation period of coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) from publicly reported confirmed cases: estimation and application.&#x201d;. Annals of internal medicine, 14, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7081172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan An, Liu Li, Wang Chaolong, Guo Huan, Hao Xingjie, Wang Qi, Huang Jiao, He Na, Yu Hongjie, Lin Xihong, Wei Sheng, and Wu Tangchun. Association of Public Health Interventions With the Epidemiology of the COVID-19 Outbreak in Wuhan, China. JAMA, 323(19):1915&#x2013;1923, 05 2020. ISSN 0098-7484. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.6130 URL 10.1001/jama.2020.6130</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.6130</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7149375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32275295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ray Debashree, Salvatore Maxwell, Bhattacharyya Rupam, Wang Lili, Du Jiacong, Mohammed Shariq, Purkayastha Soumik, Halder Aritra, Rix Alexander, Barker Daniel, Kleinsasser Michael, Zhou Yiwang, Bose Debraj, Song Peter, Banerjee Mousumi, Baladandayuthapani Veerabhadran, Ghosh Parikshit, and Mukherjee Bhramar. Predictions, role of interventions and effects of a historic national lockdown in india&#x2019;s response to the the covid-19 pandemic: Data science call to arms. Harvard Data Science Review, 6
2020. doi: 10.1162/99608f92.60e08ed5 URL https://hdsr.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/r1qq01kw.
https://hdsr.mitpress.mit.edu/pub/r1qq01kw.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1162/99608f92.60e08ed5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7326342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32607504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>RStudio Team. Rstudio: Integrated development environment for r, 2020.  URL http://www.rstudio.com/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saxena A. Here are the key takeaways from delhi&#x2019;s serological survey. The Indian Express, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saxena A. 1 in 5 in delhi sero-survey developed antibodies, indicating spread of virus. The Indian Express, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharfstein Joshua M, Becker Scott J, and Mello Michelle M. Diagnostic testing for the novel coronavirus. Jama, 323(15):1437&#x2013;1438, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Song Peter X, Wang Lili, Zhou Yiwang, He Jie, Zhu Bin, Wang Fei, Tang Lu, and Eisenberg Marisa. An epidemiological forecast model and software assessing interventions on covid-19 epidemic in china. MedRxiv, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tang Lu, Zhou Yiwang, Wang Lili, Purkayastha Soumik, Zhang Leyao, He Jie, Wang Fei, and Song Peter X.-K.. A review of multi-compartment infectious disease models. International Statistical Review, August 2020. doi: 10.1111/insr.12402 URL 10.1111/insr.12402</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/insr.12402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7436714</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tong Zhen-Dong, Tang An, Li Ke-Feng, Li Peng, Wang Hong-Ling, Yi Jing-Ping, Zhang Yong-Li, and Yan Jian-Bo. Potential presymptomatic transmission of sars-cov-2, zhejiang province, china, 2020. Emerging infectious diseases, 26(5):1052, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7181913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johns Hopkins University. Covid-19 dashboard by the center for systems science and engineering (csse) atjohns hopkins university (jhu). https://gisanddata.maps.arcgis.com/apps/opsdashboard/index.html#/bda7594740fd40299423467b48e9ecf6, Accessed = 2020-07-04, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van den Driessche Pauline. Reproduction numbers of infectious disease models. Infectious Disease Modelling, 2 (3):288&#x2013;303, 2017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6002118</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29928743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>West Colin P, Montori Victor M, and Sampathkumar Priya. Covid-19 testing: the threat of false-negative results. In Mayo Clinic Proceedings, volume 95, pages 1127&#x2013;1129. Elsevier, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7151274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32376102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. www.who.int/news-room/commentaries/detail/estimating-mortality-from-covid-19, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woloshin Steven, Patel Neeraj, and Kesselheim Aaron S. False negative tests for sars-cov-2 infection&#x2014;challenges and implications. New England Journal of Medicine, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32502334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Joseph T, Leung Kathy, and Leung Gabriel M. Nowcasting and forecasting the potential domestic and international spread of the 2019-ncov outbreak originating in wuhan, china: a modelling study. The Lancet, 395 (10225):689&#x2013;697, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32014114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Yang, Yang Minghui, Shen Chenguang, Wang Fuxiang, Yuan Jing, Li Jinxiu, Zhang Mingxia, Wang Zhaoqin, Xing Li, Wei Jinli, et al. Laboratory diagnosis and monitoring the viral shedding of 2019-ncov infections. MedRxiv, 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7609236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33169119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou Yiwang, Wang Lili, Zhang Leyao, Shi Lan, Yang Kangping, He He, Zhao Bangyao, Overton William, Purkayastha Soumik, and Song Peter. A spatiotemporal epidemiological prediction model to inform county-level covid-19 risk in the usa. Harvard Data Science Review, 2020.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>