<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">39893390</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2025</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>05</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>25</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2025</Year><Month>Feb</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A novel graph neural network based approach for influenza-like illness nowcasting: exploring the interplay of temporal, geographical, and functional spatial features.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>408</StartPage><MedlinePgn>408</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">408</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12889-025-21618-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Accurate and timely monitoring of influenza prevalence is essential for effective healthcare interventions. This study proposes a graph neural network (GNN)-based method to address the issue of cross-regional connectivity in predicting influenza outbreaks, aiming to achieve real-time and accurate influenza prediction.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">We proposed a GNN-based approach with dual topology processing, capturing both geographical and socio-economic associations among counties/cities. The model inputs consist of weekly matrices of influenza-like illness (ILI) rates at city level, along with geographical topology and functional topology. The model construction involves temporal feature extraction through 1-dimensional gated causal convolution, spatial feature embedding through graph convolution, and additional adjustments to enhance spatiotemporal interaction exploration. Evaluation metrics include four commonly used measures: root mean square error (RMSE), mean absolute percentage error (MAPE), mean absolute error (MAE), and Pearson correlation (Corr).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">Our approach for predicting influenza outbreaks achieves competitive performance on real-world datasets (Corr = 0.8202; RMSE = 0.0017; MAE = 0.0013; MAPE = 0.0966), surpassing established baselines. Notably, our approach exhibits excellent capability in accurately and timely capturing short-term influenza outbreaks during the flu season, outperforming competitors across all evaluation metrics.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">The incorporation of dual topology processing and the subsequent fusion mechanism allows the model to explore in-depth spatiotemporal feature interactions. Demonstrating superior performance, our approach shows great potential in early detection of flu trends for facilitating public health decisions and resource optimization.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2025. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Jiajia</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health (Shenzhen), Sun Yat-sen University, Shenzhen, 518107, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xuan</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health (Shenzhen), Sun Yat-sen University, Shenzhen, 518107, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Fan</LastName><ForeName>Xiaomao</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Big Data and Internet, Shenzhen Technology University, Shenzhen, 518118, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>He</LastName><ForeName>Yuxin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Urban Transportation and Logistics, Shenzhen Technology University, Shenzhen, 518118, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Du</LastName><ForeName>Xiangjun</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health (Shenzhen), Sun Yat-sen University, Shenzhen, 518107, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chen</LastName><ForeName>Yao-Qing</ForeName><Initials>YQ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health (Shenzhen), Sun Yat-sen University, Shenzhen, 518107, Guangdong, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhao</LastName><ForeName>Yang</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Public Health (Shenzhen), Sun Yat-sen University, Shenzhen, 518107, Guangdong, China. zhaoy393@mail.sysu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>SGDX20210823104003030</GrantID><Agency>Shen Zhen-Hong Kong-Macao Science and Technology Project Fund</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2023YFC2307305</GrantID><Agency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2025</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="Y">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016571" MajorTopicYN="Y">Neural Networks, Computer</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062211" MajorTopicYN="N">Spatio-Temporal Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005544" MajorTopicYN="N">Forecasting</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000098422" MajorTopicYN="N">Graph Neural Networks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Functional topology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Graph neural network (GNN)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Socio-economic association</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Spatiotemporal interaction</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declarations. Ethics approval and consent to participate: This study did not involve human participants, data, or tissue. It was conducted using only aggregated and anonymized data. Institutional review board approval was not required. Consent for publication: Not applicable. Competing interest: The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2025</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2025</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2025</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2025</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39893390</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11786584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-025-21618-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12889-025-21618-6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Influenza (Seasonal). 2023 [cited 2024 Nov 27]. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/influenza-(seasonal).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Francisco N, Donadel M, Jit M, Hutubessy R. A systematic review of the social and economic burden of influenza in low-and middle-income countries. Vaccine. 2015;33(48):6537&#x2013;44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2015.10.066</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26597032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Putri WC, Muscatello DJ, Stockwell MS, Newall AT. Economic burden of seasonal influenza in the United States. Vaccine. 2018;36(27):3960&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2018.05.057</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29801998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macias AE, McElhaney JE, Chaves SS, Nealon J, Nunes MC, Samson SI, et al. The disease burden of influenza beyond respiratory illness. Vaccine. 2021;39:A6&#x2013;14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.09.048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7545338</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33041103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hung SK, Wu CC, Singh A, Li JH, Lee C, Chou EH, et al. Developing and validating clinical features-based machine learning algorithms to predict influenza infection in influenza-like illness patients. Biomed J. 2023;46(5):100561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10498408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36150651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng HY, Wu YC, Lin MH, Liu YL, Tsai YY, Wu JH, et al. Applying machine learning models with an ensemble approach for accurate real-time influenza forecasting in Taiwan: Development and validation study. J Med Internet Res. 2020;22(8):e15394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/15394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7439145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32755888</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woo H, Cho Y, Shim E, Lee JK, Lee CG, Kim SH. Estimating influenza outbreaks using both search engine query data and social media data in South Korea. J Med Internet Res. 2016;18(7):e177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/jmir.4955</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4949385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27377323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Z, Tao H. Epidemiology and ARIMA model of positive-rate of influenza viruses among children in Wuhan, China: A nine-year retrospective study. Int J Infect Dis. 2018;74:61&#x2013;70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2018.07.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29990540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rutland BE, Weese JS, Bolin C, Au J, Malani AN. Human-to-dog transmission of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus. Emerg Infect Dis. 2009;15(8):1328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1508.081635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2815967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19751611</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazer D, Kennedy R, King G, Vespignani A. The parable of Google Flu: traps in big data analysis. Science. 2014;343(6176):1203&#x2013;5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1248506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24626916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newbold P. ARIMA model building and the time series analysis approach to forecasting. J Forecast. 1983;2(1):23&#x2013;35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/for.3980020104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Chakraborty P, Mekaru SR, Brownstein JS, Ye J, Ramakrishnan N. Dynamic poisson autoregression for influenza-like-illness case count prediction. In: Proceedings of the 21th ACM SIGKDD international conference on knowledge discovery and data mining. New York: ACM (Association for Computing Machinery); 2015. p. 1285&#x2013;94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima U, Hina S, Wasif M. A novel global clustering coefficient-dependent degree centrality (GCCDC) metric for large network analysis using real-world datasets. J Comput Sci. 2023;70:102008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jocs.2023.102008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima U, Hina S. Efficient algorithm for maximal clique size evaluation. Int J Adv Comput Sci Appl. 2019;10(7):444&#x2013;52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Yang J, He Y, Zhang M, Han X, Hu X, et al. Enhancing infectious diseases early warning: A deep learning approach for influenza surveillance in China. Prev Med Rep. 2024;43:102761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pmedr.2024.102761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11127166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38798906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He Y, Zhao Y, Chen Y, Yuan HY, Tsui KL. Nowcasting influenza-like illness (ILI) via a deep learning approach using google search data: An empirical study on Taiwan ILI. Int J Intell Syst. 2022;37(3):2648&#x2013;74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/int.22788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu X, Fu B, Yang Y, Ma Y, Hao J, Chen S, et al. Attention-based recurrent neural network for influenza epidemic prediction. BMC Bioinformatics. 2019;20(18):1&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6876090</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31760945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kara A. Multi-step influenza outbreak forecasting using deep LSTM network and genetic algorithm. Expert Syst Appl. 2021;180:115153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2021.115153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu H, Chen S, Lu W, Chen K, Feng Y, Xie Z, et al. Study on the influence of meteorological factors on influenza in different regions and predictions based on an LSTM algorithm. BMC Public Health. 2022;22(1):1&#x2013;17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-14299-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9745690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36514013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang P. Nowcasting influenza using Google flu trend and deep learning model. In: Proceedings of the 2020 2nd International Conference on Economic Management and Cultural Industry (ICEMCI 2020). Paris: Atlantis Press; 2020. p. 407&#x2013;16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xi G, Yin L, Li Y, Mei S. A deep residual network integrating spatial-temporal properties to predict influenza trends at an intra-urban scale. In: Proceedings of the 2nd ACM SIGSPATIAL international workshop on AI for geographic knowledge discovery. New York: ACM (Association for Computing Machinery); 2018. p. 19&#x2013;28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Athanasiou M, Fragkozidis G, Zarkogianni K, Nikita KS. Long Short-term Memory-Based Prediction of the Spread of Influenza-Like Illness Leveraging Surveillance, Weather, and Twitter Data: Model Development and Validation. J Med Internet Res. 2023;25:e42519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/42519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9941907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36745490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Z, Pan S, Chen F, Long G, Zhang C, Philip SY. A comprehensive survey on graph neural networks. IEEE Trans Neural Netw Learn Syst. 2020;32(1):4&#x2013;24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TNNLS.2020.2978386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32217482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Y, Si X, Hu C, Zhang J. A review of recurrent neural networks: LSTM cells and network architectures. Neural Comput. 2019;31(7):1235&#x2013;70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1162/neco_a_01199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31113301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Z, Liu F, Yang W, Peng S, Zhou J. A survey of convolutional neural networks: analysis, applications, and prospects. IEEE Trans Neural Netw Learn Syst. 2021;33(12):6999&#x2013;7019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TNNLS.2021.3084827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34111009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu Y, Fu Y, Xu J, Yin H, Zhou Q, Liu D. Heterogeneous question answering community detection based on graph neural network. Inf Sci. 2023;621:652&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ins.2022.10.126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casas S, Gulino C, Liao R, Urtasun R. Spagnn: Spatially-aware graph neural networks for relational behavior forecasting from sensor data. In: Proceedings of the 2020 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA). Piscataway: IEEE; 2020. p. 9491&#x2013;7.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dauparas J, Anishchenko I, Bennett N, Bai H, Ragotte RJ, Milles LF, et al. Robust deep learning-based protein sequence design using ProteinMPNN. Science. 2022;378(6615):49&#x2013;56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.add2187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9997061</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36108050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gao C, Wang X, He X, Li Y. Graph neural networks for recommender system. In: Proceedings of the fifteenth ACM international conference on web search and data mining. New York: ACM (Association for Computing Machinery); 2022. p. 1623&#x2013;5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bui KHN, Cho J, Yi H. Spatial-temporal graph neural network for traffic forecasting: An overview and open research issues. Appl Intell. 2022;52(3):2763&#x2013;74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10489-021-02587-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu L, Chen Y, Shen K, Guo X, Gao H, Li S, et al. Graph neural networks for natural language processing: A survey. Found Trends Mach Learn. 2023;16(2):119&#x2013;328.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1561/2200000096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung S, Moon J, Park S, Hwang E. Self-attention-based deep learning network for regional influenza forecasting. IEEE J Biomed Health Inform. 2021;26(2):922&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JBHI.2021.3093897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34197330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moon J, Jung S, Park S, Hwang E. RESEAT: Recurrent Self-Attention Network for Multi-Regional Influenza Forecasting. IEEE J Biomed Health Inform. 2023;27(5):2585&#x2013;96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JBHI.2023.3247687</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37027675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eggo RM, Cauchemez S, Ferguson NM. Spatial dynamics of the 1918 influenza pandemic in England, Wales and the United States. J R Soc Interface. 2011;8(55):233&#x2013;43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsif.2010.0216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3033019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20573630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller HJ. Tobler&#x2019;s first law and spatial analysis. Ann Assoc Am Geogr. 2004;94(2):284&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8306.2004.09402005.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charu V, Zeger S, Gog J, Bj&#xf8;rnstad ON, Kissler S, Simonsen L, et al. Human mobility and the spatial transmission of influenza in the United States. PLoS Comput Biol. 2017;13(2):e1005382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5349690</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28187123</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang JR, Hsu SZ, Kuo CY, Huang HY, Huang TY, Wang HC, et al. An epidemic surge of influenza A (H3N2) virus at the end of the 2016&#x2013;2017 season in Taiwan with an increased viral genetic heterogeneity. J Clin Virol. 2018;99:15&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2017.12.012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29278832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu YL, Fang LQ, de Vlas SJ, Gao Y, Richardus JH, Cao WC. Dual seasonal patterns for influenza, China. Emerg Infect Dis. 2010;16(4):725.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid1604.091578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3321959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20350403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ginsberg J, Mohebbi MH, Patel RS, Brammer L, Smolinski MS, Brilliant L. Detecting influenza epidemics using search engine query data. Nature. 2009;457(7232):1012&#x2013;4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature07634</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19020500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang F, Guan P, Wu W, Huang D. Forecasting influenza epidemics by integrating internet search queries and traditional surveillance data with the support vector machine regression model in Liaoning, from 2011 to 2015. PeerJ. 2018;6:e5134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.5134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6022725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29967755</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Poirier C, Hswen Y, Bouzill&#xe9; G, Cuggia M, Lavenu A, Brownstein JS, et al. Influenza forecasting for French regions combining EHR, web and climatic data sources with a machine learning ensemble approach. PLoS ONE. 2021;16(5):e0250890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0250890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8133501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34010293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang R, Wu H, Wu Y, Zheng J, Li Y. Improving influenza surveillance based on multi-granularity deep spatiotemporal neural network. Comput Biol Med. 2021;134:104482.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2021.104482</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34051452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamran H, Aleman DM, Carter MW, Moore KM. Spatio-Temporal Clustering of Multi-Location Time Series to Model Seasonal Influenza Spread. IEEE J Biomed Health Inform. 2023;27(4):2138&#x2013;48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JBHI.2023.3234818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37018610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou X, Yang F, Feng Y, Li Q, Tang F, Hu S, et al. A spatial-temporal method to detect global influenza epidemics using heterogeneous data collected from the Internet. IEEE/ACM Trans Comput Biol Bioinforma. 2017;15(3):802&#x2013;12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TCBB.2017.2690631</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28391203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo X, Xiong NN, Wang H, Ren J. Design and analysis of a prediction system about influenza-like illness from the latent temporal and spatial information. IEEE Trans Syst Man Cybern Syst. 2021;52(1):66&#x2013;77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TSMC.2020.3048946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radin JM, Wineinger NE, Topol EJ, Steinhubl SR. Harnessing wearable device data to improve state-level real-time surveillance of influenza-like illness in the USA: a population-based study. Lancet Digit Health. 2020;2(2):e85&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2589-7500(19)30222-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8048388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33334565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taiwan Centers for Disease Control. Health insurance outpatient and emergency visits - influenza. Taiwan CDC. [cited 2024 Nov 27]. Available from: https://data.cdc.gov.tw/en/dataset/hi-outpatient-emergency-visit-influenza-like-illness. </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rice L, Wong E, Kolter Z. Overfitting in adversarially robust deep learning. In: Proceedings of the International Conference on Machine Learning. Cheltenham: PMLR; 2020. p. 8093&#x2013;104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Box GE, Jenkins GM, Reinsel GC, Ljung GM. Time series analysis: forecasting and control. Hoboken: Wiley; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickey DA, Fuller WA. Distribution of the estimators for autoregressive time series with a unit root. J Am Stat Assoc. 1979;74(366a):427&#x2013;31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01621459.1979.10482531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akaike H. A new look at the statistical model identification. IEEE Trans Autom Control. 1974;19(6):716&#x2013;23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TAC.1974.1100705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lai G, Chang WC, Yang Y, Liu H. Modeling long-and short-term temporal patterns with deep neural networks. In: The 41st international ACM SIGIR conference on research &amp; development in information retrieval. 2018. pp. 95&#x2013;104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hochreiter S, Schmidhuber J. Long short-term memory. Neural Comput. 1997;9(8):1735&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1162/neco.1997.9.8.1735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9377276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi X, Chen Z, Wang H, Yeung DY, Wong WK, Woo WC. Convolutional LSTM network: a machine learning approach for precipitation nowcasting. In: Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 28 (NeurIPS 2015). Red Hook: Curran Associates, Inc.; 2015. p. 802&#x2013;10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Velickovic P, Cucurull G, Casanova A, Romero A, Lio P, Bengio Y, et al. Graph attention networks. Stat. 2017;1050(20):10&#x2013;48550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Vaccine (influenza). Updated 2024 Jun 3 [cited 2024 Nov 27]. https://www.cdc.gov.tw/Category/Page/LnrbufSY9uTyIprhOZ15NA.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). National, regional, and state level outpatient illness and viral surveillance. CDC. [cited 2024 Nov 27]. Available from: https://gis.cdc.gov/grasp/fluview/fluportaldashboard.html. </Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>