<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">40238055</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2025</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>15</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1179-1942</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>48</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2025</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Drug safety</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Drug Saf</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Signal Monitoring for Adverse Events Following Immunisation with COVID-19 Vaccines During the SARS-CoV-2 Pandemic: An Evaluation of the South African Surveillance System.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>909</StartPage><EndPage>922</EndPage><MedlinePgn>909-922</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s40264-025-01547-4</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Monitoring of adverse events following immunisation (AEFI) is recommended for post-licensure surveillance. We investigated whether the South African surveillance system could detect signals of disproportionate reporting and whether these signals aligned with globally identified AEFI and adverse events of special interest (AESI) post-coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19) vaccination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This retrospective pharmacovigilance study undertook disproportionality analysis of the National Department of Health AEFI database from the start of the COVID-19 vaccine rollout on 17 May 2021 to 31 December 2022. We complemented this with AEFI reports for vaccines not on the routine Expanded Programme on Immunisation schedule, to address potential masking of signals due to the high reporting rate of COVID-19 vaccine AEFI.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">During the study period, 3846 AEFI were reported for 37,537,009 doses of COVID-19 vaccines (BNT162b2 and Ad26.COV2.S) administered. The overall reporting rate was 10.2 per 100,000 doses, 18.1/100,000 and 7.9/100,000 for Ad26.COV2.S and BNT162b2, respectively. Comparison with other countries suggests underreporting. Disproportionate reporting signals were obtained for three and seven AEFI following BNT162b2 and Ad26.COV2.S vaccines, respectively. An additional three AEFI signals from Ad26.COV2.S emerged in the augmented dataset, indicating masking. All Ad26.COV2.S signals, and one BNT162b2 signal, appear in the vaccines' product information. Among nine AESI evaluated, myocarditis/pericarditis presented as a signal of disproportionate reporting following BNT162b2 vaccination.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">This study is one of the first from a lower-middle-income country, using a spontaneous reporting system for signal detection post-COVID-19 vaccination. Signals aligned with those reported globally. The study highlights the need to further investigate underreporting, masking, and system attributes for system strengthening.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2025. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sankar</LastName><ForeName>Chenoa</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0009-0007-7869-2026</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Public Health Surveillance and Response, National Institute for Communicable Diseases, Johannesburg, South Africa. ChenoaS@nicd.ac.za.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa. ChenoaS@nicd.ac.za.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Evans</LastName><ForeName>Stephen</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1474-2596</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meyer</LastName><ForeName>Johanna Catharina</ForeName><Initials>JC</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0462-5713</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health Pharmacy and Management, Sefako Makgatho Health Sciences University, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South African Vaccination and Immunisation Centre, Sefako Makgatho Health Sciences University, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gunter</LastName><ForeName>Hannah May</ForeName><Initials>HM</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-3027-0602</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Pharmacology, Department of Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sekiti</LastName><ForeName>Victoria</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>South African Health Products Regulatory Authority, Pretoria, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McCarthy</LastName><ForeName>Kerrigan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8958-9795</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Public Health Surveillance and Response, National Institute for Communicable Diseases, Johannesburg, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Respiratory and Meningeal Pathogens Research Unit, University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2025</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>New Zealand</Country><MedlineTA>Drug Saf</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9002928</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0114-5916</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000090982">BNT162 Vaccine</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013019" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">South Africa</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016907" MajorTopicYN="Y">Adverse Drug Reaction Reporting Systems</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060735" MajorTopicYN="N">Pharmacovigilance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000090982" MajorTopicYN="N">BNT162 Vaccine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Declarations. Funding: Open access funding provided by University of Pretoria. Conflict of interest: The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. Consent to participate: Not applicable Consent for publication: Consent was obtained from all co-authors, no other consent to publish was required Data Availability Statement: Data that support the findings in this manuscript are not openly available as they are sensitive patient-based data. Data can be made available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request Author contributions: All authors read and approved the final version of this manuscript. Chenoa Sankar&#x2014;conceptualization, methodology, software, formal analysis, investigation, writing original draft, review and editing, and visualization; Stephen Evans&#x2014;methodology, supervision, review and editing, and resources; Johanna Meyer, Hannah May Gunter, and Victoria Sekiti&#x2014;review and editing, and resources; Kerrigan McCarthy&#x2014;conceptualization, supervision, investigation, review and editing, and resources. Ethics approval: Ethics approval was provided by the University of Pretoria Faculty of Health Sciences Research Ethics committee (ethics approval no. 659/2022).</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2025</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2025</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>28</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2025</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>35</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2025</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>24</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">40238055</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC12259799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s40264-025-01547-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1007/s40264-025-01547-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Western Cape Department of Health CDC-EPI. Standard Operational Procedure (SOP) for adverse events following immunisation (AEFI) for COVID-19 vaccinations. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Health. EPI Disease Surveillance Guideline. Guidelines for detecting, reporting, investigation and responding to EPI priority diseases. 2015; 3rd Edition.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mort M, Baleta A, Destefano F, Nsubuga JG, Vellozzi C, Mehta U, Pless R, Abdoellah SA, Yosephine P, Karolina S, World Health Organization. Vaccine safety basics: learning manual. World Health Organization; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization-Uppsala Monitoring Centre. What is a signal? WHO-UMC. Uppsala, Sweden: World Health Organization&#x2014;Uppsala Monitoring Centre. 2022. https://who-umc.org/signal-work/what-is-a-signal/. Accessed 20 Apr 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>RStudio. RStudio: Integrated Development Environment for R. Version 2023.06.1. RStudio, Inc. 2023. https://www.rstudio.com. Accessed 02 Jan 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CIOMS: Council for International Organizations of Medical Sciences. Practical aspects of signal detection in pharmacovigilance: report of CIOMS Working Group VIII. 2010. https://cioms.ch/wp&#x2010;content/uploads/2018/03/WG8&#x2010;Signal&#x2010;Detection.pdf. Accessed 10 Feb 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lindquist M. VigiBase, the WHO global ICSR database system: basic facts. Drug Inf J. 2008;42(5):409&#x2013;19.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization-Uppsala Monitoring Centre. The UMC measures of disproportionate reporting: a brief guide to their interpretation. WHO-UMC. 2016. https://who-umc.org/media/164041/measures-of-disproportionate-reporting_2016.pdf. Accessed 23 Apr 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bate A, Lindquist M, Edwards IR, Olsson S, Orre R, Lansner A, De Freitas RM. A Bayesian neural network method for adverse drug reaction signal generation. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 1998;54:315&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9696956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Puijenbroek EP, Diemont WL, van Grootheest K. Application of quantitative signal detection in the Dutch spontaneous reporting system for adverse drug reactions. Drug Saf. 2003;26:293&#x2013;301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12650632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bate A, Evans SJ. Quantitative signal detection using spontaneous ADR reporting. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2009;18(6):427&#x2013;36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19358225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nor&#xe9;n GN, Hopstadius J, Bate A. Shrinkage observed-to-expected ratios for robust and transparent large-scale pattern discovery. Stat Methods Med Res. 2013;22(1):57&#x2013;69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6331976</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21705438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Puijenbroek EP, Bate A, Leufkens HG, Lindquist M, Orre R, Egberts AC. A comparison of measures of disproportionality for signal detection in spontaneous reporting systems for adverse drug reactions. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2002;11(1):3&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11998548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Voss EA, et al. Contextualising adverse events of special interest to characterise the baseline incidence rates in 24 million patients with COVID-19 across 26 databases: a multinational retrospective cohort study. EClinicalMedicine. 2023;1:58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10072853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37034358</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization: COVID-19[Internet]. WHO. https://covid19.who.int/region/afro/country/za. Accessed 18 Oct 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (PAHO). Consolidated regional and global information on adverse events following immunization (AEFI) against COVID-19 and other updates: thirty-fifth report. PAHO. 2022 Apr 30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kant A, van Hunsel F, van Puijenbroek E. Numbers of spontaneous reports: how to use and interpret? Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2022;88(3):1365&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34355808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gianfredi V, Minerva M, Casu G, Capraro M, Chiecca G, Gaetti G, Mazzocchi RM, Musar&#xf2; P, Basteri P, Bertini B, Ferri C. Immediate adverse events following COVID-19 immunization. A cross-sectional study of 314,664 Italian subjects. Acta Bio Med Atenei Parm. 2021;92(Suppl 6):e2021487.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8851022</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34739452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chapin-Bardales J, Gee J, Myers T. Reactogenicity following receipt of mRNA-based COVID-19 vaccines. J Am Med Assoc. 2021;325(21):2201&#x2013;2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33818592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menni C, Klaser K, May A, Polidori L, Capdevila J, Louca P, Sudre CH, Nguyen LH, Drew DA, Merino J, Hu C. Vaccine side-effects and SARS-CoV-2 infection after vaccination in users of the COVID Symptom Study app in the UK: a prospective observational study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2021;21(7):939&#x2013;49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8078878</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33930320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ad26.COV2.S [package insert]. European Medicines Agency: JCOVDEN. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>BNT162b2 [package insert]. European Medicines Agency: Comirnaty. 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centre for Disease Control and Prevention. Myocarditis and Pericarditis. CDC. 2023 Sept 12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Douxfils J, Favresse J, Dogn&#xe9; JM, Lecompte T, Susen S, Cordonnier C, Lebreton A, Gosselin R, Si&#xe9; P, Pernod G, Gruel Y. Hypotheses behind the very rare cases of thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome after SARS-CoV-2 vaccination. Thromb Res. 2021;1(203):163&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8123522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34029848</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sankar C, Meyer JC, Sch&#xf6;nfeldt M, Gunter H, Dawood H, Sekiti V, Pickard N, Mubaiwa L, Mawela D, Dlamini S, Peter J. Vaccine safety surveillance in South Africa through COVID-19: a journey to systems strengthening. Vaccine. 2025;6(46): 126535.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39645433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization: VigiAccess[Internet].WHO. https://www.vigiaccess.org/. Accessed 15 Oct 2023.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>