<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">29623091</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1687-8728</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>2018</Volume><PubDate><Year>2018</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of dentistry</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Dent</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The Prevalence and Underreporting of Needlestick Injuries among Dental Healthcare Workers in Pakistan: A Systematic Review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>9609038</StartPage><MedlinePgn>9609038</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">9609038</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1155/2018/9609038</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Needlestick injuries (NSIs) are a major occupational health problem among dental healthcare workers (HCWs) in Pakistan, which places them at a significant risk of acquiring blood-borne infections. However, not all NSIs are reported, leading to an underestimation of the actual prevalence. The harmful impacts of NSIs on the healthcare delivery necessitate an urgent need to measure its actual prevalence. <i>Objectives</i>. The aim of this study was to review literature to estimate the prevalence and reporting rates of NSIs among dental-HCWs in Pakistan. <i>Methods</i>. 713 potentially relevant citations were identified by electronic databases and hand searching of articles. Nine primary studies were subsequently identified to be included in the review. <i>Results</i>. The results of the included studies indicate that the prevalence of NSIs among Pakistani dental-HCWs was between 30% and 73%. The rate of reporting of NSIs was between 15% and 76%, and the most common reason was found to be the lack of awareness regarding the reporting system, or of the need to report NSIs. <i>Conclusion</i>. It is evident from the review of the included studies that there is a significantly high prevalence and a low rate of reporting of NSIs among dental-HCWs in Pakistan, suggesting the need to setup an occupational health department in dental settings, for preventing, managing, recording, and monitoring NSIs.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pervaiz</LastName><ForeName>Mehak</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5550-4121</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>APPNA Institute of Public Health, Jinnah Sindh Medical University, Karachi, Pakistan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gilbert</LastName><ForeName>Ruth</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Healthcare Practice, University of Bedfordshire, Putteridge Bury, Luton, Bedfordshire LU2 8LE, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ali</LastName><ForeName>Nasreen</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-2017-8482</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Health Research, University of Bedfordshire, Putteridge Bury, Luton, Bedfordshire LU2 8LE, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2018</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Dent</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101524183</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1687-8728</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2017</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2017</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2018</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2018</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2018</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2018</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29623091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5829343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2018/9609038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization&#x2013;WHO. Occupational health, needlestick injuries. 2016.   http://www.who.int/occupational_health/topics/needinjuries/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Health Services&#x2013;NHS. What should I do if I injure myself with a used needle? 2015.   http://www.nhs.uk/chq/Pages/2557.aspx?CategoryID=72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith A., Cameron S., Bagg J., Kennedy D. Management of needlestick injuries in general dental practice. British Dental Journal. 2001;19(12):645&#x2013;650. doi: 10.1038/sj.bdj.4801064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.4801064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11453154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gatto M., Bandini L., Montevecchi M., Checchi L. Occupational exposure to blood and body fluids in a department of oral sciences: results of a thirteen-year surveillance study. The Scientific World Journal. 2013;2013:7. doi: 10.1155/2013/459281.459281</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2013/459281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3586493</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23476136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Canadian Centre for Occupational Health and Safety-CCOHS. Needlestick and sharps injuries. 2015.   http://www.ccohs.ca/oshanswers/diseases/needlestick_injuries.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naghavi S. H., Shabestari O., Alcolado J. Post-traumatic stress disorder in trainee doctors with previous needlestick injuries. Occupational Medicine. 2013;63(4):260&#x2013;265. doi: 10.1093/occmed/kqt027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/occmed/kqt027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23580567</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayatollahi J., Ayatollahi F., Ardekani A., et al. Occupational hazards to dental staff. Dental Research Journal. 2012;9(1):2&#x2013;7. doi: 10.4103/1735-3327.92919.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/1735-3327.92919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3283973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22363355</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centres for Disease Control and Prevention&#x2013;CDC. Infection control. 2013.   http://www.cdc.gov/oralhealth/infectioncontrol/faq/bloodborne_exposures.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rashid H. Needle stick injuries in restorative dentistry: the need for prevention. Journal of Restorative Dentistry. 2014;2(3):p. 157. doi: 10.4103/2321-4619.143601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/2321-4619.143601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaber M. A survey of needle sticks and other sharp injuries among dental undergraduate students. International Journal of Infection Control. 2011;7(3):1&#x2013;10. doi: 10.3396/ijic.v7i3.022.11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3396/ijic.v7i3.022.11</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharma R., Rasania S., Verma A., Singh S. Study of prevalence and response to needle stick injuries among health care workers in a Tertiary Care Hospital in Delhi, India. Indian Journal of Community Medicine. 2010;35(1):74&#x2013;77. doi: 10.4103/0970-0218.62565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0970-0218.62565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2888373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20606925</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alavian S., Mahboobi N. Hepatitis B infection in dentistry setting needs more attention. Medical Principles and Practice. 2011;20(5):491&#x2013;492. doi: 10.1159/000328427.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000328427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21757945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azodo C., Ehigiator O., Ojo M. Occupational risks and hepatitis B vaccination status of dental auxiliaries in Nigeria. Medical Principles and Practice. 2010;19(5):364&#x2013;366. doi: 10.1159/000316374.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000316374</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20639659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singhal V., Bora D., Singh S. Hepatitis B in healthcare workers: Indian scenario. Journal of Laboratory Physicians. 2009;1(2):41&#x2013;48. doi: 10.4103/0974-2727.59697.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0974-2727.59697</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3167966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21938248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kohn W., Collins A., Cleveland J., Harte J., Eklund K., Malvitz D. Guidelines for infection control in dental health-care settings. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report-MMWR. 2003;52(17):1&#x2013;61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14685139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotelchuck D., Murphy D., Younai F. Impact of underreporting on the management of occupational bloodborne exposures in a dental teaching environment. Journal of Dental Education. 2004;68(6):614&#x2013;622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15217080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shahzad M., Hassan S., Memon M., Bashir U., Shams S. Needle stick injuries among dental students, house officers and paradental staff working at Liaquat Medical University Hospital, Hyderabad. Pakistan Oral and Dental Journal. 2013;33(1):23&#x2013;25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Younai F., Murphy D., Kotelchuck D. Occupational exposures to blood in a dental teaching environment: results of a ten-year surveillance study. Journal of Dental Education. 2001;65(5):436&#x2013;448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11425248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ebrahimi S., Shadman N., Ghaempanah I. Needlestick injuries in dentists and their assistants in Kerman, Iran: prevalence, knowledge, and practice. Journal of Oral Health and Oral Epidemiology. 2013;2(1):23&#x2013;27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sawyer M. Preventing Needle-Stick Injuries and the Use of Dental Safety Syringes. Richmond, BC, Canada: Work Safe BC-Workers Compensation Board of British Columbia; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gambhi R., Kapoor V. Knowledge, awareness and practice regarding needle stick injuries in dental profession in India. International Journal of Preventive Medicine. 2015;6:p. 55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4505396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26236442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khader Y., Burgan S., Amarin Z. Self-reported needle stick injuries among dentists in North Jordan. East Mediterranean Health Journal. 2009;15(1):185&#x2013;189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19469442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Askarian M., Malekmakan L. The prevalence of needle stick injuries in medical, dental, nursing and midwifery students at the university teaching hospitals of Shiraz, Iran. Indian Journal of Medical Sciences. 2006;60(6):227&#x2013;232. doi: 10.4103/0019-5359.25904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0019-5359.25904</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16790948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hashemipour M., Sadeghi A. Needlestick injuries among medical and dental students at the University of Kerman. A questionnaire study. Journal of dentistry. 2007;5(2):71&#x2013;76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qureshi H., Bile K. M., Jooma R., Alam S. E., Afridi H. U. Prevalence of hepatitis B and C viral infections in Pakistan: findings of a national survey. East Mediterranean Health Journal. 2010;16(15&#x2013;23)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21495584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jan S., Akhund T., Akhtar M., Shaikh J. Needle stick injuries among dental health care providers: a survey done at Hyderabad and Karachi. Pakistan Oral and Dental Journal. 2014;34(2):339&#x2013;343.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sofola O., Folayan M., Denloye O., Okeigbemen S. Occupational exposure to bloodborne pathogens and management of exposure incidents in Nigerian Dental Schools. Journal of Dental Education. 2007;71(6):832&#x2013;837.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17554101</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pavithran V. K., Murali R., Krishna M., Shamala A., Yalamalli M., Kumar A. Knowledge, attitude, and practice of needle stick and sharps injuries among dental professionals of Bangalore, India. Journal of International Society of preventive and Community Dentistry. 2015;5(5):406&#x2013;412. doi: 10.4103/2231-0762.165932.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/2231-0762.165932</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4606606</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26539394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>STROBE Statement, STROBE checklists, checklist for case-control studies. 2009.   http://www.strobe-statement.org/index.php?id=available-checklists.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyle M. Guidelines for evaluating prevalence studies. Evidence Based Mental Health. 1998;1(2):37&#x2013;39. doi: 10.1136/ebmh.1.2.37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/ebmh.1.2.37</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barreto L., Oliveira F., Nunes S., et al. Epidemiologic study of charcot-marie-tooth disease: a systematic review. Neuro-Epidemiology. 2016;46(3):157&#x2013;165. doi: 10.1159/000443706.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1159/000443706</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26849231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Etemadifar M., Nasr Z., Khalili B., Taherioun M., Vosoughi R. Epidemiology of neuromyelitis optica in the world: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Multiple Sclerosis International. 2015;2015:8. doi: 10.1155/2015/174720.174720</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2015/174720</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4417948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25973275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popay J., Roberts H., Sowden A., et al. Guidance on the Conduct of Narrative Synthesis in Systematic Reviews. Lancaster, UK: Lancaster University; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan R. Cochrane Consumers and Communication Review Group: Data Synthesis and Analysis. 2013.   http://cccrg.cochrane.org/sites/cccrg.cochrane.org/files/uploads/AnalysisRestyled.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brugha T., Matthews R., Morgan Z., Hill T., Alonso J., Jones D. Methodology and reporting of systematic reviews and meta-analyses of observational studies in psychiatric epidemiology: systematic review. British Journal of Psychiatry. 2012;200(6):446&#x2013;453. doi: 10.1192/bjp.bp.111.098103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1192/bjp.bp.111.098103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22661677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boland A., Cherry G., Dickson R. Doing a Systematic Review: a Student&#x2019;s Guide. London, UK: SAGE Publications Ltd.; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins J., Thompson S., Deeks J., Altman D. Measuring inconsistencies in meta-analysis. British Medical Journal. 2003;327(7414):557&#x2013;560. doi: 10.1136/bmj.327.7414.557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.327.7414.557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC192859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12958120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ikram K., Siddiqui H., Maqbool S., Altaf M., Khan S. Frequency of needle stick injury among dental students and dentists in Karachi. World Journal of Dentistry. 2015;6(4):213&#x2013;216. doi: 10.5005/jp-journals-10015-1345.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10015-1345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik A., Shaukat M., Qureshi A. Needle-stick injury: a rising bio-hazard. Journal of Ayub Medical College Abbottabad. 2012;24(3-4):144&#x2013;146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24669637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashfaq M., Chatha M., Sohail A. Awareness of needlestick injuries among the dental health professionals at Lahore Medical and Dental College. Pakistan Oral and Dental Journal. 2011;31(2):255&#x2013;257.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baig M., Baloch S., Muslim M. Estimation of risk of needle stick injury and the level of awareness of prophylaxis among the students, house officers and supporting staff of dentistry. New York Science Journal. 2014;7(1):120&#x2013;123.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gichki A., Islam A., Murad W. Knowledge and awareness about needle stick injuries among dental students of Bolan Medical College, Quetta. Pakistan Oral and Dental Journal. 2015;35(4):562&#x2013;566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan A., Rahim A., Bangash T., Chugtai M., Mehboob Z. Infection control in dentistry knowledge and practice regarding barrier techniques, post exposure management and prophylaxis&#x2013;a study. Pakistan Oral and Dental Journal. 2009;29(2):235&#x2013;240.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehboob B., Khan M., Fahim-ud-din Khan A., Qiam F. Professional hazards among dentists of the two public sector teaching hospitals of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa province of Pakistan. Pakistan Oral and Dental Journal. 2012;32(3):376&#x2013;380.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ansari S., Aldaijy M., Almijlad A., et al. Determining the prevalence and awareness of needlestick injuries among dental health professionals in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. International Journal of Current Research. 2015;7(1):12102&#x2013;12105.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arrieta-Vergara K., Diaz-C&#xe1;rdenas S., Gonz&#xe1;lez-Mart&#xed;nez F. Prevalence of occupational accidents and related factors in students of dentistry. Revista de Salud Publica. 2013;15(1):23&#x2013;31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24892568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barlean L., Danila I., Saveanu I., Balcos C. Occupational health problems among dentists in Moldavian Region of Romania. Revista medico-chirurgicala a Societatii de Medici si Naturalisti din Iasi. 2013;117(3):784&#x2013;788.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24502051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowanadisai S., Kukiattrakoon B., Yapong B., Leggat P. Occupational health problems of dentists in Southern Thailand. International Dental Journal. 2000;50(1):36&#x2013;40. doi: 10.1111/j.1875-595x.2000.tb00544.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1875-595x.2000.tb00544.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10945178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaghagian S., Golkari A., Pardis S., Rezayi A. Occupational exposure of Shiraz Dental Students to patients&#x2019; blood and body fluid. Journal of Dentistry Shiraz University of Medical Sciences. 2015;16(3):206&#x2013;213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4554314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26331151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization&#x2013;WHO. Best Practices for Injections and Related Procedures Toolkit. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO press; 2010.   http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/44298/1/9789241599252_eng.pdf.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23741781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leavy P., Templeton A., Young L., McDonnell C. Reporting of occupational exposures to blood and body fluids in the primary dental care setting in Scotland: an evaluation of current practice and attitudes. British Dental Journal. 2014;217(4):p. E7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25146830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng H., Su C., Yen A., Huang C. Factors affecting occupational exposure to needlestick and sharps injuries among Dentists in Taiwan: a nationwide survey. PLoS One. 2012;7(4) doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0034911.e34911</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3318009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22509367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leggat P., Smith D. Prevalence of percutaneous exposure incidents amongst dentists in Queensland. Australian Dental Journal. 2008;51(2):158&#x2013;161. doi: 10.1111/j.1834-7819.2006.tb00420.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1834-7819.2006.tb00420.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16848264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bindra S., Reddy K., Chakrabarty A., Chaudhary K. Awareness about needle stick injures and sharps disposal: a study conducted at Army College of Dental Sciences. Journal of Maxillofacial and Oral Surgery. 2014;13(4):419&#x2013;424. doi: 10.1007/s12663-013-0526-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12663-013-0526-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4518779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26225005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guruprasad Y., Chauhan D. Knowledge, attitude and practice regarding risk of HIV infection through accidental needlestick injuries among dental students of Raichur, India. National Journal of Maxillofacial Surgery. 2011;2(2):152&#x2013;155. doi: 10.4103/0975-5950.94470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0975-5950.94470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3343388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22639503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins A., Santos N., Lima M., Pereira R., Ferreira R. Needlestick and sharp instrument injuries among dentists in Montes Claros, Brazil. Arquivos em Odontologia. 2010;46(3)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu Y., Zhu J., Huang C., Hu X., Xiong Y. Occupation exposure to blood and body fluids among dental personnel in a Chinese Dental Hospital. Chinese Journal of Dental Research. 2013;16(2):119&#x2013;125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24436947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glanz K., Rimer B., Viswanath K. Health Behavior and Health Education, Theory, Research and Practice. 4th. San Francisco, CA, USA: Jossey-Bass; 2008.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>