<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">36722328</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>01</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0258</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Apr</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Statistics in medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Stat Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>In praise of Prais-Winsten: An evaluation of methods used to account for autocorrelation in interrupted time series.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1277</StartPage><EndPage>1288</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1277-1288</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/sim.9669</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Interrupted time series are increasingly being used to assess the population impact of public health interventions. These data are usually correlated over time (auto correlated) and this must be accounted for in the analysis. Typically, this is done using either the Prais-Winsten method, the Newey-West method, or autoregressive-moving-average (ARMA) modeling. In this paper, we illustrate these methods via a study of pneumococcal vaccine introduction and explore their performance under 20 simulated autocorrelation scenarios with sample sizes ranging between 20 and 300. We show that in terms of mean square error, the Prais-Winsten and ARMA methods perform best, while in terms of coverage the Prais-Winsten method generally performs better than other methods. All three methods are unbiased. As well as having good statistical properties, the Prais-Winsten method is attractive because it is decision-free and produces a single measure of autocorrelation that can be compared between studies and used to guide sample size calculations. We would therefore encourage analysts to consider using this simple method to analyze interrupted time series.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2023 The Authors. Statistics in Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bottomley</LastName><ForeName>C</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-5241-8412</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>London School of Tropical Medicine &amp; Hygiene, MRC International Statistics and Epidemiology Group, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ooko</LastName><ForeName>M</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>London School of Tropical Medicine &amp; Hygiene, MRC International Statistics and Epidemiology Group, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology and Demography, Kemri-Wellcome Trust Research Programme, Kilifi, Kenya.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gasparrini</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Environments and Society, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Statistical Methodology, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Keogh</LastName><ForeName>R H</ForeName><Initials>RH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6504-3253</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medical Statistics, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>MR/R010161/1</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>MR/S017968/1</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Stat Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8215016</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0277-6715</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D065186" MajorTopicYN="Y">Interrupted Time Series Analysis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018401" MajorTopicYN="N">Sample Size</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">autocorrelation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">interrupted time series</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">intervention analysis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36722328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10946734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/sim.9669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bernal JL, Cummins S, Gasparrini A. Interrupted time series regression for the evaluation of public health interventions: a tutorial. Int J Epidemiol. 2017;46(1):348&#x2010;355.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5407170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27283160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wooldridge JM. Chapter 12: serial correlation and heteroskedasticity in time series regressions. Introductory Econometrics: A Modern Approach. fifth ed. Mason, OH: South&#x2010;Western; 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prais SJ, Winsten CB. Trend estimators and serial correlation. Cowles Commission Discussion Paper No. 383. Chicago; 1954.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyndman RJ, Athanasopoulos G. Forecasting: Principles and Practice. second ed. Melbourne, Australia. OTexts.com/fpp2: OTexts; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Box GEP, Tiao GC. Intervention analysis with applications to economic and environmental problems. J Am Stat Assoc. 1975;70(349):70&#x2010;79.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newey WK, West KD. A simple, positive semi&#x2010;definite, heteroskedasticity and autocorrelation consistent covariance matrix. Econom. 1987;55(3):703&#x2010;708.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner SL, Forbes AB, Karahalios A, Taljaard M, McKenzie JE. Evaluation of statistical methods used in the analysis of interrupted time series studies: a simulation study. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2021;21(1):181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8403376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34454418</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKnight SD, McKean JW, Huitema BE. A double bootstrap method to analyze linear models with autoregressive error terms. Psychol Methods. 2000;5(1):87&#x2010;101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10937324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bence JR. Analysis of short time series: correcting for autocorrelation. Ecology. 1995;76(2):628&#x2010;639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alpargu G, Dutilleul P. Efficiency and validity analyses of two&#x2010;stage estimation procedures and derived testing procedures in quantitative linear models with AR(1) errors. Commun Stat Part B: Simul Comput. 2003;32(3):799&#x2010;833.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bottomley C, Scott JAG, Isham V. Analysing interrupted time series with a control. Epidemiol Methods. 2019;8(1):20180010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey A, Koopman SJ. Structural time series models in medicine. Stat Methods Med Res. 1996;5(1):23&#x2010;49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8743077</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton JD. Time Series Analysis. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press; 1994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cochran WG. Some methods for strengthening the common &#x3c7;2 tests. Biometrics. 1954;10(4):417&#x2010;451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akaike H. On the likelihood of a time series model. J R Stat Soc Series D. 1978;27(3/4):217&#x2010;235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyndman RJ, Khandakar Y. Automatic time series forecasting: the forecast package for R. J Stat Softw. 2008;27(3):1&#x2010;22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White H. A heteroskedasticity&#x2010;consistent covariance matrix estimator and a direct test for heteroskedasticity. Econometrica. 1980;48(4):817&#x2010;838.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang KY, Zeger SL. Longitudinal data analysis using generalized linear models. Biometrika. 1986;73(1):13&#x2010;22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newey WK, West KD. Automatic lag selection in covariance matrix estimation. Rev Econ Stud. 1994;61(4):631&#x2010;653.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Andrews DWK. Heteroskedasticity and autocorrelation consistent covariance matrix estimation. Econometrica. 1991;59(3):817&#x2010;858.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus E, Lewis DJ, Stock JH, Watson MW. HAR inference: recommendations for practice. J Bus Econ Stat. 2018;36(4):541&#x2010;559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silaba M, Ooko M, Bottomley C, et al. Effect of 10&#x2010;valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine on the incidence of radiologically&#x2010;confirmed pneumonia and clinically&#x2010;defined pneumonia in Kenyan children: an interrupted time&#x2010;series analysis. Lancet Glob Health. 2019;7(3):e337&#x2010;e346.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6379823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30784634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team . R: a language and environment for statistical computing. Published Online; 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeileis A. Econometric computing with HC and HAC covariance matrix estimators. J Stat Softw. 2004;11(10):1&#x2010;17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohr F. prais: Prais&#x2010;Winsten estimator for AR(1) serial correlation. R Package Version 1.1.1; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner SL, Karahalios A, Forbes AB, Taljaard M, Grimshaw JM, McKenzie JE. Comparison of six statistical methods for interrupted time series studies: empirical evaluation of 190 published series. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2021;21(1):134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8235830</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34174809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheang WK, Reinsel GC. Bias reduction of autoregressive estimates in time series regression model through restricted maximum likelihood. J Am Stat Assoc. 2000;95(452):1173&#x2010;1184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gasparini A. rsimsum: summarise results from Monte Carlo simulation studies. J Open Source Softw. 2018;3(26):739.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kakwani NC. The unbiasedness of Zellner's seemingly unrelated regression equations estimators. J Am Stat Assoc. 1967;62(317):141&#x2010;142.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diggle PJ, Heagerty P, Liang KY, Zeger SL. Analysis of Longitudinal Data. second ed. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press; 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spilke J, Piepho HP, Hu X. A simulation study on tests of hypotheses and confidence intervals for fixed effects in mixed models for blocked experiments with missing data. J Agric Biol Environ Stat. 2005;10(3):374&#x2010;389.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tunnicliffe WG. On the use of marginal likelihood in time series model estimation. J R Stat Soc Series B. 1989;51(1):15&#x2010;27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giesbrecht FG, Burns JC. Two&#x2010;stage analysis based on a mixed model: large&#x2010;sample asymptotic theory and small&#x2010;sample simulation results. Biometrics. 1985;41(2):477&#x2010;486.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fai AHT, Cornelius PL. Approximate f&#x2010;tests of multiple degree of freedom hypotheses in generalized least squares analyses of unbalanced split&#x2010;plot experiments. J Stat Comput Simul. 1996;54(4):363&#x2010;378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kenward MG, Roger JH. Small sample inference for fixed effects from restricted maximum likelihood. Biometrics. 1997;53(3):983&#x2010;997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9333350</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Satterthwhaite FE. An approximate distribution of estimates of variance components. Biometrics. 1946;2(6):110&#x2010;114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20287815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vrieze SI. Model selection and psychological theory: a discussion of the differences between the Akaike information criterion (AIC) and the Bayesian information criterion (BIC). Psychol Methods. 2012;17(2):228&#x2010;243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3366160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22309957</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenander U. On the estimation of regression coefficients in the case of an autocorrelated disturbance. Ann Math Stat. 1954;25(2):252&#x2010;272.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rao P, Griliches Z. Small&#x2010;sample properties of several two&#x2010;stage regression methods in the context of auto&#x2010;correlated errors. J Am Stat Assoc. 1969;64(325):253&#x2010;272.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Spitzer JJ. Small&#x2010;sample properties of nonlinear least squares and maximum likelihood estimators in the context of autocorrelated errors. J Am Stat Assoc. 1979;74(365):41&#x2010;47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatfield C. Model uncertainty, data mining and statistical inference. J R Stat Soc Series A. 1995;158(3):419&#x2010;466.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turner SL, Karahalios A, Forbes AB, et al. Design characteristics and statistical methods used in interrupted time series studies evaluating public health interventions: a review. J Clin Epidemiol. 2020;122:1&#x2010;11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32109503</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>