<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">23271959</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2013</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1549-1676</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>12</Issue><PubDate><Year>2012</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PLoS medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Research on implementation of interventions in tuberculosis control in low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e1001358</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e1001358</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e1001358</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001358</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Several interventions for tuberculosis (TB) control have been recommended by the World Health Organization (WHO) over the past decade. These include isoniazid preventive therapy (IPT) for HIV-infected individuals and household contacts of infectious TB patients, diagnostic algorithms for rule-in or rule-out of smear-negative pulmonary TB, and programmatic treatment for multidrug-resistant TB. There is no systematically collected data on the type of evidence that is publicly available to guide the scale-up of these interventions in low- and middle-income countries. We investigated the availability of published evidence on their effectiveness, delivery, and cost-effectiveness that policy makers need for scaling-up these interventions at country level.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS AND FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">PubMed, Web of Science, EMBASE, and several regional databases were searched for studies published from 1 January 1990 through 31 March 2012 that assessed health outcomes, delivery aspects, or cost-effectiveness for any of these interventions in low- or middle-income countries. Selected studies were evaluated for their objective(s), design, geographical and institutional setting, and generalizability. Studies reporting health outcomes were categorized as primarily addressing efficacy or effectiveness of the intervention. These criteria were used to draw landscapes of published research. We identified 59 studies on IPT in HIV infection, 14 on IPT in household contacts, 44 on rule-in diagnosis, 19 on rule-out diagnosis, and 72 on second-line treatment. Comparative effectiveness studies were relatively few (n = 9) and limited to South America and sub-Saharan Africa for IPT in HIV-infection, absent for IPT in household contacts, and rare for second-line treatment (n = 3). Evaluations of diagnostic and screening algorithms were more frequent (n = 19) but geographically clustered and mainly of non-comparative design. Fifty-four studies evaluated ways of delivering these interventions, and nine addressed their cost-effectiveness.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">There are substantial gaps in published evidence for scale-up for five WHO-recommended TB interventions settings at country level, which for many countries possibly precludes program-wide implementation of these interventions. There is a strong need for rigorous operational research studies to be carried out in programmatic settings to inform on best use of existing and new interventions in TB control.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cobelens</LastName><ForeName>Frank</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Health, Academic Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands. f.cobelens@aighd.org</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van Kampen</LastName><ForeName>Sanne</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ochodo</LastName><ForeName>Eleanor</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Atun</LastName><ForeName>Rifat</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lienhardt</LastName><ForeName>Christian</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2012</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>18</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101231360</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1549-1277</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000995">Antitubercular Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>V83O1VOZ8L</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D007538">Isoniazid</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000465" MajorTopicYN="N">Algorithms</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000995" MajorTopicYN="N">Antitubercular Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D060085" MajorTopicYN="N">Coinfection</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003362" MajorTopicYN="N">Cost-Benefit Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003695" MajorTopicYN="Y">Delivery of Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000191" MajorTopicYN="N">economics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003906" MajorTopicYN="Y">Developing Countries</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019317" MajorTopicYN="N">Evidence-Based Medicine</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007538" MajorTopicYN="N">Isoniazid</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016730" MajorTopicYN="Y">Program Development</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014397" MajorTopicYN="N">Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="Y">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="Y">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2011</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2012</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2012</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2012</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2013</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2012</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23271959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3525528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001358</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PMEDICINE-D-11-00938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>(2010) Global tuberculosis control: a short update to the 2009 report. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stop TB Partnership, World Health Organization (2010) The Global Plan to Stop TB, 2011&#x2013;2015. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lienhardt C, Cobelens FGJ (2011) Operational research for improved tuberculosis control: the scope, the needs and the way forward. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 15: 6&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21276290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sch&#xfc;nemann HJ, Sch&#xfc;nemann AHJ, Oxman AD, Brozek J, Glasziou P, et al. (2008) Grading quality of evidence and strength of recommendations for diagnostic tests and strategies. BMJ 336: 1106&#x2013;1110.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2386626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18483053</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Last JM (2000) A dictionary of epidemiology. 4th edition. New York: Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Sanders D, Haines A (2006) Implementation research is needed to achieve international health goals. PLoS Med
3: e186
doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.0030186.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1472551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16729844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thiam S, LeFevre AM, Hane F, Ndiaye A, Ba F, et al. (2007) Effectiveness of a strategy to improve adherence to tuberculosis treatment in a resource-poor setting: a cluster randomized controlled trial. JAMA 297: 380&#x2013;386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17244834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pai M, Minion J, Steingart K, Ramsay A (2010) New and improved tuberculosis diagnostics: evidence, policy, practice, and impact. Curr Opin Pulm Med 16: 271&#x2013;284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20224410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mann G, Squire SB, Bissell K, Eliseev P, Du Toit E, et al. (2010) Beyond accuracy: creating a comprehensive evidence base for TB diagnostic tools. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 14: 1518&#x2013;1524.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21144235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vassall A, Compernolle P (2006) Estimating the resource needs of scaling-up HIV/AIDS and tuberculosis interventions in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic review for national policy makers and planners. Health Policy 79: 1&#x2013;15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16388874</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuberculosis (z.d.). Available: http://www.stoptb.org/global/plan/main/default.asp. Accessed 2 Nov 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Onozaki I, Raviglione M (2010) Stopping tuberculosis in the 21st century: goals and strategies. Respirology 15: 32&#x2013;43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20199633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stop TB Partnership: TB/HIV working group (2003) Guidelines for implementing collaborative TB and HIV programme activities. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (2006) Guidance for national tuberculosis programmes on the management of tuberculosis in children. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24999516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2003) Treatment of tuberculosis: guidelines for national programmes. 3rd edition. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2007) Improving the diagnosis and treatment of smear-negative pulmonary and extrapulmonary tuberculosis among adults and adolescents. Recommendations for HIV-prevalent and resource-constrained settings. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2000) Guidelines for establishing DOTS-PLUS pilot projects for the management of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB). Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durovni B, Cavalcante SC, Saraceni V, Vellozo V, Israel G, et al. (2010) The implementation of isoniazid preventive therapy in HIV clinics: the experience from the TB/HIV in Rio (THRio) study. AIDS 24 Suppl 5: S49&#x2013;56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3066070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21079428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant AD, Coetzee L, Fielding KL, Lewis JJ, Ntshele S, et al. (2010) &#x201c;Team up against TB&#x201d;: promoting involvement in Thibela TB, a trial of community-wide tuberculosis preventive therapy. AIDS 24 Suppl 5: S37&#x2013;44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21079426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mello FC de Q, Bastos LG do V, Soares SLM, Rezende VMC, Conde MB, et al. (2006) Predicting smear negative pulmonary tuberculosis with classification trees and logistic regression: a cross-sectional study. BMC Public Health 6: 43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1402281</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16504086</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lambert ML, Sugulle H, Seyoum D, Abdurahman S, Abdinasir A, et al. (2003) How can detection of infectious tuberculosis be improved? Experience in the Somali region of Ethiopia. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 7: 485&#x2013;488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12757051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (2007) Improving the diagnosis and treatment of smear-negative pulmonary and extrapulmonary tuberculosis among adults and adolescents Recommendations for HIV-prevalent and resource-constrained settings. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holtz TH, Kabera G, Mthiyane T, Zingoni T, Nadesan S, et al. (2011) Use of a WHO-recommended algorithm to reduce mortality in seriously ill patients with HIV infection and smear-negative pulmonary tuberculosis in South Africa: an observational cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis 11: 533&#x2013;540.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21514234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walley J, Kunutsor S, Evans M, Thoulass J, Katabira E, et al. (2011) Validation in Uganda of the new WHO diagnostic algorithm for smear-negative pulmonary tuberculosis in HIV prevalent settings. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr 57: e93&#x2013;100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21637111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soto A, Solari L, Gotuzzo E, Acinelli R, Vargas D, et al. (2011) Performance of an algorithm based on WHO recommendations for the diagnosis of smear-negative pulmonary tuberculosis in patients without HIV infection. Trop Med Int Health 16: 424&#x2013;430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21208352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Koole O, Thai S, Khun KE, Pe R, van Griensven J, et al.  (2011) Evaluation of the 2007 WHO guideline to improve the diagnosis of tuberculosis in ambulatory HIV-positive adults. PLoS ONE
6: e18502
doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0018502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0018502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3071837</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21494694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson D, Mbhele L, Badri M, Morroni C, Nachega J, et al. (2011) Evaluation of the World Health Organization algorithm for the diagnosis of HIV-associated sputum smear-negative tuberculosis. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 15: 919&#x2013;924.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21682965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen DTM, Hung NQ, Giang LT, Dung NH, Lan NTN, et al. (2011) Improving the diagnosis of pulmonary tuberculosis in HIV-infected individuals in Ho Chi Minh City, Viet Nam. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 15: 1528&#x2013;1534.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22008768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Deun A, Maug AKJ, Salim MAH, Das PK, Sarker MR, et al. (2010) Short, highly effective, and inexpensive standardized treatment of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 182: 684&#x2013;692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20442432</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loveday M, Wallengren K, Voce A, Margot B, Reddy T, et al. (2012) Comparing early treatment outcomes of MDR-TB in decentralised and centralised settings in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 16: 209&#x2013;215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3281510</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22236922</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leimane V, Dravniece G, Riekstina V, Sture I, Kammerer S, et al. (2010) Treatment outcome of multidrug/extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis in Latvia, 2000&#x2013;2004. Eur. Respir J 36: 584&#x2013;593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20185428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Podewils LJ, Holtz T, Riekstina V, Skripconoka V, Zarovska E, et al. (2011) Impact of malnutrition on clinical presentation, clinical course, and mortality in MDR-TB patients. Epidemiol Infect 139: 113&#x2013;120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20429966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark PM, Karagoz T, Apikoglu-Rabus S, Izzettin FV (2007) Effect of pharmacist-led patient education on adherence to tuberculosis treatment. Am J Health Syst Pharm 64: 497&#x2013;505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17322163</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kunawararak P, Pongpanich S, Chantawong S, Pokaew P, Traisathit P, et al. (2011) Tuberculosis treatment with mobile-phone medication reminders in northern Thailand. Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health 42: 1444&#x2013;1451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22299414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quelapio MID, Mira NRC, Orillaza-Chi RB, Belen V, Mu&#xf1;ez N, et al. (2010) Responding to the multidrug-resistant tuberculosis crisis: mainstreaming programmatic management to the Philippine National Tuberculosis Programme. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 14: 751&#x2013;757.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20487615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heller T, Lessells RJ, Wallrauch CG, B&#xe4;rnighausen T, Cooke GS, et al. (2010) Community-based treatment for multidrug-resistant tuberculosis in rural KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 14: 420&#x2013;426.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20202299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Acha J, Sweetland A, Guerra D, Chalco K, Castillo H, et al. (2007) Psychosocial support groups for patients with multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: five years of experience. Glob Public Health 2: 404&#x2013;417.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19283636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Bonnet M, Pardini M, Meacci F, Orr&#xf9; G, Yesilkaya H, et al.  (2011) Treatment of tuberculosis in a region with high drug resistance: outcomes, drug resistance amplification and re-infection. PLoS ONE
6: e23081
doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0023081.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3160294</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21886778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith PG, Morrow RH (1991) Methods for field trials of interventions against tropical diseases: a toolbox. New York: Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray DM (1998) Design and analysis of group-randomized trials. 1st edition. New York: Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Gambia Hepatitis Study Group (1987) The Gambia Hepatitis Intervention Study. Cancer Res 47: 5782&#x2013;5787.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2822233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hussey MA, Hughes JP (2007) Design and analysis of stepped wedge cluster randomized trials. Contemp Clin Trials 28: 182&#x2013;191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16829207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown CA, Lilford RJ (2006) The stepped wedge trial design: a systematic review. BMC Med Res Methodol 6: 54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1636652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17092344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Squire SB, Ramsay ARC, van den Hof S, Millington KA, Langley I, et al. (2011) Making innovations accessible to the poor through implementation research. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 15: 862&#x2013;870.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21682960</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathanson E, Gupta R, Huamani P, Leimane V, Pasechnikov AD, et al. (2004) Adverse events in the treatment of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis: results from the DOTS-Plus initiative. Int J. Tuberc Lung Dis 8: 1382&#x2013;1384.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15581210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nathanson E, Lambregts-van Weezenbeek C, Rich ML, Gupta R, Bayona J, et al. (2006) Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis management in resource-limited settings. Emerging Infect Dis 12: 1389&#x2013;1397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3294733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17073088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Dwan K, Altman DG, Arnaiz JA, Bloom J, Chan A-W, et al.  (2008) Systematic review of the empirical evidence of study publication bias and outcome reporting bias. PLoS ONE
3: e3081
doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003081.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003081</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2518111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18769481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Getahun H, Granich R, Sculier D, Gunneberg C, Blanc L, et al. (2010) Implementation of isoniazid preventive therapy for people living with HIV worldwide: barriers and solutions. AIDS 24 Suppl 5: S57&#x2013;65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21079430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leung CC, Rieder HL, Lange C, Yew WW (2011) Treatment of latent infection with Mycobacterium tuberculosis: update 2010. Eur Respir J 37: 690&#x2013;711.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20693257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Getahun H, Harrington M, O'Brien R, Nunn P (2007) Diagnosis of smear-negative pulmonary tuberculosis in people with HIV infection or AIDS in resource-constrained settings: informing urgent policy changes. Lancet 369: 2042&#x2013;2049.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17574096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Cobelens FGJ, Heldal E, Kimerling ME, Mitnick CD, Podewils LJ, et al.  (2008) Scaling up programmatic management of drug-resistant tuberculosis: a prioritized research agenda. PLoS Med
5: e150
doi:10.1371/journal.pmed.0050150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2443187</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18613746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mount FW, Ferebee SH (1961) Preventive effects of isoniazid in the treatment of primary tuberculosis in children. N Engl J Med 265: 713&#x2013;721.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14476667</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferebee SH, Mount FW (1962) Tuberculosis morbidity in a controlled trial of the prophylactic use of isoniazid among household contacts. Am. Rev Respir Dis 85: 490&#x2013;510.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13892318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egsmose T, Ang'awa JO, Poti SJ (1965) The use of isoniazid among household contacts of open cases of pulmonary tuberculosis. Bull World Health Organ 33: 419&#x2013;433.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2475854</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5321762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Del Castillo H, Bautista L, Jacinto C, Lorenzo C, Lapuz S, et al. (1965) Chemoprophylaxis in the Philippines. A controlled pilot study among household contacts of tuberculosis cases. Bull Quezon Institute 7: 277&#x2013;290.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comstock GW, Ferebee SH, Hammes LM (1967) A controlled trial of community-wide isoniazid prophylaxis in Alaska. Am Rev Respir Dis 95: 935&#x2013;943.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6026165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kochi A (1997) Tuberculosis control&#x2013;is DOTS the health breakthrough of the 1990s? World Health Forum 18: 225&#x2013;232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9478136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stop TB Partnership (2011) An international roadmap for tuberculosis research. Geneva: World Health Organization. Available: www.stoptb.org/assets/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stop TB Partnership, The Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria (2011) Priorities in operational research to improve tuberculosis care and control. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marais BJ, Raviglione MC, Donald PR, Harries AD, Kritski AL, et al. (2010) Scale-up of services and research priorities for diagnosis, management, and control of tuberculosis: a call to action. Lancet 375: 2179&#x2013;2191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20488521</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (2011) Use of tuberculosis interferon-gamma release assays (IGRAs) in low- and middle-income countries: policy statement.WHO/HTM/TB/2011.18. Available: http://www.who.int/tb/publications/2011/en/index.html. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26269875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2006) WHO Report 2006. Tuberculosis control: surveillance, planning, financing. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>(2008) Anti-tuberculosis drug resistance in the world. Fourth global report. Geneva: World Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thorpe KE, Zwarenstein M, Oxman AD, Treweek S, Furberg CD, et al. (2009) A pragmatic-explanatory continuum indicator summary (PRECIS): a tool to help trial designers. J Clin Epidemiol 62: 464&#x2013;475.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19348971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cain KP, McCarthy KD, Heilig CM, Monkongdee P, Tasaneeyapan T, et al. (2010) An algorithm for tuberculosis screening and diagnosis in people with HIV. N Engl J Med 362: 707&#x2013;716.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20181972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monkongdee P, McCarthy KD, Cain KP, Tasaneeyapan T, Nguyen HD, et al. (2009) Yield of acid-fast smear and mycobacterial culture for tuberculosis diagnosis in people with human immunodeficiency virus. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 180: 903&#x2013;908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19628775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>