<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37153208</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0361-1981</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>2677</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Transportation research record</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Transp Res Rec</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impacts of Daily Travel by Distances on the Spread of COVID-19: An Artificial Neural Network Model.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>934</StartPage><EndPage>945</EndPage><MedlinePgn>934-945</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1177/03611981211066899</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The continued spread of COVID-19 poses significant threats to the safety of the community. Since it is still uncertain when the pandemic will end, it is vital to understand the factors contributing to new cases of COVID-19, especially from the transportation perspective. This paper examines the effect of the United States residents' daily trips by distances on the spread of COVID-19 in the community. The artificial neural network method is used to construct and test the predictive model using data collected from two sources: Bureau of Transportation Statistics and the COVID-19 Tracking Project. The dataset uses ten daily travel variables by distances and new tests from March to September 2020, with a sample size of 10,914. The results indicate the importance of daily trips at different distances in predicting the spread of COVID-19. More specifically, trips shorter than 3&#x2009;mi and trips between 250 and 500&#x2009;mi contribute most to predicting daily new cases of COVID-19. Additionally, daily new tests and trips between 10 and 25&#x2009;mi are among the variables with the lowest effects. This study's findings can help governmental authorities evaluate the risk of COVID-19 infection based on residents' daily travel behaviors and form necessary strategies to mitigate the risks. The developed neural network can be used to predict the infection rate and construct various scenarios for risk assessment and control.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; National Academy of Sciences: Transportation Research Board 2022.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Truong</LastName><ForeName>Dothang</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6900-6916</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Graduate Studies, Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University, Daytona Beach, FL.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Truong</LastName><ForeName>My D</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>College of Business, University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Transp Res Rec</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101481512</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0361-1981</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">artificial intelligence and advanced computing applications</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">data and data science</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health and transportation metrics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">neural networks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">statistical methods</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sustainability and resilience</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transportation and public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transportation and society</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>41</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>13</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37153208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10149352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/03611981211066899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1177_03611981211066899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). United States COVID-19 Cases and Deaths by State. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention COVID Data Tracker, 2020. https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#cases_casesinlast7days. Accessed October 13, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moreland A., Herlihy C., Tynan M. A., Sunshine G., McCord R. F., Hilton C., Poovey J., et al. Timing of State and Territorial COVID-19 Stay-at-Home Orders and Changes in Population Movement&#x2014;United States, March 1&#x2013;May 31, 2020. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report, Vol. 69, No. 35, 2020, p. 1198.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7470456</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32881851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bureau of Transportation Statistics (BTSa). Daily Travel During the COVID-19 Public Health Emergency. BTS Statistical Products and Data, 2020. https://www.bts.gov/browse-statistical-products-and-data/trips-distance/daily-travel-during-covid-19-pandemic. Accessed October 12, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Bruin Y. B., Lequarre A. S., McCourt J., Clevestig P., Pigazzani F., Jeddi M. Z., Colosio C., Goulart M.Initial Impacts of Global Risk Mitigation Measures Taken During the Combatting of the COVID-19 Pandemic. Safety Science, Vol. 128, 2020, p. 104773.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7158845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32296266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gostic K., Gomez A. C., Mummah R. O., Kucharski A. J., Lloyd-Smith J. O. Estimated Effectiveness of Symptom and Risk Screening to Prevent the Spread of COVID-19. eLife, Vol. 9, 2020, p. e55570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7060038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32091395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linka K., Rahman P., Goriely A., Kuhl E.Is It Safe to Lift COVID-19 Travel Bans? The Newfoundland Story. Computational Mechanics, Vol. 66, No. 5, 2020, pp. 1081&#x2013;1092.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7456209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32904431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Vos J. The Effect of COVID-19 and Subsequent Social Distancing on Travel Behavior. Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives, Vol. 5, 2020, p. 100121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7180344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34171016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beck M. J., Hensher D. A.Insights Into the Impact of COVID-19 on Household Travel and Activities in Australia&#x2013;The Early Days Under Restrictions. Transport Policy, Vol. 96, 2020, pp. 76&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7330570</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong D., Truong M. D.Projecting Daily Travel Behavior by Distance During the Pandemic and the Spread of COVID-19 Infections&#x2013;Are We in a Closed Loop Scenario? Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives, Vol. 9, 2021, p. 100283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7836771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33763643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang S., Pierson E., Koh P. W., Gerardin J., Redbird B., Grusky D., Leskovec J.Mobility Network Models of COVID-19 Explain Inequities and Inform Reopening. Nature, Vol. 589, No. 7840, 2021, pp. 82&#x2013;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33171481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nouvellet P., Bhatia S., Cori A., Ainslie K. E., Baguelin M., Bhatt S., Boonyasiri A., et al. Reduction in Mobility and COVID-19 Transmission. Nature Communications, Vol. 12, No. 1, 2021, pp. 1&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7889876</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33597546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carten&#xec; A., Di Francesco L., Martino M.How Mobility Habits Influenced the Spread of the COVID-19 Pandemic: Results From the Italian Case Study. The Science of the Total Environment, Vol. 741, 2020, p.140489.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7313484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32599395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenelius E., Cebecauer M.Impacts of COVID-19 on Public Transport Ridership in Sweden: Analysis of Ticket Validations, Sales and Passenger Counts. Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives, Vol. 8, 2020, p. 100242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7575262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34173478</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borkowski P., Ja&#x17c;d&#x17c;ewska-Gutta M., Szmelter-Jarosz A.Lockdowned: Everyday Mobility Changes in Response to COVID-19. Journal of Transport Geography, Vol. 90, 2021, p. 102906.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9188832</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35721765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badr H. S., Du H., Marshall M., Dong E., Squire M. M., Gardner L. M.Association Between Mobility Patterns and COVID-19 Transmission in the USA: A Mathematical Modelling Study. The Lancet Infectious Diseases, Vol. 20, No. 11, 2020, pp. 1247&#x2013;1254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7329287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32621869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pawar D. S., Yadav A. K., Akolekar N., Velaga N. R.Impact of Physical Distancing due to Novel Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) on Daily Travel for Work During Transition to Lockdown. Transportation Research Interdisciplinary Perspectives, Vol. 7, 2020, p. 100203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7437436</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34173467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong D.Estimating the Impact of COVID-19 on Air Travel in the Medium and Long Term Using Neural Network and Monte Carlo Simulation. Journal of Air Transport Management, Vol. 96, 2021, p. 102126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9759209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36569042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). COVID-19 Forecasts: Deaths. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, August31, 2020. https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/COVID-data/forecasting-us.html.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID-19 Simulator Consortium. COVID-19 Policy Simulator. MGH Institute for Technology Assessment, August31, 2020. https://www.COVID19sim.org/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation (IHME). COVID-19 Model FAQs. Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, August30, 2020. http://www.healthdata.org/COVID/faqs#Scenarios.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuffery S.Data Mining and Statistics for Decision Making. Chichester, Hoboken, NJ; Wiley, West Sussex, 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong D., Choi W.Using Machine Learning Algorithms to Predict the Risk of Small Unmanned Aircraft System Violations in the National Airspace System. Journal of Air Transport Management, Vol. 86, 2020, p. 101822.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haykin S. S.Neural Networks and Learning Machines, 3rd ed.Prentice Hall/Pearson, New York, NY, 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarma K. S.Predictive Modeling With SAS Enterprise Miner &#x2013; Practical Solutions for Business Applications, 2nd ed.SAS Press, Cary, NC, 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieira S., Pinaya W. H., Mechelli A.Using Deep Learning to Investigate the Neuroimaging Correlates of Psychiatric and Neurological Disorders: Methods and Applications. Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews, Vol. 74, 2017, pp. 58&#x2013;75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28087243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>COVID Tracking Project. United States Historical Data. The COVID Tracking Project, October12, 2020. https://covidtracking.com/data.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maryland Transportation Institute (MTI). Institutes, Centers, and Labs. University of Maryland, 2020. https://mti.umd.edu/research/institutes-labs-centers.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center for Advanced Transportation Technology (CATT). Center for Advanced Transportation Technology Research. University of Maryland, 2020. http://www.catt.umd.edu/research.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bureau of Transportation Statistics (BTS). Trips by Distance Data Source. BTS Statistical Products and Data, 2020. https://data.bts.gov/Research-and-Statistics/Trips-by-Distance/w96p-f2qv.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong D., Friend M. A., Chen H.Applications of Business Analytics in Predicting Flight on-Time Performance in a Complex and Dynamic System. Transportation Journal, Vol. 57, No. 1, 2018, pp. 24&#x2013;52.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>