<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37528626</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2026</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>11</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0258</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>42</Volume><Issue>24</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>30</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Statistics in medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Stat Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A guide to regression discontinuity designs in medical applications.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>4484</StartPage><EndPage>4513</EndPage><MedlinePgn>4484-4513</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/sim.9861</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We present a practical guide for the analysis of regression discontinuity (RD) designs in biomedical contexts. We begin by introducing key concepts, assumptions, and estimands within both the continuity-based framework and the local randomization framework. We then discuss modern estimation and inference methods within both frameworks, including approaches for bandwidth or local neighborhood selection, optimal treatment effect point estimation, and robust bias-corrected inference methods for uncertainty quantification. We also overview empirical falsification tests that can be used to support key assumptions. Our discussion focuses on two particular features that are relevant in biomedical research: (i) fuzzy RD designs, which often arise when therapeutic treatments are based on clinical guidelines, but patients with scores near the cutoff are treated contrary to the assignment rule; and (ii) RD designs with discrete scores, which are ubiquitous in biomedical applications. We illustrate our discussion with three empirical applications: the effect CD4 guidelines for anti-retroviral therapy on retention of HIV patients in South Africa, the effect of genetic guidelines for chemotherapy on breast cancer recurrence in the United States, and the effects of age-based patient cost-sharing on healthcare utilization in Taiwan. Complete replication materials employing publicly available data and statistical software in Python, R and Stata are provided, offering researchers all necessary tools to conduct an RD analysis.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2023 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cattaneo</LastName><ForeName>Matias D</ForeName><Initials>MD</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0493-7506</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Operations Research and Financial Engineering, Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Keele</LastName><ForeName>Luke</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3859-2713</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Surgery, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Titiunik</LastName><ForeName>Roc&#xed;o</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5145-3059</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dept. of Politics, Princeton University, Princeton, New Jersey, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 GM072611-16</GrantID><Agency>Foundation for the National Institutes of Health</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SES-2019432</GrantID><Agency>National Science Foundation</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><GrantID>SES-2241575</GrantID><Agency>National Science Foundation</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Stat Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8215016</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0277-6715</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012044" MajorTopicYN="N">Regression Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001943" MajorTopicYN="N">Breast Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017143" MajorTopicYN="N">Fuzzy Logic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012107" MajorTopicYN="N">Research Design</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D035843" MajorTopicYN="Y">Biomedical Research</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003627" MajorTopicYN="N">Data Interpretation, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">causal inference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">natural experiments</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">regression discontinuity</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2026</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>56</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>2</Hour><Minute>2</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37528626</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/sim.9861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Craig P, Katikireddi SV, Leyland A, Popham F. Natural experiments: An overview of methods, approaches, and contributions to public health intervention research. Annu Rev Public Health. 2017;38:39-56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hern&#xe1;n MA. The C-word: Scientific euphemisms do not improve causal inference from observational data. Am J Public Health. 2018;108(5):616-619.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hern&#xe1;n MA, Robins JM. Causal Inference: What If. Boca Raton: Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR. Design of Observational Studies. New York, NY: Springer; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imbens GW, Rubin DB. Causal Inference in Statistics, Social, and Biomedical Sciences. New York, NY: Cambridge University Press; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abadie A, Cattaneo MD. Econometric methods for program evaluation. Annu Rev Econom. 2018;10:465-503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bor J, Moscoe E, Mutevedzi P, Newell ML, B&#xe4;rnighausen T. Regression discontinuity designs in epidemiology: Causal inference without randomized trials. Epidemiology. 2014;25(5):729-737.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Keeffe AG, Geneletti S, Baio G, Sharples LD, Nazareth I, Petersen I. Regression discontinuity designs: An approach to the evaluation of treatment efficacy in primary care using observational data. BMJ. 2014;349:g5293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bor J, Moscoe E, B&#xe4;rnighausen T. Three approaches to causal inference in regression discontinuity designs. Epidemiology. 2015;26(2):e28-e30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maciejewski ML, Basu A. Regression discontinuity design. JAMA. 2020;324(4):381-382.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Titiunik R. Natural experiments. In: Druckman JN, Gree DP, eds. Advances in Experimental Political Science. New York, NY: Cambridge University Press; 2021:103-129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boon MH, Craig P, Thomson H, Campbell M, Moore L. Regression discontinuity designs in health: A systematic review. Epidemiology. 2021;32(1):87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thistlethwaite DL, Campbell DT. Regression-discontinuity analysis: An alternative to the ex-post facto experiment. J Educ Psychol. 1960;51(6):309-317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Titiunik R. Regression discontinuity designs. Annu Rev Econom. 2022;14:821-851.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Idrobo N, Titiunik R. A practical introduction to regression discontinuity designs: Foundations. Cambridge elements: Quantitative and Computational Methods for Social Science. New York, NY: Cambridge University Press; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Idrobo N, Titiunik R. A practical introduction to regression discontinuity designs: Extensions. Cambridge Elements: Quantitative and Computational Methods for Social Science. New York, NY: Cambridge University Press; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bor J, Fox MP, Rosen S, et al. Treatment eligibility and retention in clinical HIV care: A regression discontinuity study in South Africa. PLoS Med. 2017;14(11):e1002463.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanser F, Hosegood V, B&#xe4;rnighausen T, et al. Cohort profile: Africa centre demographic information system (ACDIS) and population-based HIV survey. Int J Epidemiol. 2007;37(5):956-962.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houlihan CF, Bland RM, Mutevedzi PC, et al. Cohort profile: Hlabisa HIV treatment and care programme. Int J Epidemiol. 2010;40(2):318-326.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calonico S, Cattaneo MD, Titiunik R. Optimal data-driven regression discontinuity plots. J Am Stat Assoc. 2015;110(512):1753-1769.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korting C, Lieberman C, Matsudaira J, Pei Z, Shen Y. Visual inference and graphical representation in regression discontinuity designs. Q J Econ. 2023;138(3):1977-2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCrary J. Manipulation of the running variable in the regression discontinuity design: A density test. J Econ. 2008;142(2):698-714.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Crump RK, Farrell MH, Feng Y. On Binscatter. arXiv preprint, arXiv:1902.09608 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Titiunik R, Vazquez-Bare G. Comparing inference approaches for RD designs: A reexamination of the effect of head start on child mortality. J Policy Anal Manage. 2017;36(3):643-681.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hahn J, Todd P, Klaauw vdW. Identification and estimation of treatment effects with a regression-discontinuity design. Econometrica. 2001;69(1):201-209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Keele L, Titiunik R, Vazquez-Bare G. Extrapolating treatment effects in multi-cutoff regression discontinuity designs. J Am Stat Assoc. 2021;116(536):1941-1952.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Frandsen B, Titiunik R. Randomization inference in the regression discontinuity design: An application to party advantages in the U.S Senate. J Causal Inference. 2015;3(1):1-24.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong Y. Alternative assumptions to identify LATE in fuzzy regression discontinuity designs. Oxf Bull Econ Stat. 2018;80(5):1020-1027.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Keele L, Titiunik R, Vazquez-Bare G. Interpreting regression discontinuity designs with multiple cutoffs. J Polit. 2016;78(4):1229-1248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arai Y, Hsu Y, Kitagawa T, Mourifi&#xe9; I, Wan Y. Testing identifying assumptions in fuzzy regression discontinuity designs. Quant Econ. 2022;13(1):1-28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baiocchi M, Cheng J, Small DS. Instrumental variable methods for causal inference. Stat Med. 2014;33(13):2297-2340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaptchuk TJ, Miller FG. Placebo effects in medicine. N Engl J Med. 2015;373(1):8-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan J, Gijbels I. Local polynomial Modelling and Its Applications. Vol 66. Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press; 1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calonico S, Cattaneo MD, Titiunik R. Robust nonparametric confidence intervals for regression-discontinuity designs. Econometrica. 2014;82(6):2295-2326.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calonico S, Cattaneo MD, Farrell MH, Titiunik R. Regression discontinuity designs using covariates. Rev Econ Stat. 2019;101(3):442-451.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Vazquez-Bare G. The Choice of neighborhood in regression discontinuity designs. Observat Stud. 2016;2:134-146.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calonico S, Cattaneo MD, Farrell MH. Optimal bandwidth choice for robust bias corrected inference in regression discontinuity designs. Econ J. 2020;23(2):192-210.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu KL. Regression discontinuity with categorical outcomes. J Econ. 2017;201(1):1-18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arai Y, Ichimura H. Simultaneous selection of optimal bandwidths for the sharp regression discontinuity estimator. Quant Econ. 2018;9(1):441-482.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong Y, Lee YY, Gou M. Regression discontinuity designs with a continuous treatment. J Am Stat Assoc. 2021;118(541):208-221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arai Y, Otsu T, Seo MH. Regression discontinuity design with potentially many covariates. arXiv preprint, arXiv:2109.08351 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calonico S, Cattaneo MD, Farrell MH. On the effect of bias estimation on coverage accuracy in nonparametric inference. J Am Stat Assoc. 2018;113(522):767-779.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calonico S, Cattaneo MD, Farrell MH. Coverage error optimal confidence intervals for local polynomial regression. Bernoulli. 2022;28(4):2998-3022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kamat V. On Nonparametric Inference in the Regression Discontinuity Design. Economet Theor. 2018;34(3):694-703.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuvaandorj P. Regression discontinuity designs, white noise models, and minimax. J Econ. 2020;218(2):587-608.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganong P, J&#xe4;ger S. A permutation test for the regression kink design. J Am Stat Assoc. 2018;113(522):494-504.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyytinen A, Meril&#xe4;inen J, Saarimaa T, Toivanen O, Tukiainen J. When does regression discontinuity design work? Evidence from random election outcomes. Quant Econ. 2018;9(2):1019-1051.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Magalh&#xe3;es L, Hangartner D, Hirvonen S, Meril&#xe4;inen J, Ruiz N, Tukiainen J. How much should we trust regression discontinuity design estimates? Evidence from Experimental Benchmarks of the Incumbency Advantage. working paper. Turku: Aboa Centre for Economics (ACE); 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Keele L, Titiunik R. Covariate adjustment in regression discontinuity designs. In: Small DS, Zubizarreta JR, Rosenbaum PR, eds. Handbook of Matching and Weighting in Causal Inference. Boca Raton, FL: Chapman &amp; Hall; 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ernst MD. Permutation methods: A basis for exact inference. Stat Sci. 2004;19(4):676-685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keele LJ, Small DS, Grieve R. Randomization based instrumental variables methods for binary outcomes with an application to the IMPROVE trial. J R Stat Soc Ser A. 2017;180(2):569-586.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang H, Peck L, Keele L. Inference for instrumental variables: A randomization inference approach. J R Stat Soc Ser A. 2018;181(4):1231-1254.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekhon JS, Titiunik R. Understanding regression discontinuity designs as observational studies. Observat Stud. 2016;2:174-182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sekhon JS, Titiunik R. On interpreting the regression discontinuity design as a local experiment. In: Cattaneo MD, Escanciano JC, eds. Regression Discontinuity Designs: Theory and Applications (Advances in Econometrics). Vol 38. Bingley, UK: Emerald Group Publishing; 2017:1-28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cattaneo MD, Jansson M, Ma X. Simple local polynomial density estimators. J Am Stat Assoc. 2020;115(531):1449-1455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Glymour MM, Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ, Robins JM. Credible mendelian randomization studies: Approaches for evaluating the instrumental variable assumptions. Am J Epidemiol. 2012;175(4):332-339.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pizer SD. Falsification testing of instrumental variables methods for comparative effectiveness research. Health Serv Res. 2016;51(2):790-811.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keele LJ, Zhao Q, Kelz RR, Small DS. Falsification tests for instrumental variable designs with an application to tendency to operate. Med Care. 2019;57(2):167-171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feir D, Lemieux T, Marmer V. Weak identification in fuzzy regression discontinuity designs. J Bus Econ Stat. 2016;34(2):185-196.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies NM, Thomas KH, Taylor AE, et al. How to compare instrumental variable and conventional regression analyses using negative controls and bias plots. Int J Epidemiol. 2017;46(6):2067-2077.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Branson Z, Keele L. Evaluating a key instrumental variable assumption using randomization tests. Am J Epidemiol. 2020;189(11):1412-1420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han HW, Lien HM, Yang TT. Patient cost-sharing and healthcare utilization in early childhood: evidence from a regression discontinuity design. Am Econ J Econ Pol. 2020;12(3):238-278.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paik S, Tang G, Shak S, et al. Gene expression and benefit of chemotherapy in women with node-negative, estrogen receptor-positive breast cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2006;24(23):3726-3734.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sparano JA, Paik S. Development of the 21-gene assay and its application in clinical practice and clinical trials. J Clin Oncol. 2008;26(5):721-728.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albain KS, Barlow WE, Shak S, et al. Prognostic and predictive value of the 21-gene recurrence score assay in postmenopausal women with node-positive, oestrogen-receptor-positive breast cancer on chemotherapy: A retrospective analysis of a randomised trial. Lancet Oncol. 2010;11(1):55-65.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papay JP, Willett JB, Murnane RJ. Extending the regression-discontinuity approach to multiple assignment variables. J Econ. 2011;161(2):203-207.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reardon SF, Robinson JP. Regression discontinuity designs with multiple rating-score variables. J Res Educ Effect. 2012;5(1):83-104.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keele LJ, Titiunik R. Geographic boundaries as regression discontinuities. Polit Anal. 2015;23(1):127-155.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keele LJ, Titiunik R, Zubizarreta J. Enhancing a geographic regression discontinuity design through matching to estimate the effect of ballot initiatives on voter turnout. J R Stat Soc Ser A. 2015;178(1):223-239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Card D, Lee DS, Pei Z, Weber A. Inference on causal effects in a generalized regression kink design. Econometrica. 2015;83(6):2453-2483.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barreca AI, Lindo JM, Waddell GR. Heaping-induced bias in regression-discontinuity designs. Econ Inq. 2016;54(1):268-293.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartalotti O, Brummet Q, Dieterle S. A correction for regression discontinuity designs with group-specific mismeasurement of the running variable. J Bus Econ Stat. 2021;39(3):833-848.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>