<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">34259625</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2050-084X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>eLife</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Elife</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Relationship between changing malaria burden and low birth weight in sub-Saharan Africa: A difference-in-differences study via a pair-of-pairs approach.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e65133</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7554/eLife.65133</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">According to the World Health Organization (WHO), in 2018, an estimated 228 million malaria cases occurred worldwide with most cases occurring in sub-Saharan Africa. Scale-up of vector control tools coupled with increased access to diagnosis and effective treatment has resulted in a large decline in malaria prevalence in some areas, but other areas have seen little change. Although interventional studies demonstrate that preventing malaria during pregnancy can reduce the rate of low birth weight (i.e. child's birth weight &lt;2500 g), it remains unknown whether natural changes in parasite transmission and malaria burden can improve birth outcomes.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">We conducted an observational study of the effect of changing malaria burden on low birth weight using data from 18,112 births in 19 countries in sub-Saharan African countries during the years 2000-2015. Specifically, we conducted a difference-in-differences study via a pair-of-pairs matching approach using the fact that some sub-Saharan areas experienced sharp drops in malaria prevalence and some experienced little change.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">A malaria prevalence decline from a high rate (<i>Plasmodium falciparum</i> parasite rate in children aged 2-up-to-10 (i.e. PfPR<sub>2-10</sub>) &gt; 0.4) to a low rate (PfPR<sub>2-10</sub> &lt; 0.2) is estimated to reduce the rate of low birth weight by 1.48 percentage points (95% confidence interval: 3.70 percentage points reduction, 0.74 percentage points increase), which is a 17% reduction in the low birth weight rate compared to the average (8.6%) in our study population with observed birth weight records (1.48/8.6 &#x2248; 17%). When focusing on first pregnancies, a decline in malaria prevalence from high to low is estimated to have a greater impact on the low birth weight rate than for all births: 3.73 percentage points (95% confidence interval: 9.11 percentage points reduction, 1.64 percentage points increase).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">Although the confidence intervals cannot rule out the possibility of no effect at the 95% confidence level, the concurrence between our primary analysis, secondary analyses, and sensitivity analyses, and the magnitude of the effect size, contribute to the weight of the evidence suggesting that declining malaria burden can potentially substantially reduce the low birth weight rate at the community level in sub-Saharan Africa, particularly among firstborns. The novel statistical methodology developed in this article-a pair-of-pairs approach to a difference-in-differences study-could be useful for many settings in which different units are observed at different times.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FUNDING">Ryan A. Simmons is supported by National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences (UL1TR002553). The funder had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2021, Heng et al.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Heng</LastName><ForeName>Siyu</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9313-3667</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Graduate Group in Applied Mathematics and Computational Science, School of Arts and Sciences, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, The Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Meara</LastName><ForeName>Wendy P</ForeName><Initials>WP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Health Institute, School of Medicine, Duke University, Durham, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simmons</LastName><ForeName>Ryan A</ForeName><Initials>RA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Health Institute, School of Medicine, Duke University, Durham, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, School of Medicine, Duke University, Durham, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Small</LastName><ForeName>Dylan S</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4928-2646</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, The Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>UL1 TR002553</GrantID><Acronym>TR</Acronym><Agency>NCATS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Elife</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101579614</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2050-084X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017954" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Africa South of the Sahara</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007230" MajorTopicYN="Y">Infant, Low Birth Weight</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008288" MajorTopicYN="N">Malaria</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="Y">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016778" MajorTopicYN="N">Malaria, Falciparum</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010963" MajorTopicYN="N">Plasmodium falciparum</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011247" MajorTopicYN="N">Pregnancy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherAbstract Type="plain-language-summary" Language="eng"><AbstractText>Malaria infects around 230 million people each year, mostly in sub-Saharan Africa, and causes more than 400,000 deaths. Pregnant women are particularly susceptible to malaria. The parasite that causes malaria can sap the mother&#x2019;s iron stores and may starve the baby of nutrients. Babies born to infected mothers often have low birth weights, which can have lasting effects on their health and brain development. Previous studies suggest that preventing malaria in pregnant women using insecticide-treated bed nets or medications may improve birth outcomes. Successful efforts to prevent malaria have led to substantially fewer infections in sub-Saharan Africa. But success has been uneven with some communities continuing to have high rates of infection. These differences may allow scientists to better understand the community-level impact of falling rates of malaria on pregnancy outcomes in the real world. Heng et al. estimated that reducing malaria transmission minimises the number of infants born with low birth weights in communities in sub-Saharan Africa. In an observational study, they used data on more than 18,000 births in 19 countries in this region between 2000 and 2015 to assess the effects of declining malaria rates on birth weights. They found that a decrease of malaria prevalence is estimated to reduce the rate of low birth weight by 1.48%, which is a 17% reduction in the number of observed newborns with low birth weight in the study population. First-born infants appeared to benefit the most. This highlights that malaria interventions are beneficial for pregnant women and their newborns. Most analyses of the impact and cost-benefit of malaria control have ignored the potential advantages of malaria control on birth weight, and may thus undermine the benefits of malaria control. The approach used by Heng et al. may further be useful for other epidemiologists studying global health.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2021, Heng et al.</CopyrightInformation></OtherAbstract><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">birth weight</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">community-level effect</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">global health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">malaria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">observational studies</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>SH, WO, RS, DS No competing interests declared</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34259625</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8279759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7554/eLife.65133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">65133</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Abadie A. Semiparametric difference-in-differences estimators. The Review of Economic Studies. 2005;72:1&#x2013;19. doi: 10.1111/0034-6527.00321.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/0034-6527.00321</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angrist JD, Pischke J-S. Mostly Harmless Econometrics: An Empiricist&#x2019;s Companion. Princeton University Press; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ashenfelter O, Card D. Using the longitudinal structure of earnings to estimate the effect of training programs. The Review of Economics and Statistics. 1985;67:648&#x2013;660. doi: 10.2307/1924810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/1924810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Athey S, Imbens GW. Identification and inference in nonlinear difference-in-differences models. Econometrica. 2006;74:431&#x2013;497. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-0262.2006.00668.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1468-0262.2006.00668.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avchen RN, Scott KG, Mason CA. Birth weight and school-age disabilities: a population-based study. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2001;154:895&#x2013;901. doi: 10.1093/aje/154.10.895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/154.10.895</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11700243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ayele DG, Zewotir TT, Mwambi HG. The risk factor indicators of malaria in Ethiopia. International Journal of Medicine and Medical Sciences. 2013;5:335&#x2013;347.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baragatti M, Fournet F, Henry MC, Assi S, Ouedraogo H, Rogier C, Salem G. Social and environmental malaria risk factors in urban areas of Ouagadougou, Burkina Faso. Malaria Journal. 2009;8:13&#x2013;14. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-8-13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-8-13</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2640411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19144144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Basu P, Small DS. Constructing a more closely matched control group in a difference-in-differences analysis: its effect on history interacting with group bias. Observational Studies. 2020;6:103&#x2013;130. doi: 10.1353/obs.2020.0011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1353/obs.2020.0011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhatt S, Weiss DJ, Cameron E, Bisanzio D, Mappin B, Dalrymple U, Battle K, Moyes CL, Henry A, Eckhoff PA, Wenger EA, Bri&#xeb;t O, Penny MA, Smith TA, Bennett A, Yukich J, Eisele TP, Griffin JT, Fergus CA, Lynch M, Lindgren F, Cohen JM, Murray CLJ, Smith DL, Hay SI, Cibulskis RE, Gething PW. The effect of malaria control on Plasmodium falciparum in Africa between 2000 and 2015. Nature. 2015;526:207&#x2013;211. doi: 10.1038/nature15535.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature15535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4820050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26375008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blanc AK, Wardlaw T. Monitoring low birth weight: an evaluation of international estimates and an updated estimation procedure. Bulletin of the World Health Organization. 2005;83:178&#x2013;185. doi: 10.1590/S0042-96862005000300010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1590/S0042-96862005000300010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2624216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15798841</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boerma JT, Weinstein KI, Rutstein SO, Sommerfelt AE. Data on birth weight in developing countries: can surveys help? Bulletin of the World Health Organization. 1996;74:209.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2486906</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8706237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyle EH, King M, Sobek M. 2019. IPUMS-Demographic and Health Surveys: Version 7. Minnesota Population Center and ICF International.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18128/D080.V7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooke OG, Anderson HR, Bland JM, Peacock JL, Stewart CM. Effects on birth weight of smoking, alcohol, caffeine, socioeconomic factors, and psychosocial stress. BMJ. 1989;298:795&#x2013;801. doi: 10.1136/bmj.298.6676.795.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.298.6676.795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1836053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2496859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Card D, Krueger AB. Minimum wages and employment: a case study of the fast-food industry in New Jersey and Pennsylvania: reply. American Economic Review. 2000;90:1397&#x2013;1420. doi: 10.1257/aer.90.5.1397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1257/aer.90.5.1397</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpenter J, Kenward M. Multiple Imputation and Its Application. John Wiley &amp; Sons; 2012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/9781119942283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen XK, Wen SW, Sun LM, Yang Q, Walker MC, Krewski D. Recent oral contraceptive use and adverse birth outcomes. European Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology and Reproductive Biology. 2009;144:40&#x2013;43. doi: 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2008.12.016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2008.12.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19233538</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corsi DJ, Neuman M, Finlay JE, Subramanian SV. Demographic and health surveys: a profile. International Journal of Epidemiology. 2012;41:1602&#x2013;1613. doi: 10.1093/ije/dys184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ije/dys184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23148108</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dellicour S, Tatem AJ, Guerra CA, Snow RW, ter Kuile FO. Quantifying the number of pregnancies at risk of malaria in 2007: a demographic study. PLOS Medicine. 2010;7:e1000221. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2811150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20126256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DHS  . Methodology - Collecting Geographic Data. Demographic and Health Surveys; 2019. https://dhsprogram.com/methodology/GPS-Data-Collection.cfm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dimick JB, Ryan AM. Methods for evaluating changes in health care policy: the difference-in-differences approach. JAMA. 2014;312:2401&#x2013;2402. doi: 10.1001/jama.2014.16153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.16153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25490331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyle O, Hegarty M, Owens C. Population-based system of parenting support to reduce the prevalence of child social, emotional, and behavioural problems: difference-in-differences study. Prevention Science. 2018;19:772&#x2013;781. doi: 10.1007/s11121-018-0907-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11121-018-0907-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29725791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eisele TP, Larsen DA, Anglewicz PA, Keating J, Yukich J, Bennett A, Hutchinson P, Steketee RW. Malaria prevention in pregnancy, birthweight, and neonatal mortality: a meta-analysis of 32 national cross-sectional datasets in africa. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2012;12:942&#x2013;949. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(12)70222-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(12)70222-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22995852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fakhouri THI, Martin CB, Chen TC, Akinbami LJ, Ogden CL, Paulose-Ram R, Riddles MK, Van de Kerckhove W, Roth SB, Clark J, Mohadjer LK, Fay RE. An investigation of nonresponse bias and survey location variability in the 2017-2018 national health and nutrition examination survey. Vital and Health Statistics. Series 2, Data Evaluation and Methods Research. 2020;1:1&#x2013;36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33541513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fowkes FJI, Davidson E, Moore KA, McGready R, Simpson JA. The invisible burden of malaria-attributable stillbirths. The Lancet. 2020;395:268. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)33011-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)33011-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31982063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser AM, Brockert JE, Ward RH. Association of young maternal age with adverse reproductive outcomes. New England Journal of Medicine. 1995;332:1113&#x2013;1118. doi: 10.1056/NEJM199504273321701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJM199504273321701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7700283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ga&#x142;ecki A, Burzykowski T. Linear mixed-effects model. In: Ga&#x142;ecki A, editor. Linear Mixed-Effects Models Using R. Springer; 2013. pp. 245&#x2013;273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4614-3900-4_13</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gelman A, Jakulin A, Pittau MG, Su Y-S. A weakly informative default prior distribution for logistic and other regression models. The Annals of Applied Statistics. 2008;2:1360&#x2013;1383. doi: 10.1214/08-AOAS191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/08-AOAS191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gemperli A, Vounatsou P, Kleinschmidt I, Bagayoko M, Lengeler C, Smith T. Spatial patterns of infant mortality in Mali: the effect of malaria endemicity. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2004;159:64&#x2013;72. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwh001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kwh001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14693661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gething P, Hay S, Weiss D. The invisible burden of malaria-attributable stillbirths - Authors' reply. The Lancet. 2020;395:268&#x2013;269. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(19)32968-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(19)32968-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31982062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goetgeluk S, Vansteelandt S. Conditional generalized estimating equations for the analysis of clustered and longitudinal data. Biometrics. 2008;64:772&#x2013;780. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-0420.2007.00944.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1541-0420.2007.00944.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18047524</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grace K, Davenport F, Hanson H, Funk C, Shukla S. Linking climate change and health outcomes: examining the relationship between temperature, precipitation and birth weight in africa. Global Environmental Change. 2015;35:125&#x2013;137. doi: 10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.06.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.06.010</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guyatt HL, Snow RW. Impact of malaria during pregnancy on low birth weight in sub-Saharan africa. Clinical Microbiology Reviews. 2004;17:760&#x2013;769. doi: 10.1128/CMR.17.4.760-769.2004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/CMR.17.4.760-769.2004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC523568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15489346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen BB. Full matching in an observational study of coaching for the SAT. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2004;99:609&#x2013;618. doi: 10.1198/016214504000000647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1198/016214504000000647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen BB, Klopfer SO. Optimal full matching and related designs via network flows. Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics. 2006;15:609&#x2013;627. doi: 10.1198/106186006X137047.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1198/106186006X137047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasegawa RB, Webster DW, Small DS. Evaluating Missouri's handgun&#xa0;purchaser&#xa0;law: a bracketing&#xa0;method for addressing concerns about history interacting with group. Epidemiology. 2019;30:371&#x2013;379. doi: 10.1097/EDE.0000000000000989.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/EDE.0000000000000989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30969945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hay SI, Snow RW. The malaria atlas project: developing global maps of malaria risk. PLOS Medicine. 2006;3:e473. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.0030473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030473</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1762059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17147467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heckman JJ, Ichimura H, Todd PE. Matching as an econometric evaluation estimator: evidence from evaluating a job training programme. The Review of Economic Studies. 1997;64:605&#x2013;654. doi: 10.2307/2971733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2971733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heckman JJ, Robb R. Alternative methods for evaluating the impact of interventions. Journal of Econometrics. 1985;30:239&#x2013;267. doi: 10.1016/0304-4076(85)90139-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0304-4076(85)90139-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heitjan DF, Basu S. Distinguishing &#x201c;missing at random&#x201d; and &#x201c;missing completely at random&#x201d;. The American Statistician. 1996;50:207&#x2013;213. doi: 10.2307/2684656.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2684656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heng S. Malaria-and-Low-Birth-Weight. faf6455GitHub. 2021a https://github.com/siyuheng/Malaria-and-Low-Birth-Weight</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heng S. Malaria-and-Low-Birth-Weight. swh:1:rev:faf6455f95bca6bab364ab95699ea7cd81af1061Software Heritage. 2021b https://archive.softwareheritage.org/swh:1:dir:f2d442b573ee3568d02ba95c0ba9ad1ac71faecc;origin=https://github.com/siyuheng/Malaria-and-Low-Birth-Weight;visit=swh:1:snp:e1d9faf64e90397ab6aa2f03f69d2fcd9b9450f5;anchor=swh:1:rev:faf6455f95bca6bab364ab95699ea7cd81af1061</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ho DE, Imai K, King G, Stuart EA. Matching as nonparametric preprocessing for reducing model dependence in parametric causal inference. Political Analysis. 2007;15:199&#x2013;236. doi: 10.1093/pan/mpl013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/pan/mpl013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huynh BT, Fievet N, Gbaguidi G, Dechavanne S, Borgella S, Gu&#xe9;zo-M&#xe9;vo B, Massougbodji A, Ndam NT, Deloron P, Cot M. Influence of the timing of malaria infection during pregnancy on birth weight and on maternal Anemia in Benin. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2011;85:214&#x2013;220. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.2011.11-0103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2011.11-0103</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3144815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21813837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huynh BT, Cottrell G, Cot M, Briand V. Burden of malaria in early pregnancy: a neglected problem? Clinical Infectious Diseases. 2015;60:598&#x2013;604. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciu848.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciu848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25362205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ICF . Demographic and Health Surveys (Various) [Datasets]. Funded by USAID. Rockville, Maryland: ICF [Distributor] Technical Report; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ichino A, Mealli F, Nannicini T. From temporary help jobs to permanent employment: what can we learn from matching estimators and their sensitivity? Journal of Applied Econometrics. 2008;23:305&#x2013;327. doi: 10.1002/jae.998.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jae.998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imbens GW. Sensitivity to exogeneity assumptions in program evaluation. American Economic Review. 2003;93:126&#x2013;132. doi: 10.1257/000282803321946921.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1257/000282803321946921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kayentao K, Garner P, van Eijk AM, Naidoo I, Roper C, Mulokozi A, MacArthur JR, Luntamo M, Ashorn P, Doumbo OK, ter Kuile FO. Intermittent preventive therapy for malaria during pregnancy using 2 vs 3 or more doses of sulfadoxine-pyrimethamine and risk of low birth weight in africa: systematic review and meta-analysis. JAMA. 2013;309:594&#x2013;604. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.216231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2012.216231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4669677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23403684</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy E, Gray N, Azzopardi P, Creati M. Adolescent fertility and family planning in east asia and the Pacific: a review of DHS reports. Reproductive Health. 2011;8:11. doi: 10.1186/1742-4755-8-11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1742-4755-8-11</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3113330</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21545708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Krefis AC, Schwarz NG, Nkrumah B, Acquah S, Loag W, Sarpong N, Adu-Sarkodie Y, Ranft U, May J. Principal component analysis of socioeconomic factors and their association with malaria in children from the ashanti region, Ghana. Malaria Journal. 2010;9:1&#x2013;7. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-9-201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-9-201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2914064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20626839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larsen DA, Grisham T, Slawsky E, Narine L. An individual-level meta-analysis assessing the impact of community-level sanitation access on child stunting, anemia, and diarrhea: evidence from DHS and MICS surveys. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2017;11:e0005591. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0005591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005591</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5464528</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28594828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MAP  2020. Malaria Atlas Project. The MAP Group. https://malariaatlas.org/malaria-burden-data-download/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayor A, Bardaj&#xed; A, Macete E, Nhampossa T, Fonseca AM, Gonz&#xe1;lez R, Maculuve S, Cister&#xf3; P, Rup&#xe9;rez M, Campo J, Vala A, Siga&#xfa;que B, Jim&#xe9;nez A, Machevo S, de la Fuente L, Nhama A, Luis L, Aponte JJ, Ac&#xe1;cio S, Nhacolo A, Chitnis C, Doba&#xf1;o C, Sevene E, Alonso PL, Men&#xe9;ndez C. Changing trends in P. falciparum burden, immunity, and disease in pregnancy. The New England Journal of Medicine. 2015;373:1607&#x2013;1617. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1406459.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1406459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26488692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCormick MC, Brooks-Gunn J, Workman-Daniels K, Turner J, Peckham GJ. The health and developmental status of very low-birth-weight children at school age. JAMA: The Journal of the American Medical Association. 1992;267:2204&#x2013;2208. doi: 10.1001/jama.1992.03480160062035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.1992.03480160062035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1556798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGregor IA, Wilson ME, Billewicz WZ. Malaria infection of the placenta in the Gambia, West Africa; its incidence and relationship to stillbirth, birthweight and placental weight. Transactions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 1983;77:232&#x2013;244. doi: 10.1016/0035-9203(83)90081-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(83)90081-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6346592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Menendez C, Ordi J, Ismail MR, Ventura PJ, Aponte JJ, Kahigwa E, Font F, Alonso PL. The impact of placental malaria on gestational age and birth weight. The Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2000;181:1740&#x2013;1745. doi: 10.1086/315449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/315449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10823776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng X-L. Multiple-imputation inferences with uncongenial sources of input. Statistical Science. 1994;1:538&#x2013;558. doi: 10.1214/ss/1177010269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/ss/1177010269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metselaar D, Van Thiel P. Classification of malaria. Tropical and Geographical Medicine. 1959;11:157&#x2013;161.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuman MD, Rosenbaum PR, Ludwig JM, Zubizarreta JR, Silber JH. Anesthesia technique, mortality, and length of stay after hip fracture surgery. JAMA. 2014;311:2508&#x2013;2517. doi: 10.1001/jama.2014.6499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.2014.6499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4344128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25058085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Padhi BK, Baker KK, Dutta A, Cumming O, Freeman MC, Satpathy R, Das BS, Panigrahi P. Risk of adverse pregnancy outcomes among women practicing poor sanitation in rural India: a population-based prospective cohort study. PLOS Medicine. 2015;12:e1001851. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1001851.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4511257</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26151447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pimentel SD, Kelz RR, Silber JH, Rosenbaum PR. Large, sparse optimal matching with refined covariate balance in an observational study of the health outcomes produced by new surgeons. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2015;110:515&#x2013;527. doi: 10.1080/01621459.2014.997879.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01621459.2014.997879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4531000</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26273117</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Development Core Team  . Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2020. http://www.r-project.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radeva-Petrova D, Kayentao K, ter Kuile FO, Sinclair D, Garner P, Cochrane Infectious Diseases Group Drugs for preventing malaria in pregnant women in endemic Areas: any drug regimen versus placebo or no treatment. Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews. 2014;9:CD000169. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD000169.pub3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000169.pub3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4498495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25300703</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richards M, Hardy R, Kuh D, Wadsworth ME. Birth weight and cognitive function in the british 1946 birth cohort: longitudinal population based study. BMJ. 2001;322:199&#x2013;203. doi: 10.1136/bmj.322.7280.199.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.322.7280.199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC26584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11159613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts D, Matthews G. Risk factors of malaria in children under the age of five years old in Uganda. Malaria Journal. 2016;15:1&#x2013;11. doi: 10.1186/s12936-016-1290-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-016-1290-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4848810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27121122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robles A, Goldman N. Can accurate data on birthweight be obtained from health interview surveys? International Journal of Epidemiology. 1999;28:925&#x2013;931. doi: 10.1093/ije/28.5.925.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ije/28.5.925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10597993</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogerson SJ, Mwapasa V, Meshnick SR. Malaria in pregnancy: linking immunity and pathogenesis to prevention. &#xa0;American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2007;77:iii. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.2007.77.iii.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2007.77.iii</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18165470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR. The consquences of adjustment for a concomitant variable that has been affected by the treatment. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society:&#xa0;Series A. 1984;147:656&#x2013;666. doi: 10.2307/2981697.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2981697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR. Optimal matching for observational studies. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 1989;84:1024&#x2013;1032. doi: 10.1080/01621459.1989.10478868.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01621459.1989.10478868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR. Observational Studies. Springer; 2002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PRS.0b013e3181f44abc</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR. Design of Observational Studies. Springer; 2010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/978-1-4419-1213-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR, Rubin DB. Assessing sensitivity to an unobserved binary covariate in an observational study with binary outcome. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B. 1983a;45:212&#x2013;218. doi: 10.1111/j.2517-6161.1983.tb01242.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.2517-6161.1983.tb01242.x</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR, Rubin DB. The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects. Biometrika. 1983b;70:41&#x2013;55. doi: 10.1093/biomet/70.1.41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/biomet/70.1.41</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR, Silber JH. Amplification of sensitivity analysis in matched observational studies. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2009;104:1398&#x2013;1405. doi: 10.1198/jasa.2009.tm08470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1198/jasa.2009.tm08470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3416023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22888178</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ross A, Smith T. The effect of malaria transmission intensity on neonatal mortality in endemic Areas. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2006;75:74&#x2013;81. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.2006.75.74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2006.75.74</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16931818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. The use of matched sampling and regression adjustment to remove bias in observational studies. Biometrics. 1973;29:185&#x2013;203. doi: 10.2307/2529685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2529685</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Using multivariate matched sampling and regression adjustment to control bias in observational studies. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 1979;74:318&#x2013;328. doi: 10.2307/2286330.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2286330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Multiple Imputation for Nonresponse in Surveys. John Wiley &amp; Sons; 1987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/3172772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Multiple imputation after 18+ years. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 1996;91:473&#x2013;489. doi: 10.1080/01621459.1996.10476908.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01621459.1996.10476908</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Matched Sampling for Causal Effects. Cambridge University Press; 2006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/CBO9780511810725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. The design versus the analysis of observational studies for causal effects: parallels with the design of randomized trials. Statistics in Medicine. 2007;26:20&#x2013;36. doi: 10.1002/sim.2739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/sim.2739</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17072897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahn DE, Stifel DC. Urban-Rural inequality in living standards in Africa. Journal of African Economics. 2003;12:564&#x2013;597. doi: 10.1093/jae/12.4.564.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jae/12.4.564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schafer JL. Multiple imputation: a primer. Statistical Methods in Medical Research. 1999;8:3&#x2013;15. doi: 10.1177/096228029900800102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/096228029900800102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10347857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmiegelow C, Matondo S, Minja DTR, Resende M, Pehrson C, Nielsen BB, Olomi R, Nielsen MA, Deloron P, Salanti A, Lusingu J, Theander TG. Plasmodium falciparum infection early in pregnancy has profound consequences for fetal growth. The Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2017;216:1601&#x2013;1610. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jix530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jix530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29029247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selvin S, Janerich DT. Four factors influencing birth weight. Journal of Epidemiology &amp; Community Health. 1971;25:12&#x2013;16. doi: 10.1136/jech.25.1.12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/jech.25.1.12</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC478624</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5551228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shadish WR, Cook TD, Campbell DT. Experimental and Quasi&#x2011;Experimental Designs For&#xa0;Generalized Causal Inference. Boston: Houghton Mifflin; 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shadish WR. Campbell and Rubin: a primer and comparison of their approaches to causal inference in field settings. Psychological Methods. 2010;15:3&#x2013;17. doi: 10.1037/a0015916.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/a0015916</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20230099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silber JH, Rosenbaum PR, Ross RN, Ludwig JM, Wang W, Niknam BA, Hill AS, Even-Shoshan O, Kelz RR, Fleisher LA. Indirect standardization matching: assessing specific advantage and risk synergy. Health Services Research. 2016;51:2330&#x2013;2357. doi: 10.1111/1475-6773.12470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1475-6773.12470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5134157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26927625</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith DL, Guerra CA, Snow RW, Hay SI. Standardizing estimates of the Plasmodium falciparum parasite rate. Malaria Journal. 2007;6:1&#x2013;10. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-6-131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-6-131</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2072953</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17894879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>St. Clair T, Cook TD. Difference-in-differences methods in public finance. National Tax Journal. 2015;68:319&#x2013;338. doi: 10.17310/ntj.2015.2.04.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.17310/ntj.2015.2.04</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strobino DM, Ensminger ME, Kim YJ, Nanda J. Mechanisms for maternal age differences in birth weight. American Journal of Epidemiology. 1995;142:504&#x2013;514. doi: 10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a117668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a117668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7677129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stuart EA. Matching methods for causal inference: a review and a look forward. Statistical Science. 2010;25:1. doi: 10.1214/09-STS313.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/09-STS313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2943670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20871802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sulyok M, R&#xfc;ckle T, Roth A, M&#xfc;rbeth RE, Chalon S, Kerr N, Samec SS, Gobeau N, Calle CL, Ib&#xe1;&#xf1;ez J, Sulyok Z, Held J, Gebru T, Granados P, Br&#xfc;ckner S, Nguetse C, Mengue J, Lalremruata A, Sim BKL, Hoffman SL, M&#xf6;hrle JJ, Kremsner PG, Mordm&#xfc;ller B. DSM265 for Plasmodium falciparum chemoprophylaxis: a randomised, double blinded, phase 1 trial with controlled human malaria infection. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2017;17:636&#x2013;644. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30139-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30139-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5446410</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28363637</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valea I, Tinto H, Drabo MK, Huybregts L, Sorgho H, Ouedraogo JB, Guiguemde RT, van Geertruyden JP, Kolsteren P, D'Alessandro U, FSP/MISAME study Group An analysis of timing and frequency of malaria infection during pregnancy in relation to the risk of low birth weight, anaemia and perinatal mortality in burkina faso. Malaria Journal. 2012;11:71. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-11-71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-11-71</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3338396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22433778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valero De Bernab&#xe9; J, Soriano T, Albaladejo R, Juarranz M, Calle ME, Mart&#xed;nez D, Dom&#xed;nguez-Rojas V. Risk factors for low birth weight: a review. European Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology and Reproductive Biology. 2004;116:3&#x2013;15. doi: 10.1016/j.ejogrb.2004.03.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ejogrb.2004.03.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15294360</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Visconti G, Zubizarreta JR. Handling limited overlap in observational studies with cardinality matching. Observational Studies. 2018;4:217&#x2013;249. doi: 10.1353/obs.2018.0012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1353/obs.2018.0012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volpp KG, Rosen AK, Rosenbaum PR, Romano PS, Even-Shoshan O, Canamucio A, Bellini L, Behringer T, Silber JH. Mortality among patients in VA hospitals in the first 2 years following ACGME resident duty hour reform. JAMA. 2007;298:984&#x2013;992. doi: 10.1001/jama.298.9.984.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.298.9.984</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17785643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker PG, ter Kuile FO, Garske T, Menendez C, Ghani AC. Estimated risk of placental infection and low birthweight attributable to Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Africa in 2010: a modelling study. The Lancet Global Health. 2014;2:e460&#x2013;e467. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(14)70256-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(14)70256-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25103519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>West SG, Thoemmes F. Campbell's and Rubin's perspectives on causal inference. Psychological Methods. 2010;15:18&#x2013;37. doi: 10.1037/a0015917.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1037/a0015917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20230100</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO . Global Malaria Action Plan 1 (2000&#x2013;2015) Roll Back Malaria Partnership/World Health Organization; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO . World Malaria Report 2016&#xa0;Technical Report. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO . World Malaria Report 2019,&#xa0;Technical Report. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wing C, Simon K, Bello-Gomez RA. Designing difference in difference&#xa0;studies: best&#xa0;practices for public health policy research. Annual Review of Public Health. 2018;39:453&#x2013;469. doi: 10.1146/annurev-publhealth-040617-013507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-publhealth-040617-013507</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29328877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zeka A, Melly SJ, Schwartz J. The effects of socioeconomic status and indices of physical environment on reduced birth weight and preterm births in eastern massachusetts. Environmental Health. 2008;7:60. doi: 10.1186/1476-069X-7-60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1476-069X-7-60</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2607263</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19032747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang B, Small DS. A calibrated sensitivity analysis for matched observational studies with application to the effect of second-hand smoke exposure on blood lead levels in children. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C. 2020;69:1285&#x2013;1305. doi: 10.1111/rssc.12443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/rssc.12443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zubizarreta JR. Using mixed integer programming for matching in an observational study of kidney failure after surgery. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2012;107:1360&#x2013;1371. doi: 10.1080/01621459.2012.703874.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01621459.2012.703874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4673003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26664027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zubizarreta JR, Paredes RD, Rosenbaum PR. Matching for balance, pairing for heterogeneity in an observational study of the effectiveness of for-profit and not-for-profit high schools in Chile. The Annals of Applied Statistics. 2014;8:204&#x2013;231. doi: 10.1214/13-AOAS713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/13-AOAS713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>