<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">37644974</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>31</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2639-8028</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>5</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Critical care explorations</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Crit Care Explor</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Delayed Treatment of Bloodstream Infection at Admission is Associated With Initial Low Early Warning Score and Increased Mortality.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0959</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0959</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0959</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/CCE.0000000000000959</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To identify factors associated with antibiotic treatment delay in patients admitted with bloodstream infections (BSIs).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DESIGN" NlmCategory="METHODS">Retrospective cohort study.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="SETTING" NlmCategory="METHODS">North Zealand Hospital, Denmark.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="PATIENTS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Adult patients with positive blood cultures obtained within the first 48 hours of admission between January 1, 2015, and December 31, 2015 (<i>n</i> = 926).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MEASUREMENTS AND MAIN RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">First recorded Early Warning Score (EWS), patient characteristics, time to antibiotic treatment, and survival at day 60 after admission were obtained from electronic health records and medicine module. Presence of contaminants and the match between the antibiotic treatment and susceptibility of the cultured microorganism were included in the analysis. Data were stratified according to EWS quartiles. Overall, time from admission to prescription of antibiotic treatment was 3.7 (3.4-4.0) hours, whereas time from admission to antibiotic treatment was 5.7 (5.4-6.1) hours. A gap between prescription and administration of antibiotic treatment was present across all EWS quartiles. Importantly, 23.4% of patients admitted with BSI presented with an initial EWS 0-1. Within this group of patients, time to antibiotic treatment was markedly higher among nonsurvivors at day 60 compared with survivors. Furthermore, time to antibiotic treatment later than 6 hours was associated with increased mortality at day 60. Among patients with an initial EWS of 0-1, 51.3% of survivors received antibiotic treatment within 6 hours, whereas only 19.0% of nonsurvivors received antibiotic treatment within 6 hours.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Among patients with initial low EWS, delay in antibiotic treatment of BSIs was associated with increased mortality at day 60. Lag from prescription to administration may contribute to delayed antibiotic treatment. A more frequent reevaluation of patients with infections with a low initial EWS and reduction of time from prescription to administration may reduce the time to antibiotic treatment, thus potentially improving survival.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2023 The Authors. Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of the Society of Critical Care Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fischer</LastName><ForeName>Christian P</ForeName><Initials>CP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Diseases, Hvidovre Hospital, Hvidovre, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kastoft</LastName><ForeName>Emili</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Infectious Diseases, North Zealand Hospital, North Zealand, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Forensic Medicine, University of Copenhagen, K&#xf8;benhavn, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olesen</LastName><ForeName>Bente Ruth Scharvik</ForeName><Initials>BRS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology, Herlev and Gentofte Hospital, Herlev, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Myrup</LastName><ForeName>Bjarne</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Pulmonary and Infectious Diseases, North Zealand Hospital, North Zealand, Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Crit Care Explor</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101746347</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2639-8028</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacteremia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood culture</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">organ dysfunction scores</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">systemic inflammatory response syndrome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">triage</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors have disclosed that they do not have any potential conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>3</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37644974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10461960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/CCE.0000000000000959</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rudd KE, Johnson SC, Agesa KM, et al. : Global, regional, and national sepsis incidence and mortality, 1990-2017: Analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study. Lancet Lond Engl 2020; 395:200&#x2013;211</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6970225</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31954465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans L, Rhodes A, Alhazzani W, et al. : Executive summary: Surviving sepsis campaign: International guidelines for the management of sepsis and septic shock 2021. Crit Care Med 2021; 49:1974&#x2013;1982</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34643578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar A, Roberts D, Wood KE, et al. : Duration of hypotension before initiation of effective antimicrobial therapy is the critical determinant of survival in human septic shock. Crit Care Med 2006; 34:1589&#x2013;1596</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16625125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Puskarich MA, Trzeciak S, Shapiro NI, et al. ; Emergency Medicine Shock Research Network (EMSHOCKNET): Association between timing of antibiotic administration and mortality from septic shock in patients treated with a quantitative resuscitation protocol. Crit Care Med 2011; 39:2066&#x2013;2071</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3158284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21572327</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrer R, Martin-Loeches I, Phillips G, et al. : Empiric antibiotic treatment reduces mortality in severe sepsis and septic shock from the first hour: Results from a guideline-based performance improvement program. Crit Care Med 2014; 42:1749&#x2013;1755</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24717459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu VX, Fielding-Singh V, Greene JD, et al. : The timing of early antibiotics and hospital mortality in sepsis. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2017; 196:856&#x2013;863</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5649973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28345952</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peltan ID, Brown SM, Bledsoe JR, et al. : ED door-to-antibiotic time and long-term mortality in sepsis. Chest 2019; 155:938&#x2013;946</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6533450</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30779916</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ljungstr&#xf6;m L, Andersson R, Jacobsson G: Incidences of community onset severe sepsis, sepsis-3 sepsis, and bacteremia in Sweden&#x2014;A prospective population-based study. PLoS One 2019; 14:e0225700.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6894792</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31805110</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu D, Unger D, Unge C, et al. : Correlation of clinical sepsis definitions with microbiological characteristics in patients admitted through a sepsis alert system: A prospective cohort study. Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob 2022; 21:7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8864844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35193588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komori A, Abe T, Kushimoto S, et al. ; JAAM FORECAST group: Characteristics and outcomes of bacteremia among ICU-admitted patients with severe sepsis. Sci Rep 2020; 10:2983.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7031517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32076046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mellhammar L, Kahn F, Whitlow C, et al. : Bacteremic sepsis leads to higher mortality when adjusting for confounders with propensity score matching. Sci Rep 2021; 11:6972.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7998031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33772090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu A, Yo C-H, Nie L, et al. : Comparing mortality between positive and negative blood culture results: An inverse probability of treatment weighting analysis of a multicenter cohort. BMC Infect Dis 2021; 21:182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7887786</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33596842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Guo J, Yang H, et al. : Comparison of culture-negative and culture-positive sepsis or septic shock: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit Care Lond Engl 2021; 25:167</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8106121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33964934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nestor D, Andersson H, Kihlberg P, et al. : Early prediction of blood stream infection in a prospectively collected cohort. BMC Infect Dis 2021; 21:316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8017733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33810788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prytherch DR, Smith GB, Schmidt PE, et al. : ViEWS&#x2014;towards a National Early Warning Score for detecting adult inpatient deterioration. Resuscitation 2010; 81:932&#x2013;937</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20637974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaimes F, Arango C, Ruiz G, et al. : Predicting bacteremia at the bedside. Clin Infect Dis Off Publ Infect Dis Soc Am 2004; 38:357&#x2013;362</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14727205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hodgson LE, Dragolea N, Venn R, et al. : An external validation study of a clinical prediction rule for medical patients with suspected bacteraemia. Emerg Med J EMJ 2016; 33:124&#x2013;129</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26246024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlson ME, Pompei P, Ales KL, et al. : A new method of classifying prognostic comorbidity in longitudinal studies: Development and validation. J Chronic Dis 1987; 40:373&#x2013;383</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3558716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGinley A, Pearse RM: A national Early Warning Score for acutely ill patients. BMJ 2012; 345:e5310.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22875955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corl KA, Zeba F, Caffrey AR, et al. : Delay in antibiotic administration is associated with mortality among septic shock patients with <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> bacteremia.
Crit Care Med
2020; 48:525&#x2013;532</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32205599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bias TE, Vincent WR, Trustman N, et al. : Impact of an antimicrobial stewardship initiative on time to administration of empirical antibiotic therapy in hospitalized patients with bacteremia. Am J Health-Syst Pharm AJHP Off J Am Soc Health-Syst Pharm 2017; 74:511&#x2013;519</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28336761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam N, Hobbelink EL, van Tienhoven AJ, et al. : The impact of the use of the Early Warning Score (EWS) on patient outcomes: A systematic review. Resuscitation 2014; 85:587&#x2013;594</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24467882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu VX, Lu Y, Carey KA, et al. : Comparison of early warning scoring systems for hospitalized patients with and without infection at risk for in-hospital mortality and transfer to the intensive care unit. JAMA Netw Open 2020; 3:e205191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7237982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32427324</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bone RC, Balk RA, Cerra FB, et al. : American College of Chest Physicians/Society of Critical Care Medicine Consensus Conference: Definitions for sepsis and organ failure and guidelines for the use of innovative therapies in sepsis. Crit Care Med 1992; 20:864&#x2013;874</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1597042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singer M, Deutschman CS, Seymour CW, et al. : The third international consensus definitions for sepsis and septic shock (sepsis-3). JAMA 2016; 315:801&#x2013;810</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4968574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26903338</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim EH, Sherman G, Ward S, et al. : The influence of inadequate antimicrobial treatment of bloodstream infections on patient outcomes in the ICU setting. Chest 2000; 118:146&#x2013;155</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10893372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey DJ, Albert S: Standardized definition of contamination and evidence-based target necessary for high-quality blood culture contamination rate audit. J Hosp Infect 2013; 83:265&#x2013;266</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23313025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schifman RB, Strand CL, Meier FA, et al. : Blood culture contamination: A College of American Pathologists Q-Probes study involving 640 institutions and 497134 specimens from adult patients. Arch Pathol Lab Med 1998; 122:216&#x2013;221</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9823858</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pien BC, Sundaram P, Raoof N, et al. : The clinical and prognostic importance of positive blood cultures in adults. Am J Med 2010; 123:819&#x2013;828</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20800151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>