<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">22460396</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2012</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1752-8550</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>3</Volume><PubDate><Year>2010</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Emerging health threats journal</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Emerg Health Threats J</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Innovation in observation: a vision for early outbreak detection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e6</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e6</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e6</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3134/ehtj.10.006</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The emergence of new infections and resurgence of old onesFhealth threats stemming from environmental contamination or purposeful acts of bioterrorismFcall for a worldwide effort in improving early outbreak detection, with the goal of ameliorating current and future risks. In some cases, the problem of outbreak detection is logistically straightforward and mathematically easy: a single case of a disease of great concern can constitute an outbreak. However, for the vast majority of maladies, a simple analytical solution does not exist. Furthermore, each step in developing reliable, sensitive, effective surveillance systems demonstrates enormous complexities in the transmission, manifestation, detection, and control of emerging health threats. In this communication, we explore potential future innovations in early outbreak detection systems that can overcome the pitfalls of current surveillance. We believe that modern advances in assembling data, techniques for collating and processing information, and technology that enables integrated analysis will facilitate a new paradigm in outbreak definition and detection. We anticipate that moving forward in this direction will provide the highly desired sensitivity and specificity in early detection required to meet the emerging challenges of global disease surveillance.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fefferman</LastName><ForeName>Nh</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Ecology, Evolution and Natural Resources, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Naumova</LastName><ForeName>En</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>U19 AI062627</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Sweden</Country><MedlineTA>Emerg Health Threats J</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101484599</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1752-8550</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2010</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2010</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2010</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2012</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22460396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3167656</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3134/ehtj.10.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">EHTJ-3-e6</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Burr T, Michalak S, Picard R. Mathematical and statistical estimation approaches in epidemiology. In: Castillo-Chavez C, editor. Mathematical and Statistical Estimation Approaches in Epidemiology. Springer: The Netherlands; 2009. pp. 163&#x2013;87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tokars JI, Burkom H, Xing J, English R, Bloom S, Cox K, et al. Enhancing time-series detection algorithms for automated biosurveillance. Emerg Infect Dis. 2009;15:533&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2671446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19331728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson WW, Shay DK, Weintraub E, Brammer L, Cox N, Anderson LJ, et al. Mortality associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in the United States. JAMA. 2003;289:179&#x2013;86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12517228</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong W-K, Moore A, Cooper G, Wagner MM. Rule-based anomaly pattern detection for detecting disease outbreaks; 2002. pp. 217&#x2013;23. Proc Eighteenth Natl Conf Artif Intell (AAAI-02)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fricker RD, Jr, Hegler BL, Dunfee DA. Comparing syndromic surveillance detection methods: EARS&#x2019; versus a CUSUM-based methodology. Stat Med. 2008;27:3407&#x2013;29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18240128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodall WH. The use of control charts in health-care and publichealth surveillance. J Qual Technol. 2006;38:1&#x2013;16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodall WH, Marshall MDJ, Jr, Joner MD, Fraker SE, Abdel-Salam ASG. On the use and evaluation of prospective scan methods for health-related surveillance. J R Stat Soc Ser A (Stat Soc) 2008;171:223&#x2013;37.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy SP, Burkom H. Recombinant temporal aberration detection algorithms for enhanced biosurveillance. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2008;15:77&#x2013;86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2274875</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17947614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reis BY, Kohane IS, Mandl KD. An epidemiological network model for disease outbreak detection. PLoS Med. 2007;4:e210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1896205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17593895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sintchenko V, Gallego B, Chung G, Coiera E. Towards bioinformatics assisted infectious disease control. BMC Bioinformatics. 2009;10(Suppl 2):S10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2646247</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19208185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guasticchi G, Giorgi Rossi P, Lori G, Genio S, Biagetti F, Gabriele S, et al. Syndromic surveillance: sensitivity and positive predictive value of the case definitions. Epidemiol Infect. 2009;137:662&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18937875</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bork KH, Klein BM, Molbak K, Trautner S, Pedersen UB, Heegaard E. Surveillance of ambulance dispatch data as a tool for early warning. Eurosurveillance. 2006;11:229&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17370966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cooper DL, Smith GE, Regan M, Large S, Groenewegen PP. Tracking the spatial diffusion of influenza and norovirus using telehealth data: a spatiotemporal analysis of syndromic data. BMC Med. 2008;6:16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2464582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18582364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edge VL, Pollari F, Ng LK, Michel P, McEwen SA, Wilson JB, et al. Syndromic surveillance of Norovirus using over-the-counter sales of medications related to gastrointestinal illness. Can J Infect Dis Med Microbiol. 2006;17:235&#x2013;41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2095074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18382634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Dijk A, McGuinness D, Rolland E, Moore KM. Can Telehealth Ontario respiratory call volume be used as a proxy for emergency department respiratory visit surveillance by public health? CJEM. 2008;10:18&#x2013;24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18226314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu P, de Courten M, Pan E, Galea G, Pryor J. The development and evaluation of a PDA-based method for public health surveillance data collection in developing countries. Int J Med Inform. 2009;78:532&#x2013;42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19369114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hulth A, Rydevik G, Linde A. Web queries as a source for syndromic surveillance. PLoS One. 2009;4:e4378.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2634970</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19197389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McEntee JC, Casronovo DA, Jagai JS, Chui K, Naumova EN. Application of novel analytical tools in global disease monitoring: remote sensing in public health research and practice. In: Finkel ML, editor. Perspectives in Public Health: Challenges for the 21st Century. Westport, CT: Praeger Press; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brownstein JS, Freifeld CC, Madoff LC. Influenza A (H1N1) virus, 2009&#x2014;online monitoring. N Engl J Med. 2009;360:2156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2922951</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19423868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linge JP, Steinberger R, Weber TP, Yangarber R, van der Goot E, Al Khudhairy DH, et al. Internet surveillance systems for early alerting of health threats. Euro Surveill. 2009;14:1&#x2013;2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19341610</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burr T, Graves T, Klamann R, Michalak S, Picard R, Hengartner N. Accounting for seasonal patterns in syndromic surveillance data for outbreak detection. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2006;6:40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1698911</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17144927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naumova EN, Jagai JS, Matyas B, DeMaria A, Jr, MacNeill IB, Griffiths JK. Seasonality in six enterically transmitted diseases and ambient temperature. Epidemiol Infect. 2007;135:281&#x2013;92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2870561</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17291363</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy PP, Valleron AJ. Toward unsupervised outbreak detection through visual perception of new patterns. BMC Public Health. 2009;9:179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2706246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19515246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bravata DM, McDonald KM, Smith WM, Rydzak C, Szeto H, Buckeridge DL, et al. Systematic review: surveillance systems for early detection of bioterrorism-related diseases. Ann Intern Med. 2004;140:910&#x2013;22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15172906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hafen RP, Anderson DE, Cleveland WS, Maciejewski R, Ebert DS, Abusalah A, et al. Syndromic surveillance: STL for modeling, visualizing, and monitoring disease counts. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2009;9:21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2680402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19383138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutwagner L, Browne T, Seeman GM, Fleischauer AT. Comparing aberration detection methods with simulated data. Emerg Infect Dis. 2005;11:314&#x2013;16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3320440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15752454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagner MM, Tsui FC, Espino JU, Dato VM, Sittig DF, Caruana RA, et al. The emerging science of very early detection of disease outbreaks. J Public Health Manag Pract. 2001;7:51&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11710168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinez-Beneito MA, Conesa D, Lopez-Quilez A, Lopez-Maside A. Bayesian Markov switching models for the early detection of influenza epidemics. Stat Med. 2008;27:4455&#x2013;68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18618414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buckeridge DL. Outbreak detection through automated surveil lance: a review of the determinants of detection. J Biomed Inform. 2007;40:370&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17095301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang AY, Parrales ME, Jimenez J, Sobieszczyk ME, Hammer SM, Copenhaver DJ, et al. Combining Google Earth and GIS mapping technologies in a dengue surveillance system for developing countries. Int J Health Geogr. 2009;8:49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2729741</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19627614</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greig JD, Ravel A. Analysis of foodborne outbreak data reported internationally for source attribution. Int J Food Microbiol. 2009;130:77&#x2013;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19178974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castronovo DA, Chui KK, Naumova EN. Dynamic maps: a visualanalytic methodology for exploring spatio-temporal disease patterns. Environ Health. 2009;8:61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2806342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20042115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo D. Flow mapping and multivariate visualization of large spatial interaction data. IEEE Trans Visual Comp Graphics. 2009;15:1041&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19834170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo D, Liao K, Morgan M. Visualizing patterns in a global terrorism incident database. Environ Plan B Plan Design. 2007;34:767&#x2013;84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fefferman NH, Naumova EN. Combinatorial decomposition of an outbreak signature. Math Biosci. 2006;202:269&#x2013;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2537994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16631819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naumova EN, Macneill IB. Signature-forecasting and early outbreak detection system. Environmetrics. 2005;16:749&#x2013;66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2518402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18716671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colizza V, Barrat A, Barthelemy M, Valleron AJ, Vespignani A. Modeling the worldwide spread of pandemic influenza: baseline case and containment interventions. PLoS Med. 2007;4:e13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1779816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17253899</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichner M, Schwehm M, Duerr HP, Brockmann SO. The influenza pandemic preparedness planning tool InfluSim. BMC Infect Dis. 2007;7:17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1832202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17355639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu B, Wang J, McGowan M, Vaidyanathan G, Younger K. Gryphon: A Hybrid Agent-Based Modeling and Simulation Platform for Infectious Diseases. 1st edn. Springer: Berlin/Heidelberg; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Neil EA, Naumova EN. Defining outbreak: breaking out of confusion. J Public Health Policy. 2007;28:442&#x2013;55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17955009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levin SA. Complex adaptive systems: exploring the known, the unknown and the unknowable. Bull Am Math Soc. 2002;40:3&#x2013;19.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>