<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37845807</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1742-6723</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>36</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Emergency medicine Australasia : EMA</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Emerg Med Australas</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Benchmarking blood culture quality in the emergency department: Contamination, single sets and positivity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>206</StartPage><EndPage>212</EndPage><MedlinePgn>206-212</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/1742-6723.14330</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE">To benchmark blood culture (BC) quality in an Australian ED, explore groups at risk of suboptimal BC collection, and identify potential areas for improvement.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">This retrospective observational study was undertaken to benchmark quality of BCs in a tertiary adult ED in terms of number of BC sets per patient and proportion of patients with false positive (contaminated) BC results.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">A single BC set was taken for 55% of patients, with lower acuity patients being more likely to have a single BC set taken. BC false positives occurred in 3.4% of presentations, with higher frequency in some critically unwell patient groups. The true positive BC rate was 10.9%, with pathogens most frequently isolated in older patients, those with a haematological condition or genitourinary source, and those admitted to inpatient wards. Hospital length of stay did not differ between patients with negative and patients with false positive BCs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">BC quality standards in the ED such as false positive rate &lt;3% and single culture rate &lt;20% are required to facilitate benchmarking and prospective quality improvement. The sensitivity and specificity of this common and critical test can be improved. Patient subgroups associated with poor-quality BC collection can be identified and should be a focus of future work.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2023 Australasian College for Emergency Medicine.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hills</LastName><ForeName>Angela Z</ForeName><Initials>AZ</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9832-0461</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency and Trauma Centre, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ray</LastName><ForeName>Mercedes</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency and Trauma Centre, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Williams</LastName><ForeName>Julian</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency and Trauma Centre, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Greenslade</LastName><ForeName>Jaimi</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency and Trauma Centre, Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Australian Centre for Health Services Innovation, Centre for Healthcare Transformation, Faculty of Health, Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Queensland, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Emergency Medicine Foundation</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D064888">Observational Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Australia</Country><MedlineTA>Emerg Med Australas</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101199824</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1742-6723</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000368" MajorTopicYN="N">Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000071997" MajorTopicYN="Y">Blood Culture</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019985" MajorTopicYN="N">Benchmarking</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011446" MajorTopicYN="N">Prospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001315" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Australia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004636" MajorTopicYN="N">Emergency Service, Hospital</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016470" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bacteremia</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">bacteraemia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">blood cultures</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">diagnostic test</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">emergency medicine</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37845807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/1742-6723.14330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Long B, Koyfman A. Best clinical practice: blood culture utility in the emergency department. J. Emerg. Med. 2016; 51: 529-539.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nannan Panday R, Lammers E, Alam N, Nanayakkara P. An overview of positive cultures and clinical outcomes in septic patients: a sub-analysis of the Prehospital Antibiotics Against Sepsis (PHANTASi) trial. Crit. Care 2019; 23: 182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans L, Rhodes A, Alhazzani W et al. Surviving sepsis campaign: international guidelines for management of sepsis and septic shock 2021. Intensive Care Med. 2021; 47: 1181-1247.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee C, Lee N, Chuang M, Chen P, Chang C, Ko W. The impact of overcrowding on the bacterial contamination of blood cultures in the ED. Am. J. Emerg. Med. 2012; 30: 839-845.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halverson S, Malani PN, Newton DW, Habicht A, Vander Have K, Younger JG. Impact of hourly emergency department patient volume on blood culture contamination and diagnostic yield. J. Clin. Microbiol. 2013; 51: 1721-1726.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chang C, Wu C, Hsu H et al. Factors associated with blood culture contamination in the emergency department: critical illness, end-stage renal disease, and old age. PLoS One 2015; 10: e0137653.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Willems E, Smismans A, Cartuyvels R et al. The preanalytical optimization of blood cultures: a review and the clinical importance of benchmarking in 5 Belgian hospitals. Diagn. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 2012; 73: 1-8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denny KJ, Sweeny A, Crilly J, Maloney S, Keijzers G. Is it time for a culture change? Blood culture collection in the emergency department. Emerg. Med. Australas. 2018; 30: 575-577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alahmadi Y, Aldeyab M, McElnay J et al. Clinical and economic impact of contaminated blood cultures within the hospital setting. J. Hosp. Infect. 2011; 77: 233-236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klucher JM, Davis K, Lakkad M, Painter JT, Dare RK. Risk factors and clinical outcomes associated with blood culture contamination. Infect. Control Hosp. Epidemiol. 2022; 43: 291-297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hall K, Lyman J. Updated review of blood culture contamination. Clin. Microbiol. Rev. 2006; 19: 788-802.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown L, Chapman S, Ferguson P. Blood cultures and bacteraemia in an Australian emergency department: evaluating a predictive rule to guide collection and their clinical impact. Emerg. Med. Australas. 2017; 29: 56-62.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen A, Bilker W, Hamilton K, O'Donnell J, Nachamkin I. Blood culture utilization at an academic hospital: addressing a gap in benchmarking. Infect. Control Hosp. Epidemiol. 2018; 39: 1353-1359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Choi J, Ensafi S, Chartier L, Van Praet O. A quality improvement initiative to decrease the rate of solitary blood cultures in the emergency department. Acad. Emerg. Med. 2017; 24: 1080-1087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Temkin E, Biran D, Braun T, Schwartz D, Carmeli Y. Analysis of blood culture collection and laboratory processing practices in Israel. JAMA Netw. Open 2022; 5: e2238309.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNab L, Varndell W, Vecellio E, Chiew A. Clean the skin: reducing blood culture contamination in the emergency department. Emerg. Med. Australas. 2022; 34: 1006-1008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nannan Panday R, Wang S, van de Ven P, Hekker T, Alam N, Nanayakkara P. Evaluation of blood culture epidemiology and efficiency in a large European teaching hospital. PLoS One 2019; 14: e0214052.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson P, Russell A, Inverarity D. The effect of a quality improvement programme reducing blood culture contamination on the detection of bloodstream infection in an emergency department. J. Infect. Prev. 2015; 16: 82-87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halstead D, Sautter R, Snyder J, Crist A, Nachamkin I. Reducing blood culture contamination rates: experiences of four hospital systems. Infect. Dis. Ther. 2020; 9: 389-401.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garcia RA, Spitzer ED, Beaudry J et al. Multidisciplinary team review of best practices for collection and handling of blood cultures to determine effective interventions for increasing the yield of true-positive bacteraemias, reducing contamination, and eliminating false-positive central line-associated blood stream infections. Am. J. Infect. Control 2015; 43: 1222-1237.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee A, Mirrett S, Reller LB, Weinstein MP. Detection of bloodstream infections in adults: how many blood cultures are needed? J. Clin. Microbiol. 2007; 45: 3546-3548.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Heijden F, Miller G, Wright P, Shepherd B, Daniels T, Talbot T. Clinical impact of blood cultures contaminated with coagulase-negative Staphylococci at an academic medical center. Infect. Control Hosp. Epidemiol. 2011; 32: 623-625.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter EJ, Pouch SM, Larson EL. The relationship between emergency department crowding and patient outcomes: a systematic review. J. Nurs. Scholarsh. 2014; 46: 106-115.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>