<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">34394762</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1866-9956</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>14</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Cognitive computation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Cognit Comput</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Quantum Machine Learning Architecture for COVID-19 Classification Based on Synthetic Data Generation Using Conditional Adversarial Neural Network.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1677</StartPage><EndPage>1688</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1677-1688</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1007/s12559-021-09926-6</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">COVID-19 is a novel virus that affects&#xa0;the upper respiratory tract, as well as the lungs. The scale of the global COVID-19 pandemic, its spreading rate,&#xa0;and deaths are increasing regularly. Computed tomography (CT) scans can be used carefully to detect and analyze&#xa0;COVID-19 cases. In CT images/scans, ground-glass opacity (GGO) is found in the early stages of infection. While&#xa0;in later stages, there is a superimposed pulmonary consolidation.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">This research investigates the quantum machine learning&#xa0;(QML) and classical machine learning (CML) approaches for the analysis of COVID-19 images. The recent&#xa0;developments in quantum computing have led researchers to explore new ideas and approaches using QML. The&#xa0;proposed approach consists of two phases: in phase I, synthetic CT images are generated through the conditional&#xa0;adversarial network (CGAN) to increase the size of the dataset for accurate training and testing. In phase II, the&#xa0;classification of COVID-19/healthy images is performed, in which two models are proposed: CML and QML.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULT" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The proposed model achieved 0.94&#xa0;precision (Pn), 0.94 accuracy (Ac), 0.94 recall (Rl), and 0.94 F1-score (Fe) on POF Hospital dataset while 0.96 Pn,&#xa0;0.96 Ac, 0.95 Rl, and 0.96 Fe on UCSD-AI4H dataset.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="UNASSIGNED">The proposed method achieved better results when compared to&#xa0;the latest published work in this domain.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer Science+Business Media, LLC, part of Springer Nature 2021.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amin</LastName><ForeName>Javaria</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, University of Wah, 47040, Wah Cantt, Pakistan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.442867.b</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0401 3861</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sharif</LastName><ForeName>Muhammad</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, COMSATS University Islamabad, Wah Campus, 47040, Wah Cantt, Pakistan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.418920.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0607 0704</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gul</LastName><ForeName>Nadia</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MBBS, FCPS Diagnostic Radiology, Consultant Radiologist POF Hospital and Associate Professor Radiology Wah Medical College, Wah Cantt, Pakistan.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.412956.d</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 0609 0537</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kadry</LastName><ForeName>Seifedine</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Applied Computing and Technology, Noroff University College, Kristiansand, Norway.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.512929.4</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0004 8023 4383</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chakraborty</LastName><ForeName>Chinmay</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Birla Institute of Technology, Mesra, Jharkhand India.</Affiliation><Identifier Source="GRID">grid.418391.6</Identifier><Identifier Source="ISNI">0000 0001 1015 3164</Identifier></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Cognit Comput</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101499358</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1866-9956</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">CGAN</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Classical machine learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quanvolutional neural network</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ReLU</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Softmax</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflict of InterestThe authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34394762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8353617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s12559-021-09926-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">9926</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Machhi J, Herskovitz J, Senan AM, Dutta D, Nath B, Oleynikov MD, et al. The natural history, pathobiology, and clinical manifestations of SARS-CoV-2 infections. J Neuroimmune Pharmacol. 2020;21:1&#x2013;28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7373339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32696264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacLean OA, Lytras S, Weaver S, Singer JB, Boni MF, Lemey P, et al.&#xa0;Natural selection in the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 in bats, not humans, created a highly capable human pathogen. BioRxiv.&#xa0;2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7990310</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33711012</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marvel SW, House JS, Wheeler M, Song K, Zhou YH, Wright FA, et al<i>.</i>&#xa0;The COVID-19 Pandemic Vulnerability Index (PVI) Dashboard: Monitoring county-level vulnerability using visualization, statistical modeling, and machine learning, Accessed by https://covid19.who.int/?gclid=CjwKCAiAgJWABhArEiwAmNVTBxT9Yp12C6zDLVWxYOAefSlJb4FO-iRrgXZshtiWMSGfD5FNAqjoTxoC13gQAvD_BwE, Environ Health Perspect.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7785295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33400596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin YH, Cai L, Cheng ZS, Cheng H, Deng T, Fan YP, et al. A rapid advice guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) infected pneumonia (standard version) Mil Med Res. 2020;7:4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7003341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32029004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothan HA, Byrareddy&#xa0;SN. The epidemiology and pathogenesis of coronavirus disease (COVID-19) outbreak. J Autoimmun. 2020;p. 102433.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7127067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32113704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> Ai T, Yang Z, Hou H, Zhan C, Chen C, Lv&#xa0;W, et al<i>.</i>&#xa0;Correlation of chest CT and RT-PCR testing in coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in China: a report of 1014 cases, Radiology<i>. </i>2020;p. 200642.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7233399</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32101510</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wujtewicz M, Dylczyk-Sommer A, Aszkie&#x142;owicz A, Zdanowski S, Piwowarczyk S, Owczuk R. COVID-19&#x2013;what should anaethesiologists and intensivists know about it? Anaesthesiology intensive therapy. 2020;52:34&#x2013;41. doi: 10.5114/ait.2020.93756.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5114/ait.2020.93756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10173133</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32191830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Romagnoli S, Peris A, De Gaudio AR, Geppetti P. SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19: from the bench to the bedside. Physiol Rev. 2020;100:1455. doi: 10.1152/physrev.00020.2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1152/physrev.00020.2020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7347954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32496872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> Shi F, Wang J, Shi J, Wu Z, Wang Q, Tang&#xa0;Z<i>, </i>et al. Review of artificial intelligence techniques in imaging data acquisition, segmentation and diagnosis for covid-19, IEEE Rev Biomed Eng. 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32305937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yasmin M, Sharif M, Irum I, Mehmood W, Fernandes SL. Combining multiple color and shape features for image retrieval. IIOAB J. 2016;7:97&#x2013;110.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nida N, Sharif M, Khan MUG, Yasmin M, Fernandes SL. A framework for automatic colorization of medical imaging. IIOAB J. 2016;7:202&#x2013;209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin J, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Ali H, Fernandes SL. A method for the detection and classification of diabetic retinopathy using structural predictors of bright lesions. Journal of Computational Science. 2017;19:153&#x2013;164. doi: 10.1016/j.jocs.2017.01.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jocs.2017.01.002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah JH, Chen Z, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Fernandes SL. A novel biomechanics-based approach for person re-identification by generating dense color sift salience features. Journal of Mechanics in Medicine and Biology. 2017;17:1740011. doi: 10.1142/S0219519417400115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1142/S0219519417400115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fatima Bokhari ST, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Fernandes SL. Fundus image segmentation and feature extraction for the detection of glaucoma: a new approach.&#xa0;Current Medical Imaging. 2018;vol. 14, pp. 77&#x2013;87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naqi S, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Fernandes SL. Lung nodule detection using polygon approximation and hybrid features from CT images. Current Medical Imaging. 2018;14:108&#x2013;117. doi: 10.2174/1573405613666170306114320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2174/1573405613666170306114320</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin J, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Fernandes SL. Big data analysis for brain tumor detection: Deep convolutional neural networks. Futur Gener Comput Syst. 2018;87:290&#x2013;297. doi: 10.1016/j.future.2018.04.065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.future.2018.04.065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin J, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Fernandes SL. A distinctive approach in brain tumor detection and classification using MRI.&#xa0;Pattern Recogn Lett. 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin J, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Saba T, Anjum MA, Fernandes SL. A new approach for brain tumor segmentation and classification based on score level fusion using transfer learning. J Med Syst. 2019;43:1&#x2013;16. doi: 10.1007/s10916-019-1453-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10916-019-1453-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31643004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhammad N, Sharif M, Amin J, Mehboob R, Gilani SA, Bibi N, et al. Neurochemical alterations in sudden unexplained perinatal deaths&#x2014;a review. Front Pediatr. 2018;6:6. doi: 10.3389/fped.2018.00006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fped.2018.00006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5788892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29423392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin J, Sharif M, Yasmin M, Saba T, Raza M. Use of machine intelligence to conduct analysis of human brain data for detection of abnormalities in its cognitive functions. Multimedia Tools and Applications. 2020;79:10955&#x2013;10973. doi: 10.1007/s11042-019-7324-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11042-019-7324-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharif M, Amin J, Siddiqa A, Khan HU, Malik MSA, Anjum MA, et al. Recognition of different types of leukocytes using YOLOv2 and optimized bag-of-features. IEEE Access. 2020;8:167448&#x2013;167459. doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3021660.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3021660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amin J, Sharif M, Anjum MA, Khan HU, Malik MSA, Kadry S. An integrated design for classification and localization of diabetic foot ulcer based on CNN and YOLOv2-DFU models. IEEE Access<i>.</i>&#xa0;2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ieracitano C, Mammone N, Hussain A, Morabito FC. A novel explainable machine learning approach for EEG-based brain-computer interface systems.&#xa0;Neural Comput Applic.&#xa0;2021;pp. 1&#x2013;14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang S, Kang B, Ma J, Zeng X, Xiao M, Guo J<i>, </i>et al.&#xa0;A deep learning algorithm using CT images to screen for Corona Virus Disease (COVID-19). MedRxiv. 2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7904034</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33629156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yadav SS, Jadhav SM. Deep convolutional neural network based medical image classification for disease diagnosis. Journal of Big Data. 2019;6:113. doi: 10.1186/s40537-019-0276-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s40537-019-0276-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen G, Dlugolinsky S, Bob&#xe1;k M, Tran V, Garc&#xed;a &#xc1;L, Heredia I, et al. Machine Learning and Deep Learning frameworks and libraries for large-scale data mining: a survey. Artif Intell Rev. 2019;52:77&#x2013;124. doi: 10.1007/s10462-018-09679-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10462-018-09679-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay S, DUTTA S. Detection of fraud transactions using recurrent neural network during COVID-19. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang Y, Chen H, Loew M, Ko H. COVID-19 CT image synthesis with a conditional generative adversarial network. arXiv preprint arXiv:2007.14638.&#xa0;2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8545178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33275588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbas A, Abdelsamea MM, Gaber M. 4S-DT: self supervised super sample decomposition for transfer learning with application to COVID-19 detection, arXivpreprint arXiv:2007.11450.&#xa0;2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8544943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34038371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng Y, Zhao X, Huang K, Tan T. Semi-supervised learning and feature evaluation for RGB-D object recognition. Comput Vis Image Underst. 2015;139:149&#x2013;160. doi: 10.1016/j.cviu.2015.05.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cviu.2015.05.007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xin B, Peng W. Prediction for chaotic time series-based AE-CNN and transfer learning.&#xa0;Complexity.&#xa0;vol. 2020, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahiner B, Pezeshk A, Hadjiiski LM, Wang X, Drukker K, Cha KH, et al. Deep learning in medical imaging and radiation therapy. Med Phys. 2019;46:e1&#x2013;e36. doi: 10.1002/mp.13264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/mp.13264</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9560030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30367497</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajinikanth V, Dey N, Raj ANJ, Hassanien AE, Santosh K, Raja N. Harmony-search and otsu based system for coronavirus disease (COVID-19) detection using lung CT scan images.&#xa0;arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.03431<i>.</i>&#xa0;2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra BK, Keshri AK, Rao YS, Mishra BK, Mahato B, Ayesha S<i>, </i>et al.&#xa0;COVID-19 created chaos across the globe: three novel quarantine epidemic models. Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals<i>.</i> 2020;p. 109928.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7247522</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32501378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang GZ, Nelson BJ, Murphy RR, Choset H, Christensen H, Collins SH<i>, </i>et al.&#xa0;Combating COVID-19&#x2014;the role of robotics in managing public health and infectious diseases. ed: Sci Robot.&#xa0;2020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33022599</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nguyen TT. Artificial intelligence in the battle against coronavirus (COVID-19): a survey and future research directions. Preprint, DOI,&#xa0;2020;vol. 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu K-H, Beam AL, Kohane IS. Artificial intelligence in healthcare. Nature biomedical engineering. 2018;2:719&#x2013;731. doi: 10.1038/s41551-018-0305-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41551-018-0305-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31015651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vishnuvarthanan A, Rajasekaran MP, Govindaraj V, Zhang Y, Thiyagarajan A. An automated hybrid approach using clustering and nature inspired optimization technique for improved tumor and tissue segmentation in magnetic resonance brain images. Appl Soft Comput. 2017;57:399&#x2013;426. doi: 10.1016/j.asoc.2017.04.023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.asoc.2017.04.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>To&#x11f;a&#xe7;ar M, Ergen B, C&#xf6;mert Z. COVID-19 detection using deep learning models to exploit Social Mimic Optimization and structured chest X-ray images using fuzzy color and stacking approaches.&#xa0;Comput Biol Med.&#xa0;2020;p. 103805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7202857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32568679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nour M, C&#xf6;mert Z, Polat K. A novel medical diagnosis model for COVID-19 infection detection based on deep features and Bayesian optimization.&#xa0;Appl Soft Comput.&#xa0;2020;p. 106580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7385069</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32837453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozturk T, Talo M, Yildirim EA, Baloglu UB, Yildirim O, Acharya UR. Automated detection of COVID-19 cases using deep neural networks with X-ray images.&#xa0;Comput Biol Med.&#xa0;2020;p. 103792.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7187882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32568675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunjko V, Briegel HJ. Machine learning &amp; artificial intelligence in the quantum domain: a review of recent progress.&#xa0;Rep Prog Phys.&#xa0;2018;vol. 81, p. 074001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29504942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciliberto C, Herbster M, Ialongo AD, Pontil M, Rocchetto A, Severini S, et al. Quantum machine learning: a classical perspective. Proceedings of the Royal Society A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences. 2018;474:20170551. doi: 10.1098/rspa.2017.0551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rspa.2017.0551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5806018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29434508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuld M. Quantum machine learning for supervised pattern recognition.&#xa0;2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anthimopoulos M, Christodoulidis S, Ebner L, Christe A, Mougiakakou S. Lung pattern classification for interstitial lung diseases using a deep convolutional neural network. IEEE Trans Med Imaging. 2016;35:1207&#x2013;1216. doi: 10.1109/TMI.2016.2535865.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/TMI.2016.2535865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26955021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassal I, Whitfield JD, Perdomo-Ortiz A, Yung M-H, Aspuru-Guzik A. Simulating chemistry using quantum computers. Annu Rev Phys Chem. 2011;62:185&#x2013;207. doi: 10.1146/annurev-physchem-032210-103512.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev-physchem-032210-103512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21166541</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunjko V, Taylor JM, Briegel HJ. Quantum-enhanced machine learning.&#xa0;Phys Rev Lett.&#xa0;2016;vol. 117, p. 130501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27715099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Radford A, Metz L, Chintala S. Unsupervised representation learning with deep convolutional generative adversarial networks.&#xa0;arXiv preprint arXiv:1511.06434. 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henderson M, Shakya S, Pradhan S, Cook T. Quanvolutional neural networks: powering image recognition with quantum circuits. Quantum Machine Intelligence. 2020;2:1&#x2013;9. doi: 10.1007/s42484-020-00012-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s42484-020-00012-y</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergholm V, Izaac J, Schuld M, Gogolin C, Alam MS, Ahmed S<i>, </i>et al.&#xa0;Pennylane: automatic differentiation of hybrid quantum-classical computations.&#xa0;arXiv preprint arXiv:1811.04968.&#xa0;2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergholm V, Izaac J, Schuld M, Gogolin C, Alam MS, Ahmed S<i>, </i>et al.&#xa0;PennyLane: automatic differentiation of hybrid quantum-classical computations. 2018,&#xa0;https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.04968 v3. Accessed on Thu.&#xa0;2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao J, Zhang Y, He X, Xie P. Covid-ct-dataset: a ct scan dataset about covid-19. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang X, He X, Zhao J, Zhang Y, Zhang S, Xie P. COVID-CT-dataset: a CT scan dataset about COVID-19. ArXiv e-prints,&#xa0;p. arXiv: 2003.13865.&#xa0;2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horry MJ, Chakraborty S, Paul M, Ulhaq A, Pradhan B, Saha M, et al. COVID-19 detection through transfer learning using multimodal imaging data. IEEE Access. 2020;8:149808&#x2013;149824. doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3016780.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3016780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8668160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34931154</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burgos-Artizzu XP. Computer-aided covid-19 patient screening using chest images (X-Ray and CT scans).&#xa0;medRxiv<i>.</i>&#xa0;2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Z, Liu Q, Dou Q. Contrastive cross-site learning with redesigned net for COVID-19 CT classification. IEEE J Biomed Health Inform. 2020;24:2806&#x2013;2813. doi: 10.1109/JBHI.2020.3023246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/JBHI.2020.3023246</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8545175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32915751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewen N, Khan N. Targeted self supervision for classification on a small COVID-19 CT scan dataset. arXiv preprint arXiv:2011.10188<i>.</i> 2020.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>