<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">21408071</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2011</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>05</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>6</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2011</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>09</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adherence to drug-refill is a useful early warning indicator of virologic and immunologic failure among HIV patients on first-line ART in South Africa.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e17518</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e17518</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e17518</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0017518</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Affordable strategies to prevent treatment failure on first-line regimens among HIV patients are essential for the long-term success of antiretroviral therapy (ART) in sub-Saharan Africa. WHO recommends using routinely collected data such as adherence to drug-refill visits as early warning indicators. We examined the association between adherence to drug-refill visits and long-term virologic and immunologic failure among non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI) recipients in South Africa.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">In 2008, 456 patients on NNRTI-based ART for a median of 44 months (range 12-99 months; 1,510 person-years) were enrolled in a retrospective cohort study in Soweto. Charts were reviewed for clinical characteristics before and during ART. Multivariable logistic regression and Kaplan-Meier survival analysis assessed associations with virologic (two repeated VL&gt;50 copies/ml) and immunologic failure (as defined by WHO).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">After a median of 15 months on ART, 19% (n&#x200a;=&#x200a;88) and 19% (n&#x200a;=&#x200a;87) had failed virologically and immunologically respectively. A cumulative adherence of &lt;95% to drug-refill visits was significantly associated with both virologic and immunologic failure (p&lt;0.01). In the final multivariable model, risk factors for virologic failure were incomplete adherence (OR 2.8, 95%CI 1.2-6.7), and previous exposure to single-dose nevirapine or any other antiretrovirals (adj. OR 2.1, 95%CI 1.2-3.9), adjusted for age and sex. In Kaplan-Meier analysis, the virologic failure rate by month 48 was 19% vs. 37% among adherent and non-adherent patients respectively (logrank p value&#x200a;=&#x200a;0.02).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">One in five failed virologically after a median of 15 months on ART. Adherence to drug-refill visits works as an early warning indicator for both virologic and immunologic failure.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>El-Khatib</LastName><ForeName>Ziad</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Global Health (IHCAR), Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden. ziad.khatib@gmail.com</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Katzenstein</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Marrone</LastName><ForeName>Gaetano</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laher</LastName><ForeName>Fatima</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohapi</LastName><ForeName>Lerato</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Petzold</LastName><ForeName>Max</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Morris</LastName><ForeName>Lynn</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ekstr&#xf6;m</LastName><ForeName>Anna Mia</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI066922</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>2 U2R TW006878</GrantID><Acronym>TW</Acronym><Agency>FIC NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2011</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D023241" MajorTopicYN="Y">Antiretroviral Therapy, Highly Active</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018791" MajorTopicYN="N">CD4 Lymphocyte Count</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003710" MajorTopicYN="N">Demography</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="Y">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053208" MajorTopicYN="N">Kaplan-Meier Estimate</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010349" MajorTopicYN="Y">Patient Compliance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D057566" MajorTopicYN="N">Self Report</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013019" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">South Africa</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017211" MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment Failure</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement><b>Competing Interests: </b>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2010</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2011</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2011</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21408071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3052314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO), Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS, UNICEF. Progress report; 2008. Towards universal access: Scaling up priority HIV/AIDS interventions in the health sector. pp. 1&#x2013;77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harries AD, Zachariah R, van Oosterhout JJ, Reid SD, Hosseinipour MC, et al. Diagnosis and management of antiretroviral-therapy failure in resource-limited settings in sub-Saharan Africa: challenges and perspectives. Lancet Infect Dis. 2010;10:60&#x2013;65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20129150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simon V, Ho DD, Karim QA. HIV/AIDS epidemiology, pathogensis, prevention, and treatment. Lancet. 2006;368</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2913538</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16890836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuritzkes DR. Preventing and managing antiretroviral resistance. AIDS Patient Care STDs. 2004;18:259&#x2013;273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15186710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calmy A, Ford N, Hirschel B, Reynolds SJ, Lynen L, et al. HIV viral load monitoring in resource-limited regions: optional or necessary? Clin Infect Dis. 2007;44:128&#x2013;134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17143828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rewari B, Bachani D, Rajasekaran S, Deshpande A, Chan P, et al. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr Oct 1 [Epub ahead of print]; 2010. Evaluating patients for second-line antiretroviral therapy in India: the role of targeted viral load testing.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20890211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kantor R, Diero L, Delong A, Kamle L, Muyonga S, et al. Misclassification of first-line antiretroviral treatment failure based on immunological monitoring of HIV infection in resource-limited settings. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;49:454&#x2013;462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4859427</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19569972</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosseinipour MC, van Oosterhout JG, Weigel R, Phiri S, Kamwendo D, et al. The public health approach to identify antiretroviral therapy failure: high-level nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor resistance among Malawians failing first-line antiretroviral therapy. AIDS. 2009;23:1127&#x2013;1134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2896488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19417582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) HIV drug resistance early warning indicators (HIVDR-EWI) 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hedt BL, Wadonda-Kabondo N, Makombe S, Harries AD, Schouten EJ, et al. Early warning indicators for HIV drug resistance in Malawi. Antivir Ther. 2008;13(Suppl 2):69&#x2013;75.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18575193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nachega JB, Hislop M, Dowdy DW, Lo M, Omer S, et al. Adherence to highly active antiretroviral therapy assessed by pharmacy claims predicts survival in HIV-infected South African adults. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2006;43:78&#x2013;84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16878045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cambiano V, Lampe F, Rodger A, Smith C, Geretti A, et al. Use of a prescription-based measure of antiretroviral therapy adherence to predict viral rebound in HIV-infected individuals with viral suppression. HIV Med. 2010;11:216&#x2013;224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20002781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parienti JJ, Massari V, Descamps D, Vabret A, Bouvet E, et al. Predictors of virologic failure and resistance in HIV-infected patients treated with nevirapine- or efavirenz-based antiretroviral therapy. Clin Infect Dis. 2004;38:1311&#x2013;1316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15127346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barth RE, van der Loeff MF, Schuurman R, Hoepelman AI, Wensing AM. Virological follow-up of adult patients in antiretroviral treatment programmes in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic review. Lancet Infect Dis. 2010;10:155&#x2013;166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20185094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Khatib Z, Ekstrom AM, Ledwaba J, Mohapi L, Laher F, et al. Viremia and drug resistance among HIV-1 patients on antiretroviral treatment: a cross-sectional study in Soweto, South Africa. AIDS. 2010;24:1679&#x2013;1687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2894994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20453629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hatano H, Delwart EL, Norris PJ, Lee TH, Neilands TB, et al. AIDS; 2010. Evidence of persistent low-level viremia in long-term HAART-suppressed, HIV-infected individuals.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2954261</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20651585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammer SM, Eron JJ J, Reiss P, Schooley RT, Thompson MA, et al. Antiretroviral treatment of adult HIV infection: 2008 recommendations of the International AIDS Society-USA panel. JAMA. 2008;300:555&#x2013;570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18677028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothman KJ, Boice J. Newton, MA, Epidemiology resources; 1982. Epidemiologic analysis with a programmable calculator, 2nd ed.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Khatib Z, Ekstrom AM, Ledwaba J, Mohapi L, Laher F, et al. Viremia and drug resistance among HIV-1 patients on antiretroviral treatment &#x2013; a cross-sectional study in Soweto, South Africa. AIDS. 2010;24</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2894994</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20453629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martinson NA, Morris L, Johnson J, Gray GE, Pillay V, et al. Women exposed to single-dose nevirapine in successive pregnancies: effectiveness and nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor resistance. AIDS. 2009;23:809&#x2013;816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19287298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Khatib Z, DeLong AK, Katzenstein D, Ekstrom AM, Ledwaba J, et al. Drug resistance patterns and virus re-suppression among HIV-1 subtype C infected patients receiving non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors in South Africa. 2010. In review.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3174802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21927716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Khatib Z, Ekstrom AM, Laher F, Karstaedt AS, Petzold M, et al. 2009. Medical review-South African adherence and virologic evaluation (MR. SAVE) tool. 1.0 ed. Stockholm: Creative Commons (CC); ziad.khatib@gmail.com.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Khatib Z. 2004.  Questionnaire design and data entry in EpiData ( http://onkpat.ki.se/1?node=47234). Stockholm, Sweden:
Division of Clinical Cancer Epidemiology - Karolinska Institutet.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EpiData foundation. 2008.  EpiData for data entry and documentation ( www.epidata.dk).
Denmark.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Geneva, Switzerland: WHO; 2004. Scaling up antiretroviral therapy in resource-limited settings: treatment guidelines for a public health approach: 2003 revision.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paredes R, Clote B, Ruiz L. Comparison of the efficacy of HAART: single, dual or triple-class antiretroviral therapy. In: De Clercq E, Vandamme AM, editors. Combination therapy of AIDS. Birkhauser Verlag/Switzerland; 2004. pp. 53&#x2013;71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Datay MI, Boulle A, Mant D, Yudkin P. Associations with virologic treatment failure in adults on antiretroviral therapy in South Africa. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2010;54:489&#x2013;495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20395870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coovadia A, Hunt G, Abrams EJ, Sherman G, Meyers T, et al. Persistent minority K103N mutations among women exposed to single-dose nevirapine and virologic response to Nonnucleoside Reverse-Transcriptase Inhibitor-based therapy. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;48:462&#x2013;472.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2810158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19133804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ford N, Darder M, Spelman T, Maclean E, Mills E, et al.  Early adherence to antiretroviral medication as a predictor of
long-term HIV virological suppression: five-year follow up of an
observational cohort. PLoS One. 2010;5:e10460. doi: 10410.11371/journal.pone.0010460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2864744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20485480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boulle A, Van Cutsem G, Hilderbrand K, Cragg C, Abrahams M, et al. Seven-year experience of a primary care antiretroviral treatment programme in Khayelitsha, South Africa. AIDS. 2010;24:563&#x2013;572.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20057311</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>StataCorp LP. Stata/SE 10.1, College Station, TX 77845 USA 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prism G. version 4.0c. La Jolla, CA 92037 USA 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Geneve; 2010. Antiretroviral therapy for HIV infection in adults and adolescents.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23741771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanne IM, Westreich D, Macphail AP, Rubel D, Majuba P, et al. Long-term outcomes of antiretroviral therapy in a large HIV/AIDS care clinic in urban South Africa: a prospective cohort study. J Int AIDS Soc. 2009;12:38.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2811100</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20017918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keiser O, Orrell C, Egger M, Wood R, Brinkhof MW, et al. Public-health and individual approaches to antiretroviral therapy: Township South Africa and Switzerland compared. PLoS Med. 2008;5:e148.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2443185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18613745</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lampe FC, Harding R, Smith CJ, Phillips AN, Johnson M, et al. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr; 2010. Physical and psychological symptoms and risk of virologic rebound among patients with virologic suppression on antiretroviral therapy.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20150819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lampe FC, Gatell JM, Staszewski S, Johnson MA, Pradier C, et al. Changes over time in risk of initial virological failure of combination antiretroviral therapy: a multicohort analysis, 1996 to 2002. Arch Intern Med. 2006;166:521&#x2013;528.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16534038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phillips AN, Pradier C, Lazzarin A, Clotet B, Goebel FD, et al. Viral load outcome of non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor regimens for 2203 mainly antiretroviral-experienced patients. AIDS. 2001;15:2385&#x2013;2395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11740189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Datay M, Boulle A, Mant D, Yudkin P. Associations with virologic treatment failure in adults on antiretroviral therapy in South Africa. Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes. 2010;54:489&#x2013;495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20395870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson JB, Becker-Pergola G, Guay LA, Musoke P, Mracna M, et al. Identification of the K103N resistance mutation in Ugandan women receiving nevirapine to prevent HIV-1 vertical transmission. AIDS. 2000;14:F111&#x2013;115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10983633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eshleman S, Hoover D, Chen S, Hudelson S, Guay L, et al. Resistance after single-dose nevirapine prophylaxis emerges in a high proportion of Malawian newborns. AIDS. 2005;19:2167&#x2013;2169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16284468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Madge S, Smith C, Lampe F, Sabin C, Youle M, et al. An audit of viral load in one clinical population to describe features of viraemic patients on antiretroviral therapy. HIV Med. 2008;9:208&#x2013;213.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18298577</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taiwo BO, Murphy RL. Clinical applications and availability of CD4+ T cell count testing in sub-Saharan Africa. Clinical Cytometry. 2008;74B:S11&#x2013;S18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18061953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egger M. CROI. Los Angeles, USA: 2007. Outcomes of antiretroviral treatment in resource limited and industrialized countries.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisson G, Gross R, Bellamy S, Chittams J, Hislop M, et al. Pharmacy refill adherence compared with CD4 count changes for monitoring HIV-infected adults on antiretroviral therapy. PLoS Med. 2008;5:e109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2386831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18494555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mee P, Fielding KL, Charalambous S, Churchyard GJ, Grant AD. Evaluation of the WHO criteria for antiretroviral treatment failure among adults in South Africa. AIDS. 2008;22:1971&#x2013;1977.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18784460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badri M, Lawn S, Wood R. Utility of CD4 cell counts for early prediction of virological failure during antiretroviral therapy in a resource-limited setting. BMC Infect Dis. 2008;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2459184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18601727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kagee A, Remien RH, Berkman A, Hoffman S, Campos L, et al. Glob Public Health; 2010. Structural barriers to ART adherence in Southern Africa: challenges and potential ways forward. pp. 1&#x2013;15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3056922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20509066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nattrass N. AIDS, science and governance: the battle over antiretroviral
therapy in post-apartheid South Africa. 2006.  Southern African Journal of HIV Medicine Accessed  http://www.aidstruth.org/documents/nattrass.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richard T, Lester PR, Mills EdwardJ, Kariri Antony, Karanja Sarah, Chung MichaelH, et al.  Effects of a mobile phone short message service on antiretroviral
treatment adherence in Kenya (WelTel Kenya1): a randomised
trial. Lancet. 2010 DOI: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61997-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)61997-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21071074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paterson DL, Swindells S, Mohr J, Brester M, Vergis EN, et al. Adherence to protease inhibitor therapy and outcomes in patients with HIV infection. Ann Intern Med. 2000;136:21&#x2013;30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10877736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low-Beer S, Yip B, O'Shaughnessy M, Hogg R, Montaner J. Adherence to triple therapy and viral load response. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2000;23:360&#x2013;361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10836763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nachega JB, Mills EJ, Schechter M. Antiretroviral therapy adherence and retention in care in middle-income and low-income countries: current status of knowledge and research priorities. Curr Opin HIV AIDS. 2010;5:70&#x2013;77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20046150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shuter J, Sarlo J, Kanmaz T, Rode R, Zingman B. HIV-infected patients receiving lopinavir/ritonavir-based antiretroviral therapy achieve high rates of virologic suppression despite adherence rates less than 95%. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2007;45:4&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17460469</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nachega JB, Hislop M, Dowdy DW, Chaisson RE, Regensberg L, et al. Adherence to nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor-based HIV therapy and virologic outcomes. Ann Intern Med. 2007;146:564&#x2013;574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17438315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martin M, Del Cacho E, Codina C, Tuset M, De Lazzari E, et al. Relationship between adherence level, type of the antiretroviral regimen, and plasma HIV type 1 RNA viral load: A prospective cohort study. AIDS Res Hum Retrovirus. 2008;24:1263&#x2013;1268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18834323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Unge C, Sodergard B, Marrone G, Thorson A, Lukhwaro A, et al.  Long-term adherence to antiretroviral treatment and program
drop-out in a high-risk urban setting in sub-Saharan Africa: a prospective
cohort study. PLoS One. 2010;5:e13613. doi: 13610.11371/journal.pone.0013613.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2963610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21049045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>