<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20670448</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2011</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>10</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2458</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>10</Volume><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>29</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Public health triangulation: approach and application to synthesizing data to understand national and local HIV epidemics.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>447</StartPage><MedlinePgn>447</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/1471-2458-10-447</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Public health triangulation is a process for reviewing, synthesising and interpreting secondary data from multiple sources that bear on the same question to make public health decisions. It can be used to understand the dynamics of HIV transmission and to measure the impact of public health programs. While traditional intervention research and meta-analysis would be ideal sources of information for public health decision making, they are infrequently available, and often decisions can be based only on surveillance and survey data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The process involves examination of a wide variety of data sources and both biological, behavioral and program data and seeks input from stakeholders to formulate meaningful public health questions. Finally and most importantly, it uses the results to inform public health decision-making. There are 12 discrete steps in the triangulation process, which included identification and assessment of key questions, identification of data sources, refining questions, gathering data and reports, assessing the quality of those data and reports, formulating hypotheses to explain trends in the data, corroborating or refining working hypotheses, drawing conclusions, communicating results and recommendations and taking public health action.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Triangulation can be limited by the quality of the original data, the potentials for ecological fallacy and "data dredging" and reproducibility of results.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Nonetheless, we believe that public health triangulation allows for the interpretation of data sets that cannot be analyzed using meta-analysis and can be a helpful adjunct to surveillance, to formal public health intervention research and to monitoring and evaluation, which in turn lead to improved national strategic planning and resource allocation.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rutherford</LastName><ForeName>George W</ForeName><Initials>GW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Health Sciences, University of California, San Francisco, California, USA. grutherford@psg.ucsf.edu</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McFarland</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Spindler</LastName><ForeName>Hilary</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>White</LastName><ForeName>Karen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Sadhna V</ForeName><Initials>SV</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Aberle-Grasse</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sabin</LastName><ForeName>Keith</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Nathan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tach&#xe9;</LastName><ForeName>Stephanie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Calleja-Garcia</LastName><ForeName>Jesus M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stoneburner</LastName><ForeName>Rand L</ForeName><Initials>RL</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>U62/CCU922423</GrantID><Agency>PHS HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013487">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968562</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2458</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011159" MajorTopicYN="N">Population Surveillance</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="Y">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011634" MajorTopicYN="Y">Public Health</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013223" MajorTopicYN="N">Statistics as Topic</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="Y">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2010</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2011</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20670448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2920890</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-10-447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1471-2458-10-447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Denzin NK, ed. Sociological Methods. A Sourcebook. Chicago: Aldine Publishing; 1970. pp. 471&#x2013;475.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donoghue TA, Punch KF. Qualitative Educational Research in Action: Doing and Reflecting. London: Routlege Falmer; 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen L, Manion L. Research Methods in Education. London: Croom Helm; 1986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Webb EJ, Campbell DT, Schwartz RD, Sechrest L. Unobtrusive Measures: Nonreactive Measures in the Social Sciences. Chicago: Rand McNally; 1966.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denzin NK. The Research Act in Sociology. Chicago: Aldine Publishing; 1970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson GR. Illustrating triangulation in mixed-methods nursing research. Nurse Res. 2005;12(4):7&#x2013;18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16045043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halcomb E, Andrew S. Triangulation as a method for contemporary nursing research. Nurse Res. 2005;13:71&#x2013;82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16416981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Docherty B. Using triangulation in health services research. Prof Nurse. 2000;16:926&#x2013;927.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12029872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arksey H, O'Malley L. Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework. Int J Soc Res Methodol. 2005;8:19&#x2013;32. doi: 10.1080/1364557032000119616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/1364557032000119616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Global Evidence Mapping Initiative: putting research into context. http://www.evidencemap.org/ Accessed June 1, 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pawon R. Evidence-Based Policy: a Realist Perspective. London: Sage Publishing; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pawson R, Greenhalgh T, Harvey G, Walshe K. Realist review-a new method of systematic review designed for complex policy interventions. J Health Serv Res Policy. 2005;10(Suppl 1):21&#x2013;34. doi: 10.1258/1355819054308530.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1258/1355819054308530</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16053581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook DJ, Mulrow CD, Haynes RB. Systematic reviews: synthesis of best evidence for clinical decisions. Ann Intern Med. 1997;126:376&#x2013;380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9054282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dixon-Woods M, Cavers D, Agarwal S, Annandale E, Arthur A, Harvey J, Hsu R, Katbamna S, Olsen R, Smith L, Riley R, Sutton AJ. Conducting a critical interpretive synthesis of the literature on access to healthcare by vulnerable groups. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2006;6:35. doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-6-35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2288-6-35</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1559637</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16872487</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Razum O, Gerhardus A. Methodological triangulation in public health research - advancement or mirage? Trop Med Int Health. 1999;4:243&#x2013;244. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-3156.1999.00399.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3156.1999.00399.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10357860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoneburner R, Montagu D, Pervilhac C, Fidzani B, Gill W, Kennedy G, Spindler H, Rutherford G. Declines in adult HIV mortality in Botswana, 2003-2005: evidence for an impact of antiretroviral therapy programs [Abstract THLB 0507] Abstracts of the XVI International AIDS Conference, Toronto, Canada. 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoneburner RL, Low-Beer D, Tembo GS, Mertens TE, Asiimwe-Okiror G. Human immunodeficiency virus infection dynamics in East Africa deduced from surveillance. Am J Epidemiol. 1996;12:435&#x2013;449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8823065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Low-Beer D, Stoneburner RL. Rapid communication change in reducing HIV: is Uganda unique? Afr J AIDS Res. 2003;2:9&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25871935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoneburner RL, Low-Beer D. Population-level HIV declines and behavioral risk avoidance in Uganda. Science. 2004;304:714&#x2013;8. doi: 10.1126/science.1093166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1093166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15118157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoneburner RL, Low-Beer D. Elements of sexual behaviour change associated with HIV prevalence declines in Uganda: comparative analyses of HIV and behavioural data in Uganda, Kenya, Malawi and Zambia [Abstract ThOrC721] Abstracts of the XIII International Conference on AIDS, Durban, South Africa. 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS. AIDS Epidemic Update: 2004. Geneva, Switzerland: UNAIDS; 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS; AIDS Division, Ministry of Public Health, Thailand. Evaluation of 100% Condom Programme in Thailand (UNAIDS/00.18E) Geneva, Switzerland: UNAIDS; 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Valdiserri R, Ogden L, McCray E. Accomplishments in HIV prevention science: implications for stemming the epidemic. Nat Med. 2003;91:881&#x2013;886. doi: 10.1038/nm0703-881.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nm0703-881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12835709</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoneburner RL, Des Jarlais DC, Benezra D, Gorelkin L, Sotheran JL, Friedman SR, Schultz S, Marmor M, Mildvan D, Maslansky R. A larger spectrum of severe HIV-1-related disease in intravenous drug users in New York City. Science. 1988;242:916&#x2013;9. doi: 10.1126/science.3187532.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.3187532</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3187532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truong HM, Kellogg T, Klausner JD, Katz MH, Dilley J, Knapper K, Chen S, Prabhu R, Grant RM, Louie B, McFarland W. Increases in sexually transmitted infections and sexual risk behaviour without a concurrent increase in HIV incidence among men who have sex with men in San Francisco: a suggestion of HIV serosorting? Sex Transm Infect. 2006;82:461&#x2013;6. doi: 10.1136/sti.2006.019950.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/sti.2006.019950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2563862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17151031</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria. Technical Background Document on the Scale and Scope of the Five-Year Evaluation of the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria. Geneva, Switzerland: Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria; 2006. http://www.theglobalfund.org/en/terg/evaluations/sa1/ Accessed 8 November 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scheer S, Chu PL, Klausner JD, Katz MH, Schwarcz SK. Effect of highly active antiretroviral therapy on diagnoses of sexually transmitted diseases in people with AIDS. Lancet. 2001;357:432&#x2013;435. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(00)04007-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(00)04007-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11273063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, Department of HIV/AIDS, Department of Child and Adolescent Health and Development. Rapid assessment and response technical guide. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2003. (WHO/HIV 2002.22).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Policy Project. A-squared: analysis &amp; advocacy. http://www.policyproject.com/abstract.cfm/2462</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitson D, Horth R, Gon&#xe7;alves S.  In: Analaysis of HIV prevention response and modes of HIV transmission: the UNAIDS-GAMET supported synthesis process. Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS, Regional Support Team for Eastern and Southern Africa, and World Bank-GAMET. Calvin M, Gorgens-Albino M, Kaesdale S, editor. Analysis of HIV prevention and modes of HIV transmission: Mozambique country synthesis.http://www.unaidsrstesa.org/files/MoT_0.pdf Accessed 27 July 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS. UNAIDS Annual Report: Knowing Your Epidemic (UNAIDS/08.21E) Geneva: UNAIDS; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Altman DG. Systematic reviews of evaluations of prognostic variables. BMJ. 2001;323:224&#x2013;228. doi: 10.1136/bmj.323.7306.224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.323.7306.224</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1120839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11473921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jadad AR, Moore RA, Carroll D, Jenkinson C, Reynolds DJ, Gavaghan DJ, McQuay HJ. Assessing the quality of reports of randomized clinical trials: is blinding necessary? Control Clin Trials. 1996;17:1&#x2013;12. doi: 10.1016/0197-2456(95)00134-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0197-2456(95)00134-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8721797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huwiler-M&#xfc;ntener K, J&#xfc;ni P, Junker C, Egger M. Quality reporting of randomized trials as a measure of methodologic quality. JAMA. 2002;287:2801&#x2013;2804. doi: 10.1001/jama.287.21.2801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1001/jama.287.21.2801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12038917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hill AB. Environment and disease: association or causation? Proc R Soc Med. 1965;58:295&#x2013;300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1898525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14283879</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National AIDS Council, Republic of Mozambique. Report of Mozambique triangulation project: synthesis of data on trends in the national and local HIV epidemics and the reach and intensity of prevention efforts. http://globalhealthsciences.ucsf.edu/PPHG/triangulation/country_reports.html Accessed June 2, 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. HIV Triangulation Resource Guide: Synthesis of Results from Multiple Data Sources for Evaluation and Decision-Making. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO; 2009. Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/ADIS, Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>University of California, San Francisco, Global Health Sciences, Prevention and Public Health Group. Triangulation: country reports. http://globalhealthsciences.ucsf.edu/PPHG/triangulation/country_reports.html Accessed June 2, 2010.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>