<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20186274</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2010</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1549-1676</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Feb</Month><Day>23</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PLoS medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Automated detection of infectious disease outbreaks in hospitals: a retrospective cohort study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e1000238</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e1000238</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e1000238</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000238</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Detection of outbreaks of hospital-acquired infections is often based on simple rules, such as the occurrence of three new cases of a single pathogen in two weeks on the same ward. These rules typically focus on only a few pathogens, and they do not account for the pathogens' underlying prevalence, the normal random variation in rates, and clusters that may occur beyond a single ward, such as those associated with specialty services. Ideally, outbreak detection programs should evaluate many pathogens, using a wide array of data sources.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS AND FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We applied a space-time permutation scan statistic to microbiology data from patients admitted to a 750-bed academic medical center in 2002-2006, using WHONET-SaTScan laboratory information software from the World Health Organization (WHO) Collaborating Centre for Surveillance of Antimicrobial Resistance. We evaluated patients' first isolates for each potential pathogenic species. In order to evaluate hospital-associated infections, only pathogens first isolated &gt;2 d after admission were included. Clusters were sought daily across the entire hospital, as well as in hospital wards, specialty services, and using similar antimicrobial susceptibility profiles. We assessed clusters that had a likelihood of occurring by chance less than once per year. For methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) or vancomycin-resistant enterococci (VRE), WHONET-SaTScan-generated clusters were compared to those previously identified by the Infection Control program, which were based on a rule-based criterion of three occurrences in two weeks in the same ward. Two hospital epidemiologists independently classified each cluster's importance. From 2002 to 2006, WHONET-SaTScan found 59 clusters involving 2-27 patients (median 4). Clusters were identified by antimicrobial resistance profile (41%), wards (29%), service (13%), and hospital-wide assessments (17%). WHONET-SaTScan rapidly detected the two previously known gram-negative pathogen clusters. Compared to rule-based thresholds, WHONET-SaTScan considered only one of 73 previously designated MRSA clusters and 0 of 87 VRE clusters as episodes statistically unlikely to have occurred by chance. WHONET-SaTScan identified six MRSA and four VRE clusters that were previously unknown. Epidemiologists considered more than 95% of the 59 detected clusters to merit consideration, with 27% warranting active investigation or intervention.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Automated statistical software identified hospital clusters that had escaped routine detection. It also classified many previously identified clusters as events likely to occur because of normal random fluctuations. This automated method has the potential to provide valuable real-time guidance both by identifying otherwise unrecognized outbreaks and by preventing the unnecessary implementation of resource-intensive infection control measures that interfere with regular patient care. Please see later in the article for the Editors' Summary.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huang</LastName><ForeName>Susan S</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases and Health Policy Research Institute, University of California Irvine School of Medicine, Irvine, California, United States of America. susan.huang@uci.edu</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yokoe</LastName><ForeName>Deborah S</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stelling</LastName><ForeName>John</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Placzek</LastName><ForeName>Hilary</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kulldorff</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kleinman</LastName><ForeName>Ken</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Brien</LastName><ForeName>Thomas F</ForeName><Initials>TF</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Calderwood</LastName><ForeName>Michael S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vostok</LastName><ForeName>Johanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dunn</LastName><ForeName>Julie</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Platt</LastName><ForeName>Richard</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 RR025040</GrantID><Acronym>RR</Acronym><Agency>NCRR NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>U01 GM076672</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>RR025040-02</GrantID><Acronym>RR</Acronym><Agency>NCRR NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>1U01 GM076672</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>23</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101231360</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1549-1277</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015331" MajorTopicYN="N">Cohort Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="Y">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006761" MajorTopicYN="N">Hospitals</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="Y">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017053" MajorTopicYN="N">Infection Control</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012984" MajorTopicYN="Y">Software</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>RP has received research grants from Sanofi-Aventis, GlaxoSmithKline, Pfizer, and TAP Pharmaceuticals in the past two years. DSY has received research support from Sage Products. MK developed the space-time permutation scan statistic method and the free SaTScan software that were used and evaluated in the study. All other authors report no disclosures.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2009</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20186274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2826381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000238</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zaza S, Jarvis WR. Hospital epidemiology and infection control. In: Mayhall CG, editor. Baltimore: Williams &amp; Wilkins; 1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haley RW, Tenney JH, Lindsey JO, Garner JS, Bennett JV. How frequent are clusters of nosocomial infection in community hospitals? Infect Control. 1985;6:233&#x2013;236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3848422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wenzel RP, Thompson RL, Landry SM, Russell BS, Miller PJ, et al. Hospital acquired infections in intensive care unit patients: an overview with emphasis on epidemics. Infect Control. 1983;4:371&#x2013;375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6556158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gastmeier P, Stamm-Balderjahn S, Hansen S, Zuschneid I, Sohr D, et al. Where should one search when confronted with clusters of nosocomial infection? Am J Infect Control. 2006;34:603&#x2013;605.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17097458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mellmann A, Friedrich AW, Rosenkotter N, Rothganger J, Karch H, et al.  Automated DNA sequence-based early warning system for the detection of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus outbreaks. PLoS Medicine. 2006;3:e33. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.0030033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0030033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1325475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16396609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute. Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing; seventeenth informational supplement. M100-S17. Wayne, Pennsylvania: CLSI; 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHONET Software. from the World Health Organization (WHO) Collaborating Centre for Surveillance of Antimicrobial Resistance. 2009.  Available:  http://www.who.int/drugresistance/whonetsoftware. Accessed 30 June 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SatScan. SatScan. 2005.  Available:  http://www.satscan.org/. Accessed 16 July 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulldorff M. A spatial scan statistic. Commun Stat Theory Methods. 1997;26:1481&#x2013;1496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulldorff M, Athas W, Feuer E, Miller B, Key C. Evaluating cluster alarms: a space-time scan statistic and brain cancer in Los Alamos. Am J Public Health. 1998;88:1377&#x2013;1380.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1509064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9736881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulldorff M. Prospective time-periodic geographical disease surveillance using a scan statistic. J R Stat Soc Ser A. 2001;164:61&#x2013;72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kulldorff M, Heffernan R, Hartman J, Assun&#xe7;&#xe3;o R, Mostashari F. A space-time per-mutation scan statistic for disease outbreak detection. PLoS Med. 2005;2:e59. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.0020059.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC548793</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15719066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kleinman K, Lazarus R, Platt R. A generalized linear mixed models approach for detecting incident clusters of disease in small areas, with an application to biological terrorism. Am J Epidemiol. 2004;159:217&#x2013;224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14742279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klompas M, Yokoe D. Automated surveillance of health care-associated infections. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;48:1268&#x2013;1275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19335166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>