<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">32836680</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0304-4076</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>220</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of econometrics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Econom</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Identification and estimation of the SEIRD epidemic model for COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>63</StartPage><EndPage>85</EndPage><MedlinePgn>63-85</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jeconom.2020.07.038</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This paper studies the SEIRD epidemic model for COVID-19. First, I show that the model is poorly identified from the observed number of deaths and confirmed cases. There are many sets of parameters that are observationally equivalent in the short run but lead to markedly different long run forecasts. Second, I show that the basic reproduction number <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> </mml:msub> </mml:math> can be identified from the data, conditional on epidemiologic parameters, and propose several nonlinear SUR approaches to estimate <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> </mml:msub> </mml:math> . I examine the performance of these methods using Monte Carlo studies and demonstrate that they yield fairly accurate estimates of <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> </mml:msub> </mml:math> . Next, I apply these methods to estimate <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> </mml:msub> </mml:math> for the US, California, and Japan, and document heterogeneity in the value of <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> </mml:msub> </mml:math> across regions. My estimation approach accounts for possible underreporting of the number of cases. I demonstrate that if one fails to take underreporting into account and estimates <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> </mml:msub> </mml:math> from the reported cases data, the resulting estimate of <mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> <mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow> <mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow> </mml:msub> </mml:math> may be biased downward and the resulting forecasts may exaggerate the long run number of deaths. Finally, I discuss how auxiliary information from random tests can be used to calibrate the initial parameters of the model and narrow down the range of possible forecasts of the future number of deaths.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2020 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Korolev</LastName><ForeName>Ivan</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics, Binghamton University, 4400 Vestal Parkway East, PO Box 6000, Binghamton, NY 13902-6000, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2020</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>30</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Econom</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101085117</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0304-4076</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Parameter identification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SEIR model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Seemingly unrelated equations</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2020</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2020</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2020</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32836680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7392128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jeconom.2020.07.038</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0304-4076(20)30262-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Acemoglu D., Chernozhukov V., Werning I., Whinston M.D. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020. Optimal targeted lockdowns in a multi-group SIR model. (Working Paper Series).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkeson A. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020. How deadly is COVID-19? Understanding the difficulties with estimation of its fatality rate. (Working Paper Series).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkeson A. UCLA; 2020. Lockdowns and GDP: Is there a tradeoff?</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkeson A. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020. What will be the economic impact of COVID-19 in the US? Rough estimates of disease scenarios. (Working Paper Series).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avery C., Bossert W., Clark A., Ellison G., Ellison S.F. Policy implications of models of the spread of coronavirus: perspectives and opportunities for economists. COVID Econ. 2020;12:21&#x2013;68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berger D.W., Herkenhoff K.F., Mongey S. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020. An SEIR infectious disease model with testing and conditional quarantine. (Working Paper Series).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bommer C., Vollmer S. Working Paper. University of G&#xf6;ttingen; 2020. Average detection rate of SARS-CoV-2 infections has improved since our last estimates but is still as low as nine percent on March 30th.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowell G., Ammon C., Hengartner N., Hyman J. Transmission dynamics of the great influenza pandemic of 1918 in geneva, Switzerland: Assessing the effects of hypothetical interventions. J. Theoret. Biol. 2006;241(2):193&#x2013;204.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16387331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowell G., Fenimore P., Castillo-Garsow M., Castillo-Chavez C. SARS Outbreaks in Ontario, Hong Kong and Singapore: the role of diagnosis and isolation as a control mechanism. J. Theoret. Biol. 2003;224(1):1&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7134599</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12900200</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowell G., Nishiura H., Bettencourt L.s.M. Comparative estimation of the reproduction number for pandemic influenza from daily case notification data. J. R. Soc. Interface. 2007;4(12):155&#x2013;166.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2358966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17254982</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davidson R., MacKinnon J.G. Oxford University Press; 1993. Estimation and inference in econometrics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ducrot A., Magal P., Nguyen T., Webb G. Identifying the number of unreported cases in SIR epidemic models. Math. Med. Biol. 2019</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31271207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichenbaum M.S., Rebelo S., Trabandt M. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020. The macroeconomics of epidemics. (Working Paper Series).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellison G. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020. Implications of heterogeneous SIR models for analyses of COVID-19. (Working Paper Series).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez-Villaverde J., Jones C. National Bureau of Economic Research; 2020. Estimating and simulating a sird model of covid-19 for many countries, states, and cities. (Working Paper Series).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8799324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35125563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gallant A. Seemingly unrelated nonlinear regressions. J. Econometrics. 1975;3(1):35&#x2013;50.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hausman J.A. Specification tests in econometrics. Econometrica. 1978;46(6):1251&#x2013;1271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korolev I. Binghamton University; 2020. What does the infection fatality ratio really measure?</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauer S.A., Grantz K.H., Bi Q., Jones F.K., Zheng Q., Meredith H.R., Azman A.S., Reich N.G., Lessler J. The incubation period of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) from publicly reported confirmed cases: estimation and application. Annal. Internal Med. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7081172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewbel A. The identification zoo: Meanings of identification in econometrics. J. Econ. Lit. 2019;57(4):835&#x2013;903.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Q., Zhao S., Gao D., Lou Y., Yang S., Musa S.S., Wang M.H., Cai Y., Wang W., Yang L. A conceptual model for the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in Wuhan, China with individual reaction and governmental action. Intl. J. Infect. Dis. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32145465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Y., Gayle A.A., Wilder-Smith A., Rockl&#xf6;v J. The reproductive number of COVID-19 is higher compared to SARS coronavirus. J. Travel Med. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7074654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32052846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magal P., Webb G. The parameter identification problem for SIR epidemic models: identifying unreported cases. J. Math. Biol. 2018;77(6&#x2013;7):1629&#x2013;1648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29330615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manski C.F., Molinari F. Estimating the COVID-19 infection rate: Anatomy of an inference problem. J. Econometrics. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7200382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32377030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marinov T.T., Marinova R.S., Omojola J., Jackson M. Inverse problem for coefficient identification in SIR epidemic models. Comput. Math. Appl. 2014;67(12):2218&#x2013;2227. Efficient Algorithms for Large Scale Scientific Computations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piguillem F., Shi L. Einaudi Institute for Economics and Finance (EIEF); 2020. The optimal COVID-19 quarantine and testing policies.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rackauckas C., Nie Q. Differentialequations. jl &#x2013; a performant and feature-rich ecosystem for solving differential equations in julia. J. Open Res. Softw. 2017;5(1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sanche S., Lin Y.T., Xu C., Romero-Severson E., Hengartner N., Ke R. High contagiousness and rapid spread of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2. Emerg. Infect. Diseases. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7323562</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32255761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toda A.A.  2020. Susceptible-infected-recovered (SIR) dynamics of COVID-19 and economic impact. ArXiv preprint  arXiv:2003.11221.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H., Wang Z., Dong Y., Chang R., Xu C., Yu X., Zhang S., Tsamlag L., Shang M., Huang J. Phase-adjusted estimation of the number of coronavirus disease 2019 cases in Wuhan, China. Cell Discov. 2020;6(1):1&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7039910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32133152</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White H. Consequences and detection of misspecified nonlinear regression models. J. Amer. Statist. Assoc. 1981;76(374):419&#x2013;433.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>