<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">34183531</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>09</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1531-5487</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>32</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Epidemiology (Cambridge, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Epidemiology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Identifiability and Estimation Under the Test-negative Design With Population Controls With the Goal of Identifying Risk and Preventive Factors for SARS-CoV-2 Infection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>690</StartPage><EndPage>697</EndPage><MedlinePgn>690-697</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/EDE.0000000000001385</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Owing to the rapidly evolving coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) virus, quick public health investigations of the relationships between behaviors and infection risk are essential. Recently the test-negative design (TND) was proposed to recruit and survey participants who are symptomatic and being tested for SARS-CoV-2 infection with the goal of evaluating associations between the survey responses (including behaviors and environment) and testing positive on the test. It was also proposed to recruit additional controls who are part of the general population as a baseline comparison group to evaluate risk factors specific to SARS-CoV-2 infection. In this study, we consider an alternative design where we recruit among all individuals, symptomatic and asymptomatic, being tested for the virus in addition to population controls. We define a regression parameter related to a prospective risk factor analysis and investigate its identifiability under the two study designs. We review the difference between the prospective risk factor parameter and the parameter targeted in the typical TND where only symptomatic and tested people are recruited. Using missing data directed acyclic graphs, we provide conditions and required data collection under which identifiability of the prospective risk factor parameter is possible and compare the benefits and limitations of the alternative study designs and target parameters. We propose a novel inverse probability weighting estimator and demonstrate the performance of this estimator through simulation study.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2021 Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schnitzer</LastName><ForeName>Mireille E</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Faculty of Pharmacy, Universit&#xe9; de Montr&#xe9;al, Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, School of Public Health, Universit&#xe9; de Montr&#xe9;al, Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Occupational Health, McGill University, Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Harel</LastName><ForeName>Daphna</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Applied Statistics, Social Science, and Humanities, Steinhardt School of Culture Education and Human Development, New York University, New York, NY.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Practice and Research at the Intersection of Information, Society, and Methodology (PRIISM), Steinhardt School of Culture Education and Human Development, New York University, New York, NY.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ho</LastName><ForeName>Vikki</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, School of Public Health, Universit&#xe9; de Montr&#xe9;al, Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Montr&#xe9;al Hospital Research Centre (CRCHUM), Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koushik</LastName><ForeName>Anita</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, School of Public Health, Universit&#xe9; de Montr&#xe9;al, Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Montr&#xe9;al Hospital Research Centre (CRCHUM), Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Merckx</LastName><ForeName>Joanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Occupational Health, McGill University, Montr&#xe9;al, Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Epidemiology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9009644</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1044-3983</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006040" MajorTopicYN="N">Goals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011155" MajorTopicYN="N">Population Control</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011446" MajorTopicYN="N">Prospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>J.M. is an employee of bioM&#xe9;rieux. This work is unrelated to her function as Director Medical Affairs, bioM&#xe9;rieux Canada, Inc. The other authors have declared no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>55</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34183531</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/EDE.0000000000001385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00001648-202109000-00011</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>He X, Lau EHY, Wu P, et al. Author correction: temporal dynamics in viral shedding and transmissibility of COVID-19. Nat Med. 2020;26:1491&#x2013;1493.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cummings MJ, Baldwin MR, Abrams D, et al. Epidemiology, clinical course, and outcomes of critically ill adults with COVID-19 in New York City: a prospective cohort study. Lancet. 2020;395:1763&#x2013;1770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang D, Hu B, Hu C, et al. Clinical characteristics of 138 hospitalized patients with 2019 novel coronavirus-infected pneumonia in Wuhan, China. JAMA. 2020;323:1061&#x2013;1069.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Respiratory Virus Infections Working Group. Canadian Public Health Laboratory Network Best Practices for COVID-19. Can Commun Dis Rep. 2020;46:112&#x2013;118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hern&#xe1;n MA, Hern&#xe1;ndez-D&#xed;az S, Robins JM. A structural approach to selection bias. Epidemiology. 2004;15:615&#x2013;625.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Serres G, Skowronski DM, Wu XW, Ambrose CS. The test-negative design: validity, accuracy and precision of vaccine efficacy estimates compared to the gold standard of randomised placebo-controlled clinical trials. Euro Surveill. 2013;18:20585.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fukushima W, Hirota Y. Basic principles of test-negative design in evaluating influenza vaccine effectiveness. Vaccine. 2017;35:4796&#x2013;4800.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Foppa IM, Ferdinands JM, Chaves SS, et al. The case test-negative design for studies of the effectiveness of influenza vaccine in inpatient settings. Int J Epidemiol. 2016;45:2052&#x2013;2059.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sullivan SG, Tchetgen Tchetgen EJ, Cowling BJ. Theoretical basis of the test-negative study design for assessment of influenza vaccine effectiveness. Am J Epidemiol. 2016;184:345&#x2013;353.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandenbroucke JP, Pearce N. Test-negative designs: differences and commonalities with other case-control studies with &#x201c;other patient&#x201d; controls. Epidemiology. 2019;30:838&#x2013;844.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandenbroucke JP, Brickley EB, Vandenbroucke-Grauls CMJE, Pearce N. The test-negative design with additional population controls: a practical approach to rapidly obtain information on the causes of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic. Epidemiology. 2020;31:836&#x2013;843.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karmakar B, Small DS. Inference for a test-negative case-control study with added controls. arXiv. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi M, An Q, Ainslie KEC, Haber M, Orenstein WA. A comparison of the test-negative and the traditional case-control study designs for estimation of influenza vaccine effectiveness under nonrandom vaccination. BMC Infect Dis. 2017;17:757.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horvitz DG, Thompson DJ. A generalization of sampling without replacement from a finite universe. J Am Stat Assoc. 1952;47:663&#x2013;685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins J, Rotnitzky A, Zhao L. Analysis of semiparametric regression models for repeated outcomes in the presence of missing data. J Am Stat Assoc. 1995;90:106&#x2013;121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cole SR, Hern&#xe1;n MA. Constructing inverse probability weights for marginal structural models. Am J Epidemiol. 2008;168:656&#x2013;664.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shmueli G. To explain or to predict? Stat Sci. 2010;25:289&#x2013;310.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schooling CM, Jones HE. Clarifying questions about &#x201c;risk factors&#x201d;: predictors versus explanation. Emerg Themes Epidemiol. 2018;15:10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Westreich D, Hudgens MG. Invited commentary: beware the test-negative design. Am J Epidemiol. 2016;184:354&#x2013;356.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniel RM, Kenward MG, Cousens SN, De Stavola BL. Using causal diagrams to guide analysis in missing data problems. Stat Methods Med Res. 2012;21:243&#x2013;256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohan K, Pearl J, Tian J. Graphical models for inference with missing data. Adv Neural Inf Process Syst. 2013;26:1277&#x2013;1285.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cole SR, Platt RW, Schisterman EF, et al. Illustrating bias due to conditioning on a collider. Int J Epidemiol. 2010;39:417&#x2013;420.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson ML, Phillips CH, Benoit J, et al. The impact of selection bias on vaccine effectiveness estimates from test-negative studies. Vaccine. 2018;36:751&#x2013;757.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Laan MJ. Estimation based on case-control designs with known prevalence probability. Int J Biostat. 2008;4:Article 17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang CY, Wang S, Carroll RJ. Estimation in choice-based sampling with measurement error and bootstrap analysis. J Econom. 1997;77:65&#x2013;86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pirracchio R, Petersen ML, van der Laan M. Improving propensity score estimators&#x2019; robustness to model misspecification using super learner. Am J Epidemiol. 2015;181:108&#x2013;119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morozova O, Cohen T, Crawford FW. Risk ratios for contagious outcomes. J R Soc Interface. 2018;15:20170696.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>