<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20394659</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2011</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1558-5646</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>64</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Evolution; international journal of organic evolution</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Evolution</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Uncoordinated phylogeography of Borrelia burgdorferi and its tick vector, Ixodes scapularis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>2653</StartPage><EndPage>2663</EndPage><MedlinePgn>2653-63</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01001.x</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Vector-borne microbes necessarily co-occur with their hosts and vectors, but the degree to which they share common evolutionary or biogeographic histories remains unexplored. We examine the congruity of the evolutionary and biogeographic histories of the bacterium and vector of the Lyme disease system, the most prevalent vector-borne disease in North America. In the eastern and midwestern US, Ixodes scapularis ticks are the primary vectors of Borrelia burgdorferi, the bacterium that causes Lyme disease. Our phylogeographic and demographic analyses of the 16S mitochondrial rDNA suggest that northern I. scapularis populations originated from very few migrants from the southeastern US that expanded rapidly in the Northeast and subsequently in the Midwest after the recession of the Pleistocene ice sheets. Despite this historical gene flow, current tick migration is restricted even between proximal sites within regions. In contrast, B. burgdorferi suffers no barriers to gene flow within the northeastern and midwestern regions but shows clear interregional migration barriers. Despite the intimate association of B. burgdorferi and I. scapularis, the population structure, evolutionary history, and historical biogeography of the pathogen are all contrary to its arthropod vector. In the case of Lyme disease, movements of infected vertebrate hosts may play a larger role in the contemporary expansion and homogenization of the pathogen than the movement of tick vectors whose populations continue to bear the historical signature of climate-induced range shifts.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2010 The Author(s). Journal compilation &#xa9; 2010 The Society for the Study of Evolution.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Humphrey</LastName><ForeName>Parris T</ForeName><Initials>PT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Caporale</LastName><ForeName>Diane A</ForeName><Initials>DA</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brisson</LastName><ForeName>Dustin</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI076342</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI097137</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>U01CK000170</GrantID><Acronym>CK</Acronym><Agency>NCEZID CDC HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>AI076342</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013487">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Evolution</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0373224</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0014-3820</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D025041" MajorTopicYN="N">Animal Migration</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001096" MajorTopicYN="N">Arachnid Vectors</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="Y">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D025065" MajorTopicYN="N">Borrelia burgdorferi</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="Y">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051456" MajorTopicYN="N">Gene Flow</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014644" MajorTopicYN="N">Genetic Variation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005843" MajorTopicYN="Y">Geography</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006239" MajorTopicYN="N">Haplotypes</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018884" MajorTopicYN="N">Ixodes</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="Y">microbiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="N">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="Y">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011157" MajorTopicYN="N">Population Dynamics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2011</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20394659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS196371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2919648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01001.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">EVO1001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Anderson JF, Magnarelli LA, Burgdorfer W, Barbour AG. Spirochetes in Ixodes-Dammini and Mammals from Connecticut. American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 1983;32:818&#x2013;824.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6881431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avise JC. Phylogeography: The History and Formation of Species. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press; 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avise JC, Walker D. Pleistocene phylogeographic effects on avian populations and the speciation process. Proc Biol Sci. 1998;265:457&#x2013;463.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1688909</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9569664</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avise JC, Walker D, Johns GC. Speciation durations and Pleistocene effects on vertebrate phylogeography. Proc Biol Sci. 1998;265:1707&#x2013;1712.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1689361</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9787467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bahlo M, Griffiths RC. Inference from gene trees in a subdivided population. Theor Popul Biol. 2000;57:79&#x2013;95.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10792974</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brisson D, Dykhuizen DE. ospC diversity in Borrelia burgdorferi: different hosts are different niches. Genetics. 2004;168:713&#x2013;722.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1448846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15514047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brisson D, Dykhuizen DE. A modest model explains the distribution and abundance of Borrelia burgdorferi strains. American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2006;74:615&#x2013;622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1851668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16606995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brisson D, Dykhuizen DE, Ostfeld RS. Conspicuous impacts of inconspicuous hosts on the Lyme disease epidemic. Proceedings of the Royal Society, Biological Sciences. 2008;275:227&#x2013;235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2596186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18029304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bunikis J, Garpmo U, Tsao J, Berglund J, Fish D, Barbour AG. Sequence typing reveals extensive strain diversity of the Lyme borreliosis agents Borrelia burgdorferi in North America and Borrelia afzelii in Europe. Microbiology. 2004;150:1741&#x2013;1755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15184561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burgdorfer W, Barbour AG, Hayes SF, Benach JL, Grunwaldt E, Davis JP. Lyme disease - a tick-borne spirochetosis. Science. 1982;216:1317&#x2013;1319.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7043737</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Church SA, Kraus JM, Mitchell JC, Church DR, Taylor DR. Evidence for multiple Pleistocene refugia in the postglacial expansion of the eastern tiger salamander, Ambystoma tigrinum tigrinum. Evolution Int J Org Evolution. 2003;57:372&#x2013;383.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12683533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark KL, Oliver JH, Jr, James AM, Durden LA, Banks CW. Prevalence of borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato infection among rodents and host-seeking ticks in South Carolina. J Med Entomol. 2002;39:198&#x2013;206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11931257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clement M, Posada D, Crandall KA. TCS: a computer program to estimate gene genealogies. Mol Ecol. 2000;9:1657&#x2013;1659.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11050560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dennis DT, Nekomoto TS, Victor JC, Paul WS, Piesman J. Reported distribution of Ixodes scapularis and Ixodes pacificus (Acari: Ixodidae) in the United States. Journal of Medical Entomology. 1998;35:629&#x2013;638.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9775584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diuk-Wasser MA, Gatewood AG, Cortinas MR, Yaremych-Hamer S, Tsao J, Kitron U, Hickling G, Brownstein JS, Walker E, Piesman J, Fish D. Spatiotemporal patterns of host-seeking Ixodes scapularis nymphs (Acari: Ixodidae) in the United States. Journal of Medical Entomology. 2006;43:166&#x2013;176.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16619595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dykhuizen DE, Brisson D, Sandigursky S, Wormser GP, Nowakowski J, Nadelman R, Schwartz I. The propensity of different Borrelia burgdorferi sensu stricto genotypes to cause disseminated infections in humans. American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2008;78:806&#x2013;810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2387051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18458317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Excoffier L, Laval G, Schneider S. Arlequin (version 3.0): An integrated software package for population genetics data analysis. Evol Bioinform Online. 2005;1:47&#x2013;50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2658868</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19325852</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Excoffier L, Smouse PE, Quattro JM. Analysis of molecular variance inferred from metric distances among DNA haplotypes: application to human mitochondrial DNA restriction data. Genetics. 1992;131:479&#x2013;491.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1205020</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1644282</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gatewood AG, Liebman KA, Vourc'h G, Bunikis J, Hamer SA, Cortinas R, Melton F, Cislo P, Kitron U, Tsao J, Barbour AG, Fish D, Diuk-Wasser MA. Climate and tick seasonality are predictors of Borrelia burgdorferi genotype distribution. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2009;75:2476&#x2013;2483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2675205</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19251900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gray JS, Dautel H, Estrada-Pena A, Kahl O, Lindgren E. Effects of climate change on ticks and tick-borne diseases in europe. Interdiscip Perspect Infect Dis. 2009 2009: 593232.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2648658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19277106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanincova K, Kurtenbach K, Diuk-Wasser M, Brei B, Fish D. Epidemic spread of Lyme borreliosis, northeastern United States. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2006;12:604&#x2013;611.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3294694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16704808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huelsenbeck JP, Ronquist F. MRBAYES: Bayesian inference of phylogenetic trees. Bioinformatics. 2001;17:754&#x2013;755.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11524383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hutcheson HJ, Oliver JH, Jr, Houck MA, Strauss RE. Multivariate morphometric discrimination of nymphal and adult forms of the blacklegged tick (Acari: Ixodidae), a principal vector of the agent of Lyme disease in eastern North America. Journal of Medical Entomology. 1995;32:827&#x2013;842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8551506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson JO, DeFoliart GR. Ixodes scapularis Say in northern Wisconsin. J Med Entomol. 1970;7:124&#x2013;125.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5435805</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimmel M, Chakraborty R, King JP, Bamshad M, Watkins WS, Jorde LB. Signatures of population expansion in microsatellite repeat data. Genetics. 1998;148:1921&#x2013;1930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1460085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9560405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knowles LL. Did the pleistocene glaciations promote divergence? Tests of explicit refugial models in montane grasshopprers. Mol Ecol. 2001;10:691&#x2013;701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11298980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhner MK. LAMARC 2.0: maximum likelihood and Bayesian estimation of population parameters. Bioinformatics. 2006;22:768&#x2013;770.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16410317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lane RS, Piesman J, Burgdorfer W. Lyme borreliosis: relation of its causative agent to its vectors and hosts in North America and Europe. Annual Review of Entomology. 1991;36:587&#x2013;609.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2006870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larkin MA, Blackshields G, Brown NP, Chenna R, McGettigan PA, McWilliam H, Valentin F, Wallace IM, Wilm A, Lopez R, Thompson JD, Gibson TJ, Higgins DG. Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0. Bioinformatics. 2007;23:2947&#x2013;2948.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17846036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liveris D, Wormser GP, Nowakowski J, Nadelman R, Bittker S, Cooper D, Varde S, Moy FH, Forseter G, Pavia CS, Schwartz I. Molecular typing of Borrelia burgdorferi from Lyme disease patients by PCR-restriction fragment length polymorphism analysis. Journal of Clinical Microbiology. 1996;34:1306&#x2013;1309.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC229006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8727927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>LoGiudice K, Ostfeld RS, Schmidt KA, Keesing F. The ecology of infectious disease: Effects of host diversity and community composition on Lyme disease risk. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 2003;100:567&#x2013;571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC141036</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12525705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magnarelli LA, Anderson JF, Fish D. Transovarial transmission of Borrelia burgdorferi in Ixodes dammini (Acari:Ixodidae) Journal of Infectious Diseases. 1987;156:234&#x2013;236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3598218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Margos G, Gatewood AG, Aanensen DM, Hanincova K, Terekhova D, Vollmer SA, Cornet M, Piesman J, Donaghy M, Bormane A, Hurn MA, Feil EJ, Fish D, Casjens S, Wormser GP, Schwartz I, Kurtenbach K. MLST of housekeeping genes captures geographic population structure and suggests a European origin of Borrelia burgdorferi. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008;105:8730&#x2013;8735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2435589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18574151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maruyama T, Fuerst PA. Population bottlenecks and nonequilibrium models in population genetics. I. Allele numbers when populations evolve from zero variability. Genetics. 1984;108:745&#x2013;763.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1202438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6500263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mather TN, Telford SR, 3rd, Adler GH. Absence of transplacental transmission of Lyme disease spirochetes from reservoir mice (Peromyscus leucopus) to their offspring. Journal of Infectious Disease. 1991;164:564&#x2013;567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1869842</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNabb SJ, Jajosky RA, Hall-Baker PA, Adams DA, Sharp P, Worshams C, Anderson WJ, Javier AJ, Jones GJ, Nitschke DA, Rey A, Wodajo MS. Summary of notifiable diseases--United States, 2006. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2008;55:1&#x2013;92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18354375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mila B, Girman DJ, Kimura M, Smith TB. Genetic evidence for the effect of a postglacial population expansion on the phylogeography of a North American songbird. Proc Biol Sci. 2000;267:1033&#x2013;1040.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1690639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10874754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neigel JE, Avise JC. Application of a random walk model to geographic distributions of animal mitochondrial DNA variation. Genetics. 1993;135:1209&#x2013;1220.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1205751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8307331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogden NH, Bigras-Poulin M, O'Callaghan C J, Barker IK, Kurtenbach K, Lindsay LR, Charron DF. Vector seasonality, host infection dynamics and fitness of pathogens transmitted by the tick Ixodes scapularis. Parasitology. 2007;134:209&#x2013;227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17032476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogden NH, Lindsay LR, Hanincova K, Barker IK, Bigras-Poulin M, Charron DF, Heagy A, Francis CM, O'Callaghan CJ, Schwartz I, Thompson RA. Role of migratory birds in introduction and range expansion of Ixodes scapularis ticks and of Borrelia burgdorferi and Anaplasma phagocytophilum in Canada. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2008;74:1780&#x2013;1790.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2268299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18245258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliver JH., Jr Lyme borreliosis in the southern United States: a review. J Parasitol. 1996;82:926&#x2013;935.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8973401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orloski K, Hayes E, Campbell GL, Dennis DT. Surveillance for Lyme disease -- United States, 1992&#x2013;1998. MMWR CDC Surveill Summ. 2000;49:1&#x2013;11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10817483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patrican LA. Absence of Lyme disease spirochetes in larval progeny of naturally infected Ixodes scapularis (Acari:Ixodidae) fed on dogs. J Med Entomol. 1997;34:52&#x2013;55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9086711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patz JA, Campbell-Lendrum D, Holloway T, Foley JA. Impact of regional climate change on human health. Nature. 2005;438:310&#x2013;317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16292302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pielou EC. After the Ice Age: The Return of Life to Glaciated North America. Chicago: University Of Chicago Press; 1992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piesman J, Donahue JG, Mather TN, Spielman A. Transovarially acquired Lyme disease spirochetes (Borrelia burgdorferi) in field-collected larval Ixodes dammini (Acari, Ixodidae) Journal of Medical Entomology. 1986;23 219-219.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3701806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu WG, Bruno JF, McCaig WD, Xu Y, Livey I, Schriefer ME, Luft BJ. Wide distribution of a high-virulence Borrelia burgdorferi clone in Europe and North America. Emerg Infect Dis. 2008;14:1097&#x2013;1104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2600328</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18598631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiu WG, Dykhuizen DE, Acosta MS, Luft BJ. Geographic uniformity of the Lyme disease spirochete (Borrelia burgdorferi) and its shared history with tick vector (Ixodes scapularis) in the northeastern United States. Genetics. 2002;160:833&#x2013;849.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1462027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11901105</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raymond M, Rousset F. An exact test for population differentiation. Evolution. 1995;49:1280&#x2013;1283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28568523</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rich SM, Caporale DA, Telford SR, 3rd, Kocher TD, Hartl DL, Spielman A. Distribution of the Ixodes ricinus-like ticks of eastern North America. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America U S A. 1995;92:6284&#x2013;6288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC41502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7603983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JD, Fernando K, Banerjee SN, Durden LA, Byrne SK, Banerjee M, Mann RB, Morshed MG. Birds disperse ixodid (Acari: Ixodidae) and Borrelia burgdorferi- infected ticks in Canada. Journal of Medical Entomology. 2001;38:493&#x2013;500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11476328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seinost G, Dykhuizen DE, Dattwyler RJ, Golde WT, Dunn JJ, Wang IN, Wormser GP, Schriefer ME, Luft BJ. Four clones of Borrelia burgdorferi sensu stricto cause invasive infection in humans. Infection and Immunity. 1999;67:3518&#x2013;3524.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC116539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10377134</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slatkin M, Hudson RR. Pairwise Comparisons of Mitochondrial-DNA Sequences in Stable and Exponentially Growing Populations. Genetics. 1991;129:555&#x2013;562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1204643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1743491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thompson JD, Higgins DG, Gibson TJ. CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice. Nucleic Acids Res. 1994;22:4673&#x2013;4680.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC308517</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7984417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wormser GP, Brisson D, Liveris D, Hanincova K, Sandigursky S, Nowakowski J, Nadelman RB, Ludin S, Schwartz I. Borrelia burgdorferi Genotype Predicts the Capacity for Hematogenous Dissemination during Early Lyme Disease. J Infect Dis. 2008;198:1358&#x2013;1364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2776734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18781866</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>