<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38180740</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1944-7884</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>95</Volume><Issue>1S</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of acquired immune deficiency syndromes (1999)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Triangulation of Routine Antenatal HIV Prevalence Data and Adjusted HIV Estimates in Mozambique.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e70</StartPage><EndPage>e80</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e70-e80</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/QAI.0000000000003333</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Routine health system data are central to monitoring HIV trends. In Mozambique, the reported number of women receiving antenatal care (ANC) and antiretroviral therapy for prevention of mother-to-child transmission (PMTCT) has exceeded the Spectrum-estimated number of pregnant women since 2017. In some provinces, reported HIV prevalence in pregnant women has declined faster than epidemiologically plausible. We hypothesized that these issues are linked and caused by programmatic overenumeration of HIV-negative pregnant women at ANC.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">We triangulated program-reported ANC client numbers with survey-based fertility estimates and facility birth data adjusted for the proportion of facility births. We used survey-reported ANC attendance to produce adjusted time series of HIV prevalence in pregnant women, adjusted for hypothesized program double counting. We calibrated the Spectrum HIV estimation models to adjusted HIV prevalence data to produce adjusted adult and pediatric HIV estimates.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">ANC client numbers were not consistent with facility birth data or modeled population estimates indicating ANC data quality issues in all provinces. Adjusted provincial ANC HIV prevalence in 2021 was median 45% [interquartile range 35%-52% or 2.3 percentage points (interquartile range 2.5-3.5)] higher than reported HIV prevalence. In 2021, calibrating to adjusted antenatal HIV prevalence lowered PMTCT coverage to less than 100% in most provinces and increased the modeled number of new child infections by 35%. The adjusted results better reconciled adult and pediatric antiretroviral treatment coverage and antenatal HIV prevalence with regional fertility estimates.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">Adjusting HIV prevalence in pregnant women using nationally representative household survey data on ANC attendance produced estimates more consistent with surveillance data. The number of children living with HIV in Mozambique has been substantially underestimated because of biased routine ANC prevalence. Renewed focus on HIV surveillance among pregnant women would improve PMTCT coverage and pediatric HIV estimates.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2023 Written work prepared by employees of the Federal Government as part of their official duties is, under the U.S. Copyright Act, a &#x201c;work of the United States Government&#x201d; for which copyright protection under Title 17 of the United States Code is not available. As such, copyright does not extend to the contributions of employees of the Federal Government.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Stevens</LastName><ForeName>Oliver</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6842-9434</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boothe</LastName><ForeName>Makini</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Data for Impact, The Joint United Nations Program on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS), Maputo, Mozambique.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tiberi</LastName><ForeName>Orrin</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National STI and HIV/AIDS Control Program, Ministry of Health Maputo, Maputo, Mozambique.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mahy</LastName><ForeName>Mary</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Data for Impact, The Joint United Nations Program on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS), Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Walker</LastName><ForeName>Patrick</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Glaubius</LastName><ForeName>Robert</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Modeling, Planning and Policy Analysis, Avenir Health, Glastonbury, CT.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McOwen</LastName><ForeName>Jordan</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Maputo, Mozambique; and.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Couto</LastName><ForeName>Aleny</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National STI and HIV/AIDS Control Program, Ministry of Health Maputo, Maputo, Mozambique.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cunha</LastName><ForeName>Morais</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National STI and HIV/AIDS Control Program, Ministry of Health Maputo, Maputo, Mozambique.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Imai-Eaton</LastName><ForeName>Jeffrey W</ForeName><Initials>JW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Communicable Disease Dynamics, Department of Epidemiology, Harvard T. H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI152721</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100892005</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1525-4135</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011247" MajorTopicYN="N">Pregnancy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009073" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Mozambique</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="Y">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018445" MajorTopicYN="N">Infectious Disease Transmission, Vertical</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012107" MajorTopicYN="N">Research Design</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have no funding or conflicts of interest to disclose.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>11</Hour><Minute>16</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38180740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10769169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QAI.0000000000003333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00126334-202401011-00008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Instituto Nacional de Sa&#xfa;de. INSIDA Factsheet; 2021. Available at: https://phia.icap.columbia.edu/mozambique-summary-sheet-en-pt-2021/. Accessed April 26, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS Global. AIDS Update; 2021. Available at: https://www.unaids.org/en/resources/documents/2021/2021-global-aids-update. Accessed May 12, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eaton JW, Brown T, Puckett R, et al. The estimation and projection package age-sex model and the r-hybrid model: new tools for estimating HIV incidence trends in sub-Saharan Africa. AIDS. 2019;33(suppl 3):S235&#x2013;S244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6919231</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31800403</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stover J, Glaubius R, Mofenson L, et al. Updates to the Spectrum/AIM model for estimating key HIV indicators at national and subnational levels. AIDS. 2019;33(suppl 3):S227&#x2013;S234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6919230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31805028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS and WHO. Guidelines for Conducting HIV Sentinel Serosurveys Among Pregnant Women and Other Groups. Geneva, Switzerland: Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS); 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaba B, Boerma T, White R. Monitoring the AIDS epidemic using HIV prevalence data among young women attending antenatal clinics: prospects and problems. AIDS. 2000;14:1633&#x2013;1645.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10983651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaba BW, Carpenter LM, Boerma JT, et al. Adjusting ante-natal clinic data for improved estimates of HIV prevalence among women in sub-Saharan Africa. AIDS. 2000;14:2741&#x2013;2750.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11125893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker N, Stanecki KA, Brown T, et al. Methods and procedures for estimating HIV/AIDS and its impact: the UNAIDS/WHO estimates for the end of 2001. AIDS. 2003;17:2215&#x2013;2225.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14523279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghys PD, Brown T, Grassly NC, et al. The UNAIDS estimation and projection package: a software package to estimate and project national HIV epidemics. Sex Transm Infect. 2004;80(suppl 1):5&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1765839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15249692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Unlinked Anonymous Screening for the Public Health Surveillance of HIV Infections. Geneva, Switzerland: Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS); 1989.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alkema L, Raftery AE, Clark SJ. Probabilistic projections of HIV prevalence using Bayesian melding. Ann Appl Stat. 2007;1:229&#x2013;248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demographic Health Surveys. Key Findings National Survey on Prevalence, Behavioral Risks and Information About HIV and AIDS (2009 INSIDA) MOZAMBIQUE. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO; 2021. Available at: www.measuredhs.com. Accessed June 01, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yeatman S, Eaton JW, Beckles Z, et al. Impact of ART on the fertility of HIV-positive women in sub-Saharan Africa. Trop Med Int Health. 2016;21:1071&#x2013;1085.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27371942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marsh K, Mahy M, Salomon JA, et al. Assessing and adjusting for differences between HIV prevalence estimates derived from national population-based surveys and antenatal care surveillance, with applications for Spectrum 2013. AIDS. 2014;28:S497&#x2013;S505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4247262</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25203158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gouws E, Mishra V, Fowler TB. Comparison of adult HIV prevalence from national population-based surveys and antenatal clinic surveillance in countries with generalised epidemics: implications for calibrating surveillance data. Sex Transm Infect. 2008;84(suppl 1):i17&#x2013;i23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2569190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18647861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eaton JW, Rehle TM, Jooste S, et al. Recent HIV prevalence trends among pregnant women and all women in sub-Saharan Africa: implications for HIV estimates. AIDS. 2014;28(suppl 1):S507&#x2013;S514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4247272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25406753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eaton JW, Bao L. Accounting for nonsampling error in estimates of HIV epidemic trends from antenatal clinic sentinel surveillance. AIDS. 2017;31(suppl 1):S61&#x2013;S68.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5679137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28296801</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Conducting HIV Surveillance Based on Routine Programme Data Among Pregnant Women Attending ANC. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng B, Eaton JW, Mahy M, et al. Comparison of HIV prevalence among antenatal clinic attendees estimated from routine testing and unlinked anonymous testing. Stat Biosci. 2020;12:279&#x2013;294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7863791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33552307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheng B, Marsh K, Slavkovic AB, et al. Statistical models for incorporating data from routine HIV testing of pregnant women at antenatal clinics into HIV/AIDS epidemic estimates. AIDS. 2017;31(suppl 1):S87&#x2013;S94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5356494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28296804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Young PW, Mahomed M, Horth RZ, et al. Routine data from prevention of mother-to-child transmission (PMTCT) HIV testing not yet ready for HIV surveillance in Mozambique: a retrospective analysis of matched test results. BMC Infect Dis. 2013;13:96.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3598230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23432847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woldesenbet SA, Kufa T, Barron P, et al. Assessment of readiness to transition from antenatal HIV surveillance surveys to PMTCT programme data-based HIV surveillance in South Africa: the 2017 Antenatal Sentinel HIV Survey. Int J Infect Dis. 2020;91:50&#x2013;56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8767461</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31712090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sirengo M, Rutherford GW, Otieno-Nyunya B, et al. Evaluation of Kenya's readiness to transition from sentinel surveillance to routine HIV testing for antenatal clinic-based HIV surveillance. BMC Infect Dis. 2016;16:113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4779556</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26945861</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mate KS, Bennett B, Mphatswe W, et al. Challenges for routine health system data management in a large public programme to prevent mother-to-child HIV transmission in South Africa. PLoS One. 2009;4:e5483.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2677154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19434234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gourlay A, Wringe A, Todd J, et al. Challenges with routine data sources for PMTCT programme monitoring in East Africa: insights from Tanzania. Glob Health Action. 2015;8:29987.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4695617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26715204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maheu-Giroux M Jahn A Kalua T, et al. HIV surveillance based on routine testing data from antenatal clinics in Malawi (2011&#x2013;2018): measuring and adjusting for bias from imperfect testing coverage. AIDS. 2019;33(suppl 3):S295&#x2013;S302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6919236</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31805029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MISAU. UNAIDS Spectrum Files Retrieved From 2021 UNAIDS Global HIV Estimates. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO; 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harklerode R, Schwarcz S, Hargreaves J, et al. Feasibility of establishing HIV case-based surveillance to measure progress along the health sector cascade: situational assessments in Tanzania, South Africa, and Kenya. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2017;3:e44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5525003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28694240</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicol E, Dudley L, Bradshaw D. Assessing the quality of routine data for the prevention of mother-to-child transmission of HIV: an analytical observational study in two health districts with high HIV prevalence in South Africa. Int J Med Inform. 2016;95:60&#x2013;70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27697233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kripke K, Opuni M, Odoyo-June E, et al. Data triangulation to estimate age-specific coverage of voluntary medical male circumcision for HIV prevention in four Kenyan counties. PLoS One. 2018;13:e0209385. 10.1371/journal.pone.0209385</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0209385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6298728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30562394</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eaton JW, Dwyer-Lindgren L, Gutreuter S, et al. Naomi: a new modelling tool for estimating HIV epidemic indicators at the district level in sub-Saharan Africa. J Int AIDS Soc. 2021;24(suppl 5):e25788.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8454682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34546657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MISAU. Inquerito Demografico e de Saude 2003. MISAU ; 2003. Available at:
https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/FR161/FR161.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MISAU. 
Mo&#xe7;ambique Inqu&#xe9;rito Demogr&#xe1;fi co e de Sa&#xfa;de. MISAU; 2011. Available at:
https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/FR266/FR266.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MISAU. Inqu&#xe9;rito de Indicadores de Imuniza&#xe7;&#xe3;o, Mal&#xe1;ria e HIV/SIDA em Mo&#xe7;ambique (IMASIDA) 2015; 2015. Available at: https://dhsprogram.com/publications/publication-ais12-ais-final-reports.cfm. Accessed May 11, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>MISAU. Mo&#xe7;ambique Inqu&#xe9;rito Nacional sobre Indicadores de Mal&#xe1;ria (IIM) 2018; 2019. Available at: https://dhsprogram.com/publications/publication-mis33-mis-final-reports.cfm. Accessed May 19, 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watson OJ, FitzJohn R, Eaton JW. rdhs: an R package to interact with the demographic and health surveys (DHS) program datasets. Wellcome Open Res. 2019;4:103.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lumley T. Package &#x201c;Survey&#x201d;&#x2014;Analysis of Complex Survey Samples; 2022. Available at: http://r-survey.r-forge.r-project.org/survey/. Accessed November 02, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Spectrum File Request&#x2014;UNAIDS HIV Tools; 2022. Available at: https://hivtools.unaids.org/spectrum-file-request/. Accessed August 30, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>IV RGPH 2017&#x2014;Instituto Nacional de Estatistica; 2022. Available at: http://www.ine.gov.mz/iv-rgph-2017. Accessed July 21, 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UN Population Division. World Population Prospects&#x2014;Population Division&#x2014;United Nations; 2020. Available: https://population.un.org/wpp/. Accessed April 03, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen WJ, Walker N. Fertility of HIV-infected women: insights from demographic and health surveys. Sex Transm Infect. 2010;86(suppl 4):ii22&#x2013;ii27.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3173817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21106511</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown T, Bao L, Eaton JW, et al. Improvements in prevalence trend fitting and incidence estimation in EPP 2013. AIDS. 2014;28(suppl 4):S415&#x2013;S425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4247274</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25406747</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MISAU. Modelos Diferenciados de Servi&#xe7;os em Mo&#xe7;ambique Modelos Diferenciados de Servi&#xe7;os em Mo&#xe7;ambique [in Portuguese]. Mo&#xe7;ambique: CNCS; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Updated Recommendations on Service Delivery for the Treatment and Care of People Living With HIV. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33999550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>