<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36262037</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-6591</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>76</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical infectious diseases : an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Clinically Adjudicated Reference Standards for Evaluation of Infectious Diseases Diagnostics.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>938</StartPage><EndPage>943</EndPage><MedlinePgn>938-943</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/cid/ciac829</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Lack of a gold standard can present a challenge for evaluation of diagnostic test accuracy of some infectious diseases tests, particularly when the test's accuracy potentially exceeds that of its predecessors. This approach may measure agreement with an imperfect reference, rather than correctness, because the right answer is unknown. Solutions consist of multitest comparators, including those that involve a test under evaluation if multiple new tests are being evaluated together, using latent class modeling, and clinically adjudicated reference standards. Clinically adjudicated reference standards may be considered as comparator methods when no predefined test or composite of tests is sufficiently accurate; they emulate clinical practice in that multiple data pieces are clinically assessed together.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s) 2022. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Infectious Diseases Society of America. All rights reserved. For permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Patel</LastName><ForeName>Robin</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6344-4141</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Microbiology, Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Public Health, Infectious Diseases and Occupational Medicine, Department of Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minnesota, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsalik</LastName><ForeName>Ephraim L</ForeName><Initials>EL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Emergency Medicine Service, Durham VA Health Care System, Durham, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, Duke University School of Medicine, Durham, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Danaher Diagnostics, Washington, District of Columbia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Evans</LastName><ForeName>Scott</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Biostatistics Center and the Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, George Washington Milken Institute School of Public Health, George Washington University, Washington, District of Columbia, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fowler</LastName><ForeName>Vance G</ForeName><Initials>VG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, Duke University School of Medicine, Durham, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Duke Clinical Research Institute, Durham, North Carolina, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Doernberg</LastName><ForeName>Sarah B</ForeName><Initials>SB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, University of California, San Francisco, California, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>Antibacterial Resistance Leadership Group</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>UM1 AI104681</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>UM1AI104681</GrantID><Acronym>NH</Acronym><Agency>NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9203213</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1058-4838</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003955" MajorTopicYN="Y">Diagnostic Tests, Routine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Communicable Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012015" MajorTopicYN="N">Reference Standards</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012680" MajorTopicYN="N">Sensitivity and Specificity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinically adjusted reference standards</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Potential conflicts of interest. V. G. F. reports personal fees from Novartis, Novadigm, Durata, Debiopharm, Genentech, Achaogen, Affinium, Medicines Co., Cerexa, Tetraphase, Trius, MedImmune, Bayer, Theravance, Basilea, Affinergy, Janssen, xBiotech, Contrafect, Regeneron, Basilea, Destiny, Amphliphi Biosciences, Integrated Biotherapeutics, C3J, Armata, Valanbio, Akagera, Aridis, Roche, and Pfizer; grants from the National Institutes of Health (NIH), MedImmune, Cerexa/Forest/Actavis/Allergan, Pfizer, Advanced Liquid Logics, Theravance, Novartis, Cubist/Merck, Medical Biosurfaces, Locus, Affinergy, Contrafect, Karius, Genentech, Regeneron, Basilea, Janssen, from Green Cross, Cubist, Cerexa, Durata, Theravance, and Debiopharm. Royalties from UpToDate. V. G. F. also reports support for attending meetings and/or travel from Contrafect to present phase 2 data at 2019 ECCMID; patents planned, issued, or pending (Sepsis Diagnostics); a role as Associate Editor, Clinical Infectious Diseases (2017&#x2013;2022); and stock or stock options from ArcBio and Valanbio. R. P. reports grants from ContraFect, TenNor Therapeutics Limited, and BioFire. R. P. is a consultant to Curetis, PathoQuest, Selux Diagnostics, 1928 Diagnostics, PhAST, Torus Biosystems, Day Zero Diagnostics, Mammoth Biosciences, and Qvella; monies are paid to Mayo Clinic. Mayo Clinic and R. P. have a relationship with Pathogenomix. R. P. has research supported by Adaptive Phage Therapeutics. Mayo Clinic has a royalty-bearing know-how agreement and equity in Adaptive Phage Therapeutics. R. P. is also a consultant to Netflix, Abbott Laboratories, and CARB-X. In addition, R. P. has a patent on Bordetella pertussis/parapertussis polymerase chain reaction issued, a patent on a device/method for sonication with royalties paid by Samsung to Mayo Clinic, and a patent on an antibiofilm substance issued. R. P. receives honoraria from the NBME, Up-to-Date, and the Infectious Diseases Board Review Course. E. L. T. reports grants or contracts from NIAID, DTRA, Sanofi, NIGMS, DARPA, Karius, Department of Veterans Affairs, and Department of Defense. E. L. T. has patents issued or pending for methods for characterizing infections and methods for developing tests for the same; host based molecular signatures of human infection with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2; transcriptional signature for candidemia, gene expression signature useful to predict or diagnose sepsis and methods of using the same; methods to diagnose and treat acute respiratory infections; and biomarkers for the molecular classification of bacterial infection; E. L. T. is an employee of Danaher Corp and previously received consulting fees from Biomeme and has stock or stock options for Biomeme and Danaher. S. R. E. reports grant support from NIH; a contract with DeGruyter; royalties from Taylor &amp; Francis; honoraria from the Analgesic, Anesthetic, and Addiction Clinical Trial Translations, Innovations, Opportunities, and Networks (ACTTION); meeting support from the Food and Drug Administration, Deming Conference on Applied Statistics, Clinical Trial Transformation Initiative, Council for International Organizations of Medical Sciences, International Chinese Statistical Association Applied Statistics Symposium, Antimicrobial Resistance and Stewardship Conference; unpaid board membership from the American Statistical Association, Society for Clinical Trials, Frontier Science Foundation; consulting fees from Genentech, AstraZeneca, Takeda, Microbiotix, Johnson &amp; Johnson, Endologix, ChemoCentryx, Becton Dickenson, Atricure, Roivant, Neovasc, Nobel Pharma, Horizon, International Drug Development Institute, and SVB Leerink; data and safety monitoring board or advisory board service for NIH, Breast International Group, University of Pennsylvania, Washington University, Duke University, Roche, Pfizer, Takeda, Akouos, Apellis, Teva, Vir, DayOneBio, Alexion, Tracon, Rakuten, Abbvie, GSK, Eli Lilly, Nuvelution, Clover, FHI Clinical, Lung Biotech, SAB Biopharm, and Advantagene/Candel. S. B. D. reports research funding related to coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) from Gilead, Regeneron, Shinogi, and the NIH and non&#x2013;COVID-19-related consulting and research funding from Genentech, Basilea, Shinogi, J + J, and the NIH; support for travel from IDSA, and patents issued (WO2006116688A3). All other authors report no potential conflicts. All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest. Conflicts that the editors consider relevant to the content of the manuscript have been disclosed.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36262037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10226744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciac829</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">6763734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Glasziou P, Irwig L, Deeks JJ. When should a new test become the current reference standard? Ann Intern Med 2008; 149:816&#x2013;22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19047029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Obuchowski NA, Subhas N, Schoenhagen P. Testing for interchangeability of imaging tests. Acad Radiol 2014; 21:1483&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25300725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barnhart HX, Kosinski AS, Haber MJ. Assessing individual agreement. J Biopharm Stat 2007; 17:697&#x2013;719.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17613649</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Self WH, Rosen J, Sharp SC, et al. Diagnostic accuracy of FebriDx: a rapid test to detect immune responses to viral and bacterial upper respiratory infections. J Clin Med 2017; 6:94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5664009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28991170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Doernberg SB, Komarow L, Tran TTT, et al. 
Simultaneous evaluation of diagnostic assays for pharyngeal and rectal <i>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</i> and <i>Chlamydia trachomatis</i> using a master protocol. Clin Infect Dis 2020; 71:2314&#x2013;22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7713680</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31734695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stout JE, Wu Y, Ho CS, et al. Evaluating latent tuberculosis infection diagnostics using latent class analysis. Thorax 2018; 73:1062&#x2013;70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6494673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29982223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller RR III, Lopansri BK, Burke JP, et al. Validation of a host response assay, SeptiCyte LAB, for discriminating sepsis from systemic inflammatory response syndrome in the ICU. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2018; 198:903&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6835074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29624409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleming-Dutra KE, Hersh AL, Shapiro DJ, et al. Prevalence of inappropriate antibiotic prescriptions among US ambulatory care visits, 2010&#x2013;2011. JAMA 2016; 315:1864&#x2013;73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27139059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collins J, Huynh M. Estimation of diagnostic test accuracy without full verification: a review of latent class methods. Stat Med 2014; 33:4141&#x2013;69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4199084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24910172</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Smeden M, Naaktgeboren CA, Reitsma JB, Moons KGM, de Groot JAH. Latent class models in diagnostic studies when there is no reference standard-A systematic review. Am J Epidemiol 2014; 179:423&#x2013;31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24272278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peel TN, Dylla BL, Hughes JG, et al. Improved diagnosis of prosthetic joint infection by culturing periprosthetic tissue specimens in blood culture bottles. mBio 2016; 7:e01776&#x2013;15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4725002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26733067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albert PS, Dodd LE. A cautionary note on the robustness of latent class models for estimating diagnostic error without a gold standard. Biometrics 2004; 60:427&#x2013;35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15180668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reitsma JB, Rutjes AW, Khan KS, Coomarasamy A, Bossuyt PM. A review of solutions for diagnostic accuracy studies with an imperfect or missing reference standard. J Clin Epidemiol 2009; 62:797&#x2013;806.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19447581</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones J, Hunter D. Consensus methods for medical and health services research. BMJ 1995; 311:376&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2550437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7640549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertens LC, Broekhuizen BD, Naaktgeboren CA, et al. Use of expert panels to define the reference standard in diagnostic research: a systematic review of published methods and reporting. PLoS Med 2013; 10:e1001531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3797139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24143138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>G&#xe1;mez-D&#xed;az LY, Enriquez LE, Matute JD, et al. Diagnostic accuracy of HMGB-1, sTREM-1, and CD64 as markers of sepsis in patients recently admitted to the emergency department. Acad Emerg Med 2011; 18:807&#x2013;15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21762470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Fowler VG, Allen KB, Moreira ED, et al. 
Effect of an investigational vaccine for preventing <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i> infections after cardiothoracic surgery: a randomized trial. JAMA 2013; 309:1368&#x2013;78.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23549582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Fowler VG Jr, Boucher HW, Corey GR, et al. 
Daptomycin versus standard therapy for bacteremia and endocarditis caused by <i>Staphylococcus aureus</i>. N Engl J Med 2006; 355:653&#x2013;65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16914701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holland TL, Raad I, Boucher HW, et al. Effect of algorithm-based therapy vs usual care on clinical success and serious adverse events in patients with staphylococcal bacteremia: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA 2018; 320:1249&#x2013;58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6233609</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30264119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivy MI, Sharma K, Greenwood-Quaintance KE, et al. Synovial fluid &#x3b1; defensin has comparable accuracy to synovial fluid white blood cell count and polymorphonuclear percentage for periprosthetic joint infection diagnosis. Bone Joint J 2021; 103-b:1119&#x2013;26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34058872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ko ER, Henao R, Frankey K, et al. Prospective validation of a rapid host gene expression test to discriminate bacterial from viral respiratory infection. JAMA Netw Open 2022; 5:e227299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9011121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35420659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Houten CB, Naaktgeboren CA, Ashkenazi-Hoffnung L, et al. Expert panel diagnosis demonstrated high reproducibility as reference standard in infectious diseases. J Clin Epidemiol 2019; 112:20&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30930247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Sinclair A, Xie X, Teltscher M, Dendukuri N. Systematic review and meta-analysis of a urine-based pneumococcal antigen test for diagnosis of community-acquired pneumonia caused by <i>Streptococcus pneumoniae</i>. J Clin Microbiol 2013; 51:2303&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3697702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23678060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vancikova Z, Trojanek M, Zemlickova H, et al. Pneumococcal urinary antigen positivity in healthy colonized children: is it age dependent? Wien Klin Wochenschr 2013; 125:495&#x2013;500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23928934</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisano ED. Digital compared with screen-film mammography: measures of diagnostic accuracy among women screened in the Ontario breast screening program&#x2013;evidence that direct radiography is superior to computed radiography for cancer detection. Radiology 2016; 278:311&#x2013;2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26789598</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pisano ED, Hendrick RE, Yaffe MJ, et al. Diagnostic accuracy of digital versus film mammography: exploratory analysis of selected population subgroups in DMIST. Radiology 2008; 246:376&#x2013;83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2659550</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18227537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewin JM, Hendrick RE, D'Orsi CJ, et al. Comparison of full-field digital mammography with screen-film mammography for cancer detection: results of 4,945 paired examinations. Radiology 2001; 218:873&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11230669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bankier AA, Levine D, Halpern EF, Kressel HY. Consensus interpretation in imaging research: is there a better way? Radiology 2010; 257:14&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20851935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodino KG, Toledano M, Norgan AP, et al. Retrospective review of clinical utility of shotgun metagenomic sequencing testing of cerebrospinal fluid from a U. S. Tertiary care medical center. J Clin Microbiol 2020; 58:e01729&#x2013;20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7685881</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32938739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Thoendel M, Jeraldo P, Greenwood-Quaintance KE, et al. 
A novel prosthetic joint infection pathogen, <i>Mycoplasma salivarium</i>, identified by metagenomic shotgun sequencing. Clin Infect Dis 2017; 65:332&#x2013;5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5848249</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28379472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee R, Komarow L, Virk A, et al. Randomized trial evaluating clinical impact of RAPid IDentification and susceptibility testing for gram-negative bacteremia: rAPIDS-GN. Clin Infect Dis 2021; 73:e39&#x2013;46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8246790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32374822</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Banerjee R, Teng CB, Cunningham SA, et al. Randomized trial of rapid multiplex polymerase chain reaction-based blood culture identification and susceptibility testing. Clin Infect Dis 2015; 61:1071&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4560903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26197846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>