<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38591424</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1539-1612</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>23</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Season>Sep-Oct</Season></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Pharmaceutical statistics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Pharm Stat</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dynamic borrowing of historical controls adjusting for covariates in vaccine efficacy clinical trials.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>630</StartPage><EndPage>644</EndPage><MedlinePgn>630-644</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/pst.2384</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Traditional vaccine efficacy trials usually use fixed designs and often require large sample sizes. Recruiting a large number of subjects can make the trial expensive, long, and difficult to conduct. A possible approach to reduce the sample size and speed up the development is to use historical controls. In this paper, we extend the robust mixture prior (RMP) approach (a well established approach for Bayesian dynamic borrowing of historical controls) to adjust for covariates. The adjustment is done using classical methods from causal inference: inverse probability of treatment weighting, G-computation and double-robust estimation. We evaluate these covariate-adjusted RMP approaches using a comprehensive simulation study and demonstrate their use by performing a retrospective analysis of a prophylactic human papillomavirus vaccine efficacy trial. Adjusting for covariates reduces the drift between current and historical controls, with a beneficial effect on bias, control of type I error and power.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024 GSK Biologicals SA. Pharmaceutical Statistics published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Callegaro</LastName><ForeName>Andrea</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-4805-5118</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, GSK, Rixensart, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Luo</LastName><ForeName>Yongyi</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-0447-329X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Mathematics, Swiss Federal Institute of Technology Lausanne (EPFL), Lausanne, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Karkada</LastName><ForeName>Naveen</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, GSK, Rixensart, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zahaf</LastName><ForeName>Toufik</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, GSK, Rixensart, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>GlaxoSmithKline Biologicals SA</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Pharm Stat</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101201192</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1539-1604</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D053918">Papillomavirus Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053918" MajorTopicYN="Y">Papillomavirus Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001499" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bayes Theorem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018401" MajorTopicYN="N">Sample Size</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003198" MajorTopicYN="Y">Computer Simulation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012107" MajorTopicYN="N">Research Design</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002986" MajorTopicYN="N">Clinical Trials as Topic</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016896" MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030361" MajorTopicYN="N">Papillomavirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015982" MajorTopicYN="N">Bias</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Bayesian inference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">G&#x2010;estimation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">adaptive design</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">causal inference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">clinical trials</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">double robust estimator</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dynamic borrowing</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">historical controls</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">propensity score</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">robust mixture prior</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vaccine efficacy trial</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Andrea Callegaro, Naveen Karkada and Toufik Zahaf are employees of and hold shares in GSK. Yongyi Luo has no conflicts of interest to declare.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>23</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>16</Hour><Minute>20</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38591424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pst.2384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Pocock SJ. The combination of randomized and historical controls in clinical trials. J Chron Dis. 1976;29:175&#x2010;188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ibrahim JG, Chen MH. Power prior distributions for regression models. Statistical Science. 2000;46&#x2010;60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duan Y, Ye K, Smith EP. Evaluating water quality using power priors to incorporate historical data. Environ. 2006;17:95&#x2010;106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuenschwander B, Branson M, Spiegelhalter DJ. A note on the power prior. Stat Med. 2009;28:3562&#x2010;3566.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuenschwander B, Capkun&#x2010;Niggli G, Branson M, Spiegelhalter DJ. Summarizing historical data on controls in clinical trials. Clin Trial. 2010;7:5&#x2010;18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hobbs BP, Carlin BP, Mandrekar SJ, et al. Hierarchical commensurate and power prior models for adaptive incorporation of historical data in clinical trials. Biometrics. 2011;67:1047&#x2010;1056.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schmidli H, Gsteiger S, Roychoudhury S, O'Hagan A, Spiegelhalter D, Neuenschwander B. Robust meta&#x2010;analytic&#x2010;predictive priors in clinical trials with historical control information. Biometrics. 2014;70:1023&#x2010;1032.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen MH, Ibrahim JG. The relationship between the power prior and hierarchical models. Bayesian Anal. 2006;1:551&#x2010;574.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viele K, Berry S, Neuenschwander B, et al. Use of historical control data for assessing treatment effects in clinical trials. Pharm Stat. 2014;13:41&#x2010;54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Rosmalen J, Dejardin D, van Norden Y, L&#xf6;wenberg B, Lesaffre E. Including historical data in the analysis of clinical trials: is it worth the effort? Stat Methods Med Res. 2018;27:3167&#x2010;3182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callegaro A, Galwey N, Abellan JJ. Historical controls in clinical trials: a note on linking Pocock's model with the robust mixture priors. Biostatistics. 2023;24(2):443&#x2010;448.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jin M, Feng D, Liu G. Bayesian approaches on borrowing historical data for vaccine efficacy trials. Stat Biopharm Res. 2020;12(3):284&#x2010;292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callegaro A, Karkada N, Aris E, Zahaf T. Vaccine clinical trials with dynamic borrowing of historical controls: two retrospective studies. Pharm Stat. 2023;22:475&#x2010;491.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hernan MA, Robins JM. Causal Inference: What if. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC; 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dunning AJ. A model for immunological correlates of protection. Stat Med. 2006;25(9):1485&#x2010;1497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qin L, Gilbert PB, Corey L, McElrath MJ, Self SG. A framework for assessing immunological correlates of protection in vaccine trials. J Infect Dis. 2007;196(9):1304&#x2010;1312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Piedra PA, Jewell AM, Cron SG, Atmar RL, Glezen WP. Correlates of immunity to respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) associated&#x2010;hospitalization: establishment of minimum protective threshold levels of serum neutralizing antibodies. Vaccine. 2003;21(24):3479&#x2010;3482.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castellsagu&#xe9; X, Naud P, Chow SN, et al. Risk of newly detected infections and cervical abnormalities in women seropositive for naturally acquired human papillomavirus type 16/18 antibodies: analysis of the control arm of PATRICIA. J Infect Dis. 2014;210(4):517&#x2010;534.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X, Suttner L, Jemielita T, Li X. Propensity score&#x2010;integrated Bayesian prior approaches for augmented control designs: a simulation trial. J Biopharm Stat. 2022;32:1&#x2010;21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao H, Hobbs BP, Ma H, Jiang Q, Carlin BP. Combining non&#x2010;randomized and randomized data in clinical trials using commensurate priors. Health Serv Outcomes Res Methodol. 2016;16(3):154&#x2010;171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin J, Gamalo&#x2010;Siebers M, Tiwari R. Propensity score matched augmented controls in randomized clinical trials: a case trial. Pharm Stat. 2018;17(5):629&#x2010;647.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang C, Li H, Chen WC, et al. Propensity score&#x2010;integrated power prior approach for incorporating real&#x2010;world evidence in single&#x2010;arm clinical studies. J Biopharm Stat. 2019;29(5):731&#x2010;748.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paavonen J, Naud P, Salmer&#xf3;n J, et al. Efficacy of human papillomavirus (HPV)&#x2010;16/18 AS04&#x2010;adjuvanted vaccine against cervical infection and precancer caused by oncogenic HPV types (PATRICIA): final analysis of a double&#x2010;blind, randomised trial in young women. The Lancet. 2009;374(9686):301&#x2010;314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hildesheim A, Wacholder S, Catteau G, et al. Efficacy of the HPV&#x2010;16/18 vaccine: final according to protocol results from the blinded phase of the randomized Costa Rica HPV&#x2010;16/18 vaccine trial. Vaccine. 2014;32(39):5087&#x2010;5097.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boos DD, Stefanski LA. Essential Statistical Inference: Theory and Methods. Vol 591. Springer; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenbaum PR, Rubin DB. The central role of the propensity score in observational studies for causal effects. Biometrika. 1983;70(1):41&#x2010;55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morgan SL, Todd JL. A diagnostic routine for the detection of consequential heterogeneity of causal effects. Sociological Methodology. 2008;38:231&#x2010;281.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Assignment to treatment group on the basis of a covariate. Journal of Educational Statistics. 1977;2:1&#x2010;26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mercatanti A, Li F. Do debit cards increase household spending? Evidence from a semiparametric causal analysis of a survey. The Annals of Applied Statistics. 2014;8(4):2485&#x2010;2508.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bang H, Robins JM. Doubly robust estimation in missing data and causal inference models. Biometrics. 2005;61(4):962&#x2010;973.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins J, Sued M, Lei&#x2010;Gomez Q, Rotnitzky A. Comment: performance of double&#x2010;robust estimators when &#x201c;inverse probability&#x201d; weights are highly variable. Statistical Science. 2007;22(4):544&#x2010;559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morita S, Thall PF, Mueller P. Determining the effective sample size of a parametric prior. Biometrics. 2008;64(2):595&#x2010;602.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Der Laan MJ, Rubin D. Targeted maximum likelihood learning. SU.C. Berkeley division of biostatistics working paper series. Targeted Maximum Likelihood Learning. 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weber S, Li Y, Seaman JW, Kakizume T, Schmidli H. Applying meta&#x2010;analytic&#x2010;predictive priors with the R Bayesian evidence synthesis tools. J Stat Softw. 2021;100(19):1&#x2010;32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cuffe RL. The inclusion of historical control data may reduce the power of a confirmatory study. Stat Med. 2011;30(12):1329&#x2010;1338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Funk MJ, Westreich D, Wiesen C, St&#xfc;rmer T, Brookhart MA, Davidian M. Doubly robust estimation of causal effects. Am J Epidemiol. 2011;173(7):761&#x2010;767.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>