<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">41573816</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2468-0427</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2026</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Infectious Disease Modelling</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Infect Dis Model</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multi-event dynamic capture-recapture model for big data: Estimating undetected COVID-19 cases in British Columbia, Canada.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>764</StartPage><EndPage>786</EndPage><MedlinePgn>764-786</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.idm.2025.12.016</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The accurate quantification of the impact of COVID-19 pandemic on both public health and the economy is essential for informed policy-making. However, the true scope of the pandemic remains challenging to ascertain due to undetected cases, particularly when relying on reported cases, which rely heavily on test availability and strategies. To accurately quantify COVID-19 cases in British Columbia (BC), we develop a Susceptible-Infectious-Recovered multi-event capture-recapture (SIRMECR) model to capture the dynamics of COVID-19. Specifically, we present a time-varying Markov model to estimate the number of undetected COVID-19 cases in five Health Authority Regions in BC, Canada, during the year 2020. We utilize individual-level information available from Population Data BC database to estimate the case detection probability, infection probability, survival probability, and recovery probability by incorporating testing volumes as covariates that improve the estimate of our parameters. We develop a Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm to estimate SIRMECR model parameters. However, analyzing this big COVID-19 data set prompts a discussion on the computational challenges encountered. Therefore, we developed divide-and-conquer strategies to address the challenges. Our application provides an estimate of the total COVID-19 burden in year 2020 and found the percentage of undetected varying from 77.4 % to 84.0 %. More specifically, we validate our results through a simulation study and N-mixture model for Northern Health Authority Region of BC.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2026 The Authors. Publishing services by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of KeAi Communications Co. Ltd&#xe9;.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olobatuyi</LastName><ForeName>Kehinde</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Victoria, 3800 Finnerty Street, Victoria, V8P 5C2, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ma</LastName><ForeName>Junling</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Victoria, 3800 Finnerty Street, Victoria, V8P 5C2, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brown</LastName><ForeName>Patrick</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics and Actuarial Science, University of Toronto, 27 King's College Cir, Toronto, M5S 1A1, Ontario, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cowen</LastName><ForeName>Laura L E</ForeName><Initials>LLE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistics, University of Victoria, 3800 Finnerty Street, Victoria, V8P 5C2, British Columbia, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>China</Country><MedlineTA>Infect Dis Model</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101692406</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2468-0427</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Capture-recapture model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Computational efficiency</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Divide-and-Conquer approach</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Markov chain Monte Carlo</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multi-event model</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2025</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2026</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>31</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2026</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>30</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2026</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>57</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2026</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">41573816</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC12819040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.idm.2025.12.016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2468-0427(25)00144-7</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Alene M., Yismaw L., Assemie M.A., Ketema D.B., Mengist B., Kassie B., Birhan T.Y. Magnitude of asymptomatic covid-19 cases throughout the course of infection: A systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS One. 2021;16(3)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7987199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33755688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appleby J.A., King N., Saunders K.E., Bast A., Rivera D., Byun J., Cunningham S., Khera C., Duffy A.C. Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on the experience and mental health of university students studying in Canada and the UK: A cross-sectional study. BMJ Open. 2022;12(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8787844</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35074809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardenet R., Doucet A., Holmes C. International conference on machine learning. PMLR; 2014. Towards scaling up Markov Chain Monte Carlo : An adaptive subsampling approach; pp. 405&#x2013;413.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>B&#xe9;land D., Dinan S., Rocco P., Waddan A. Social policy responses to covid-19 in Canada and the United States: Explaining policy variations between two liberal welfare state regimes. Social Policy and Administration. 2021;55(2):280&#x2013;294.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benhaiem S., Marescot L., Hofer H., East M.L., Lebreton J.-D., Kramer-Schadt S., Gimenez O. Robustness of eco-epidemiological capture-recapture parameter estimates to variation in infection state uncertainty. Frontiers in Veterinary Science. 2018;5:197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6121098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30211175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown G., Ghysels E., Yi L. University of North Carolina; 2021. Estimating undetected covid-19 infections, the case of north Carolina2020DP.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buzdugan S.N., Vergne T., Grosbois V., Delahay R.J., Drewe J.A. Inference of the infection status of individuals using longitudinal testing data from cryptic populations: Towards a probabilistic approach to diagnosis. Scientific Reports. 2017;7(1):1111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5430431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28424454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conn P.B., Cooch E.G. Multistate capture&#x2013;recapture analysis under imperfect state observation: An application to disease models. Journal of Applied Ecology. 2009;46(2):486&#x2013;492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Culina A., Lachish S., Pradel R., Choquet R., Sheldon B.C. A multievent approach to estimating pair fidelity and heterogeneity in state transitions. Ecology and Evolution. 2013;3(13):4326&#x2013;4338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3856734</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24340175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cypress B.S. Vol. 57. Wiley Online Library; 2022. Covid-19: The economic impact of a pandemic on the healthcare delivery system in the United States; pp. 323&#x2013;327. (Nursing Forum). 2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34845736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desprez M., McMahon C.R., Hindell M.A., Harcourt R., Gimenez O. Known unknowns in an imperfect world: Incorporating uncertainty in recruitment estimates using multi-event capture&#x2013;recapture models. Ecology and Evolution. 2013;3(14):4658&#x2013;4668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3867902</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24363895</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong E., Du H., Gardner L. An interactive web-based dashboard to track covid-19 in real time. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2020;20(5):533&#x2013;534.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32087114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dougherty B.P., Smith B.A., Carson C.A., Ogden N.H. Exploring the percentage of covid-19 cases reported in the community in Canada and associated case fatality ratios. Infectious Disease Modelling. 2021;6:123&#x2013;132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7718109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33313456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman J., Liu P., Troeger C.E., Carter A., Reiner R.C., Jr., Barber R.M., Collins J., Lim S.S., Pigott D.M., Vos T., Hay S.I., Murray C.J.L., Gakidou E. Predictive performance of international covid-19 mortality forecasting models. Nature Communications. 2021;12(1):2609.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8110547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33972512</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gimenez O., Lebreton J.-D., Gaillard J.-M., Choquet R., Pradel R. Estimating demographic parameters using hidden process dynamic models. Theoretical Population Biology. 2012;82(4):307&#x2013;316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22373775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>He J., Guo Y., Mao R., Zhang J. Proportion of asymptomatic coronavirus disease 2019: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Journal of Medical Virology. 2021;93(2):820&#x2013;830.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7404334</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32691881</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Z., Gelman A. 2005. Sampling for bayesian computation with large datasets. Available at: SSRN 1010107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huo X., Chen J., Ruan S. Estimating asymptomatic, undetected and total cases for the covid-19 outbreak in wuhan: A mathematical modeling study. BMC Infectious Diseases. 2021;21(1):476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8148404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34034662</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ioannidis J.P. Infection fatality rate of covid-19 inferred from seroprevalence data. Bulletin of the World Health Organization. 2020;99(1):19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7947934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33716331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>K&#xe9;ry M., Schaub M. Academic Press; 2011. Bayesian population analysis using WinBUGS: A hierarchical perspective.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawless J.F., Yan P. On testing for infections during epidemics, with application to Covid-19 in Ontario, Canada. Infectious Disease Modelling. 2021;6:930&#x2013;941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8297971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34316526</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lebreton J.-D., Nichols J.D., Barker R.J., Pradel R., Spendelow J.A. Modeling individual animal histories with multistate capture&#x2013;recapture models. Advances in Ecological Research. 2009;41:87&#x2013;173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li C., Zhu Y., Qi C., Liu L., Zhang D., Wang X., She K., Jia Y., Liu T., He D., Xiong M., Li X. Estimating the prevalence of asymptomatic covid-19 cases and their contribution in transmission, using Henan province, China, as an example. Frontiers of Medicine. 2021;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8260942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34249953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maclaurin D., Adams R.P. 2014. Firefly monte carlo: Exact mcmc with subsets of data. arXiv preprint arXiv:1403.5693.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marescot L., Benhaiem S., Gimenez O., Hofer H., Lebreton J.-D., Olarte-Castillo X.A., Kramer-Schadt S., East M.L. Social status mediates the fitness costs of infection with canine distemper virus in serengeti spotted hyenas. Functional Ecology. 2018;32(5):1237&#x2013;1250.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7163977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32313354</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullah M.A.S., Yan P. A semi-parametric mixed model for short-term projection of daily covid-19 incidence in Canada. Epidemics. 2022;38</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8767942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35078118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy T.J., Swail H., Jain J., Anderson M., Awadalla P., Behl L., Brown P.E., Charlton C.L., Colwill K., Drews S.J., Gingras A., Hinshaw D., Jha P., Kanji J.N., Kirsh V.A., Lang A.L.S., Langlois M., Lee S., Lewin A., O&#x2019;Brien S.F., Pambrun C., et al. The evolution of sars-cov-2 seroprevalence in Canada: A time-series study, 2020&#x2013;2023. Canadian Medical Association Journal. 2023;195(31):E1030&#x2013;E1037.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10426348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37580072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nemeth C., Fearnhead P. Stochastic gradient markov chain Monte Carlo. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2021;116(533):433&#x2013;450.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nemeth C., Sherlock C. Merging MCMC subposteriors through gaussian-process approximations. Bayesian Analysis. 2018;13(2):507&#x2013;530.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker M.R., Li Y., Elliott L.T., Ma J., Cowen L.L. Under-reporting of covid-19 in the northern health authority region of British Columbia. Canadian Journal of Statistics. 2021;49(4):1018&#x2013;1038.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8653369</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34898817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pezzullo A.M., Axfors C., Contopoulos-Ioannidis D.G., Apostolatos A., Ioannidis J.P. Age-stratified infection fatality rate of covid-19 in the non-elderly population. Environmental Research. 2023;216</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9613797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36341800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pradel R. Multievent: An extension of multistate capture&#x2013;recapture models to uncertain states. Biometrics. 2005;61(2):442&#x2013;447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16011690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quiroz M., Kohn R., Villani M., Tran M.-N. Speeding up mcmc by efficient data subsampling. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2019;114(526):831&#x2013;843.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robardet E., Borel C., Moinet M., Jouan D., Wasniewski M., Barrat J., Bou&#xe9; F., Montchatre-Leroy E., Servat A., Gimenez O., Cliquet F., Picard-Meyer E. Longitudinal survey of two serotine bat (eptesicus serotinus) maternity colonies exposed to eblv-1 (European bat lyssavirus type 1): Assessment of survival and serological status variations using capture-recapture models. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2017;11(11)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5693283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29149215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royle J.A., Dorazio R.M. Elsevier; 2008. Hierarchical modeling and inference in ecology: The analysis of data from populations, metapopulations and communities.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skowronski D.M., Sekirov I., Sabaiduc S., Zou M., Morshed M., Lawrence D., Smolina K., Ahmed M.A., Galanis E., Fraser M.N., Signal M., Naus M., Patrick D.M., Kaweski S.E., Mill C., Reyes R.C., Kelly K.T., Levett P.N., Petric M., Henry B., Krajden M. Low sars-cov-2 sero-prevalence based on anonymized residual sero-survey before and after first wave measures in British Columbia, Canada, march-may 2020. medRxiv. 2020:2020. 07.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sorensen R., Barber R., Pigott D., Carter A., Spencer C., Ostroff S., Reiner R., Abbafati C., Adolph C., Allorant A., Amlag J., Aravkin A., Bachmeier S., Bang-Jensen B., Bisignano C., Bloom S., Castellano R., Castro E., Collins J., Comfort H., Dai X., et al. Variation in the covid-19 infection-fatality ratio by age, time, and geography during the pre-vaccine era: A systematic analysis. The Lancet. 2022;399(10334):1469&#x2013;1488.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8871594</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35219376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Subramanian R., He Q., Pascual M. Quantifying asymptomatic infection and transmission of covid-19 in New York city using observed cases, serology, and testing capacity. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2021;118(9)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7936345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33571106</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuite A.R., Fisman D.N., Greer A.L. Mathematical modelling of covid-19 transmission and mitigation strategies in the population of ontario, Canada. Canadian Medical Association Journal. 2020;192(19):E497&#x2013;E505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7234271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32269018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welling M., Teh Y.W. Proceedings of the 28th international conference on machine learning (ICML-11) 2011. Bayesian learning via stochastic gradient langevin dynamics; pp. 681&#x2013;688. Citeseer.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilkinson D.J. Parallel bayesian computation. Statistics Textbooks and Monographs. 2006;184:477.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu S.L., Mertens A.N., Crider Y.S., Nguyen A., Pokpongkiat N.N., Djajadi S., Seth A., Hsiang M.S., Colford J.M., Jr., Reingold A., Arnold B.F., Hubbard A., Jade B. Substantial underestimation of sars-cov-2 infection in the United States. Nature Communications. 2020;11(1):4507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7481226</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32908126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>