<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">21342913</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2011</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>03</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-6591</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>52 Suppl 2</Volume><Issue>Suppl 2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2011</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical infectious diseases : an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Health care system and policy factors influencing engagement in HIV medical care: piecing together the fragments of a fractured health care delivery system.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>S238</StartPage><EndPage>S246</EndPage><MedlinePgn>S238-46</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/cid/ciq048</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Grounded in a socio-ecological framework, we describe salient health care system and policy factors that influence engagement in human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) clinical care. The discussion emphasizes successful programs and models of service delivery and highlights the limitations of current, fragmented health care system components in supporting effective, efficient, and sustained patient engagement across a continuum of care. A fundamental need exists for improved synergies between funding and service agencies that provide HIV testing, prevention, treatment, and supportive services. We propose a feedback loop whereby actionable, patient-level surveillance of HIV testing and engagement in care activities inform educational outreach and resource allocation to support integrated "testing and linkage to care plus" service delivery. Ongoing surveillance of programmatic performance in achieving defined benchmarks for linkage of patients who have newly diagnosed HIV infection and retention of those patients in care is imperative to iteratively inform further educational efforts, resource allocation, and refinement of service delivery.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mugavero</LastName><ForeName>Michael J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases, School of Medicine, Universityof Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham, Alabama, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Norton</LastName><ForeName>Wynne E</ForeName><Initials>WE</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saag</LastName><ForeName>Michael S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P30 AI027767</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>K23 MH082641</GrantID><Acronym>MH</Acronym><Agency>NIMH NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>P30AI27767</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R24 AI067039</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R24AI067039-1</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>K23MH082641</GrantID><Acronym>MH</Acronym><Agency>NIMH NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9203213</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1058-4838</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003695" MajorTopicYN="Y">Delivery of Health Care</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006678" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="Y">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006296" MajorTopicYN="Y">Health Services</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006301" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Services Needs and Demand</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012959" MajorTopicYN="N">Socioeconomic Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014481" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United States</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2011</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2011</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2012</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21342913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3106258</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciq048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ciq048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Aberg JA, Kaplan JE, Libman H, et al. Primary care guidelines for the management of persons infected with human immunodeficiency virus: 2009 update by the HIV Medicine Association of the Infectious Diseases Society of America. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;49:651&#x2013;681.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19640227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheever LW. Engaging HIV-infected patients in care: their lives depend on it. Clin Infect Dis. 2007;44:1500&#x2013;1502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17479949</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Resources and Services Administration, HIV/AIDS Bureau. Outreach: engaging people in HIV care, summary of a HRSA/HAB 2005 consultation on linking PLWH into care. 2006  ftp://ftp.hrsa.gov/hab/HIVoutreach.pdf. Accessed 13 May 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ulett KB, Willig JH, Lin HY, et al. The therapeutic implications of timely linkage and early retention in HIV care. AIDS Patient Care STDS. 2009;23:41&#x2013;49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2733237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19055408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giordano TP, Gifford AL, White AC, Jr, et al. Retention in care: a challenge to survival with HIV infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2007;44:1493&#x2013;1499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17479948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horstmann E, Brown J, Islam F, Buck J, Agins BD. Retaining HIV-infected patients in care: Where are we? Where do we go from here? Clin Infect Dis. 2010;50:752&#x2013;761.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20121413</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mugavero MJ, Lin HY, Willig JH, et al. Missed visits and mortality among patients establishing initial outpatient HIV treatment. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;48:248&#x2013;256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2737584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19072715</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Granich RM, Gilks CF, Dye C, De Cock KM, Williams BG. Universal voluntary HIV testing with immediate antiretroviral therapy as a strategy for elimination of HIV transmission: a mathematical model. Lancet. 2009;373:48&#x2013;57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19038438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dieffenbach CW, Fauci AS. Universal voluntary testing and treatment for prevention of HIV transmission. JAMA. 2009;301:2380&#x2013;2382.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19509386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giordano TP, White AC, Jr., Sajja P, et al. Factors associated with the use of highly active antiretroviral therapy in patients newly entering care in an urban clinic. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2003;32:399&#x2013;405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12640198</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Project Inform. TLC+: testing, linkage to care and treatment.   http://www.projectinform.org/tlc+/. Accessed 13 May 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLeroy KR, Bibeau D, Steckler A, Glanz K. An ecological perspective on health promotion programs. Health Educ Q. 1988;15:351&#x2013;377.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3068205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brookmeyer R. Measuring the HIV/AIDS epidemic: approaches and challenges. Epidemiol Rev. 2010;32:26&#x2013;37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20203104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bozzette SA, Berry SH, Duan N, et al. The care of HIV-infected adults in the United States. HIV Cost and Services Utilization Study Consortium. N Engl J Med. 1998;339:1897&#x2013;1904.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9862946</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleming P, Byers R, Sweeney P, Daniels D, Karon J, Jansen R. Program and abstracts of the 9th Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections, Seattle. HIV prevalence in the United States, 2000 [abstract 11] pp. 24&#x2013;28. February 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNaghten AD, Wolfe MI, Onorato I, et al. Improving the representativeness of behavioral and clinical surveillance for persons with HIV in the United States: the rationale for developing a population-based approach. PLoS One. 2007;2:e550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1891089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17579722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Branson BM, Handsfield HH, Lampe MA, et al. Revised recommendations for HIV testing of adults, adolescents, and pregnant women in health-care settings. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2006;55:1&#x2013;17. quiz CE1&#x2013;4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16988643</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metsch LR, Pereyra M, Messinger S, et al. HIV transmission risk behaviors among HIV-infected persons who are successfully linked to care. Clin Infect Dis. 2008;47:577&#x2013;584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18624629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evaluating the contribution of ancillary services in improving access to primary care in the United States under the Ryan White CARE Act. AIDS Care. 2002;14:3&#x2013;136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katz MH, Cunningham WE, Fleishman JA, et al. Effect of case management on unmet needs and utilization of medical care and medications among HIV-infected persons. Ann Intern Med. 2001;135:557&#x2013;565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11601927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mugavero MJ, Lin HY, Allison JJ, et al. Failure to establish HIV care: characterizing the &#x201c;no show&#x201d; phenomenon. Clin Infect Dis. 2007;45:127&#x2013;130.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17554713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schneider J, Kaplan SH, Greenfield S, Li W, Wilson IB. Better physician-patient relationships are associated with higher reported adherence to antiretroviral therapy in patients with HIV infection. J Gen Intern Med. 2004;19:1096&#x2013;1103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1494791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15566438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelen GD, Rothman RE. Emergency department-based HIV testing: too little, but not too late. Ann Emerg Med. 2009;54:65&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19398241</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walensky RP, Weinstein MC, Smith HE, Freedberg KA, Paltiel AD. Optimal allocation of testing dollars: the example of HIV counseling, testing, and referral. Med Decis Making. 2005;25:321&#x2013;329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15951459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammer SM, Eron JJ, Jr, Reiss P, et al. Antiretroviral treatment of adult HIV infection: 2008 recommendations of the International AIDS Society-USA panel. JAMA. 2008;300:555&#x2013;570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18677028</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Panel on Antiretroviral Guidelines for Adults and Adolescents. Guidelines for the use of antiretroviral agents in HIV-1-infected adults and adolescents. Department Health Hum Serv.  1 December 2009; 1&#x2013;161.  http://www.aidsinfo.nih.gov/ContentFiles/AdultandAdolescentGL.pdf. Accessed 22 March 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Guidelines for prevention and treatment of opportunistic infections in HIV-infected adults and adolescents: recommendations from CDC, the National Institutes of Health, and the HIV Medicine Association of the Infectious Diseases Society of America. MMWR Recomm Rep. 2009;58:1&#x2013;207. quiz CE1&#x2013;4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19357635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justice AC. HIV and aging: time for a new paradigm. Curr HIV/AIDS Rep. 2010;7:69&#x2013;76.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20425560</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saag MS. Which policy to ADAP-T: waiting lists or waiting lines? Clin Infect Dis. 2006;43:1365&#x2013;1367.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17051506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Alliance of State &amp; Territorial AIDS Directors (NASTAD) The ADAP watch. 30 July 2010.  http://www.nastad.org/Docs/Public/InFocus/2010730_NASTAD%20ADAP%20Watch%20-%20July%202010.pdf. Accessed 9 September 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mugavero MJ, Saag MS. HIV care at a crossroads: the emerging crisis in the US HIV epidemic. Med Gen Med. 2007;9:58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1924992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17435658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weddle A. Program and abstracts of the 2008 National Summit on HIV Diagnosis, Prevention, and Access to Care, Session 3: Workforce needs and challenges in delivery of HIV care, Arlington, Virginia. HIVMA-FCHR survey on workforce needs [presentation] pp. 19&#x2013;21. November 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen RY, Accortt NA, Westfall AO, et al. Distribution of health care expenditures for HIV-infected patients. Clin Infect Dis. 2006;42:1003&#x2013;1010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16511767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mayer KH, Chaguturu S. Penalizing success: is comprehensive HIV care sustainable? Clin Infect Dis. 2006;42:1011&#x2013;1013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16511768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Penner M, Leone PA. Integration of testing for, prevention of, and access to treatment for HIV infection: state and local perspectives. Clin Infect Dis. 2007;45:S281&#x2013;S286.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18190300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saag MS. Ryan White: an unintentional home builder. AIDS Read. 2009;19:166&#x2013;168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19554735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenberg AE, Hader SL, Masur H, et al. Fighting HIV/AIDS in Washington, D.C. Health Aff (Millwood) 2009;28:1677&#x2013;1687.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19887408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner LI, Metsch LR, Anderson-Mahoney P, et al. Efficacy of a brief case management intervention to link recently diagnosed HIV-infected persons to care. AIDS. 2005;19:423&#x2013;431.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15750396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Craw JA, Gardner LI, Marks G, et al. Brief strengths-based case management promotes entry into HIV medical care: results of the antiretroviral treatment access study-II. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2008;47:597&#x2013;606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18285714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bradford JB, Coleman S, Cunningham W. HIV system navigation: an emerging model to improve HIV care access. AIDS Patient Care STDS. 2007;21:S49&#x2013;S58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17563290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wylie R, Marler M, Lin H, et al. Program and abstracts of the 4th International Conference on HIV Treatment Adherence. Miami. Project CONNECT: overcoming barriers to establishing HIV care; pp. 5&#x2013;7. April 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mugavero MJ. Improving engagement in HIV care: what can we do? Top HIV Med. 2008;16:156&#x2013;161.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19106431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horberg M, Hurley L, Towner W, et al. Program and abstracts of the 5th International Conference on HIV Treatment Adherence, Miami. Antiretroviral therapy (ART) adherence and HIV RNA (VL) control as HIV quality measures in Kaiser Permanente (KP) [abstract# 61795] pp. 23&#x2013;25. May 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goetz MB, Hoang T, Bowman C, et al. A system-wide intervention to improve HIV testing in the Veterans Health Administration. J Gen Intern Med. 2008;23:1200&#x2013;1207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2517965</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18452045</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Office of the White House. National HIV/AIDS Strategy for the United States. July 2010.  http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/uploads/NHAS.pdf. Accessed 9 September 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swensen SJ, Meyer GS, Nelson EC, et al. Cottage industry to postindustrial care&#x2014;the revolution in health care delivery. N Engl J Med. 2010;362:e12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20089956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>El-Sadr WM, Mayer KH, Hodder SL. AIDS in America&#x2014;forgotten but not gone. N Engl J Med. 2010;362:967&#x2013;970.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4568988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20147707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Linas BP, Losina E, Rockwell A, Walensky RP, Cranston K, Freedberg KA. Improving outcomes in state AIDS drug assistance programs. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2009;51:513&#x2013;521.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2774843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19561518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>