<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">21637342</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2011</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>6</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2011</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Early estimation of the reproduction number in the presence of imported cases: pandemic influenza H1N1-2009 in New Zealand.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e17835</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e17835</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e17835</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0017835</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We analyse data from the early epidemic of H1N1-2009 in New Zealand, and estimate the reproduction number R. We employ a renewal process which accounts for imported cases, illustrate some technical pitfalls, and propose a novel estimation method to address these pitfalls. Explicitly accounting for the infection-age distribution of imported cases and for the delay in transmission dynamics due to international travel, R was estimated to be (95% confidence interval: 107,1.47). Hence we show that a previous study, which did not account for these factors, overestimated R. Our approach also permitted us to examine the infection-age at which secondary transmission occurs as a function of calendar time, demonstrating the downward bias during the beginning of the epidemic. These technical issues may compromise the usefulness of a well-known estimator of R--the inverse of the moment-generating function of the generation time given the intrinsic growth rate. Explicit modelling of the infection-age distribution among imported cases and the examination of the time dependency of the generation time play key roles in avoiding a biased estimate of R, especially when one only has data covering a short time interval during the early growth phase of the epidemic.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roberts</LastName><ForeName>Michael George</ForeName><Initials>MG</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Mathematical Biology, Institute of Information and Mathematical Sciences, Massey University, Auckland, New Zealand. m.g.roberts@massey.ac.nz</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nishiura</LastName><ForeName>Hiroshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2011</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>26</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D050936" MajorTopicYN="Y">Basic Reproduction Number</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004641" MajorTopicYN="N">Emigration and Immigration</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="Y">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015994" MajorTopicYN="N">Incidence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053118" MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza A Virus, H1N1 Subtype</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000502" MajorTopicYN="Y">physiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="Y">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008954" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Biological</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009520" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">New Zealand</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="Y">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015203" MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility of Results</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012621" MajorTopicYN="N">Seasons</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013997" MajorTopicYN="N">Time Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement><b>Competing Interests: </b>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2010</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2011</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2011</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2011</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2011</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2011</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21637342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3102662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-10-03644</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Neumann G, Noda T, Kawaoka Y. Emergence and pandemic potential of swine-origin H1N1 influenza virus. Nature. 2009;459:931&#x2013;939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2873852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19525932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Kerkhove MD, Asikainen T, Becker NG, Bjorge S, Desenclos JC, et al. Studies needed to address public health challenges of the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic: insights from modeling. PLoS Medicine. 2010;7:e1000275.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2879409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20532237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diekmann O, Heesterbeek JAP. Mathematical epidemiology of infectious diseases: model building, analysis and interpretation. Chichester: Wiley; 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts MG. The pluses and minuses of R 0. Journal of the Royal Society Interface. 2007;4:949&#x2013;961.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2075534</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17490942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bo&#xeb;lle PY, Bernillon P, Desenclos JC. A preliminary estimation of the reproduction ratio for new influenza A(H1N1) from the outbreak in Mexico, March&#x2013;April 2009. Eurosurveillance. 2009;14:pii:19205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19442402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser C, Donnelly CA, Cauchemez S, Hanage WP, van Kerkhove MD, et al. Pandemic potential of a strain of influenza A (H1N1): Early findings. Science. 2009;324:1557&#x2013;1561.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3735127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19433588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts MG, Heesterbeek JAP. Model-consistent estimation of the basic reproduction number from the incidence of an emerging infection. Journal of Mathematical Biology. 2007;55:803&#x2013;816.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2782110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17684743</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Lipsitch M. How generation intervals shape the relationship between growth rates and reproductive numbers. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London Series B. 2007;274:599&#x2013;604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1766383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17476782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ong JBS, Chen MC, Cook AR, Lee HC, Lee VJ, et al. Real-time epidemic monitoring and forecasting of H1N1-2009 using influenza-like illness from general practice and family doctor clinics in singapore. PLoS ONE. 2010;5:e10036.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2854682</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20418945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, van Boven M, Lipsitch M. Optimizing infectious disease interventions during an emerging epidemic. Proceedings of the National Academy of Science, USA. 2010;107:923&#x2013;928.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2818907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20080777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Wilson N, Baker MG. Estimating the reproduction number of the novel influenza A virus (H1N1) in a southern hemisphere setting: preliminary estimate in New Zealand. The New Zealand Medical Journal. 2009;122:73&#x2013;77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19684651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBryde ES, Bergeri I, van Gemert C, Rotty J, Headley EJ, et al. Early transmission characteristics of influenza A(H1N1)v in Australia: Victorian state. Eurosurveillance. 2009;14:pii:19363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19883544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelly HA, Mercer GN, Fielding JE, Dowse GK, Glass K, et al. Pandemic (H1N1) 2009 influenza community transmission was established in one australian state when the virus was first identified in North America. PLoS ONE. 2010;5:e11341.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2893203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20596536</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paine S, Mercer GN, Kelly PM, Bandaranayake D, Baker MG, et al. Transmissibility of 2009 pandemic influenza A(H1N1) in New Zealand: effective reproduction number and influence of age, ethnicity and importations. Eurosurveillance. 2010;15:pii:19591.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20576236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Roberts MG. Estimation of the reproduction number for 2009 pandemic influenza A(H1N1) in the presence of imported cases. Eurosurveillance. 2010;15:pii:19622.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20667300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Castillo-Chavez C, Safan M, Chowell G. Transmission potential of the new influenza A(H1N1) virus and its age-specificity in Japan. Eurosurveillance. 2009;14:pii:19227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19497256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H. Travel and age of influenza A (H1N1) 2009 virus infection. Journal of Travel Medicine. 2010;17:269&#x2013;270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20636601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mukherjee P, Lim PL, Chow A, Barkham T, Seow E, et al. Epidemiology of travel-associated pandemic (H1N1) 2009 infection in 116 patients, Singapore. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2010;16:21&#x2013;26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2874386</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20031038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kermack WO, McKendrick AG. Contributions to the mathematical theory of epidemics. I. Proceedings of the Royal Society, Series A. 1927;115:700&#x2013;721. (reprinted in Bull Math Biol 53 (1991) 33&#x2013;118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts MG. Modeling strategies for containing an invading infection. Mathematical Population Studies. 2006;13:205&#x2013;214.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts MG, Baker K, Jennings LC, Sertsou G, Wilson N. A model for the spread and control of pandemic influenza in an isolated geographical region. Journal of the Royal Society Interface. 2007;4:325&#x2013;330.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2359860</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17251145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Chowell G, Safan M, Castillo-Chavez C. Pros and cons of estimating the reproduction number from early epidemic growth rate of influenza A (H1N1) 2009. Theoretical Biology and Medical Modelling. 2010;7:1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2821365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20056004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Klinkenberg D, Roberts MG, Heesterbeek JAP. Early epidemiological assessment of the virulence of emerging infectious diseases: a case study of an influenza pandemic. PLoS ONE. 2009;4:e6852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2729920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19718434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailey NTJ. The elements of stochastic processes with applications to the natural sciences. New York: Wiley; 1964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hahne S, Donker T, Meijer A, Timen A, van Steenbergen J, et al. Epidemiology and control of influenza A(H1N1)v in the Netherlands: the first 115 cases. Eurosurveillance. 2009;14:pii:19267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19589332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White LF, Wallinga J, Finelli L, Reed C, Riley S, et al. Estimation of the reproductive number and the serial interval in early phase of the 2009 influenza A/H1N1 pandemic in the USA. Influenza and Other Respiratory Viruses. 2010;3:267&#x2013;276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2782458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19903209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Sugimoto JD, Basta NE, Chao DL, Matrajt L, et al. The transmissibility and control of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) virus. Science. 2009;326:729&#x2013;733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2880578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19745114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jagers P. Age-dependent branching processes allowing immigration. Theory of Probability and its Applications. 1968;13:225&#x2013;236.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keyfitz BL, Keyfitz N. The McKendrick partial differential equation and its uses in epidemiology and population study. Mathematical and Computer Modelling. 1997;26:1&#x2013;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grey DR. On possible rates of growth of age-dependent branching processes with immigration. Journal of Applied Probability. 1976;13:138&#x2013;143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parthasarathy PR, Sharafali M. Age-dependent branching process with birth process immigration. International Journal of Mathematical Education in Science and Technology. 1991;22:317&#x2013;320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lipsitch M, Bergstrom CT. Invited commentary: real-time tracking of control measures for emerging infections. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2004;160:517&#x2013;519.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15353410</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White LF, Pagano M. A likelihood-based method for real-time estimation of the serial interval and reproductive number of an epidemic. Statistics in Medicine. 2008;27:2999&#x2013;3016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3951165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18058829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lloyd-Smith JD, Schreiber SJ, Kopp PE, Getz WM. Superspreading and the effect of individual variation on disease emergence. Nature. 2005;438:355&#x2013;359.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094981</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16292310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller JC, Davoudi B, Meza R, Slim AC, Pourboholoul B. Epidemics with general generation interval distributions. Journal of Theoretical Biology. 2010;262:107&#x2013;115.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19679141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Demetrius L. Measures of fitness and demographic stability. Proceedings of the National Academy of Science, USA. 1977;74:384&#x2013;386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC393266</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">264691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuljapurkar SD. Why use population entropy? it determines the rate of convergence. Journal of Mathematical Biology. 1982;13:325&#x2013;337.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Griffin JT, Garske T, Ghani AC, Clarke PS. Joint estimation of the basic reproduction number and generation time parameters for infectious disease outbreaks. Biostatistics. 2011 in press (doi: 10.1093/biostatistics/kxq058)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20858771</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scalia Tomba G, Svensson A, Asikainen T, Giesecke J. Some model based considerations on observing generation times for communicable diseases. Mathematical Biosciences. 2010;223:24&#x2013;31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19854206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H. Time variations in the generation time of an infectious disease: implications for sampling to appropriately quantify transmission potential. Mathematical Biosciences and Engineering. 2010;7:851&#x2013;869.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21077712</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>