<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">24889501</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2014</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-3156</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>9</Issue><PubDate><Year>2014</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Tropical medicine &amp; international health : TM &amp; IH</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Trop Med Int Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Dengue disease surveillance: an updated systematic literature review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1116</StartPage><EndPage>1160</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1116-60</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/tmi.12333</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To review the evidence for the application of tools for dengue outbreak prediction/detection and trend monitoring in passive and active disease surveillance systems in order to develop recommendations for endemic countries and identify important research needs.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">This systematic literature review followed the protocol of a review from 2008, extending the systematic search from January 2007 to February 2013 on PubMed, EMBASE, CDSR, WHOLIS and Lilacs. Data reporting followed the PRISMA statement. The eligibility criteria comprised (i) population at risk of dengue, (ii) dengue disease surveillance, (iii) outcome of surveillance described and (iv) empirical data evaluated. The analysis classified studies based on the purpose of the surveillance programme. The main limitation of the review was expected publication bias.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">A total of 1116 papers were identified of which 36 articles were included in the review. Four cohort-based prospective studies calculated expansion factors demonstrating remarkable levels of underreporting in the surveillance systems. Several studies demonstrated that enhancement methods such as laboratory support, sentinel-based reporting and staff motivation contributed to improvements in dengue reporting. Additional improvements for passive surveillance systems are possible by incorporating simple data forms/entry/electronic-based reporting; defining clear system objectives; performing data analysis at the lowest possible level (e.g. district); seeking regular data feedback. Six studies showed that serotype changes were positively correlated with the number of reported cases or with dengue incidence, with lag times of up to 6 months. Three studies found that data on internet searches and event-based surveillance correlated well with the epidemic curve derived from surveillance data.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Passive surveillance providing the baseline for outbreak alert should be strengthened and appropriate threshold levels for outbreak alerts investigated. Additional enhancement tools such as syndromic surveillance, laboratory support and motivation strategies can be added. Appropriate alert signals need to be identified and integrated into a risk assessment tool. Shifts in dengue serotypes/genotype or electronic event-based surveillance have also considerable potential as indicator in dengue surveillance. Further research on evidence-based response strategies and cost-effectiveness is needed.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2014 The Authors. Tropical Medicine and International Health Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Runge-Ranzinger</LastName><ForeName>S</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Special Programme for Research and Training in Tropical Diseases, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McCall</LastName><ForeName>P J</ForeName><Initials>PJ</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kroeger</LastName><ForeName>A</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Horstick</LastName><ForeName>O</ForeName><Initials>O</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>001</GrantID><Acronym>WHO_</Acronym><Agency>World Health Organization</Agency><Country>International</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2014</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Trop Med Int Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9610576</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1360-2276</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003715" MajorTopicYN="N">Dengue</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011159" MajorTopicYN="Y">Population Surveillance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">brote de dengue</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dengue</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">dengue outbreaks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemic preparedness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">preparaci&#xf3;n para epidemias</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pr&#xe9;paration aux &#xe9;pid&#xe9;mies</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">revisi&#xf3;n sistem&#xe1;tica</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">revue syst&#xe9;matique</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">systematic review</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">vigilancia</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">&#xe9;pid&#xe9;mies de la dengue</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2014</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2014</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>4</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2014</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24889501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4253126</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/tmi.12333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><ReferenceList><Title>General References</Title><Reference><Citation>Bandyopadhyay S, Lum LC. Kroeger A. Classifying dengue: a review of the difficulties in using the WHO case classification for dengue haemorrhagic fever. Tropical Medicine and International Health. 2006;11:1238&#x2013;1255.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16903887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barniol J, Gaczkowski R, Barbato EV, et al. Usefulness and applicability of the revised dengue case classification by disease: multi-centre study in 18 countries. BMC Infectious Diseases. 2010;11:106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3098176</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21510901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhatt S, Gething PW, Brady OJ, et al.  The global distribution and burden of dengue. Nature. 2013 Doi: 10.1038/nature12060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature12060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3651993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23563266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowman LR, Runge-Ranzinger S. McCall PJ. Assessing the relationship between vector indices and dengue transmission: a systematic review of the evidence. PLoS NTDs. 2014 in press.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4014441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24810901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buczak AL, Koshute PT, Babin SM, Feighner BH. Lewis SH. A data-driven epidemiological prediction method for dengue outbreaks using local and remote sensing data. BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making. 2012;12:124.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3534444</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23126401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buehler JW, Hopkins RS, Overhage JM, Sosin DM. Tong V. Framework for evaluating public health surveillance systems for early detection of outbreaks. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2004;53:1&#x2013;11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15129191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carme B, Sobesky M, Biard MH, Cotellon P, Aznar C. Fontanella JM. Non-specific alert system for dengue epidemic outbreaks in areas of endemic malaria A hospital-based evaluation in Cayenne (French Guiana) Epidemiology and Infection. 2003;130:93&#x2013;100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2869943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12613750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC. Updated guidelines for evaluating public health surveillance systems 50, RR 13, Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2001. pp. 1&#x2013;35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18634202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen CC. Chang HC. Predicting dengue outbreaks using approximate entropy algorithm and pattern recognition. Journal of Infection. 2013;67:65&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23558245</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Esu E, Lenhart A, Smith L. Horstick O. Effectiveness of peridomestic space spraying with insecticide on dengue transmission; systematic review. Tropical medicine and international health. 2010;15:619&#x2013;631.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20214764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrington J, Kroeger A, Runge-Ranzinger S. O'Dempsey T. Detecting and responding to a dengue outbreak: evaluation of existing strategies in country outbreak response planning. The Journal of Tropical Medicine. 2013;2013:9. pages, Article ID 756832.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3810135</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24222774</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henning KJ. Overview of syndromic surveillance what is syndromic surveillance? MMWR. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report. 2004;53(Suppl):5&#x2013;11.  http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/su5301a3.htm (accessed 2 May 2014)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horstick O, Runge Ranzinger S, Nathan MB. Kroeger A. Dengue vector-control services: how do they work? A systematic literature review and country case studies. Transactions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2010;104:379&#x2013;386.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20400169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horstick O, Farrar J, Lum L, et al. Reviewing the development, evidence base and application of the revised dengue case classification. Pathogens and Global Health. 2012;106:94&#x2013;101. (8)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3408880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22943544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horstick O, Jaenisch T, Martinez E, et al. 2014. Comparing the usefulness of the 1997 and 2009 WHO dengue case classification: a systematic literature review . Accepted AJTMH 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kour&#x131; G, Guzman MG, Valdes L, et al. Reemergence of dengue in Cuba: a 1997 epidemic in Santiago de Cuba. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 1998;4:89&#x2013;92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2627664</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9454563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liberati A, Altman DG, Tetzlaff J, et al. The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate health care interventions: explanation and elaboration. PLoS Med. 2009;6:e1000100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2707010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19621070</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Merlin T, Weston A. Tooher R. Extending an evidence hierarchy to include topics other than treatment: revising the Australian &#x2018;level of evidence&#x2019;. BMC Medical Research Methodology. 2009  www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2288/9/34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2700132</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19519887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NHMRC. 2000.  National Health and Medical Research Council, How to use the evidence: assessment and application of scientific evidence , February 2000.  http://www.nhmrc.gov.au/_files_nhmrc/publications/attachments/cp69.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pilger D, De Maesschalck M, Horstick O. San Martin JL. 2010.  Dengue outbreak response: documented effective interventions and evidence gaps . TropIKA Reviews.  http://journal.tropika.net/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S2078-86062010000100002&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso (accessed 2 May 2014)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pirard M, Lora J, Boelaert M, Gianella A. Van der Stuyft P. 1997. Desarrollo de un Sistema de Vigilancia para dengue en Santa Cruz, Bolivia . Bol. Centif. De CENETROP XVI.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racloz V, Ramsey R, Tong S. Hu W. Surveillance of dengue fever virus: a review of epidemiological models and early warning systems. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2012;6:e1648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3358322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22629476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rigau-P&#xe9;rez JG. Clark GG. Como responder a una epidemia de dengue: vision global y experiencia en Puerto Rico. Revista Panamericana de Salud P&#xfa;blica. 2005;17:282&#x2013;293.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15969980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Runge Ranzinger S, Horstick O, Marx M. Kroeger A. Systematic Review: what does dengue disease surveillance contribute to predicting and detecting outbreaks and describing trends? Tropical Medicine and International Health. 2008;13:1022&#x2013;1041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18768080</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stroup DF, Williamson GD, Hendon JL. Karon JM. Detection of aberrations in the occurrence of notifiable diseases surveillance data. Statistics in Medicine. 1989;8:323&#x2013;329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2540519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Talarmin A, Peneau C, Dussart P, et al. Surveillance of dengue fever in French Guiana by monitoring the results of negative malaria diagnoses. Epidemiology and Infection. 2000;125:189&#x2013;193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2869586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11057976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization and the Special Programme for Research and Training in Tropical Diseases (TDR) 2009. Dengue guidelines for diagnosis, treatment, prevention and control: new edition. 147. ISBN: 9789241547871.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. 2012.  Global Strategy for dengue prevention and control 2012&#x2013;2020  http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/75303/1/9789241504034_eng.pdf (accessed 2 May 2014)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>York Centre for Reviews and Dissemination. 2001.  Report for undertaking systematic reviews of research on effectiveness  http://www.york.ac.uk/inst/crd/report4.htm (accessed 2 May 2014)</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></ReferenceList><ReferenceList><Title>References of included studies (in numerical order as referenced in the text)</Title><Reference><Citation>Chan EH, Sahai V, Conrad C. Brownstein JS. Using web search query data to monitor dengue epidemics: a new model for neglected tropical disease surveillance. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2011;5:e1206.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3104029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21647308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Althouse BM, Ng YY. Cummings DAT. Prediction of dengue incidence using search query surveillance. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2011;5:e1258.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3149016</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21829744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee K-S, Lai Y-L, Lo S, et al.  Dengue virus surveillance for early warning Singapore. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2010;16  www.cdc.gov/eid.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2953985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20409381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee K-S, Lo S, Tan SS-Y, et al. Dengue virus surveillance in Singapore reveals high viral diversity through multiple introductions and in situ evolution. Infection Genetics and Evolution. 2012;12:77&#x2013;85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22036707</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koh BK, Ng LC, Kita Y, et al. The 2005 dengue epidemic in Singapore: epidemiology, prevention and control. Annals Academy of Medicine Singapore. 2008;37:538&#x2013;545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18695764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schreiber MJ, Holmes EC, Ong SH, et al. Genomic epidemiology of a dengue virus epidemic in urban Singapore. Journal of Virology. 2009;83:4163&#x2013;4173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2668455</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19211734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamanaka A, Mulyatno KC, Susilowati H, Hendrianto E. Ginting AP. Displacement of the predominant dengue virus from type 2 to type 1 with a subsequent genotype shift from IV to I in Surabaya, Indonesia 2008&#x2013;2010. PLoS One. 2011;6:e27322.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3210158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22087290</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li D-s, Liu W, Guigon A, Mostyn C, Grant R. Aaskov J. Rapid displacement of dengue virus type 1 by type 4, Pacific region 2007&#x2013;2009. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2010;16  www.cdc.gov/eid.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2874383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20031057</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rocha C, Morrison AC, For SB, et al. Comparison of two active surveillance programs for the detection of clinical dengue cases in Iquitos, Peru. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2009;80:656&#x2013;660.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19346395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jean-Baptiste M, Herv&#xe9; C, Gaetan T, et al. Value of syndromic surveillance within the Armed Forces for early warning during a dengue fever outbreak in French Guiana in 2006. BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making. 2008;8:29.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2459153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18597694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jefferson H, Dupuy B, Chaudet H, et al. Evaluation of a syndromic surveillance for the early detection of outbreaks among military personnel in a tropical country. Journal of Public Health. 2008;30:375&#x2013;383. Advance Access Publication 15 April 2008.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18413353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flamand C, Quenel P, Ardillon V, Carvalho L, Bringay S. Teisseire M.  User Centred Networked Health Care. Vol. 169. IOS Press 2011&#xa9; 2011 European Federation for Medical Informatics; 2011. The epidemiologic surveillance of dengue-fever in French Guiana: when achievements trigger higher goals; pp. 629&#x2013;633. In: Vol. . SeriesStudies in Health Technology and Informatics Ebook. . All rights reserved. DOI: 10.3233/978-1-60750-806-9-629.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3233/978-1-60750-806-9-629</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21893824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoen AG, Keller M, Verma AD, Buckeridge DL. Brownstein JS. Electronic event&#x2013;based surveillance for monitoring dengue, Latin America. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2012;18  www.cdc.gov/eid.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3376807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22709430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Randrianasolo L, Raoelina Y, Ratsitorahina M, et al.  Sentinel surveillance system for early outbreak detection in Madagascar. BMC Public Health. 2010;10:31.  http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2458/10/31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2823701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20092624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Standish K, Kuan G, Avil&#xe9;s W, Balmaseda A. Harris E. High dengue case capture rate in four years of a cohort study in Nicaragua compared to national surveillance data. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2010;4:e633.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2838781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20300515</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wichmann O, Yoon I-K, Vong S, Limkittikul K. Gibbons RV. Dengue in Thailand and Cambodia: an assessment of the degree of underrecognized disease burden based on reported cases. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2011;5:e996.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3066139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21468308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vong S, Goyet S, Ngan C, et al. Under-recognition and reporting of dengue in Cambodia: a capture&#x2013;recapture analysis of the National Dengue Surveillance System. Epidemiology and Infection. 2012;140:491&#x2013;499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21733251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vong S, Khieu V, Glass O, et al. Dengue Incidence in urban and rural Cambodia: results from population-based active fever surveillance 2006&#x2013;2008. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2010;4:e903.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2994922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21152061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beatty ME, Stone A, Fitzsimons DW, Hanna JN. Lam SK. Best practices in dengue surveillance: a report from the Asia-Pacific and Americas Dengue Prevention Boards. PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases. 2010;4:e890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2982842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21103381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huy R, Buchy P, Conan A, et al. National dengue surveillance in Cambodia 1980&#x2013;2008: epidemiological and virological trends and the impact of vector control. Bulletin of the World Health Organization. 2010;88:650&#x2013;657.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2930366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20865069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos MM, Arg&#xfc;ello DF, Luxemburger C, et al. Epidemiological and clinical observations on patients with dengue in Puerto Rico: results from the first year of enhanced surveillance&#x2014;June 2005&#x2013;May 2006. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2008;79:123&#x2013;127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18606775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schwartz E, Weld LH, Wilder-Smith A, et al.  Seasonality, annual trends, and characteristics of dengue among Ill returned travelers 1997&#x2013;2006. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2008;14  www.cdc.gov/eid.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2600332</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18598629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Domingo C, Niedrig M, Gascon J, et al. Molecular surveillance of circulating dengue genotypes through European travelers. Journal of Travel Medicine. 2011;18:183&#x2013;190.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21539658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Runge-Ranzinger S. 2010. Is dengue disease surveillance able to predict or detect outbreaks and initiate timely response? Assessment of National Dengue Control Programmes in Thailand and Cambodia . Doctorate Thesis, University of Heidelberg.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rediguieri CF. 2009. Is dengue disease surveillance able to predict or detect outbreaks in Brazil and Bolivia? Thesis: Master of Science in International Health, University of Heidelberg.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Isma NY. 2010. Analysis of dengue surveillance system in Indonesia: Is it effective to detect and predict outbreaks? Thesis: Master of Science in International Health, University of Heidelberg.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aishath AA. 2011. An Evaluation of the Surveillance System for Dengue virus infections in Maldives. Performed as a major assignment for the course on Infectious Disease Surveillance &#x2013; EPID6470 . Master of Clinical Epidemiology, University of Newcastle Australia.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gobbi F, Barzon L, Capelli G, et al.  Surveillance for West Nile, dengue, and chikungunya virus infections, Veneto Region, Italy 2010. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2012;18  www.cdc.gov/eid.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3309689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22469230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gjenero-Margan I, Aleraj B, Krajcar D, et al.  Autochthonous dengue fever in Croatia, August&#x2013;September 2010. Euro Surveillance: Bulletin Europ&#xe9;en sur les Maladies Transmissibles = European Communicable Disease Bulletin. 2011;16 19805.  http://www.eurosurveillance.org/ViewArticle.aspx?ArticleId=19805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21392489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruche L, Souar&#xe8;s Y, Armengaud A, et al.  First two autochthonous dengue virus infections in metropolitan France, September 2010. Euro Surveillance: Bulletin Europ&#xe9;en sur les Maladies Transmissibles = European Communicable Disease Bulletin. 2010;15 19676.  http://www.eurosurveillance.org/ViewArticle.aspx?ArticleId=19676.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20929659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoo H-S, Park O, Park H-K, et al.  Timeliness of national notifiable diseases surveillance system in Korea: a cross-sectional study. 2009.   http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2458/9/93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2676269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19331696</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuan M-M, Lin T, Chuang J-H. Wu H-S. Epidemiological trends and the effect of airport fever screening on prevention of domestic dengue fever outbreaks in Taiwan 1998&#x2013;2007. International Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2010;14:e693&#x2013;e697.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7110484</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20656647</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin C-C, Huang Y-H, Shu P-Y, et al. Characteristic of dengue disease in Taiwan: 2002&#x2013;2007. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2010;82:731&#x2013;739.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2844571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20348527</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang J-H, Liao T-L, Chang S-F, et al. Laboratory-based dengue surveillance in Taiwan 2005: a molecular epidemiologic study. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2007;77:903&#x2013;909.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17984351</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu P-Y, Su C-L, Liao T-L, et al. Molecular characterization of dengue viruses imported into Taiwan during 2003&#x2013;2007: geographic distribution and genotype shift. The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene. 2009;80:1039&#x2013;1046.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19478273</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuan MM. Chang F-Y. Airport sentinel surveillance and entry quarantine for dengue infections following a fever screening program in Taiwan. BMC Infectious Diseases. 2012;12:182.  http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2334/12/182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3462143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22867003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>