<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">36545897</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>05</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2691-3321</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>21</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JBI evidence implementation</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JBI Evid Implement</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Best practice implementation on reporting of coronavirus disease 2019 vaccine adverse events following immunization in Uasin Gishu County, Kenya.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>146</StartPage><EndPage>155</EndPage><MedlinePgn>146-155</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/XEB.0000000000000362</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">This project's aim was to implement vaccine safety surveillance best practices to improve reporting of adverse events following immunization (AEFI) during coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccination roll out in Uasin Gishu County.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Weak vaccine safety surveillance systems in developing countries has contributed to underreporting of AEFIs undermining public confidence in immunization efforts, contributing to low uptake of vaccines critical in the fight against communicable diseases.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">The JBI Practical Application of Clinical Evidence System (JBI PACES) and Getting Research into Practice (GRiP) audit tool for promoting change in healthcare practice was utilized. Preimplementation and postimplementation audit cycles carried out utilized six best practice recommendations. Context-specific strategies and resources were used to address the gaps identified.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Less than half of the AEFIs reported were in accordance with the local policy recommendation, and most of the AEFIs reported were submitted in a timely manner in the baseline and follow-up cycle. Slight improvement was recorded in the number of health facilities with AEFIs reporting forms. An improvement of 33.7% was recorded in the number of health workers providing COVID-19 vaccination services who had received education and practical training on vaccine pharmacovigilance.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Underreporting and delayed submission of COVID-19 vaccine AEFI was evident among the healthcare providers offering COVID-19 vaccination services, the majority of healthcare providers had received training on vaccine pharmacovigilance, and AEFI hard copy reporting forms were not adequate in the health facilities. Public education on vaccine safety before administration of vaccine needs emphasis in order to improve reporting of AEFI.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2022 JBI. Unauthorized reproduction of this article is prohibited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Amdany</LastName><ForeName>Henry</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Uasin Gishu County Hospital.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koech</LastName><ForeName>Barbara</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Huruma Sub County Hospital, Eldoret, Kenya.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>JBI Evid Implement</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101772772</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2691-3321</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000086663">COVID-19 Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D014612">Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086663" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007630" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Kenya</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014611" MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccination</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007114" MajorTopicYN="N">Immunization</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014612" MajorTopicYN="Y">Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000009" MajorTopicYN="N">adverse effects</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>12</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36545897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/XEB.0000000000000362</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">02205615-202306000-00006</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Safety Surveillance Manual Second Edition. 2021. Available at: https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/345178/9789240032781-eng.pdf?sequence=1 [Accessed 29 November 2021].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. COVID-19 vaccines: safety surveillance manual. 2021. Available at: https://vaccine-safety-training.org/postlicensure-vaccine-safety.html [Accessed 30 November 2021].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Library Cataloguing-in-Publication Data Global manual on surveillance of adverse events following immunization. 2014. Available at: www.who.int [Accessed 30 November 2021].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alwan NA, Burgess RA, Ashworth S, et al. Scientific consensus on the COVID-19 pandemic: we need to act now. Lancet 2020; 396:e71&#x2013;e72.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>African Union Development Agency &#x2013; NEPAD. AEFI reporting rates Africa &#x2013; Google Search [Internet]. An African perspective on implementing and conducting safety surveillance of COVID-19 vaccines. 2021. Available at: https://www.google.com/search?q=aefi+reporting+rates+africa&amp;sxsrf=AOaemvKRD2zJfS80jrMxlQNp4X6m6A9rOA%3A1638268487012&amp;ei=R_6lYb4MipfFzw__uqDIBA&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj-y9vZ8b_0AhWKS_EDHX8dCEkQ4dUDCA4&amp;uact=5&amp;oq=aefi+reporting+rates+africa&amp;gs_lcp=Cgdnd3Mtd2l6EAM6BwgAEEcQsAM6BwgjELACECdKBAhBGABQgw1Y3BlgzhxoAnACeACAAYICiAHlC5IBAzItNpgBAKABAcgBCMABAQ&amp;sclient=gws-wiz [Accessed 30 November 2021].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guignard A, Praet N, Jusot V, Bakker M, Baril L. Introducing new vaccines in low- and middle-income countries: challenges and approaches. Expert Rev Vaccines 2019; 18:119&#x2013;131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2018 assessment report of the Global Vaccine Action Plan: strategic advisory group of experts on immunization. 2018. Available at: https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/276967/WHO-IVB-18.11-ara.pdf [Accessed 13 January 2022].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salmon DA, Dudley MZ, Glanz JM, Omer SB. Vaccine hesitancy: causes, consequences, and a call to action. Vaccine 2015; 33: (Suppl 4): D66&#x2013;D71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Geoghegan S, O&#x2019;Callaghan KP, Offit PA. Vaccine safety: myths and misinformation. Front Microbiol 2020; 11:372.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Albuquerque Veloso Machado M, Roberts B, Wong BLH, van Kessel R, Mossialos E. The relationship between the COVID-19 pandemic and vaccine hesitancy: a scoping review of literature until August 2021. Front Public Health 2021; 9:747787.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar D, Chandra R, Mathur M, Samdariya S, Kapoor N. Vaccine hesitancy: understanding better to address better. Isr J Health Policy Res 2016; 5:2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Di Pasquale A, Bonanni P, Gar&#xe7;on N, Stanberry LR, El-Hodhod M, Tavares Da Silva F. Vaccine safety evaluation: practical aspects in assessing benefits and risks. Vaccine 2016; 34:6672&#x2013;6680.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crawford NW, Clothier H, Hodgson K, Selvaraj G, Easton ML, Buttery JP. Active surveillance for adverse events following immunization. Expert Rev Vaccines 2014; 13:265&#x2013;276.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perry CB, Mizer AB, Wynn AB, Kruczek C. Countering COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy. Southwest Respir Crit Care Chronicles 2020; 8:32&#x2013;46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu Z, Meng R, Yang Y, et al. Active vaccine safety surveillance: global trends and challenges in China. Heal Data Sci 2021; 2021:1&#x2013;10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute of Medicine (US) Committee on a National Surveillance System for Cardiovascular and Select Chronic Diseases. Existing surveillance data sources and systems. Washington, DC: National Academies Press; 2011. Available at: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK83157/ [Accessed 13 January 2022].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunha MPL, D&#xf3;rea JG, Marques RC, Le&#xe3;o RS. Vaccine adverse events reported during the first ten years (1998&#x2013;2008) after introduction in the state of Rondonia, Brazil. Biomed Res Int 2013; 2013:853083.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gidudu JF, Shaum A, Dodoo A, et al. Barriers to healthcare workers reporting adverse events following immunization in four regions of Ghana. Vaccine 2020; 38:1009&#x2013;1014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsson S, Pal SN, Dodoo A. Expert review of clinical pharmacology pharmacovigilance in resource-limited countries. Available at: http://www.tandfonline.com/action/journalInformation?journalCode=ierj20 [Accessed 30 November 2021].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Straus W, Rubin H. COVID-19 vaccine safety monitoring in low and middle income countries &#x2013; time for a bold new approach. Vaccine 2022; 40:4301&#x2013;4302.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UMC | VigiBase [Internet]. Available at: https://www.who-umc.org/vigibase/vigibase/ . [Accessed 30 November 2021].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ampadu HH, Hoekman J, de Bruin ML, et al. Adverse drug reaction reporting in Africa and a comparison of individual case safety report characteristics between Africa and the rest of the world: analyses of spontaneous reports in VigiBase&#xae;. Drug Saf 2016; 39:335.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsson S, Pal SN, Dodoo A. Pharmacovigilance in resource-limited countries. Expert Rev Clin Pharmacol 2015; 8:449&#x2013;460.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nauman J, Soteriades ES, Hashim MJ, et al. Global incidence and mortality trends due to adverse effects of medical treatment, 1990&#x2013;2017: a systematic analysis from the global burden of diseases, injuries and risk factors study. Cureus 2020; 12:e7265.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malande OO, Munube D, Afaayo RN, et al. Adverse events following immunization reporting and impact on immunization services in informal settlements in Nairobi, Kenya: a prospective mixed-methods study. PAMJ 2021; 40:81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masika CW, Atieli H, Were T. Knowledge, perceptions, and practice of nurses on surveillance of adverse events following childhood immunization in Nairobi, Kenya. Biomed Res Int 2016; 2016:3745298.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konduri N, Aboagye-Nyame F, Mabirizi D, et al. Digital health technologies to support access to medicines and pharmaceutical services in the achievement of sustainable development goals. Digit Health 2018; 4:2055207618771407.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>2019 Kenya Population and Housing Census Reports - Kenya National Bureau of Statistics [Internet]. Available at: https://www.knbs.or.ke/2019-kenya-population-and-housing-census-reports/ . [Accessed 17 January 2022].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadi MA, Neoh CF, Zin RM, Elrggal ME, Cheema E. Pharmacovigilance: pharmacists&#x2019; perspective on spontaneous adverse drug reaction reporting. Integr Pharm Res Pract 2017; 6:91&#x2013;98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mehmeti I, Nelaj E, Simaku A, Tomini E, Bino S. Knowledge, practice and approaches of health professionals to adverse events following immunization and their reporting in Albania. Heliyon 2017; 3:e00331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parrella A, Braunack-Mayer A, Gold M, Marshall H, Baghurst P. Healthcare providers&#x2019; knowledge, experience and challenges of reporting adverse events following immunisation: a qualitative study. BMC Health Serv Res 2013; 13:313.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agoro OO, Kibira SW, Freeman J V, Fraser HSF, Agoro OO. Barriers to the success of an electronic pharmacovigilance reporting system in Kenya: an evaluation three years post implementation. Available at: https://academic.oup.com/jamia/article/25/6/627/4484018 [Accessed 17 January 2022].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan Z, Lockwood C, Munn Z, Aromataris E. The updated Joanna Briggs Institute Model of Evidence-Based Healthcare. Int J Evid Based Healthc 2019; 17:58&#x2013;71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aywak D, Jaguga CDP, Nkonge NG, Kinuthia R, Ambale C, Awle IA. Pharmacy practice in Kenya. Can J Hosp Pharm 2017; 70:456&#x2013;462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>PvERS: the Pharmacovigilance Electronic Reporting System: Home [Internet]. Available from: https://pv.pharmacyboardkenya.org/ [Accessed 2022 Feb 21].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitehorn A. Evidence summary. Vaccination: safety surveillance (pharmacovigilance). The JBI EBP Database, JBI@Ovid 2021; JBI-ES-5000-1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Kenya. Guideline for monitoring, reporting and managing adverse events following immunization (AEFI) in Kenya. Nairobi: Government of Kenya; 2014; 70.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marques J, Ribeiro-Vaz I, Pereira AC, Pol&#xf5;nia J. A survey of spontaneous reporting of adverse drug reactions in 10&#x200a;years of activity in a pharmacovigilance centre in Portugal. Int J Pharm Pract 2014; 22:275&#x2013;282.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jusot V, Chimimba F, Dzabala N, et al. Enhancing pharmacovigilance in sub-Saharan Africa through training and mentoring: a GSK Pilot Initiative in Malawi. Drug Saf 2020; 43:583&#x2013;593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammed L, Aliyu A, Maiha B, Isa A. Knowledge, perception and reporting attitude of adverse effects following immunization among primary healthcare workers in sabon gari local government area, Zaria, Kaduna State, Nigeria. Nig J Basic Clin Sci . 2018; 15: 81&#x2013;86. Available at: https://www.njbcs.net/article.asp?issn=0331-8540;year=2018;volume=15;issue=1;spage=81;epage=86;aulast=Mohammed [Accessed 16 February 2022].</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamoah P, Bangalee V, Oosthuizen F. Knowledge and perceptions of adverse events following immunization among healthcare professionals in Africa: a case study from Ghana. Vaccines (Basel) 2019; 7:28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reumerman M, Tichelaar J, Piersma B, Richir MC, van Agtmael MA. Urgent need to modernize pharmacovigilance education in healthcare curricula: review of the literature. Eur J Clin Pharmacol 2018; 74:1235&#x2013;1248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al Dweik R, Stacey D, Kohen D, Yaya S. Factors affecting patient reporting of adverse drug reactions: a systematic review. Br J Clin Pharmacol 2017; 83:875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avery AJ, Anderson C, Bond CM, et al. Evaluation of patient reporting of adverse drug reactions to the UK &#x2018;Yellow Card Scheme&#x2019;: literature review, descriptive and qualitative analyses, and questionnaire surveys. Health Technol Assess 2011; 15:1&#x2013;234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Constantine M, Cremance T, Juru TP, et al. Evaluation of the adverse events following immunization surveillance system in Guruve District, Mashonaland central. Pan Afr Med J 2018; 31:202.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>