<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">41267014</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2026</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2334</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>25</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2025</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>20</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC infectious diseases</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The tale of two assumptions: incorporating healthcare-seeking behaviour in epidemic forecasting.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1628</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1628</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">1628</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12879-025-11940-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>BACKGROUND: Modelling efforts during the COVID-19 pandemic highlighted the importance of incorporating human behaviour into mathematical models and the challenges of making accurate forecasts. Case detection is affected by different healthcare-seeking behaviors, including visiting physicians to seek help, which can impact the number of laboratory tests performed and the number of cases identified by surveillance systems throughout an epidemic. Mathematical models for forecasting epidemics of respiratory viruses such as influenza and COVID-19 generally assume a constant rate of case detection, and only a few studies have previously used time-dependent rates. PURPOSE: This study aims to compare constant and time-dependent case detection rate approaches for the forecast and retrospective fitting of seasonal influenza data. METHODS: An age-stratified Susceptible-Infected-Removed (SIR) model that incorporates case detection for influenza is formulated. Influenza case data and case detection rates for the 2016&#x2013;2019 seasons in Alberta, Canada, are used for model training. The model fitting results are compared for the constant and time-dependent case detection assumptions. The model forecasting results using partial-season data are compared to the data for the remainder of the season for validation. RESULTS: While both constant and time-dependent case detection rate assumptions allowed an accurate retrospective fitting to the case data of an entire season, the forecasting performance showed a significant difference between the two assumptions. Models with a time-dependent case detection rate accurately predicted the influenza peak time four weeks before the actual peak occurred. The average total infections per case detected, an estimate that includes both under-ascertainment and underreporting, also showed a significant difference between the two assumptions. CONCLUSION: The incorporation of healthcare-seeking behaviour in mathematical modelling helps quantify the dynamic process of how infections are detected by surveillance systems. This is an important consideration for influenza forecasting. Since not all individuals engage in healthcare-seeking behaviour and only a fraction of those who do seek help may get tested, a proportion of infections remain undetected by the surveillance system. The retrospective forecasting results highlight that a time-dependent case detection rate is more representative of changes in healthcare-seeking behaviour during the influenza seasons than a constant case detection rate. This approach provides a reliable solution for improving forecasts of seasonal influenza and may be adaptable to other respiratory viral infections.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Varughese</LastName><ForeName>Marie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistical Sciences, University of Alberta, University Commons 5-140, Edmonton, T6G 2N8, Alberta, Canada. mvarughe@ualberta.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Health Economics, 4-122 Enterprise Square, 10230 Jasper Avenue, Edmonton, T5J 4P6, Alberta, Canada. mvarughe@ualberta.ca.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Roda</LastName><ForeName>Weston</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistical Sciences, University of Alberta, University Commons 5-140, Edmonton, T6G 2N8, Alberta, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Health Economics, 4-122 Enterprise Square, 10230 Jasper Avenue, Edmonton, T5J 4P6, Alberta, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Han</LastName><ForeName>Donglin</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistical Sciences, University of Alberta, University Commons 5-140, Edmonton, T6G 2N8, Alberta, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Xuyuan</ForeName><Initials>X</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistical Sciences, University of Alberta, University Commons 5-140, Edmonton, T6G 2N8, Alberta, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Michael Y</ForeName><Initials>MY</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Mathematics and Statistical Sciences, University of Alberta, University Commons 5-140, Edmonton, T6G 2N8, Alberta, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>20</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968551</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2334</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="Y">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005544" MajorTopicYN="N">Forecasting</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010342" MajorTopicYN="Y">Patient Acceptance of Health Care</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012621" MajorTopicYN="N">Seasons</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000416" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Alberta</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008962" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Theoretical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000090005" MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiological Models</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000098437" MajorTopicYN="N">Prediction Algorithms</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemic forecast</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">case detection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">health-seeking behaviour</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">healthcare-seeking behaviour</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">influenza</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mathematical model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">respiratory virus</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">under-ascertainment</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">underreporting</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declarations. Ethics approval and consent to participate: The study was conducted using routinely collected public health surveillance and publicly available data in collaboration with Alberta Health. The analysis involved the secondary use of aggregate-level data that was securely stored following Alberta Health&#x2019;s guidelines for confidentiality and the use of this public health surveillance data did not require ethics approval. Consent for publication: Not applicable. Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests. Supplementary information: Supplementary information includes additional tables and figures for this manuscript. The transmission rates for the seasons 2015&#x2013;2016 to 2018&#x2013;2019 are described in Tables S1). Data for $$\tilde{\rho}(t)$$ for seasons 2015&#x2013;2016 to 2018&#x2013;2019 are provided in Tables S2 to S5. The figures provided in the Appendix describe the crude CDR (Figure S1), time-dependent CDR (Figures S2 to S4), retrospective fitting results by age group (Figures S5 to S7), prospective results four weeks before influenza peak by age (Figures S8 to S10), and prospective results two weeks prior to the influenza peak (Figures S11 to S14) from seasons 2016&#x2013;2017 to 2018&#x2013;2019. Figure S16 illustrates influenza seasonal patterns taken directly from&#xa0; [65]. Marginal posterior distributions of parameters from the 2017&#x2013;2018 influenza season are described in Figure S17 to S26.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2025</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>16</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2026</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>10</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">41267014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC12632065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12879-025-11940-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12879-025-11940-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Nixon K, Jindal S, Parker F, Reich N, Ghobadi KLee E, et al. An evaluation of prospective COVID-19 modelling studies in the USA: from data to science translation. Lancet Digit Health. 2022 Oct 1;4(10):e738&#x2013;47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamilton A, Haghpanah F, Tulchinsky A, Kipshidze N, Poleon S, Lin G, et al. Incorporating endogenous human behavior in models of covid-19 transmission: a systematic scoping review. Dialogues In Health. 2024;100179.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward H, Mertens TE, Thomas C. Health seeking behaviour and the control of sexually transmitted disease. Health Policy Plann. 1997;12(1):19&#x2013;28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moss R, Zarebski AE, Carlson SJ, McCaw JM. Accounting for healthcare-seeking behaviours and testing practices in real-time influenza forecasts. Trop Med And Infect Disease. 2019;4(1):12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han Q, Bragazzi NL, Asgary A, Orbinski J, Wu J, Kong JD. Estimation of epidemiological parameters and ascertainment rate from early transmission of covid-19 across Africa. Available at SSRN (2022). 4131409.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iyaniwura SA, Falc&#xe3;o RC, Ringa N, Adu PA, Spencer M, Taylor M, et al. Mathematical modeling of covid-19 in British Columbia: an age-structured model with time-dependent contact rates. Epidemics. 2022;39:100559.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halloran ME, Ferguson NM, Eubank S, Longini IM Jr, Cummings DA, Lewis B, Xu S, et al. Modeling targeted layered containment of an influenza pandemic in the United States. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2008;105(12):4639&#x2013;44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tizzoni M, Bajardi P, Poletto C, Ramasco JJ, Balcan D, Gon&#xe7;alves B, et al. Real-time numerical forecast of global epidemic spreading: case study of 2009 a/h1n1pdm. BMC Med. 2012;10:1&#x2013;31.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Childs L, Dick DW, Feng Z, Heffernan JM, Li J, R&#xf6;st G. Modeling waning and boosting of covid-19 in Canada with vaccination. Epidemics. 2022;39:100583.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell TW, Golding N, Hellewell J, Abbott S, Wright L, Pearson CA, et al. Reconstructing the early global dynamics of under-ascertained covid-19 cases and infections. BMC Med. 2020;18(1):332.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ivorra B, Ferr&#xe1;ndez MR, Vela-P&#xe9;rez M, Ramos AM. Mathematical modeling of the spread of the coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) taking into account the undetected infections. The case of China. Commun Nonlinear Sci Numer Simul. 2020;88:105303.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levy B, Edholm C, Gaoue O, Kaondera-Shava R, Kgosimore M, Lenhart S, et al. Modeling the role of public health education in ebola virus disease outbreaks in Sudan. Infect Disease Modell. 2017;2(3):323&#x2013;40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morozova O, Li ZR, Crawford FW. One year of modeling and forecasting covid-19 transmission to support policymakers in Connecticut. Sci Rep. 2021;11(1):20271.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cunniffe N, Hamelin F, Iggidr A, Rapaport A, Sallet G. Identifiability and observability in epidemiological models - a survey. HAL, Open Science; 2023. p.02995562&#x2013;3.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibbons CL, Mangen M-J-J, Plass D, Havelaar AH, Brooke RJ, Kramarz P, Peterson KL, Stuurman AL, Cassini AF&#xe8;vre EM, et al. Measuring underreporting and under-ascertainment in infectious disease datasets: a comparison of methods. BMC Public Health. 2014;14(1):1&#x2013;17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Benatia D, Godefroy R, Lewis J. Estimates of covid-19 cases across four Canadian provinces. Can Public Policy. 2020;46(S3):203&#x2013;16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verity R, Okell LC, Dorigatti I, Winskill P, Whittaker C, Imai N, Cuomo-Dannenburg G, Thompson H, Walker PGFu H, et al. Estimates of the severity of coronavirus disease 2019: a model-based analysis. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20(6):669&#x2013;77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Irons NJ, Raftery AE. Estimating sars-cov-2 infections from deaths, confirmed cases, tests, and random surveys. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2021;118:(31):2103272118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlton CL, Nguyen LT, Bailey A, Fenton J, Plitt SS, Marohn C, et al. Pre-vaccine positivity of sars-cov-2 antibodies in alberta, Canada during the first two waves of the covid-19 pandemic. Microbiol Spectr. 2021;9(1):00291&#x2013;21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Wang X, Blau DM, Caballero MT, Feikin DR, Gill CJ, et al. Global, regional, and national disease burden estimates of acute lower respiratory infections due to respiratory syncytial virus in children younger than 5 years in 2019: a systematic analysis. Lancet. 2022;399(10340):2047&#x2013;64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Alberta: Respiratory virus dashboard: characteristics. 2025. https://www.alberta.ca/stats/dashboard/respiratory-virus-dashboard.htm?data=characteristics#characteristicsl. Accessed 2025 Apr 20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meltzer MI, Gambhir M, Atkins CY, Swerdlow DL. Standardizing scenarios to assess the need to respond to an influenza pandemic. Clin Infect Dis. 2015;60(suppl_1):1&#x2013;8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mossong J, Hens N, Jit M, Beutels P, Auranen K, Mikolajczyk R, et al. Social contacts and mixing patterns relevant to the spread of infectious diseases. PLoS Med. 2008;5(3):74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Alberta (health): Seasonal influenza in Alberta: 2019&#x2013;2020 season. 2020. https://open.alberta.ca/dataset/9044e65d-a97e-43cb-8357-9c890422f069/resource/a8d0a6cd-97a2-48e2-8ec1-f5a11463bc33/download/health-influenza-summary-report-2019-2020.pdf. Accessed 2023 May 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skowronski DM, Leir S, Sabaiduc S, Chambers C, Zou M, Rose C, et al. Influenza vaccine effectiveness by a (h3n2) phylogenetic subcluster and prior vaccination history: 2016&#x2013;2017 and 2017&#x2013;2018 epidemics in Canada. The J Infect Dis. 2022;225(8):1387&#x2013;98.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skowronski DM, Leir S, Sabaiduc S, Murti M, Dickinson JA, Olsha R, Gubbay JB, Croxen MA, Charest HChan T, et al. Interim estimates of 2018/19 vaccine effectiveness against influenza a (h1n1) pdm09, canada, Eurosurveillance. 2019 (2019, january;24(4), 1900055.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Alberta: Alberta health diagnostic codes: claims assessment. 2014. https://open.alberta.ca/publications/alberta-health-diagnostic-codes#summary. Accessed 2025 Feb 15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alberta medical association: Fee Navigator. 2023. https://www.albertadoctors.org/fee-navigator/hsc/13.59A. Accessed 2023 May 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Collaborating Centre for Drug Statistics Methodology: 2023. https://www.whocc.no/atc_ddd_index/: ATC/DDD Index. Accessed 2023 05 10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dover D, Kirwin E, Hernandez-Ceron N, Nelson K. Pandemic risk assessment model (pram): a mathematical modeling approach to pandemic influenza planning. Epidemiol Infect. 2016;144(16):3400&#x2013;11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government A. Seasonal influenza in alberta 2018&#x2013;2019 season. Technical report, analytics and performane reporting branch. Alberta Health. 2019. Also available as https://open.alberta.ca/publications/2369-0690.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seasonal influenza in Alberta. Also available as 2024. https://open.alberta.ca/publications/2561-3154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roda W, Han D. MatlabDiffNestAlg: V1.2023;4 (1.4). Zenodo. Accessed 2023 Sep 10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brewer BJ, P&#xe1;rtay LB, Cs&#xe1;nyi G. Diffusive nested sampling. Stat Comput. 2011;21:649&#x2013;56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brewer BJ, Foreman-Mackey D. Dnest4: diffusive nested sampling in c++ and python. J Stat. 2016;86(7):1&#x2013;33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roda WC. Bayesian inference for dynamical systems. Infect Disease Modell. 2020;5:221&#x2013;32. 10.1016/j.idm.2019.12.007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gelman A, Meng X-L, Stern HS. Bayesian tests for goodness of fit using tail area probabilities. Statist. Sin. 1992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gelman A. Bayesian Data analysis. Third Edn. New York, ???: Chapman and Hall/CRC Press; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cramer EY, Ray EL, Lopez VK, Bracher J, Gneiting TReich NG, et al. Evaluation of individual and ensemble probabilistic forecasts of covid-19 mortality in the United States. Proc Natl Acad Sci, India Sect B Biol Sci. 2022;119(15), 2113561119 (10.1073/pnas.2113561119.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bracher J, Ray EL, Gneiting T, Reich NG. Evaluating epidemic forecasts in an interval format. PLoS Comput Biol. 2021;17(2):1008618 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mathis SM, Webber AE, et al. Evaluation of flusight influenza forecasting in the 2021&#x2013;22 and 2022&#x2013;23 seasons with a new target laboratory-confirmed influenza hospitalizations. Nat Commun. 2024;15:6289. 10.1038/s41467-024-50601-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center for disease control and prevention: FLUVIEW interactive: National, regional, and state level outpatient illness and viral surveillance. 2023. https://gis.cdc.gov/grasp/fluview/fluportaldashboard.html. Accessed 2023 Oct 05.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Public health agency of Canada: Flu (influenza): symptoms and treatment. 2025. https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/diseases/flu-influenza.html. Accessed 2025 Aug 15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. Influenza (seasonal). 2025. https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/influenza-(seasonal). Accessed 2025 Aug 15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Center for disease control and prevention: Flu season. 2024. https://www.cdc.gov/flu/about/season.html. Accessed 2025 Aug 15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Funk S, Bansal S, Bauch CT, Eames KT, Edmunds WJ, Galvani AP, Klepac P. Nine challenges in incorporating the dynamics of behaviour in infectious diseases models. Epidemics. 2015;10:21&#x2013;25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenfeld R, Tibshirani RJ. Epidemic tracking and forecasting: lessons learned from a tumultuous year. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2021;118(51):2111456118 .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Science Foundation: incorporating human behavior in epidemiological models (IHBEM), call for proposals. 2025. https://new.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/incorporating-human-behavior-epidemiological-0#:%7E:text=The%20Incorporating%20Human%20Behavior%20in,processes%20in%20mathematical%20epidemiological%20models. Accessed 2024 Apr 15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pei S, Kandula S, Yang W, Shaman J. Forecasting the spatial transmission of influenza in the United States. In: Cane MAP, Ed. Proceedings of the National Academy of sciences. Early. Vol. 115, (11). 2018. p. 2752&#x2013;57. 10.1073/pnas.1708856115. Edition, approved December 15, 2017; PMCID: PMC5856508; PMID: 29483256.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer SC, Pei S, Shaman J. Forecasting influenza in europe using a metapopulation model incorporating cross-border commuting and air travel. PLoS Comput Biol. 2020;16(10):1008233 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008233.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Towers S, Feng Z. Pandemic h1n1 influenza: predicting the course of a pandemic and assessing the efficacy of the planned vaccination programme in the United States. Eurosurveillance. 2009;14. 10.2807/ese.14.41.19358-en.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaman J, Karspeck A. Forecasting seasonal outbreaks of influenza. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2012;109(50):20425&#x2013;30. 10.1073/pnas.1208772109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castro M, Ares S, Cuesta JA, Manrubia S. The turning point and end of an expanding epidemic cannot be precisely forecast. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2020;117(42):26190&#x2013;96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilke CO, Bergstrom CT. Predicting an epidemic trajectory is difficult. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2020;117(46):28549&#x2013;51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertozzi AL, Franco E, Mohler G, Short MB, Sledge D. The challenges of modeling and forecasting the spread of covid-19. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2020;117(29):16732&#x2013;38.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eales O, Plank MJ, Cowling BJ, Howden BP, Kucharski AJ, Sullivan SG, Vandemaele K, Viboud C, Riley S, McCaw JM, Shearer FM. Key challenges for respiratory virus surveillance while transitioning out of acute phase of covid-19 pandemic. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2024;30(2), 230768 (10.3201/eid3002.230768. Epub 2024 Jan 8; PMCID: PMC10826770.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colman E, Puspitarani GA, Enright J, Kao RR. Ascertainment rate of sars-cov-2 infections from healthcare and community testing in the UK. J Theor Biol. 2023;558, 111333.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>P&#x159;ibylov&#xe1; L, Eclerov&#xe1; V, M&#xe1;jek O, Jarkovsk&#xfd; J, Pavl&#xed;k T, Du&#x161;ek L. Using real-time ascertainment rate estimate from infection and hospitalization dataset for modeling the spread of infectious disease: covid-19 case study in the Czech Republic. PLoS One. 2023;18(7), 0287959.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baltrusaitis K, Reed C, Sewalk K, Brownstein JS, Crawley AW, Biggerstaff M. Healthcare-seeking behavior for respiratory illness among flu near you participants in the United States during the 2015&#x2013;2016 through 2018&#x2013;2019 influenza seasons. The J Infect Dis. 2022;226(2):270&#x2013;77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng H, Liao Q, Suen LKP, O&#x2019;Donoghue M, Wong CM, Yang L. Healthcare seeking behavior of patients with influenza like illness: comparison of the summer and winter influenza epidemics. BMC Infect Dis. 2016;16:1&#x2013;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biggerstaff M, Jhung M, Reed C, Garg S, Balluz L, Fry A, et al. Impact of medical and behavioural factors on influenza-like illness, healthcare-seeking, and antiviral treatment during the 2009 h1n1 pandemic: USA, 2009&#x2013;2010. Epidemiol Infect. 2014;142(1):114&#x2013;25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biggerstaff M, Jhung MA, Reed C, Fry AM, Balluz L, Finelli L. Influenza-like illness, the time to seek healthcare, and influenza antiviral receipt during the 2010&#x2013;2011 influenza season&#x2014;United States. The J Infect Dis. 2014;210(4):535&#x2013;44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peppa M, John Edmunds W, Funk S. Disease severity determines health-seeking behaviour amongst individuals with influenza-like illness in an internet-based cohort. BMC Infect Dis. 2017;17(1):1&#x2013;13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ariza M, Guerrisi C, Souty C, Rossignol L, Turbelin C, Hanslik T, Colizza V, Blanchon T. Healthcare-seeking behaviour in case of influenza-like illness in the French general population and factors associated with a gp consultation: an observational prospective study. BJGP Open. 2018;1(4).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of Alberta: Respiratory virus dashboard: laboratory-confirmed seasonal influenza cases in Alberta since the 2009&#x2013;2010 season. 2025. https://www.alberta.ca/stats/dashboard/respiratory-virus-dashboard.htm?data=summary#summary. Accessed: 2025 Oct 24.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>