<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">24063811</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2014</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1472-6785</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>13</Volume><PubDate><Year>2013</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC ecology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Ecol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A test of agent-based models as a tool for predicting patterns of pathogen transmission in complex landscapes.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>35</StartPage><MedlinePgn>35</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/1472-6785-13-35</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Landscape complexity can mitigate or facilitate host dispersal, influencing patterns of pathogen transmission. Spatial transmission of pathogens through landscapes, therefore, presents an important but not fully elucidated aspect of transmission dynamics. Using an agent-based model (LiNK) that incorporates GIS data, we examined the effects of landscape information on the spatial patterns of host movement and pathogen transmission in a system of long-tailed macaques and their gut parasites. We first examined the role of the landscape to identify any individual or additive effects on host movement. We then compared modeled dispersal distance to patterns of actual macaque gene flow to both confirm our model's predictions and to understand the role of individual land uses on dispersal. Finally, we compared the rate and the spread of two gastrointestinal parasites, Entamoeba histolytica and E. dispar, to understand how landscape complexity influences spatial patterns of pathogen transmission.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">LiNK captured emergent properties of the landscape, finding that interaction effects between landscape layers could mitigate the rate of infection in a non-additive way. We also found that the inclusion of landscape information facilitated an accurate prediction of macaque dispersal patterns across a complex landscape, as confirmed by Mantel tests comparing genetic and simulated dispersed distances. Finally, we demonstrated that landscape heterogeneity proved a significant barrier for a highly virulent pathogen, limiting the dispersal ability of hosts and thus its own transmission into distant populations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Landscape complexity plays a significant role in determining the path of host dispersal and patterns of pathogen transmission. Incorporating landscape heterogeneity and host behavior into disease management decisions can be important in targeting response efforts, identifying cryptic transmission opportunities, and reducing or understanding potential for unintended ecological and evolutionary consequences. The inclusion of these data into models of pathogen transmission patterns improves our understanding of these dynamics, ultimately proving beneficial for sound public health policy.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lane-deGraaf</LastName><ForeName>Kelly E</ForeName><Initials>KE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biological Sciences, University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, IN, USA. lanedegraaf.kelly@gmail.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kennedy</LastName><ForeName>Ryan C</ForeName><Initials>RC</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Arifin</LastName><ForeName>S M Niaz</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Madey</LastName><ForeName>Gregory R</ForeName><Initials>GR</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fuentes</LastName><ForeName>Agustin</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hollocher</LastName><ForeName>Hope</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013486">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, Non-P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2013</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Ecol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101088674</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1472-6785</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D063147" MajorTopicYN="N">Animal Distribution</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003198" MajorTopicYN="N">Computer Simulation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004463" MajorTopicYN="N">Ecology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004747" MajorTopicYN="N">Entamoeba</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000472" MajorTopicYN="Y">pathogenicity</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004749" MajorTopicYN="N">Entamoebiasis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="Y">transmission</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004777" MajorTopicYN="Y">Environment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D051456" MajorTopicYN="N">Gene Flow</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D040362" MajorTopicYN="N">Geographic Information Systems</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008251" MajorTopicYN="N">Macaca</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="Y">parasitology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008954" MajorTopicYN="Y">Models, Biological</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2013</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2013</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2013</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2013</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2014</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2013</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24063811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3850893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1472-6785-13-35</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1472-6785-13-35</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Hess GR, Randolph SE, Arneberg P, Chemini C, Furlanello C, Harwood J, Roberts MG, Swinton J. In: The Ecology of Wildlife Diseases. Hudson PJ, Rizzolo A, Grenfell BT, Heesterbeek H, Dobson AP, editor. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press; 2001. Spatial aspects of disease dynamics; pp. 102&#x2013;118.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lam SK, Chua KB. Nipah virus encephalitis outbreak in Malaysia. Clin Infect Dis. 2002;34(S2):S48&#x2013;S51. doi: 10.1086/338818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1086/338818</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11938496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley S. Large-scale spatial-transmission models of infectious disease. Science. 2007;316:1298&#x2013;1301. doi: 10.1126/science.1134695.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1134695</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17540894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Real LA, Biek R. Spatial dynamics and genetics of infectious disease on heterogeneous landscapes. J R Soc Interface. 2007;4:935&#x2013;948. doi: 10.1098/rsif.2007.1041.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsif.2007.1041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2074889</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17490941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crais RF, Ellis JH, Glass GE. Forecasting the geographical spread of smallpox cases by air travel. Epidemiol Infect. 2003;131:849&#x2013;857. doi: 10.1017/S0950268803008811.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268803008811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2870028</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14596525</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crowl TA, Crist TO, Parmenter RR, Belovsky G, Lugo AE. The spread of invasive species and infectious disease as drivers of ecosystem change. Front Ecol Environ. 2008;6(5):238&#x2013;246. doi: 10.1890/070151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1890/070151</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeling MJ, Woolhouse MEJ, Shaw DJ, Matthews L, Chase-Topping M, Haydon DT, Cornell ST, Kappey J, Wilesmith J, Grenfell BT. Dynamics of the 2001 UK foot and mouth epidemic: stochastic dispersal in a heterogeneous landscape. Science. 2001;294:813&#x2013;817. doi: 10.1126/science.1065973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1065973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11679661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atti ML C d, Merler S, Rizzo C, Ajelli M, Massari M, Manfredi P, Furlanello C, Scalia Tombo G, Ianelli M. Mitigation measures for pandemic influenza in Italy: An individual based model considering different scenarios. PLoS One. 2008;3(3):1&#x2013;11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2258437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18335060</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Remais J, Akullian A, Ding L, Seto E. Analytical methods for quantifying environmental connectivity for the control and surveillance of infectious disease spread. J R Soc Interface. 2010;7:1181&#x2013;1193. doi: 10.1098/rsif.2009.0523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsif.2009.0523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2894871</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20164085</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muller G, Grebaut P, Gouteux JP. An agent-based model of sleeping sickness: simulation trials of a forest focus in southern Cameroon. J R Biologies. 2004;327:1&#x2013;11. doi: 10.1016/j.crvi.2003.12.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.crvi.2003.12.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15015750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenfell BT, Dobson AP. Ecology of Infectious Diseases in Natural Populations. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; 1995.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morens DM, Folkers GK, Fauci AS. The challenge of emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases. Nature. 2004;430:242&#x2013;249. doi: 10.1038/nature02759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature02759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15241422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones KE, Patel NG, Levy MA, Storeygard A, Balk D, Gittleman JL. Global trends in emerging infectious diseases. Nature. 2008;451:990&#x2013;994. doi: 10.1038/nature06536.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature06536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5960580</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18288193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eisenberg JNS, Brookhart MA, Rice G, Brown M, Colford JM Jr. Disease transmission models for public health decision making: Analysis of epidemic and endemic conditions caused by waterborne pathogens. Environ Health Persp. 2002;110(8):783&#x2013;790. doi: 10.1289/ehp.02110783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.02110783</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1240949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12153759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Patz JA, Daszak P, Tabor GM, Aguirre AA, Pearl M, Epstein J, Wolfe ND, Kilpatrick AM, Foufopoulos J, Molyneux D, Bradley DH. Members of the Working Group on Land Use Change Disease Emergence. Unhealthy Landscapes: Policy Recommendations on Land Use Change and Infectious Disease Emergence. Environ Health Persp. 2004;112(10):1092&#x2013;1098. doi: 10.1289/ehp.6877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1289/ehp.6877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1247383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15238283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koopman JS. Modeling Infection Transmission &#x2013; the Pursuit of Complexities That Matter. Epidemiology. 2002;13(6):622&#x2013;624. doi: 10.1097/00001648-200211000-00004.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/00001648-200211000-00004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12410001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koopman JS, Lynch JW. Individual causal models and population system models in epidemiology. Am J Public Health. 1999;89(8):1170&#x2013;1174. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.89.8.1170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.89.8.1170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1508689</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10432901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogers DJ, Randolph SE. Studying the global distribution of infectious diseases using GIS and RS. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2003;1:231&#x2013;237. doi: 10.1038/nrmicro776.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nrmicro776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7096846</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15035027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Colwell RR. Global climate change and infectious disease: the cholera paradigm. Science. 1996;274:2025&#x2013;2031. doi: 10.1126/science.274.5295.2025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.274.5295.2025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8953025</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eisen RJ, Enscore RE, Biggerstaff BJ, Reynolds PJ, Ettestad P, Brown T, Pape J, Tanda D, Levy CE, Engelthaler DM, Cheek J, Bueno R, Targhetta J, Montenieri JA, Gage KL. Human plague in the southwestern United States, 1957&#x2013;2004: spatial models of elevated risk of human exposure to Yersinia pestis. J of Med Entomol. 2007;44(3):530&#x2013;537. doi: 10.1603/0022-2585(2007)44[530:HPITSU]2.0.CO;2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1603/0022-2585(2007)44[530:HPITSU]2.0.CO;2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17547242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mungrue K, Mahabir R. The rabies epidemic in Trinidada of 1923 to 1937: an evaluation with a geographic information system. Wild Environ Med. 2009. doi:10.1016/j.wem.2010.11.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21377116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castillo-Riquelme M, Chalabi Z, Lord J, Guhl F, Campbell-Lendrum D, Davies C, Fox-Rushby J. Modelling geographic variation in the cost-effectiveness of control policies for infectious diseases: The example of Chagas disease. J Health Econ. 2008;27:405&#x2013;426. doi: 10.1016/j.jhealeco.2007.04.005.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2007.04.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18222556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eubank S, Guclu H, Anil Kumar VS, Marathe MV, Srinivasan A, Toroczkai Z, Wang N. Modelling disease outbreaks in realistic urban social networks. Nature. 2004;429:180&#x2013;184. doi: 10.1038/nature02541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nature02541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15141212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyers LA. Contact network epidemiology: bond percolation applied to infectious disease prediction and control. B Am Math Soc. 2007;44(1):63&#x2013;86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimm V, Railsback SF. Individual-based modeling and ecology. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press; 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Segovia-Juarez JL, Gangul S, Krischner D. Identifying control mechanisms of granuloma formation during M. tuberculosis infection using an agent-based model. J Theor Biol. 2004;231:357&#x2013;376. doi: 10.1016/j.jtbi.2004.06.031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2004.06.031</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15501468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thierry B. In: Primates in Perspective. Campbell CJ, Fuentes A, MacKinnon KC, Panger M, Bearder SK, editor. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press; 2007. The Macaques: a double-layered social organization; pp. 224&#x2013;239.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Evans BJ, Supriatna J, Andayani N, Melnick DJ. Diversification of Sulawesi macaque monkeys: Decoupled evolution of mitochondrial and autosomal DNA. Evolution. 2003;57:1931&#x2013;1946.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14503633</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lane KE, Lute M, Arta Putra IGA, Wandia IN, Hollocher H, Fuentes A. In: Indonesian Primates. Gursky S, Supriatna J, editor. New York, NY: Springer; 2010. Pests, pestilence, and people: the long-tailed macaque and its role in the cultural complexities of Bali; pp. 239&#x2013;248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wheatley BP. The sacred monkeys of Bali. Prospect Heights, IL: Wavelend Press, Inc; 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuentes A, Southern M, Suaryana KG. In: Commensalism and Conflict: The primate-human interface. Patterson J, editor. American Society of Primatology Publications; 2005. Monkey forests and human landscapes: is extensive sympatry sustainable for Homo sapiens and Macaca fascicularis in Bali?</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Southern MW. An assessment of potential habitat corridors and landscape ecology for long-tailed macaques (Macaca fascicularis) on Bali, Indonesia. WA: Central Washington University; 2002. (Master&#x2019;s thesis).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jasmer DP, Goverse A, Smant G. Parasitic nematode interactions with mammals and plants. Annu Rev Phytopathol. 2003;41:245&#x2013;270. doi: 10.1146/annurev.phyto.41.052102.104023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.41.052102.104023</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14527330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts LS, Janovy J. Foundations of Parasitology, 8th ed. New York, NY: McGraw-Hill; 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lane KE, Holley C, Hollocher H, Fuentes A. The anthropogenic environment lessens the intensity and prevalence of gastrointestinal parasites in Balinese long-tailed macaques (Macaca fascicularis) Primates. 2011;52(2):117&#x2013;128. doi: 10.1007/s10329-010-0230-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10329-010-0230-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21165669</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danson FM, Craig PS, Man W, Shi D, Giraudoux P. Landscape dynamics and risk modeling of human alveolar echinococcis. Photo Eng Rem Sens. 2004;70(3):359&#x2013;366.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giraudoux P, Craig PS, Delattre P, Boa G, Bartholomot B, Harraga S, Quere J-P, Raoul F, Wang Y, Shi D, Vuitton D-A. Interactions between landscape changes and host communities can regulate Echinococcus multilocularis transmission. Parasit. 2003;127:S121&#x2013;S131. doi: 10.1017/S0031182003003469.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0031182003003469</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15027609</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trejos-Macia G, Estrada A, Cabrera AGM. Survey of helminth parasites in populations of Alouatta palliate Mexicana and A. pigra in continuous and in fragmented habitat in southern Mexico. Int J Primat. 2007;28:931&#x2013;945. doi: 10.1007/s10764-007-9137-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10764-007-9137-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ryan SJ, Brashares JS, Walsh C, Milbers K, Kilroy C, Chapman CA. A survey of gastrointestinal parasite of olive baboobs (Papio Anubis) in human settlement areas of Mole National Park, Ghana. J Parasit. 2012;98(4):885&#x2013;888. doi: 10.1645/GE-2976.1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1645/GE-2976.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22300265</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rivera WL, Yason ADL, Adao DEV. Entamoeba histolytica and E. dispar infections in captive macaques (Macaca fascicularis) in the Philippines. Primates. 2010;51(1):69&#x2013;74. doi: 10.1007/s10329-009-0174-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10329-009-0174-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19862480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tachibana H, Yanagi T, Akatsuka A, Kobayash S, Janbara H, Tsutsumi V. Isolation and characterization of a potentially virulent species of Entamoeba nuttali from captive Japanese macaques. Parasit. 2009;136(10):1169&#x2013;1177. doi: 10.1017/S0031182009990576.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0031182009990576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19635174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng M, Yang B, Yang L, Fu YF, Zhuang YJ, Liang LG, Xu G, Cheng XJ, Tachibana H. High prevalence of Entamoeba infections in captive long-tailed macaques in China. Parasit Res. 2011;109(4):1093&#x2013;1097. doi: 10.1007/s00436-011-2351-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00436-011-2351-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21484347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimm V, Berger U, DeAngelis DL, Polhill JG, Giske J, Railsback SF. The ODD protocol: a review and first update. Ecol Model. 2010;221:2760&#x2013;2768. doi: 10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2010.08.019.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2010.08.019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Java. http://java.sun.com</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Repast. http://sourceforge.repast.net</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>OpenMap. http://openmap.bbn.com</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>GeoTools. http://geotools.codehaus.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>JTS Topology Suite. http://www.vividsolutions.com/jts/jtshome.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimm V, Berger U, Bastiansen F, Eliassen S, Ginot V, Giske J, Goss-custard J, Grand T, Heinz SK, Huse G, Huth A, Jepsen JU, Jorgensen C, Mooij WM, Muller B, Pe&#x2019;er G, Piou C, Railsback SF, Robbins AM, Robbins MM, Rossmanith E, Ruger N, Strand E, Souissi S, Stillman RA, Vabo R, Visser U, DeAngelis DL. A standard protocol for describing individual-based and agent-based models. Ecol Model. 2006;198:115&#x2013;126. doi: 10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2006.04.023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2006.04.023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kennedy RC, Lane KE, Fuentes A, Hollocher H, Madey G. A GIS aware agent-based model of pathogen transmission. Int J Intell Contr Syst. 2009;14(1):51&#x2013;61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leduc A, Drapeau P, Bergeron Y, Legendre P. Study of spatial components of forest covers using partial Mantel tests and path analysis. J Veg Science. 1992;3(1):69&#x2013;78. doi: 10.2307/3236000.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/3236000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zar JH. Biostatistical Analysis. Upper Saddle River, NJ: Prentice Hall; 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright S. Isolation by distance. Genetics. 1943;28:114&#x2013;138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1209196</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17247074</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rousset F. Genetic differentiation and estimation of gene flow from F-statistics under isolation by distance. Genetics. 1997;145:1219&#x2013;1228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1207888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9093870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slatkin M. Isolation by distance in equilibrium and non-equilibrium populations. Evolution. 1993;47(1):264&#x2013;279. doi: 10.2307/2410134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/2410134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28568097</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanley SL. Pathophysiology of ameobiasis. Trends Parasitol. 2001;17(6):280&#x2013;285. doi: 10.1016/S1471-4922(01)01903-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1471-4922(01)01903-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11378035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Garine-Waichatitsky M, Caron A, Kock R, Tschopp R, Munyeme M, Hofmeyr M, Michel A. A review of bovine tuberculosis at the wildlife-livestock-human interface in sub-Saharan Africa. Epidem and Infect. 2012;141(7):1342&#x2013;1356.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9151583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23587372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amouroux E, Desvaux S, Drogoul A. Intelligent agents and multi-agent systems. Berlin, Germany: Springer Berlin; 2008. Towards Virual Epidemiology: an agent-based approach to the modeling of H5NB1 propogation and persistence in North Vietnam.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laurenson MK, Mlengeya T, Shiferaw F, Cleaveland S. Approaches to disease control in domestic canids for the conservation of wild carnivores. Cambridge, UK: IUCN Publications; 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boadella M, Vicente J, Ruiz-Fons F, de la Fuente J, Gortazar C. Effects of culling Eurasian wild boar on the prevalence of Mycobacterium bovis and Aujeszky&#x2019;s disease virus. Prevent Vet Med. 2011;107(3&#x2013;4):214&#x2013;221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22743215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beeton N, McCallum H. Models predict that culling is not a feasible strategy to prevent extinction of Tasmanian devils from facial tumour disease. J Appl Eco. pp. 1315&#x2013;1323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Donnelly CA, Woodroffe R, Cox DR, Bourne FJ, Cheeseman CL, Clifton-Hadley RS, Wei G, Gettinby G, Gilks P, Jenkins H, Johnston WT, LeFevre AM, McInerney JP, Morrison WI. Positive and negative effects of widespread culling on tuberculosis on cattle. Nature. 2006;439(16):843&#x2013;846.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16357869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodroffe R, Donnelly CA, Cox DR, Bourne FJ, Cheeseman CL, Delahay RJ, Gettinby G, McInerney JP, Morrison WI. Effects of culling on badger Meles meles spatial organization: implications for the control of bovine tuberculosis. J Appl Ecol. 2006;43(1):1&#x2013;10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodroffe R, Donnelly CA, Wei G, Cox DR, Bourne FJ, Burke T, Butlin RK, Cheeseman CL, Gettinby G, Gilks P, Heges S, Jenkins HE, Johnston WT, McInerney JP, Morrison WI, Pope LC. Social group size affects Mycobacterium bovis infection in European badgers (Meles meles) J Anim Ecol. 2009;78:818&#x2013;827. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2656.2009.01545.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2656.2009.01545.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19486382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woodroffe R, Donnelly CA, Cox DR, Gilks P, Jenkins HE, Johnston WT, LeFevre AM, Bourne FJ, Cheeseman CL, Clifton-Hadley RS, Gettinby G, Hewinson RG, McInerney JP, Mitchell AP, Morrison WI, Watkins GH. Bovine tuberculosis in cattle and badgers in localized culling areas. J Wildlife Dis. 2009;45(1):128&#x2013;143. doi: 10.7589/0090-3558-45.1.128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7589/0090-3558-45.1.128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19204342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levin R. Preparing for Uncertainty. Ecosyst Health. 1995;1:47&#x2013;57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonnell TR, Sengupta RR, Chapman CA, Goldberg TL. An agent-based model of red colobus resources and disease dynamics implicates key resource sites as hot spots of disease transmission. Ecol Model. 2010;221(20):2491&#x2013;2500. doi: 10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2010.07.020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2010.07.020</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arifin SMN, Kennedy RC, Lane KE, Fuentes A, Hollocher H, Madey G. P-SAM: A Post-Simulation Analysis Module for Agent-Based Models. Ottawa, ON: Paper presented at Proceedings of the Summer Computer Simulation Conference; 2010.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>