<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">33906237</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>05</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-6591</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>72</Volume><Issue>Suppl 3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical infectious diseases : an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Impact of Key Assumptions About the Population Biology of Soil-Transmitted Helminths on the Sustainable Control of Morbidity.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>S188</StartPage><EndPage>S194</EndPage><MedlinePgn>S188-S194</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/cid/ciab195</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The design and evaluation of control programs for soil-transmitted helminths (STHs) is based on surveillance data recording measurements of egg counts in the stool of infected individuals, which underpin estimates of the prevalence and average intensity of infection. There is considerable uncertainty around these measurements and their interpretation. The uncertainty is composed of several sources of measurement error and the limit of detection of fecal smear tests on the one hand, and key assumptions on STH biology on the other hand, including assumptions on the aggregation of worms within hosts and on the impact of density-dependent influences on worm reproduction. Using 2 independently developed models of STH transmission we show how different aspects of STH biology and human behavior impact on STH surveillance and control programs and how accounting for uncertainty can help to develop optimal and sustainable control strategies to meet the World Health Organization (WHO) morbidity target for STHs.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s) 2021. Published by Oxford University Press for the Infectious Diseases Society of America.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vegvari</LastName><ForeName>Carolin</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>London Centre for Neglected Tropical Disease Research, Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Research Council Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Giardina</LastName><ForeName>Federica</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Erasmus MC, University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Malizia</LastName><ForeName>Veronica</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Erasmus MC, University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Vlas</LastName><ForeName>Sake J</ForeName><Initials>SJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Erasmus MC, University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Coffeng</LastName><ForeName>Luc E</ForeName><Initials>LE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Public Health, Erasmus MC, University Medical Center Rotterdam, Rotterdam, The Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anderson</LastName><ForeName>Roy M</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>London Centre for Neglected Tropical Disease Research, Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Medical Research Council Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The DeWorm3 Project, Natural History Museum, London, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>MR/R015600/1</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9203213</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1058-4838</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D012987">Soil</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001695" MajorTopicYN="N">Biology</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005243" MajorTopicYN="N">Feces</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006373" MajorTopicYN="Y">Helminthiasis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006376" MajorTopicYN="Y">Helminths</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012987" MajorTopicYN="N">Soil</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">mathematical modeling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">morbidity control</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">programme planning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">soil-transmitted helminthes</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33906237</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8218855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciab195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">6255958</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>
World Health Organization.
Soil-transmitted helminth infections&#x2013;key facts. Available at: https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/soil-transmitted-helminth-infections. Accessed 25 September 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hotez PJ, Bundy DA, Beegle K, et al. Helminth infections: soil-transmitted helminth infections and schistosomiasis. In: Jamieson DT, Breman JG, Measham AR, et al. Disease control priorities in developing countries. 2nd ed. Washington (DC): The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development / The World Bank, 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brooker S, Hotez PJ, Bundy DA. Hookworm-related anaemia among pregnant women: a systematic review. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2008; 2:e291.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2553481</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18820740</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Expert Committee on the Control of Schistosomiasis. Prevention and control of schistosomiasis and soil-transmitted helminthiasis. World Health Organ Tech Rep Ser 2002; 912: i-vi, 1&#x2013;57, back cover.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12592987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2030 targets for soil-transmitted helminthiases control programme. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Guideline: preventive chemotherapy to control soil-transmitted helminth infections in at-risk population groups. Geneva: World Health Organization,2017.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29578660</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Medley GF, Turner HC, Baggaley RF, Holland C, Hollingsworth TD. The role of more sensitive helminth diagnostics in mass drug administration campaigns: elimination and health impacts. Adv Parasitol 2016; 94:343&#x2013;92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27756457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, Schad GA. Hookworm burdens and faecal egg counts: an analysis of the biological basis of variation. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 1985; 79:812&#x2013;25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3832493</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Easton AV, Oliveira RG, Walker M, et al. 
Sources of variability in the measurement of <i>Ascaris lumbricoides</i> infection intensity by Kato-Katz and qPCR. Parasit Vectors 2017; 10:256.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5445470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28545561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halliday KE, Oswald WE, Mcharo C, et al. Community-level epidemiology of soil-transmitted helminths in the context of school-based deworming: baseline results of a cluster randomised trial on the coast of Kenya. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2019; 13:e0007427.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6719894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31398204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Truscott JE, Ower AK, Werkman M, et al. Heterogeneity in transmission parameters of hookworm infection within the baseline data from the TUMIKIA study in Kenya. Parasit Vectors 2019; 12:442.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6745791</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31522687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malizia V, Giardina F, Vegvari C, et al. Modelling the impact of COVID-19-related control programme interruptions on progress towards the WHO 2030 target for soil-transmitted helminths. medRxiv 2020: doi: 2020.11.01.20220376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7798673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33313897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, May RM.. Infectious diseases of humans: dynamics and control. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coffeng LE, Bakker R, Montresor A, de Vlas SJ. Feasibility of controlling hookworm infection through preventive chemotherapy: a simulation study using the individual-based WORMSIM modelling framework. Parasit Vectors 2015; 8:541.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4618856</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26489659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardwick RJ, Truscott JE, Oswald WE, et al. Individual adherence to mass drug administration in neglected tropical disease control: a probability model conditional on past behaviour. medRxiv 2020: doi: 2020.04.17.20069476.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7857569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33481780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oswald WE, Kepha S, Halliday KE, et al. Patterns of individual non-treatment during multiple rounds of community-wide mass-drug administration for control of soil-transmitted helminths in the TUMIKIA trial, Kenya. Lancet Infect Dis 2020; 8:e1418&#x2013;26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7564382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33069302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaz Nery S, Pickering AJ, Abate E, et al. The role of water, sanitation and hygiene interventions in reducing soil-transmitted helminths: interpreting the evidence and identifying next steps. Parasit Vectors 2019; 12:273.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6540378</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31138266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Elkins DB, Haswell-Elkins M, Anderson RM. The epidemiology and control of intestinal helminths in the Pulicat Lake region of Southern India. I. Study design and pre- and post-treatment observations on <i>Ascaris lumbricoides</i> infection. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 1986; 80:774&#x2013;92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3603617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haswell-Elkins MR, Elkins DB, Manjula K, Michael E, Anderson RM. An investigation of hookworm infection and reinfection following mass anthelmintic treatment in the south Indian fishing community of Vairavankuppam. Parasitology 1988; 96 (Pt 3):565&#x2013;77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3405641</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Bundy DA, Cooper ES, Thompson DE, Anderson RM, Didier JM. Age-related prevalence and intensity of <i>Trichuris trichiura</i> infection in a St. Lucian community. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 1987; 81:85&#x2013;94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3445330</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bethony J, Brooker S, Albonico M, et al. Soil-transmitted helminth infections: ascariasis, trichuriasis, and hookworm. Lancet 2006; 367:1521&#x2013;32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16679166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, Truscott JE, Pullan RL, Brooker SJ, Hollingsworth TD. How effective is school-based deworming for the community-wide control of soil-transmitted helminths? PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2013; 7:e2027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3585037</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23469293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NTD Modelling Consortium. The potential impact of programmes interruptions due to COVID-19 on 7 neglected tropical diseases: a modelling-based analysis report [version 1; not peer reviewed]. Gates Open Res 2020; 4:115.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Coffeng LE, Truscott JE, Farrell SH, et al. 
Comparison and validation of two mathematical models for the impact of mass drug administration on <i>Ascaris lumbricoides</i> and hookworm infection. Epidemics 2017; 18:38&#x2013;47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5340859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28279454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarke NE, Clements ACA, Amaral S, et al. (S)WASH-D for worms: a pilot study investigating the differential impact of school- versus community-based integrated control programs for soil-transmitted helminths. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2018; 12:e0006389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5933686</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29723193</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Helminth control in school age children: a guide for managers of control program. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization, 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker SL, Liwanag HJ, Snyder JS, et al. Toward the 2020 goal of soil-transmitted helminthiasis control and elimination. PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis. 2018; 12:e0006606.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6091919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30106975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Giardina F, Coffeng LE, Farrell SH, et al. Sampling strategies for monitoring and evaluation of morbidity targets for soil-transmitted helminths. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2019; 13:e0007514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6615707</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31242194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cools P, Vlaminck J, Albonico M, et al. Diagnostic performance of a single and duplicate Kato-Katz, Mini-FLOTAC, FECPAKG2 and qPCR for the detection and quantification of soil-transmitted helminths in three endemic countries. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2019; 13:e0007446.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6675048</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31369558</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coffeng LE, Malizia V, Vegvari C, et al. Impact of different sampling schemes for decision making in soil-transmitted helminthiasis control programs. J Infect Dis 2019; 221:S531&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7289558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31829425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keymer A. Density-dependent mechanisms in the regulation of intestinal helminth populations. Parasitology 1982; 84:573&#x2013;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7099714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, May RM. Helminth infections of humans: mathematical models, population dynamics, and control. Adv Parasitol 1985; 24:1&#x2013;101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3904343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Asaolu SO, Holland CV, Crompton DW. Community control of <i>Ascaris lumbricoides</i> in rural Oyo State, Nigeria: mass, targeted and selective treatment with levamisole. Parasitology 1991; 103:291&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1745554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ghadirian E, Croll NA, Gyorkos TW. Socio-agricultural factors and parasitic infections in the Caspian littoral region of Iran. Trop Geogr Med 1979; 31:485&#x2013;91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">317393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Kopp SR, Coleman GT, McCarthy JS, Kotze AC. Application of in vitro anthelmintic sensitivity assays to canine parasitology: detecting resistance to pyrantel in <i>Ancylostoma caninum</i>. Vet Parasitol 2008; 152:284&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18242867</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kotze AC, Kopp SR. The potential impact of density dependent fecundity on the use of the faecal egg count reduction test for detecting drug resistance in human hookworms. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2008; 2:e297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2553282</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18827883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coffeng LE, Vaz Nery S, Gray DJ, Bakker R, de Vlas SJ, Clements ACA. Predicted short and long-term impact of deworming and water, hygiene, and sanitation on transmission of soil-transmitted helminths. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2018; 12:e0006758.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6283645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30522129</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Werkman M, Toor J, Vegvari C, et al. Defining stopping criteria for ending randomized clinical trials that investigate the interruption of transmission of soil-transmitted helminths employing mass drug administration. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 2018; 12:e0006864.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6181437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30273343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hardwick RJ, Vegvari C, Truscott JE, Anderson RM. The &#x201c;breakpoint&#x201d; of soil-transmitted helminths with infected human migration. J Theor Biol 2020; 486:110076.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6977101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31733259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vegvari C, Truscott JE, Kura K, Anderson RM. Human population movement can impede the elimination of soil-transmitted helminth transmission in regions with heterogeneity in mass drug administration coverage and transmission potential between villages: a metapopulation analysis. Parasit Vectors 2019; 12:438.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6745807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31522681</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>