<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">36035966</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1061-8600</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>31</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of computational and graphical statistics : a joint publication of American Statistical Association, Institute of Mathematical Statistics, Interface Foundation of North America</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Comput Graph Stat</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adaptive Preferential Sampling in Phylodynamics With an Application to SARS-CoV-2.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>541</StartPage><EndPage>552</EndPage><MedlinePgn>541-552</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1080/10618600.2021.1987256</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Longitudinal molecular data of rapidly evolving viruses and pathogens provide information about disease spread and complement traditional surveillance approaches based on case count data. The coalescent is used to model the genealogy that represents the sample ancestral relationships. The basic assumption is that coalescent events occur at a rate inversely proportional to the effective population size <i>N</i> <sub><i>e</i></sub> (<i>t</i>), a time-varying measure of genetic diversity. When the sampling process (collection of samples over time) depends on <i>N</i> <sub><i>e</i></sub> (<i>t</i>), the coalescent and the sampling processes can be jointly modeled to improve estimation of <i>N</i> <sub><i>e</i></sub> (<i>t</i>). Failing to do so can lead to bias due to model misspecification. However, the way that the sampling process depends on the effective population size may vary over time. We introduce an approach where the sampling process is modeled as an inhomogeneous Poisson process with rate equal to the product of <i>N</i> <sub><i>e</i></sub> (<i>t</i>) and a time-varying coefficient, making minimal assumptions on their functional shapes via Markov random field priors. We provide efficient algorithms for inference, show the model performance vis-a-vis alternative methods in a simulation study, and apply our model to SARS-CoV-2 sequences from Los Angeles and Santa Clara counties. The methodology is implemented and available in the R package adapref. Supplementary files for this article are available online.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cappello</LastName><ForeName>Lorenzo</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, Stanford University, Stanford, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Palacios</LastName><ForeName>Julia A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, Stanford University, Stanford, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Data Science, Stanford Medicine, Stanford, CA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 GM131404</GrantID><Acronym>GM</Acronym><Agency>NIGMS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Comput Graph Stat</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101470926</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1061-8600</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="UpdateOf"><RefSource>ArXiv. 2020 Sep 4:arXiv:2009.02307v1.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">32908947</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Coalescent process</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Markov random fields</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Poisson processes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Population size</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36035966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1829128</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9409340</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/10618600.2021.1987256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bouckaert R, Vaughan TG, Barido-Sottani J, Duch&#xea;ne S, Fourment M, Gavryushkina A, Heled J, Jones G, K&#xfc;hnert D, De Maio N, Matschiner M, Mendes FK, M&#xfc;ller NF, Ogilvie HA, du Plessis L, Popinga A, Rambaut A, Rasmussen D, Siveroni I, Suchard MA, Wu C-H, Xie D, Zhang C, Stadler T, Drummond AJ (2019), &#x201c;BEAST 2.5: An Advanced Software Platform for Bayesian Evolutionary Analysis,&#x201d; PLoS Computational Biology, 15, e1006650.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6472827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30958812</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cappello L, Veber A and Palacios JA (2020), &#x201c;The Tajima Heterochronous n-Coalescent: Inference From Heterochronously Sampled Molecular Data,&#x201d; arXiv:2004.06826.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpenter B, Gelman A, Hoffman MD, Lee D, Goodrich B, Betancourt M, Brubaker M, Guo J, Li P, and Riddell A (2017), &#x201c;Stan: A Probabilistic Programming Language,&#x201d; Journal of Statistical Software, 76. arXiv:2004.06826</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9788645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36568334</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carvalho CM, Polson NG and Scott JG (2010), &#x201c;The Horseshoe Estimator for Sparse Signals,&#x201d; Biometrika, 97, 465&#x2013;480.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diggle PJ, Menezes R, and Su T. l. (2010), &#x201c;Geostatistical Inference Under Preferential Sampling,&#x201d; Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series C, 59, 191&#x2013;232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond AJ, Rambaut A, Shapiro B, and Pybus OG (2005), &#x201c;Bayesian Coalescent Inference of Past Population Dynamics From Molecular Sequences,&#x201d; Molecular Biology and Evolution, 22, 1185&#x2013;1192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15703244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faria NR, da Silva Azevedo R.d.S., Kraemer MU, Souza R, Cunha MS, Hill SC, Th&#xe9;z&#xe9; J, Bonsall MB, Bowden TA, Rissanen I, Rocco IM, Nogueira JS, Maeda AY, Vasami FGDS, Macedo FLL, Suzuki A, Rodrigues SG, Cruz ACR, Nunes BT, Medeiros DBA, Rodrigues DSG, Queiroz ALN, da Silva EVP, Henriques DF, da Rosa EST, de Oliveira CS, Martins LC, Vasconcelos HB, Casseb LMN, Simith DB, Messina JP, Abade L, Louren&#xe7;o J, Alcantara LCJ, de Lima MM, Giovanetti M, Hay SI, de Oliveira RS, Lemos PDS, de Oliveira LF, de Lima CPS, da Silva SP, de Vasconcelos JM, Franco L, Cardoso JF, Vianez-J&#xfa;nior JLDSG, Mir D, Bello G, Delatorre E, Khan K, Creatore M, Coelho GE, de Oliveira WK, Tesh R, Pybus OG, Nunes MRT, Vasconcelos PFC (2016), &#x201c;Zika Virus in the Americas: Early Epidemiological and Genetic Findings,&#x201d; Science, 352, 345&#x2013;349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4918795</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27013429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faulkner JR, Magee AF, Shapiro B and Minin VN (2020), &#x201c;Horseshoe-Based Bayesian Nonparametric Estimation of Effective Population Size Trajectories,&#x201d; Biometrics, 76, 677&#x2013;690.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32277713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein J, and Rodrigo AG (1999), &#x201c;Coalescent Approaches to HIV Population Genetics,&#x201d; in The Evolution of HIV, eds. Crandall Keith A., Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, pp. 233&#x2013;272.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frost SD, and Volz EM (2010), &#x201c;Viral Phylodynamics and the Search for an Effective Number of Infections,&#x201d; Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society, Series B, 365, 1879&#x2013;1890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2880113</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20478883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gire SK, Goba A, Andersen KG, Sealfon RS, Park DJ, Kanneh L, Jalloh S, Momoh M, Fullah M, Dudas G, , Wohl S, Moses LM, Yozwiak NL, Winnicki S, Matranga CB, Malboeuf CM, Qu J, Gladden AD, Schaffner SF, Yang X, Jiang PP, Nekoui M, Colubri A, Coomber MR, Fonnie M, Moigboi A, Gbakie M, Kamara FK, Tucker V, Konuwa E, Saffa S, Sellu J, Jalloh AA, Kovoma A, Koninga J, Mustapha I, Kargbo K, Foday M, Yillah M, Kanneh F, Robert W, Massally JL, Chapman SB, Bochicchio J, Murphy C, Nusbaum C, Young S, Birren BW, Grant DS, Scheiffelin JS, Lander ES, Happi C, Gevao SM, Gnirke A, Rambaut A, Garry RF, Khan SH, Sabeti PC (2014), &#x201c;Genomic Surveillance Elucidates Ebola Virus Origin and Transmission During the 2014 Outbreak,&#x201d; Science, 345, 1369&#x2013;1372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4431643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25214632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenfell BT, Pybus OG, Gog JR, Wood JL, Daly JM, Mumford JA and Holmes EC (2004), &#x201c;Unifying the Epidemiological and Evolutionary Dynamics of Pathogens,&#x201d; Science, 303, 327&#x2013;332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14726583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hadfield J, Megill C, Bell SM, Huddleston J, Potter B, Callender C, Sagulenko P, Bedford T, and Neher RA (2018), &#x201c;Nextstrain: Real-Time Tracking of Pathogen Evolution,&#x201d; Bioinformatics, 34, 4121&#x2013;4123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6247931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29790939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasegawa M, Kishino H, and Yano T (1985), &#x201c;Dating of the Human-Ape Splitting by a Molecular Clock of Mitochondrial DNA,&#x201d; Journal of Molecular Evolution, 2, 160&#x2013;164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3934395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heled J, and Drummond AJ (2008), &#x201c;Bayesian Inference of Population Size History From Multiple Loci,&#x201d; BMC Evolutionary Biology, 8, 289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2636790</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18947398</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson RR (1990), &#x2018;Gene Genealogies and the Coalescent Process,&#x201d; Oxford Surveys in Evolutionary Biology, 7, 1&#x2013;44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huff CD, Xing J, Rogers AR, Witherspoon D, and Jorde LB (2010), &#x201c;Mobile Elements Reveal Small Population Size in the Ancient Ancestors of Homo Sapiens,&#x201d; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 107, 2147&#x2013;2152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2836654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20133859</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karcher MD, Palacios JA, Bedford T, Suchard MA, and Minin VN (2016), &#x201c;Quantifying and Mitigating the Effect of Preferential Sampling on Phylodynamic Inference,&#x201d; PLoS Computational Biology, 12, e1004789.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4777449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26938243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karcher MD, Palacios JA, Lan S, and Minin VN (2017), &#x201c;Phylodyn: An R Package for Phylodynamic Simulation and Inference,&#x201d; Molecular Ecology Resources, 17, 96&#x2013;100.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5466693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27801980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karcher MD, Suchard MA, Dudas G, and Minin VN (2020), &#x201c;Estimating Effective Population Size Changes From Preferentially Sampled Genetic Sequences,&#x201d; PloS Computational Biology, 16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7580988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33044955</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim S-J, Koh K, Boyd S, and Gorinevsky D (2009), &#x201c;<i>l</i><sub>1</sub> Trend Filtering,&#x201d; SIAM Eeview, 51, 339&#x2013;360.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kingman JF (1982a), &#x201c;On the Genealogy of Large Populations,&#x201d; Journal of Applied Probability, 19, 27&#x2013;43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>&#x2014;&#x2014;&#x2014; (1982b), &#x201c;The Coalescent,&#x201d; Stochastic Processes and Their Applications, 13, 235&#x2013;248.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lan S, Palacios JA, Karcher M, Minin VN, and Shahbaba B (2015), &#x201c;An Efficient Bayesian Inference Framework for Coalescent-Based Nonparametric Phylodynamics,&#x201d; Bioinformatics, 31, 3282&#x2013;3289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4795633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26093147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis PW, and Shedler GS (1979), &#x201c;Simulation of Nonhomogeneous Poisson Processes by Thinning,&#x201d; Naval Research Logistics Quarterly, 26, 403&#x2013;413.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorenzen ED, Nogu&#xe9;s-Bravo D, Orlando L, Weinstock J, Binladen J, Marske KA, Ugan A, Borregaard MK, Gilbert MTP, Nielsen R, Ho SY, Goebel T, Graf KE, Byers D, Stenderup JT, Rasmussen M, Campos PF, Leonard JA, Koepfli KP, Froese D, Zazula G, Stafford TW Jr., Aaris-S&#xf8;rensen K, Batra P, Haywood AM, Singarayer JS, Valdes PJ, Boeskorov G, Burns JA, Davydov SP, Haile J, Jenkins DL, Kosintsev P, Kuznetsova T, Lai X, Martin LD, McDonald HG, Mol D, Meldgaard M, Munch K, Stephan E, Sablin M, Sommer RS, Sipko T, Scott E, Suchard MA, Tikhonov A, Willerslev R, Wayne RK, Cooper A, Hofreiter M, Sher A, Shapiro B, Rahbek C, Willerslev E (2011), &#x201c;Species-Specific Responses of Late Quaternary Megafauna to Climate and Humans,&#x201d; Nature, 479, 359&#x2013;364.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4070744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22048313</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meredith LW, Hamilton WL, Warne B, Houldcroft CJ, Hosmillo M, Jahun AS, Curran MD, Parmar S, Caller LG, Caddy SL, Khokhar FA, Yakovleva A, Hall G, Feltwell T, Forrest S, Sridhar S, Weekes MP, Baker S, Brown N, Moore E, Popay A, Roddick I, Reacher M, Gouliouris T, Peacock SJ, Dougan G, T&#xf6;r&#xf6;k ME, Goodfellow I (2020), &#x201c;Rapid Implementation of SARS-CoV-2 Sequencing to Investigate Cases of Health-Care Associated Covid-19: A Prospective Genomic Surveillance Study,&#x201d; The Lancet Infectious Diseases, 20, 1263&#x2013;1272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7806511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32679081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minin VN, Bloomquist EW, and Suchard MA (2008), &#x201c;Smooth Skyride Through a Rough Skyline: Bayesian Coalescent-Based Inference of Population Dynamics,&#x201d; Molecular Biology and Evolution, 25, 1459&#x2013;1471.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3302198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18408232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munnink BBO, Nieuwenhuijse DF, Stein M, OToole &#xc1;, Haverkate M, Mollers M, Kamga SK, Schapendonk C, Pronk M, Lexmond P, van der Linden A, Bestebroer T, Chestakova I, Overmars RJ, van Nieuwkoop S, Molenkamp R, van der Eijk AA, GeurtsvanKessel C, Vennema H, Meijer A, Rambaut A, van Dissel J, Sikkema RS, Timen A, Koopmans M (2020), &#x201c;Rapid SARS-CoV-2 Whole-Genome Sequencing and Analysis for Informed Public Health Decision-Making in the Netherlands,&#x201d; Nature Medicine, 26, 1405&#x2013;1410.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32678356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palacios JA, and Minin VN (2012), &#x201c;Integrated Nested Laplace Approximation for Bayesian Nonparametric Phylodynamics,&#x201d; in Proceedings of the Twenty-Eighth Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI&#x2019;12), Arlington, VA: AUAI Press, pp. 726&#x2013;735.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palacios JA, and Minin VN (2013), &#x201c;Gaussian Process-Based Bayesian Nonparametric Inference of Population Size Trajectories From Gene Genealogies,&#x201d; Biometrics, 69, 8&#x2013;18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23409705</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parag KV, du Plessis L, and Pybus OG (2020), &#x201c;Jointly Inferring the Dynamics of Population Size and Sampling Intensity From Molecular Sequences,&#x201d; Molecular Biology and Evolution, 37, 2414&#x2013;2429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7403618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32003829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parag KV, and Pybus OG (2019), &#x201c;Robust Design for Coalescent Model Inference,&#x201d; Systematic Biology, 68, 730&#x2013;743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30726979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polonsky JA, Baidjoe A, Kamvar ZN, Cori A, Durski K, Edmunds WJ, Eggo RM, Funk S, Kaiser L, Keating P, de Waroux OLP, Marks M, Moraga P, Morgan O, Nouvellet P, Ratnayake R, Roberts CH, Whitworth J, Jombart T (2019), &#x201c;Outbreak Analytics: A Developing Data Science for Informing the Response to Emerging Pathogens,&#x201d; Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society, Series B, 374, 20180276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6558557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31104603</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pybus OG, Rambaut A, and Harvey PH (2000), &#x201c;An Integrated Framework for the Inference of Viral Population History From Reconstructed Genealogies,&#x201d; Genetics, 155, 1429&#x2013;1437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1461136</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10880500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rambaut A, Pybus OG, Nelson MI, Viboud C, Taubenberger JK, and Holmes EC (2008), &#x201c;The Genomic and Epidemiological Dynamics of Human Influenza A Virus,&#x201d; Nature, 453, 615&#x2013;619.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2441973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18418375</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothenberg TJ (1971), &#x201c;Identification in Parametric Models,&#x201d; Econometrica: Journal of the Econometric Society, 39, 577&#x2013;591.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rue H, and Held L (2005), Gaussian Markov Random Fields: Theory and Applications, London: Chapman and Hall&#x2013;CRC Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rue H, Martino S, and Chopin N (2009), &#x201c;Approximate Bayesian Inference for Latent Gaussian Models by Using Integrated Nested Laplace Approximations,&#x201d; Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series B, 71, 319&#x2013;392.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sainudiin R, Stadler T, and V&#xe9;ber A (2015), &#x201c;Finding the Best Resolution for the Kingman&#x2013;Tajima Coalescent: Theory and Applications,&#x201d; Journal of Mathematical Biology, 70, 1207&#x2013;1247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24825079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shapiro B, Drummond AJ, Rambaut A, Wilson MC, Matheus PE, Sher AV, Pybus OG, Gilbert MTP, Barnes I, Binladen J, Willerslev E, Hansen AJ, Baryshnikov GF, Burns JA, Davydov S, Driver JC, Froese DG, Harington CR, Keddie G, Kosintsev P, Kunz ML, Martin LD, Stephenson RO, Storer J, Tedford R, Zimov S, and Cooper A (2004), &#x201c;Rise and Fall of the Beringian Steppe Bison,&#x201d; Science, 306, 1561&#x2013;1565.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15567864</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shu Y, and McCauley J (2017), &#x201c;GISAID: Global Initiative on Sharing All Influenza Data&#x2013;From Vision to Reality,&#x201d; Eurosurveillance, 22, 30494.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5388101</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28382917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slatkin M, and Hudson R (1991), &#x201c;Pairwise Comparisons of Mitochondrial DNA Sequences in Stable and Exponentially Growing Populations,&#x201d; Genetics, 129, 555&#x2013;562.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1204643</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1743491</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stadler T (2010), &#x201c;Sampling-Through-Time in Birth&#x2013;Death Trees,&#x201d; Journal of Theoretical Biology, 267, 396&#x2013;404.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20851708</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stadler T, K&#xfc;hnert D, Bonhoeffer S, and Drummond AJ (2013), &#x201c;Birth&#x2013;Death Skyline Plot Reveals Temporal Changes of Epidemic Spread in HIV and Hepatitis C Virus (HCV),&#x201d; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 110, pp. 228&#x2013;233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3538216</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23248286</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Strimmer K, and Pybus OG (2001), &#x201c;Exploring the Demographic History of DNA Sequences Using the Generalized Skyline Plot,&#x201d; Molecular Biology and Evolution, 18, 2298&#x2013;2305.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11719579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volz EM, and Frost SD (2014), &#x201c;Sampling Through Time and Phylodynamic Inference With Coalescent and Birth&#x2013;Death Models,&#x201d; Journal of The Royal Society Interface, 11, 20140945.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4223917</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25401173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Volz EM, Pond SLK, Ward MJ, Brown AJL, and Frost SD (2009), &#x201c;Phylodynamics of Infectious Disease Epidemics,&#x201d; Genetics, 183, 1421&#x2013;1430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2787429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19797047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wakeley J (2009), Coalescent Theory: An Introduction, Greenwood Village, Colorado: Roberts and Co.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2021), &#x201c;Genomic Sequencing of SARS-CoV-2: A Guide to Implementation for Maximum Impact on Public Health, 8 January 2021&#x201d;.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F, Zhao S, Yu B, Chen Y-M, Wang W, Song Z-G, Hu Y, Tao Z-W, Tian J-H, Pei Y-Y et al. (2020), &#x201c;A New Coronavirus Associated With Human Respiratory Disease in China,&#x201d; Nature, 579, 265&#x2013;269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7094943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32015508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle><PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">32908947</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2331-8422</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2020</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>04</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>ArXiv</Title><ISOAbbreviation>ArXiv</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Adaptive preferential sampling in phylodynamics.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">arXiv:2009.02307v1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Longitudinal molecular data of rapidly evolving viruses and pathogens provide information about disease spread and complement traditional surveillance approaches based on case count data. The coalescent is used to model the genealogy that represents the sample ancestral relationships. The basic assumption is that coalescent events occur at a rate inversely proportional to the effective population size $N_{e}(t)$, a time-varying measure of genetic diversity. When the sampling process (collection of samples over time) depends on $N_{e}(t)$, the coalescent and the sampling processes can be jointly modeled to improve estimation of $N_{e}(t)$. Failing to do so can lead to bias due to model misspecification. However, the way that the sampling process depends on the effective population size may vary over time. We introduce an approach where the sampling process is modeled as an inhomogeneous Poisson process with rate equal to the product of $N_{e}(t)$ and a time-varying coefficient, making minimal assumptions on their functional shapes via Markov random field priors. We provide scalable algorithms for inference, show the model performance vis-a-vis alternative methods in a simulation study, and apply our model to SARS-CoV-2 sequences from Los Angeles and Santa Clara counties. The methodology is implemented and available in the R package adapref.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cappello</LastName><ForeName>Lorenzo</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Palacios</LastName><ForeName>Julia A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D000076942">Preprint</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2020</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>ArXiv</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101759493</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2331-8422</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="UpdateIn"><RefSource>J Comput Graph Stat. 2022;31(2):541-552. doi: 10.1080/10618600.2021.1987256.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">36035966</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>10</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>36</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32908947</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7480030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">2009.02307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>