<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20976213</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2011</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>5</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Oct</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Cost-effectiveness of adolescent pertussis vaccination for the Netherlands: using an individual-based dynamic model.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e13392</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e13392</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e13392</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0013392</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Despite widespread immunization programs, a clear increase in pertussis incidence is apparent in many developed countries during the last decades. Consequently, additional immunization strategies are considered to reduce the burden of disease. The aim of this study is to design an individual-based stochastic dynamic framework to model pertussis transmission in the population in order to predict the epidemiologic and economic consequences of the implementation of universal booster vaccination programs. Using this framework, we estimate the cost-effectiveness of universal adolescent pertussis booster vaccination at the age of 12 years in the Netherlands.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS/PRINCIPAL FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We designed a discrete event simulation (DES) model to predict the epidemiological and economic consequences of implementing universal adolescent booster vaccination. We used national age-specific notification data over the period 1996-2000--corrected for underreporting--to calibrate the model assuming a steady state situation. Subsequently, booster vaccination was introduced. Input parameters of the model were derived from literature, national data sources (e.g. costing data, incidence and hospitalization data) and expert opinions. As there is no consensus on the duration of immunity acquired by natural infection, we considered two scenarios for this duration of protection (i.e. 8 and 15 years). In both scenarios, total pertussis incidence decreased as a result of adolescent vaccination. From a societal perspective, the cost-effectiveness was estimated at &#x20ac;4418/QALY (range: 3205-6364 &#x20ac; per QALY) and &#x20ac;6371/QALY (range: 4139-9549 &#x20ac; per QALY) for the 8- and 15-year protection scenarios, respectively. Sensitivity analyses revealed that the outcomes are most sensitive to the quality of life weights used for pertussis disease.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS/SIGNIFICANCE" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">To our knowledge we designed the first individual-based dynamic framework to model pertussis transmission in the population. This study indicates that adolescent pertussis vaccination is likely to be a cost-effective intervention for The Netherlands. The model is suited to investigate further pertussis booster vaccination strategies.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Vries</LastName><ForeName>Robin</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Unit of Pharmacoepidemiology and Pharmacoeconomics, Department of Pharmacy, University of Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands. Robin.de.Vries@rug.nl</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kretzschmar</LastName><ForeName>Mirjam</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schellekens</LastName><ForeName>Joop F P</ForeName><Initials>JF</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Versteegh</LastName><ForeName>Florens G A</ForeName><Initials>FG</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Westra</LastName><ForeName>Tjalke A</ForeName><Initials>TA</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roord</LastName><ForeName>John J</ForeName><Initials>JJ</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Postma</LastName><ForeName>Maarten J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D010567">Pertussis Vaccine</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003362" MajorTopicYN="Y">Cost-Benefit Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015994" MajorTopicYN="N">Incidence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017059" MajorTopicYN="Y">Models, Econometric</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009426" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Netherlands</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010567" MajorTopicYN="N">Pertussis Vaccine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000008" MajorTopicYN="N">administration &amp; dosage</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000191" MajorTopicYN="Y">economics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="Y">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019057" MajorTopicYN="N">Quality-Adjusted Life Years</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013269" MajorTopicYN="N">Stochastic Processes</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014917" MajorTopicYN="N">Whooping Cough</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement><b>Competing Interests: </b>This study was supported by an unrestricted grant from GlaxoSmithKline, The Netherlands. This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2010</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20976213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2955521</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Tan T, Trindade E, Skowronski D. Epidemiology of Pertussis. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:S10&#x2013;18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15876918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Melker HE, Conyn-van Spaendonck MAE, R&#xfc;mke HC, van Wijngaarden JK, Mooi FR, et al. Pertussis in The Netherlands: an outbreak despite high levels of immunization with whole-cell vaccine. Emerg Infect Dis. 1997;3:175&#x2013;178.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2627603</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9204299</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Melker HE, Schellekens JFP, Neppelenbroek SE, Mooi FR, R&#xfc;mke HC, Conyn-van Spaendonck MAE. Reemergence of pertussis in the highly vaccinated population of the Netherlands: observations on surveillance data. Emerg Infect Dis. 2000;6:348&#x2013;357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2640897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10905967</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neppelenbroek SE, De Melker HE, Schellekens JFP, Conyn-van Spaendonck MAE. The incidence of pertussis in the Netherlands remains high since an outbreak occurred in 1996. Euro Surveill. 1999;4:133&#x2013;134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12631880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schellekens JFP, Wirsing von K&#xf6;nig CH, Gardner P. Pertussis sources of infection and routes of transmission in the vaccination era. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:S19&#x2013;24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15876919</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kowalzik F, Barbosa AP, Fernandes VR, Carvalho PR, Avila-Aguero, et al. Prospective multinational study of pertussis infection in hospitalized infants and their household contacts. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2007;26:238&#x2013;242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17484221</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Orenstein WA. Pertussis in adults: epidemiology, signs, symptoms, and implications for vaccination. Clin Infect Dis. 1999;28(Suppl 2):S147&#x2013;150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10447034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothstein E, Edwards K. Health burden of pertussis in adolescents and adults. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:S44&#x2013;47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15876923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee GM, Lett S, Schauer S, LeBaron C, Murphy TV, et al. Societal costs and morbidity of pertussis in adolscents and adults. CID. 2004;39:1572&#x2013;1580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15578353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Serres G, Shadmani R, Duval B, Boulianne N, D&#xe9;ry P, et al. Morbidity of pertussis in adolescents and adults. J Infect Dis. 2000;182:174&#x2013;179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10882595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Amersfoorth SCM, Schouls LM, van der Heide HGJ, Advani A, Hallander HO, et al. Analysis of Bordetella pertussis populations in European countries with different vaccination policies. JCM. 2005;43:2837&#x2013;2843.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1151907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15956406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutch national immunization program (RVP).   http://www.nvi-vaccin.nl/?id=564. Accessed 2008 May 1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wendelboe AM, Van Rie A, Salmaso S, Englund JA. Duration of immunity against pertussis after natural infection or vaccination. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:S58&#x2013;61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15876927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Versteegh FGA, Schellekens JFP, Nagelkerke AF, Roord JJ. Laboratory-confirmed reinfections with Bordetella pertussis. Acta Paediatr. 2002;91:95&#x2013;97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11885549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fine PE. Herd immunity: history, theory, practice. Epidemiol Rev. 1993;15:265&#x2013;302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8174658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halperin SA. Canadian experience with implementation of an acellular pertussis vaccine booster-dose program in adolescents: implications for the United States. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:S141&#x2013;146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15931142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caro JJ. Pharmacoeconomic analyses using discrete event simulation. Pharmacoeconomics. 2005;23:323&#x2013;332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15853433</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hollingworth W, Spackman DE. Emerging methods in economic modeling of imaging costs and outcomes: a short report on discrete event simulation. Acad Radiol. 2007;14:406&#x2013;410.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17368208</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karnon J. Alternative decision modeling techniques for the evaluation of health care technologies: Markov processes versus discrete event simulation. Health Economics. 2003;12:837&#x2013;848.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14508868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, May RM. Infectious diseases of humans: dynamics and control. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 1991.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kelton WD, Sadowski RP, Sadowski DA. Simulation with ARENA. New York: McGraw-Hill; 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Melker HE, Conyn-van Spaendonck MAE, Schellekens JFP. The pertussis epidemic in 1996: description and evaluation based on surveillance data from 1976 to 1996. 1997. Report no. 128507005, National Institute of Public Health and the Environment, Bilthoven, The Netherlands.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Boven M, de Melker HE, Schellekens JFP, Kretzschmar M. Waning immunity and sub-clinical infection in an epidemic model: implications for pertussis in The Netherlands. Math Biosciences. 2000;164:161&#x2013;182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10748285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrington CP. The measurement and interpretation of age-specific vaccine efficacy. Int J Epidemiol. 1992;21:1014&#x2013;1020.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1468838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramsay MEB, Farrington CP, Miller E. Age-specific efficacy of pertussis vaccine during epidemic and non-epidemic periods. Epidemiol Infect. 1993;111:41&#x2013;48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2271201</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8348931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Council of the Netherlands. Vaccination against Pertussis. Publication # 2004/04E. Den Haag: Health Council of the Netherlands; 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jefferson T, Rudin M, DiPietrantonj Systematic review of the effects of pertussis vaccines in children. Vaccine. 2003;21:2012&#x2013;2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12706690</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang L, Prietsch SOM, Axelsson I, Halperin SA. Acellular vaccines for preventing whooping cough in children. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010;1:CD001478.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21249646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward J, Cherry DJ, Chang SJ, Partridge S, Lee H, et al. Efficacy of an acellular pertussis vaccine among adolescents and adults. N Engl J Med. 2005;353:1555&#x2013;1563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16221778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frampton JE, Keam S. Reduced-antigen, combined diphtheria-tetanus-acellular pertussis vaccine, adsorbed (Boosterix&#xae; US formulation): use as a single-dose booster immunization in adolescents aged 10&#x2013;18 years. Pediatr Drugs. 2006;8:189&#x2013;195.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16774298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casey JR, Pichichero ME. Acellular pertussis vaccine safety and efficacy in children, adolescents and adults. Drugs. 2005;65:1367&#x2013;1389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15977969</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Greeff SC, Schellekens JFP, Mooi FR, de Melker HE. Pertussis in the Netherlands, 2001&#x2013;2002. 2003. RIVM report 128507010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Melker HE, Versteegh FGA, Schellekens JFP, Teunis PFM, Kretzschmar M. The incidence of Bordetella pertussis infections estimated in the population from a combination of serological surveys. Journal of Infection. 2006;53:106&#x2013;113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16352342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Teunis P, Kretzschmar M. Using data on social contacts to estimate age-specific transmission parameters for respiratory-spread infectious agents. Am J Epidemiol. 2006;164:936&#x2013;944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16968863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mylius SD, Hagenaars TJ, Lugn&#xe9;r AK, Wallinga J. Optimal allocation of pandemic influenza vaccine depends on age, risk and timing. Vaccine. 2008;26:3742&#x2013;3749.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18524428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>The World Bank.  Available  http://www.world-bank.org. Accessed 2008 September 01.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Health Care Insurance Board. Dutch Guidelines for Pharmacotherapeutics. Diemen, The Netherlands, 2008.  Available:  http://www.fk.cvz.nl. Accessed 2008 September 01.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prismant: National LMR information [online and further data requested].  Available:  http://www.prismant.nl.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oostenbrink JB, Bouwmans CAM, Koopmanschap MA, Rutten FFH. Guideline for costing research, methods and standardized prices for economic evaluations in health care. Diemen: Health Care Insurance Board; 2004.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tormans G, van Doorslaer E, van Damme P, Clara R, Schmitt HJ. Economic evaluation of pertussis prevention by whole-cell and acellular vaccine in Germany. Eur J Pediatr. 1998;157:395&#x2013;401.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9625337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee LH, Pichichero ME. Costs of illness due to Bordetella pertussis in families. Arch Fam Med. 2000;9:989&#x2013;996.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11115197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond MF, Sculpher MJ, Torrance GW, O'Brien BJ, Stoddart GL. Methods for the economic evaluation of health care programmes. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 3th edition; 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koopmanschap MA, Rutten FFH, van Ineveld BM, van Roijen L. The friction cost method for measuring indirect costs of disease. J Health Econ. 1995;14:171&#x2013;189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10154656</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics Netherlands.  Available:  http://stadline.cbs.nl. Accessed 2008 September 01.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee GM, Salomon JA, LeBaron CW, Lieu TA. Health-state valuations for pertussis: methods for valuing short-term health states. Health and Quality of Life Outcomes. 2005;3:17&#x2013;30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC555848</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15780145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee GM, Murphy TV, Lett S, Cortese MM, Kretsinger K, Schauer S, et al. Cost-effectiveness of pertussis vaccination in adults. Am J Prev Med. 2007;32:186&#x2013;193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17296470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutch guidelines for pharmacoeconomic research. Health Care Insurance Board 2006.  Available:  http://www.ispor.org/PEguidelines/source/PEguidelinesenglish.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riteco JA, De Heij LJM, van Luijn JCF, Wolff I. Guidelines for pharmacoeconomic research. Amstelveen: College voor Zorgverzekeringen; 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caro JJ, Getsios D, El-Hadi W, Payne K, O'Brien JA. Pertussis immunization of adolescents in the United States: an economic evaluation. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2005;24:S75&#x2013;82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15876932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Calugar A, Ortega-S&#xe1;nchez IR, Tiwari T, Oakes L, Jahre JA, et al. Nosocomial pertussis: costs of an outbreak and benefits of vaccinating health care workers. CID. 2006;42:981&#x2013;988.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16511764</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iskedjian M, Einarson TR, O'Brien BJ, de Serres G, Gold R, et al. Economic evaluation of a new acellular vaccine for pertussis in Canada. Pharmacoeconomics. 2001;19:551&#x2013;563.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11465300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scuffham PA, McIntyre PB. Pertussis vaccination strategies for neonates: an exploratory cost-effectiveness analysis. Vaccine. 2004;22:2953&#x2013;2964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15246632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koplan JP, Schoenbaum SC, Weinstein MC, Fraser DW. Pertussis vaccine: an analysis of benefits, risks and costs. N Engl J Med. 1979;301:906&#x2013;911.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinman AR, Koplan JP. Pertussis and pertussis vaccine: reanalysis of benefits, risks and costs. JAMA. 1984;251:3109&#x2013;3113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6427489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinman AR, Koplan JP. Pertussis and pertussis vaccine: further analysis of benefits, risks and costs. Develop Biol Standard. 1985;61:429&#x2013;437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3938968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee GM, Riffelmann M, Wirsing von Konig CH. Cost-effectiveness of adult pertussis vaccination in Germany. Vaccine. 2008;26:3673&#x2013;3679.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18538901</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beutels P, Bonanni P, Tormans G, Canale F, Crovari PC. An economic evaluation of universal pertussis vaccination in Italy. Vaccine. 1999;17:2400&#x2013;2409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10392622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ekwueme DU, Strebel PM, Hadler SC, Meltzer MI, Allen JW, et al. Economic evaluation of use of Diphtheria, tetanus and, acellular pertussis vaccine or diphtheria, tetanus, and whole-cell pertussis vaccine in the United States, 1997. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2000;154:797&#x2013;803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10922276</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iskedjian M, Walker JH, Hemels MEH. Economic evaluation of an extended acellular pertussis vaccine programme for adolescents in Ontario, Canada. Vaccine. 2004;22:4215&#x2013;4227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15474711</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iskedjian M, Walker JH, de Serres G, Einarson TR. Economic evaluation of an extended acellular pertussis vaccine program for adolescents in Qu&#xe9;bec, Canada. Pediatr Drugs. 2005;7:123&#x2013;136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15871632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Purdy KW, Hay JW, Botteman MF, Ward JI. Evaluation of strategies for use of acellular pertussis vaccine in adolescents and adults: a cost-benefit analysis. CID. 2004;39:20&#x2013;28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15206048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevenson M, Beard S, Finn A, Brennan A. Estimating the potential health gain and cost consequences of introducing a pre-school DTPa pertussis booster into the UK child vaccination schedule. Vaccine. 2002;20:1778&#x2013;1786.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11906765</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edmunds JE, Medley GF, Nokes DJ. Evaluating the cost-effectiveness of vaccination programmes: a dynamic perspective. Statist Med. 1999;18:3263&#x2013;3283.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10602150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Boven M, de Melker HE, Schellekens JFP, Kretzschmar M. A model based evaluation of the 1996&#x2013;7 pertussis epidemic in the Netherlands. Epidemiol Infect. 2001;127:73&#x2013;85.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2869732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11561978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hethcote HW. An age-structured model for pertussis transmission. Math Biosciences. 1997;145:89&#x2013;136.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9309930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hethcote HW. Simulations of pertussis epidemiology in the United States: effects of adult booster vaccinations. Math Biosciences. 1999;158:47&#x2013;73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10209936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hethcote HW, Horby P, McIntyre P. Using computer simulations to compare pertussis vaccination strategies in Australia. Vaccine. 2004;22:2181&#x2013;2191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15149775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Rie A, Hethcote HW. Adolescent and adult pertussis vaccination: computer simulations of five new strategies. Vaccine. 2004;22:3154&#x2013;3165.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15297068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coudeville L, van Rie A, Andre P. Adult pertussis vaccination strategies and their impact on pertussis in the United States: evaluation of routine and targeted (cocoon) strategies. Epidemiol Infect. 2008;136:604&#x2013;620.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2870855</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17612417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edmunds WJ, Brisson M, Melegaro A, Gay NJ. The potential cost-effectiveness of acellular pertussis booster vaccination in England and Wales. Vaccine. 2002;20:1316&#x2013;1330.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11818150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenfell BT, Anderson RM. The estimation of age-related rates of infection from case notifications and serological data. J Hygiene. 1985;95:419&#x2013;436.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2129533</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4067297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brisson M, Edmunds WJ. Economic evaluation of vaccination programmes: the impact of herd-immunity. Med Decis Making. 2003;23:76&#x2013;82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12583457</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee GM, LeBaron C, Murphy TV, Lett S, Schauer S, et al. Pertussis in adolescents and adults: should we vaccinate? Pediatrics. 2005;115:1675&#x2013;1684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15930232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Amersfoorth SCM, Schouls LM, van der Heide HGJ, Advani A, Hallander HO, et al. Analysis of Bordetella pertussis populations in European countries with different vaccination schemes. J Clin Microbiol. 2005;43:2 837&#x2013;2843.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1151907</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15956406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crowcroft NS, Andrews N, Rooney C, Brisson M, Miller E. Deaths from pertussis are underestimated in England. Arch Dis Child. 2002;86:336&#x2013;338.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1751114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11970924</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaikh R, Guris D, Strebel PM, Wharton M. Underreporting of pertussis deaths in the United States: need for improved surveillance. Pediatrics. 1998;101:323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9457164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pichichero ME, Blatter MM, Kennedy WA, Hedrick J, Descamps D, et al. Acellular pertussis vaccine booster combined with diphtheria and tetanus toxoids for adolescents. Pediatrics. 2006;117:1084&#x2013;1093.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16585302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bos JM, Postma MJ. Using pharmacoeconomics for policy making: is rational decision making enhanced by applying thresholds for cost-effectiveness? Exp Rev Pharmacoeconom Res. 2004;4:247&#x2013;50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19807306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>