<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">30541438</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2019</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>10</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>22</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2105</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>19</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2018</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>12</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC bioinformatics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Bioinformatics</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A nearest-neighbors network model for sequence data reveals new insight into genotype distribution of a pathogen.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>475</StartPage><MedlinePgn>475</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">475</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12859-018-2453-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Sequence similarity networks are useful for classifying and characterizing biologically important proteins. Threshold-based approaches to similarity network construction using exact distance measures are prohibitively slow to compute and rely on the difficult task of selecting an appropriate threshold, while similarity networks based on approximate distance calculations compromise useful structural information.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We present an alternative network representation for a set of sequence data that overcomes these drawbacks. In our model, called the Directed Weighted All Nearest Neighbors (DiWANN) network, each sequence is represented by a node and is connected via a directed edge to only the closest sequence, or sequences in the case of ties, in the dataset. Our contributions span several aspects. Specifically, we: (i) Apply an all nearest neighbors network model to protein sequence data from three different applications and examine the structural properties of the networks; (ii) Compare the model against threshold-based networks to validate their semantic equivalence, and demonstrate the relative advantages the model offers; (iii) Demonstrate the model's resilience to missing sequences; and (iv) Develop an efficient algorithm for constructing a DiWANN network from a set of sequences. We find that the DiWANN network representation attains similar semantic properties to threshold-based graphs, while avoiding weaknesses of both high and low threshold graphs. Additionally, we find that approximate distance networks, using BLAST bitscores in place of exact edit distances, can cause significant loss of structural information. We show that the proposed DiWANN network construction algorithm provides a fourfold speedup over a standard threshold based approach to network construction. We also identify a relationship between the centrality of a sequence in a similarity network of an Anaplasma marginale short sequence repeat dataset and how broadly that sequence is dispersed geographically.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">We demonstrate that using approximate distance measures to rapidly construct similarity networks may lead to significant deficiencies in the structure of that network in terms centrality and clustering analyses. We present a new network representation that maintains the structural semantics of threshold-based networks while increasing connectedness, and an algorithm for constructing the network using exact distance measures in a fraction of the time it would take to build a threshold-based equivalent.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Catanese</LastName><ForeName>Helen N</ForeName><Initials>HN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Washington State University, Pullman, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brayton</LastName><ForeName>Kelly A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Washington State University, Pullman, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Veterinary Microbiology and Pathology, Washington State University, Pullman, WA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gebremedhin</LastName><ForeName>Assefaw H</ForeName><Initials>AH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Washington State University, Pullman, WA, USA. assefaw.gebremedhin@wsu.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>IIS-1553528</GrantID><Agency>Directorate for Computer and Information Science and Engineering</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2018</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Bioinformatics</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100965194</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2105</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D011506">Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000595" MajorTopicYN="N">Amino Acid Sequence</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="Y">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016000" MajorTopicYN="N">Cluster Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="N">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011506" MajorTopicYN="N">Proteins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000737" MajorTopicYN="Y">chemistry</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Anaplasma marginale Msp1a</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Centrality</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Clustering</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">GroEL</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Network analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sequence similarity network</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>ETHICS APPROVAL AND CONSENT TO PARTICIPATE: Not applicable. CONSENT FOR PUBLICATION: Not applicable. COMPETING INTERESTS: The authors declare that they have no competing interests. PUBLISHER&#x2019;S NOTE: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2018</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2018</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2018</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2018</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2019</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2018</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>12</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30541438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6291930</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12859-018-2453-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12859-018-2453-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Mishra P, Pandey PN. A graph-based clustering method applied to protein sequences. Bioinformation. 2011;6(10):372&#x2013;4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3163914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21927545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkinson HJ, Morris JH, Ferrin TE, Babbitt PC. Using sequence similarity networks for visualization of relationships across diverse protein superfamilies. PLoS ONE. 2009; 4(2).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2631154</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19190775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roberts A, McMillan L, Wang W, Parker J, Rusyn I, Threadgill D. Inferring missing genotypes in large SNP panels using fast nearest-neighbor searches over sliding windows. Bioinformatics. 2007;23(13):401&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17646323</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weston J, Elisseeff A, Zhou D, Leslie CS, Noble WS. Protein ranking: from local to global structure in the protein similarity network. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2004;101(17):6559&#x2013;63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC404084</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15087500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Las Rivas J, Fontanillo C. Protein-protein interactions essentials: Key concepts to building and analyzing interactome networks. PLoS Comput Biol. 2010;6(6):1&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2891586</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20589078</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freschi V. Protein function prediction from interaction networks using a random walk ranking algorithm. In: Proceedings of the 7th IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Bioengineering. IEEE: 2007. p. 42&#x2013;48.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Knabe JF, Nehaniv CL, Schilstra MJ. Proceedings of the 7th German Workshop on Artificial Life. Berlin: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft; 2006. Evolutionary robustness of differentiation in genetic regulatory networks.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stuart JM, Segal E, Koller D, Kim SK. A Gene-Coexpression Network for Global Discovery of Conserved Genetic Modules. Science. 2003;302(5643):249&#x2013;55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12934013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huttenhower C, Flamholz AI, Landis JN, Sahi S, Myers CL, Olszewski KL, Hibbs MA, Siemers NO, Troyanskaya OG, Coller HA. Nearest Neighbor Networks: Clustering expression data based on gene neighborhoods. BMC Bioinform. 2007;8:1&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1941745</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17626636</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison JL, Breitling R, Higham DJ, Gilbert DR. GeneRank: Using search engine technology for the analysis of microarray experiments. BMC Bioinform. 2005;6:1&#x2013;14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1261158</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16176585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hamming RW. Error detecting and error correcting codes. Bell Syst Tech J. 1950;29:147&#x2013;60.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levenshtein VI. Binary codes capable of correcting spurious insertions and deletions of ones. Sov Phys Dokl. 1966;10:707.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Needleman SB, Wunsch CD. A General Method Applicable to the Search for Similarities in the Amino Acid Sequence of Two Proteins. J Mol Bio. 1970;48(3):443&#x2013;53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5420325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Waterman MS, Smith TF, Beyer WA. Some biological sequence metrics. Adv Math. 1976;20(3):367&#x2013;87.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson WR. Rapid and sensitive sequence comparison with FASTP and FASTA. Methods Enzymol. 1990;183(C):63&#x2013;98.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2156132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Camacho C, Coulouris G, Avagyan V, Ma N, Papadopoulos J, Bealer K, Madden TL. BLAST+: architecture and applications. BMC Bioinform. 2009;10:421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2803857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20003500</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu C, Kalyanaraman A, Cannon WR. PGraph: Efficient Parallel Construction of Large-Scale Protein Sequence Homology Graphs. IEEE Trans Parallel Distrib Syst. 2012;23(10):1923&#x2013;33.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shpaer EG, Robinson M, Yee D, Candlin JD, Mines R, Hunkapiller T. Sensitivity and selectivity in protein similarity searches: A comparison of Smith-Waterman in hardware to BLAST and FASTA. Genomics. 1996;38(2):179&#x2013;91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8954800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson WR. Searching protein sequence libraries: Comparison of the sensitivity and selectivity of the Smith-Waterman and FASTA algorithms. Genomics. 1991;11(3):635&#x2013;50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1774068</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shieh J, Keogh E. 14th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining. New York: ACM; 2008. iSAX: Indexing and Mining Terabyte Sized Time Series.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arasu A, Ganti V, Kaushik R. Proceedings of the 32nd International Conference on Very Large Data Bases. Seoul: VLDB Endowment; 2006. Efficient Exact Set-Similarity Joins.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Apeltsin L, Morris JH, Babbitt PC, Ferrin TE. Improving the quality of protein similarity network clustering algorithms using the network edge weight distribution. Bioinformatics. 2011;27(3):326&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3031030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21118823</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eppstein D, Paterson MS, Yao FF. On nearest neighbor graphs. Discret Comput Geom. 1997;17(3):263&#x2013;82.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bentley JL. Multidimensional Divide-and-Conquer. Commun ACM. 1980;23(4):214&#x2013;29.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarkson KL. Fast algorithms for the all nearest neighbors problem. In: 24th Annual Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science. IEEE: 1983. p. 226&#x2013;232.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omohundro SM. Five balltree construction algorithms. Int Comput Sci Inst Tech Rep. 1989;51(1):1&#x2013;22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sankaranarayanan J, Samet H, Varshney A. A fast all nearest neighbor algorithm for applications involving large point-clouds. Comput Graph. 2007;31(2):157&#x2013;74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dashti A, Komarov I, D&#x2019;Souza RM. Efficient Computation of k-Nearest Neighbour Graphs for Large High-Dimensional Data Sets on GPU Clusters. PLoS ONE. 2013;8(9):e74113.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3781071</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24086314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anastasiu DC, Karypis G. CIKM 2015: Proceedings of the 24th ACM International on Conference on Information and Knowledge Management. New York: ACM; 2015. L2Knng : Fast Exact K-Nearest Neighbor Graph Construction with L2-Norm Pruning.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arya S, Mount DM, Netanyahu NS, Silverman R, Wu AY. An optimal algorithm for approximate nearest neighbor searching in fixed dimensions. Proceedings of the 5th ACM-SIAM Sympos. Discret Algoritm. 1998;45(6):891&#x2013;923.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jones PW, Osipov A, Rokhlin V. A randomized approximate nearest neighbors algorithm. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2011;108(38):15679&#x2013;86.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3179075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21885738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang YM, Huang K, Geng G, Liu CL. Joint European Conference on Machine Learning and Knowledge Discovery in Databases. Berlin: Springer; 2013. Fast kNN graph construction with locality sensitive hashing.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park Y, Park S, Lee S-g, Jung W. Database Systems for Advanced Applications. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2014. Greedy filtering: A scalable algorithm for k-nearest neighbor graph construction.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paredes R, Navarro G. Proceedings of the 5th international conference on Experimental Algorithms. Berlin: Springer-Verlag; 2006. Practical Construction of k Nearest Neighbor Graphs in Metric Spaces.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong W, Moses C, Li K. Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on World Wide Web. New York: ACM; 2011. Efficient k-nearest neighbor graph construction for generic similarity measures.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaidya PM. An O(n log n) algorithm for the all-nearest-neighbors Problem. Discret Comput Geom. 1989;4:101&#x2013;15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yianilos PN. Proceedings of the fourth annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete algorithms. Philadelphia: SIAM; 1993. Data structures and algorithms for nearest neighbor search in general metric spaces.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brin S. Proceedings of the 21st VLDB Conference. San Francisco: Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc.; 1995. Near Neighbor Search in Large Metric Spaces.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarkson KL. Nearest Neighbor Queries in Metric Spaces. Discret Comput Geom. 1999;93:63&#x2013;93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catanese HN, Brayton KA, Gebremedhin AH. RepeatAnalyzer: A Tool for Analysing and Managing Short-Sequence Repeat Data. BMC Genom. 2016;17(1):422.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4891823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27260942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Welsh WJ. Heat shock proteins functioning as molecular chaperones: their roles in normal and stressed cells. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 1993;29(339):327&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8098537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown SD, Gerlt JA, Seffernick JL, Babbitt P. A gold standard set of mechanistically diverse enzyme superfamilies. Genome Biol. 2006;7(1):1&#x2013;15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1431709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16507141</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muja M, Lowe DG. Scalable Nearest Neighbour Algorithms for High Dimensional Data. IEEE Trans Pattern Anal Mach Intell. 2014;36(11):2227&#x2013;40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26353063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fruchterman TMJ, Reingold EM. Graph drawing by force-directed placement. Softw Pract Experience. 1991;21(11):1129&#x2013;64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cs&#xe1;rdi G, Nepusz T. The igraph software package for complex network research. InterJournal. 2006;Complex Sy:1695.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gleich DF. PageRank beyond the Web. SIAM Rev. 2015;57(3):321&#x2013;63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blondel VD, Guillaume J-L, Lambiotte R, Lefebvre E. Fast unfolding of communities in large networks. J Stat Mech Theory Exp. 2008;10:P10008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabezas-Cruz A, Passos LMF, Lis K, Kenneil R, Vald&#xe9;s JJ, Ferrolho J, Tonk M, Pohl AE, Grubhoffer L, Zweygarth E, Shkap V, Ribeiro MFB, Estrada-Pe&#xf1;a A, Kocan KM, de la Fuente J. Functional and Immunological Relevance of Anaplasma marginale Major Surface Protein 1a Sequence and Structural Analysis. PLoS ONE. 2013;8(6):65243.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3679145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23776456</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crooks G, Hon G, Chandonia J-M, Brenner SE. WebLogo: A Sequence Logo Generator. Genome Res. 2004;14:1188&#x2013;90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC419797</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15173120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>