<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">32775757</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2405-8440</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>6</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2020</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Heliyon</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Heliyon</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Deep learning for automated classification of tuberculosis-related chest X-Ray: dataset distribution shift limits diagnostic performance generalizability.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e04614</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e04614</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e04614</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e04614</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Machine learning has been an emerging tool for various aspects of infectious diseases including tuberculosis surveillance and detection. However, the World Health Organization (WHO) provided no recommendations on using computer-aided tuberculosis detection software because of a small number of studies, methodological limitations, and limited generalizability of the findings.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">To quantify the generalizability of the machine-learning model, we developed a Deep Convolutional Neural Network (DCNN) model using a Tuberculosis (TB)-specific chest x-ray (CXR) dataset of one population (National Library of Medicine Shenzhen No.3 Hospital) and tested it with non-TB-specific CXR dataset of another population (National Institute of Health Clinical Centers).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In the training and intramural test sets using the Shenzhen hospital database, the DCCN model exhibited an AUC of 0.9845 and 0.8502 for detecting TB, respectively. However, the AUC of the supervised DCNN model in the ChestX-ray8 dataset was dramatically dropped to 0.7054. Using the cut points at 0.90, which suggested 72% sensitivity and 82% specificity in the Shenzhen dataset, the final DCNN model estimated that 36.51% of abnormal radiographs in the ChestX-ray8 dataset were related to TB.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">A supervised deep learning model developed by using the training dataset from one population may not have the same diagnostic performance in another population. Conclusion: Technical specification of CXR images, disease severity distribution, dataset distribution shift, and overdiagnosis should be examined before implementation in other settings.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2020 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sathitratanacheewin</LastName><ForeName>Seelwan</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thai Health AI Foundation, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sunanta</LastName><ForeName>Panasun</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thai Health AI Foundation, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>True Digital Group Co., Ltd., Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pongpirul</LastName><ForeName>Krit</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Thai Health AI Foundation, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Preventive and Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of International Health and Department of Health, Behavior, and Society, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Bumrungrad International Hospital, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2020</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Heliyon</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101672560</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2405-8440</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Applied computing in medical science</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Chest X-Ray</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Computer science</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Deep learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tuberculosis</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2019</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2020</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2020</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32775757</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7396903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e04614</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2405-8440(20)31458-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . World Health Organization; Geneva: 2016. Chest Radiography in Tuberculosis Detection: Summary of Current WHO Recommendations and Guidance on Programmatic Approaches.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiens J., Shenoy E.S. Machine learning for healthcare: on the verge of a major shift in healthcare epidemiology. Clin. Infect. Dis. 2018;66(1):149&#x2013;153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5850539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29020316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang X. 2017. ChestX-ray8: Hospital-Scale Chest X-ray Database and Benchmarks on Weakly-Supervised Classification and Localization of Common Thorax Diseases. arXiv:1705.02315.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rajpurkar P. 2017. CheXNet: Radiologist-Level Pneumonia Detection on Chest X-Rays with Deep Learning. arXiv:1711.05225.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao L. 2017. Learning to Diagnose from Scratch by Exploiting Dependencies Among Labels. arXiv:1710.10501.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maduskar P. Performance evaluation of automatic chest radiograph reading for detection of tuberculosis (TB): a comparative study with a clinical officers and certified readers on TB suspects in sub-Saharan Africa. Insight Imag. 2013;4(Suppl 1)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muyoyeta M. The sensitivity and specificity of using a computer aided diagnosis program for automatically scoring chest X-rays of presumptive TB patients compared with Xpert MTB/RIF in Lusaka Zambia. PloS One. 2014;9(4)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3976315</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24705629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steiner A. Screening for pulmonary tuberculosis in a Tanzanian prison and computer-aided interpretation of chest X-rays. Public Health Action. 2015;5(4):249&#x2013;254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4682617</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26767179</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou P., Han J., Cheng G., Zhang B. Learning compact and discriminative stacked autoencoder for hyperspectral image classification. IEEE Trans. Geosci. Rem. Sens. July 2019;57(7):4823&#x2013;4833.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheng G., Yang C., Yao X., Guo L., Han J. When deep learning meets metric learning: remote sensing image scene classification via learning discriminative CNNs. IEEE Trans. Geosci. Rem. Sens. May 2018;56(5):2811&#x2013;2821.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>