<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">25505499</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">1932-6157</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>8</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2014</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The annals of applied statistics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Ann Appl Stat</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>EFFECT OF BREASTFEEDING ON GASTROINTESTINAL INFECTION IN INFANTS: A TARGETED MAXIMUM LIKELIHOOD APPROACH FOR CLUSTERED LONGITUDINAL DATA.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>703</StartPage><EndPage>725</EndPage><MedlinePgn>703-725</MedlinePgn></Pagination><Abstract><AbstractText>The PROmotion of Breastfeeding Intervention Trial (PROBIT) cluster-randomized a program encouraging breastfeeding to new mothers in hospital centers. The original studies indicated that this intervention successfully increased duration of breastfeeding and lowered rates of gastrointestinal tract infections in newborns. Additional scientific and popular interest lies in determining the causal effect of longer breastfeeding on gastrointestinal infection. In this study, we estimate the expected infection count under various lengths of breastfeeding in order to estimate the effect of breastfeeding duration on infection. Due to the presence of baseline and time-dependent confounding, specialized "causal" estimation methods are required. We demonstrate the double-robust method of Targeted Maximum Likelihood Estimation (TMLE) in the context of this application and review some related methods and the adjustments required to account for clustering. We compare TMLE (implemented both parametrically and using a data-adaptive algorithm) to other causal methods for this example. In addition, we conduct a simulation study to determine (1) the effectiveness of controlling for clustering indicators when cluster-specific confounders are unmeasured and (2) the importance of using data-adaptive TMLE.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schnitzer</LastName><ForeName>Mireille E</ForeName><Initials>ME</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Montr&#xe9;al.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>van der Laan</LastName><ForeName>Mark J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of California, Berkeley.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moodie</LastName><ForeName>Erica E M</ForeName><Initials>EE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>McGill University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Platt</LastName><ForeName>Robert W</ForeName><Initials>RW</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>McGill University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI074345</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Ann Appl Stat</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101479511</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6157</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Causal inference</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">G-computation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inverse probability weighting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">marginal effects</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">missing data</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">pediatrics</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2014</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2014</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2014</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>17</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2014</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25505499</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS611725</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4259272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/14-aoas727</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bang H, Robins JM. Doubly robust estimation in missing data and causal inference models. Biometrics. 2005;61:962&#x2013;972.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16401269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cameron AC, Gelbach JB, Miller DL. Boostrap-based improvements for inference with clustered errors. The Review of Economics and Statistics. 2008;90:414&#x2013;427.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finster M, Wood M. The apgar score has survived the test of time. Anesthesiology. 2005;102:855&#x2013;857.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15791116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gruber S, van der Laan MJ. A targeted maximum likelihood estimator of a causal effect on a bounded continuous outcome. Int J Biostat. 2010;6:Art 26, 16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3126669</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21731529</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hastie T. gam: Generalized additive models. R package version 1.04.1 2011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hern&#xe1;n MA, Brumback B, Robins JM. Marginal structural models to estimate the causal effect of zidovudine on the survival of HIV-positive men. Epidemiology. 2000;11:561&#x2013;570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10955409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kang JDY, Schafer JL. Demystifying double robustness: A comparison of alternative strategies for estimating a population mean from incomplete data. Statist Sci. 2007;22:523&#x2013;539.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2397555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18516239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer MS, Chalmers B, Hodnett ED, Sevkovskaya Z, Dzikovich I, Shapiro S, Collet JP, Vanilovich I, Mezen I, Ducruet T, Shishko G, Zubovich V, Mknuik D, Gluchanina E, Dombrovskiy V, Ustinovitch A, Kot T, Bogdanovich N, Ovchinikova L, Helsing E. Promotion of breast-feeding intervention trial (PROBIT) The Journal of the American Medical Association. 2001;285:413&#x2013;420.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11242425</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer MS, Guo T, Platt RW, Shapiro S, Collet JP, Chalmers B, Hodnett E, Sevkovskaya Z, Dzikovich I, Vanilovich I. Breastfeeding and infant growth: Biology or bias? Pediatrics. 2002;110:343&#x2013;347.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12165588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer MS, Moodie EEM, Dahhou M, Platt RW. Breastfeeding and infant size: Evidence of reverse causality. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2011;173:978&#x2013;983.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3390166</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21430194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milborrow S. In: Earth: Multivariate adaptive regression spline models. Hastie Trevor, Tibshirani Rob., editors. 2011. Derived from mda:mars.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peters A, Hothorn T. ipred: Improved predictors. R package version 0.8&#x2013;11 2011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petersen ML, Porter KE, Gruber S, Wang Y, van der Laan MJ. Diagnosing and responding to violations in the positivity assumption. Stat Methods Med Res. 2012;21:31&#x2013;54.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4107929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21030422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petersen M, Schwab J, Gruber S, Blaser N, Schomaker M, van der Laan M. Targeted maximum likelihood estimation for dynamic and static longitudinal marginal structural working models. Journal of Causal Inference. 2014 To appear.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4405134</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25909047</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polley EC, van der Laan MJ. Package &#x201c;SuperLearner&#x201d;. 2.0&#x2013;4 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Development Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. Vienna, Austria: 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins J. A new approach to causal inference in mortality studies with a sustained exposure period&#x2014;application to control of the healthy worker survivor effect. Math Modelling. 1986;7:1393&#x2013;1512.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM, Hern&#xe1;n MA, Brumback B. Marginal structural models and causal inference in epidemiology. Epidemiology. 2000;11:550&#x2013;560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10955408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM, Rotnitzky A. Recovery of information and adjustment for dependent censoring using surrogate markers. In: Jewell N, Dietz K, Farewell V, editors. AIDS Epidemiology&#x2014;Methodological Issues. Birkh&#xe4;user; Boston, MA: 1992. pp. 297&#x2013;331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenblum M, van der Laan MJ. Working paper. Univ. California, Berkeley, Division of Biostatistics; 2010a. Simple examples of estimating causal effects using targeted maximum likelihood estimation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenblum M, van der Laan MJ. Targeted maximum likelihood estimation of the parameter of a marginal structural model. Int J Biostat. 2010b;6:Art 19, 23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3126671</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21731532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Estimating causal effects of treatments in randomized and nonrandomized studies. Journal of Educational Psychology. 1974;66:688&#x2013;701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Bayesian inference for causal effects: The role of randomization. Ann Statist. 1978;6:34&#x2013;58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schnitzer ME, Moodie EEM, Platt RW. Targeted maximum likelihood estimation for marginal time-dependent treatment effects under density misspecification. Biostatistics. 2013;14:1&#x2013;14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22797173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schnitzer ME, van der Laan MJ, Moodie EEM, Platt RW. Supplement to &#x201c;Effect of breastfeeding on gastrointestinal infection in infants: A targeted maximum likelihood approach for clustered longitudinal data&#x201d;. 2014 doi: 10.1214/14-AOAS727SUPP.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1214/14-AOAS727SUPP</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4259272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25505499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snowden JM, Rose S, Mortimer KM. Implementation of G-computation on a simulated data set: Demonstration of a causal inference technique. Am J Epidemiol. 2011;173:731&#x2013;738.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3105284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21415029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stitelman OM, De Gruttola V, van der Laan MJ. A general implementation of TMLE for longitudinal data applied to causal inference in survival analysis. Int J Biostat. 2012;8:Art. 26. front matter+37.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22992289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsiatis AA. Semiparametric Theory and Missing Data. Springer; New York: 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Laan MJ. Targeted maximum likelihood based causal inference. Int J Biostat. 2010;6:Art 2, 44.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3126670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21969992</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Laan MJ, Gruber S. Targeted minimum loss based estimation of causal effects of multiple time point interventions. Int J Biostat. 2012;8:Art 9, 41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22611591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Laan MJ, Robins JM. Unified Methods for Censored Longitudinal Data and Causality. Springer; New York: 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Laan MJ, Rubin D. Targeted maximum likelihood learning. Int J Biostat. 2006;2:Art 11, 40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venables WN, Ripley BD. Modern Applied Statistics with S. 4. Springer; New York: 2002.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>