<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20195446</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2010</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>16</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1660-4601</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Jan</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>International journal of environmental research and public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Int J Environ Res Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Correcting the actual reproduction number: a simple method to estimate R(0) from early epidemic growth data.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>291</StartPage><EndPage>302</EndPage><MedlinePgn>291-302</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.3390/ijerph7010291</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The basic reproduction number, R(0), a summary measure of the transmission potential of an infectious disease, is estimated from early epidemic growth rate, but a likelihood-based method for the estimation has yet to be developed. The present study corrects the concept of the actual reproduction number, offering a simple framework for estimating R(0) without assuming exponential growth of cases. The proposed method is applied to the HIV epidemic in European countries, yielding R(0) values ranging from 3.60 to 3.74, consistent with those based on the Euler-Lotka equation. The method also permits calculating the expected value of R(0) using a spreadsheet.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nishiura</LastName><ForeName>Hiroshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PRESTO, Japan Science and Technology Agency, Saitama, 332-0012, Japan. h.nishiura@uu.nl</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>21</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Switzerland</Country><MedlineTA>Int J Environ Res Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101238455</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1660-4601</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="Y">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005060" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Europe</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="Y">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AIDS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">HIV</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">basic reproduction number</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">estimation techniques</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">statistical model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2009</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20195446</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2819789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph7010291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ijerph7010291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Diekmann O, Heesterbeek JA, Metz JA. On the definition and the computation of the basic reproduction ratio R0 in models for infectious diseases in heterogeneous populations. J. Math. Biol. 1990;28:365&#x2013;381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2117040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dietz K. The estimation of the basic reproduction number for infectious diseases. Stat. Methods. Med. Res. 1993;2:23&#x2013;41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8261248</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker NG. Analysis of Infectious Disease Data. Chapman &amp; Hall; Boca Raton, FL, USA: 1989.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith CE. Factors in the transmission of virus infections from animal to man. Sci Basis Med Ann Rev. 1964:125&#x2013;150.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5321089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kendall DG. Proceedings of the 3rd Berkeley Symposium on Mathematical Statistics and Probability. University of California Press; Berkeley, CA, USA: 1956. Deterministic and stochastic epidemics in closed populations; pp. 149&#x2013;165.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma J, Earn DJ. Generality of the final size formula for an epidemic of a newly invading infectious disease. Bull. Math. Biol. 2006;68:679&#x2013;702.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7088645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16794950</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heffernan JM, Wahl LM. Improving estimates of the basic reproductive ratio: using both the mean and the dispersal of transition times. Theor. Pop. Biol. 2006;70:135&#x2013;145.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7126117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16712889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massad E, Coutinho FA, Burattini MN, Amaku M. Estimation of R0 from the initial phase of an outbreak of a vector-borne infection. Trop. Med. Int. Health. 2009;15:120&#x2013;126.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19891761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Lipsitch M. How generation intervals shape the relationship between growth rates and reproductive numbers. Proc. Roy. Soc. Lon. Ser. B. 2007;274:599&#x2013;604.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1766383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17476782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Svensson A. A note on generation times in epidemic models. Math. Biosci. 2007;208:300&#x2013;311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17174352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diekmann O, Heesterbeek JAP. Mathematical Epidemiology of Infectious Diseases: Model Building, Analysis and Interpretation. John Wiley &amp; Son; Chichester, UK: 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garske T, Clarke P, Ghani AC. The transmissibility of highly pathogenic avian influenza in commercial poultry in industrialised countries. PLoS ONE. 2007;2:e349.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1831494</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17406673</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White LF, Pagano M. A likelihood-based method for real-time estimation of the serial interval and reproductive number of an epidemic. Stat. Med. 2008;27:2999&#x2013;3016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3951165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18058829</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amundsen EJ, Stigum H, Rottingen JA, Aalen OO. Definition and estimation of an actual reproduction number describing past infectious disease transmission: application to HIV epidemics among homosexual men in Denmark, Norway and Sweden. Epidemiol. Infect. 2004;132:1139&#x2013;1149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2870207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15635973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White PJ, Ward H, Garnett GP. Is HIV out of control in the UK? An example of analysing patterns of HIV spreading using incidence-to-prevalence ratios. AIDS. 2006;20:1898&#x2013;1901.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16954735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowell G, Nishiura H. Quantifying the transmission potential of pandemic influenza. Phys. Life. Rev. 2008;5:50&#x2013;77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser C. Estimating individual and household reproduction numbers in an emerging epidemic. PLoS ONE. 2007;2:e758.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1950082</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17712406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Chowell G. The effective reproduction number as a prelude to statistical estimation of time-dependent epidemic trends. In: Chowell G, Hyman JM, Bettencourt LMA, Castillo-Chavez C, editors. Mathematical and Statistical Estimation Approaches in Epidemiology. Springer; Dordrecht, Germany: 2009. pp. 103&#x2013;121.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiboski SC, Jewell NP. Statistical analysis of the time dependence of HIV infectivity based on partner study data. J. Amer. Statist. Assn. 1991;87:360&#x2013;372.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hollingsworth TD, Anderson RM, Fraser C. HIV-1 transmission, by stage of infection. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 2008;198:687&#x2013;693.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18662132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wawer MJ, Gray RH, Sewankambo NK, Serwadda D, Li X, Laeyendecker O, Kiwanuka N, Kigozi G, Kiddugavu M, Lutalo T, Nalugoda F, Wabwire-Mangen F, Meehan MP, Quinn TC. Rates of HIV-1 transmission per coital act, by stage of HIV-1 infection, in Rakai, Uganda. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 2005;191:1403&#x2013;1409.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15809897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abu-Raddad LJ, Longini IM. No HIV stage is dominant in driving the HIV epidemic in sub-Saharan Africa. AIDS. 2008;22:1055&#x2013;1061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18520349</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Artzrouni M. Back-calculation and projection of the HIV/AIDS epidemic among homosexual/bisexual men in three European countries: Evaluation of past projections and updates allowing for treatment effects. Eur. J. Epidemiol. 2004;19:171&#x2013;179.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15074573</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brookmeyer R, Gail MH. AIDS Epidemiology: A Quantitative Approach (Monographs in Epidemiology and Biostatistics) Oxford University Press; New York, NY, USA: 1994.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jewell NP, Dietz K, Farewell VT. AIDS Epidemiology: Methodological Issues. Birkh&#xe4;user; Berlin, Germany: 1992.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H. Lessons from previous predictions of HIV/AIDS in the United States and Japan: epidemiologic models and policy formulation. Epidemiol. Perspect. Innov. 2007;4:3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1906780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17567907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailey NTJ. The Elements of Stochastic Processes with Applications to the Natural Sciences. Wiley; New York, NY, USA: 1964.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Castillo-Chavez C, Safan M, Chowell G. Transmission potential of the new influenza A(H1N1) virus and its age-specificity in Japan. Euro. Surveill. 2009;14:19227.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19497256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Teunis P. Different epidemic curves for severe acute respiratory syndrome reveal similar impacts of control measures. Amer. J. Epidemiol. 2004;160:509&#x2013;516.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7110200</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15353409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haydon DT, Chase-Topping M, Shaw DJ, Matthews L, Friar JK, Wilesmith J, Woolhouse ME. The construction and analysis of epidemic trees with reference to the 2001 UK foot-and-mouth outbreak. Proc. Roy. Soc. Lon. Ser. B. 2003;270:121&#x2013;127.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1691228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12590749</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Schwehm M, Kakehashi M, Eichner M. Transmission potential of primary pneumonic plague: time inhomogeneous evaluation based on historical documents of the transmission network. J. Epidemiol. Community Health. 2006;60:640&#x2013;645.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2566243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16790838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacquez JA, Simon CP, Koopman JS. The reproduction number in deterministic models of contagious diseases. Comments Theor. Biol. 1991;2:159&#x2013;209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grassly NC, Fraser C. Mathematical models of infectious disease transmission. Nat. Rev. Microbiol. 2008;6:477&#x2013;487.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7097581</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18533288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Chowell G, Heesterbeek H, Wallinga J. The ideal reporting interval for an epidemic to objectively interpret the epidemiological time course. J. R. Soc. Interface. 2010;7:297&#x2013;307.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2842610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19570792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Chowell G, Safan M, Castillo-Chavez C. Pros and cons of estimating the reproduction number from early epidemic growth rate of influenza A (H1N1) 2009. Theor. Biol. Med. Model. 2010;7:1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2821365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20056004</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hethcote HW, Yorke JA. Gonorrhea Transmission Dynamics and Control (Lecture Notes in Biomathematics, 56) Springer-Verlag; Berlin, Germany: 1980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muller H, Bauch C.When do sexual partnerships need to be accounted for in transmission models of human papilloma virus Int J Environ Res Public Health 2010. submitted</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2872280</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20616995</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>