<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">23650442</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0162-1459</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>107</Volume><Issue>500</Issue><PubDate><Year>2012</Year><Month>Dec</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of the American Statistical Association</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Am Stat Assoc</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Measurement Error Case Series Models with Application to Infection-Cardiovascular Risk in OlderPatients on Dialysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1310</StartPage><EndPage>1323</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1310-1323</MedlinePgn></Pagination><Abstract><AbstractText>Infection and cardiovascular disease are leading causes of hospitalization and death in older patients on dialysis. Our recent work found an increase in the relative incidence of cardiovascular outcomes during the ~ 30 days after infection-related hospitalizations using the case series model, which adjusts for measured and unmeasured baseline confounders. However, a major challenge in modeling/assessing the infection-cardiovascular risk hypothesis is that the exact time of infection, or more generally "exposure," onsets cannot be ascertained based on hospitalization data. Only imprecise markers of the timing of infection onsets are available. Although there is a large literature on measurement error in the predictors in regression modeling, to date there is no work on measurement error on the timing of a time-varying exposure to our knowledge. Thus, we propose a new method, the measurement error case series (MECS) models, to account for measurement error in time-varying exposure onsets. We characterized the general nature of bias resulting from estimation that ignores measurement error and proposed a bias-corrected estimation for the MECS models. We examined in detail the accuracy of the proposed method to estimate the relative incidence. Hospitalization data from United States Renal Data System, which captures nearly all (&gt; 99%) patients with end-stage renal disease in the U.S. over time, is used to illustrate the proposed method. The results suggest that the estimate of the cardiovascular incidence following the 30 days after infections, a period where acute effects of infection on vascular endothelium may be most pronounced, is substantially attenuated in the presence of infection onset measurement error.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mohammed</LastName><ForeName>Sandra M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sandra M. Mohammed is Ph.D. Student, Division of Biostatistics, University of California, Davis. Damla &#x15e;ent&#xfc;rk is Assistant Professor, Department of Biostatistics, University of California, Los Angeles, CA 90095. Lorien S. Dalrymple is Assistant Professor, Division of Nephrology, Department of Medicine, University of California, Sacramento, CA 95691. Danh V. Nguyen ( ucdnguyen@ucdavis.edu ) is Professor, Division of Biostatistics, University of California, Davis, CA 95616.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sent&#xfc;rk</LastName><ForeName>Damla</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dalrymple</LastName><ForeName>Lorien S</ForeName><Initials>LS</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nguyen</LastName><ForeName>Danh V</ForeName><Initials>DV</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 DK092232</GrantID><Acronym>DK</Acronym><Agency>NIDDK NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>UL1 RR024146</GrantID><Acronym>RR</Acronym><Agency>NCRR NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Am Stat Assoc</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>01510020R</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0162-1459</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Cardiovascular outcomes</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Case series models</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">End stage renal disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Measurement error</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Non-homogeneous Poisson process</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Time-varying exposure onset</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">United States Renal Data System</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2013</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2013</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2013</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2013</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23650442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS389882</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3643015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1080/01621459.2012.695648</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Carroll RJ, Ruppert D, Stefanski LA, Crainiceanu CM. Measurement Error in Nonlinear Models: A Modern Perspective. Chapman and Hall/CRC; Boca Raton: 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook JR, Stefanski LA. Simulation-Extrapolation Estimation in Parametric Measurement Error Models. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 1994;89:1314&#x2013;1328.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalrymple LS, Mohammed SM, Mu Y, Johansen KL, Chertow GM, Grimes B, Kaysen GA, Nguyen DV. The Risk of Cardiovascular-Related Events Following Infection-Related Hospitalizations in Older Patients on Dialysis. Clinical Journal of the American Society of Nephrology. 2011;6:1708&#x2013;1713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3133476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21566109</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farrington CP. Relative Incidence Estimation From Case Series for Vaccine Safety Evaluation. Biometrics. 1995;51:228&#x2013;235.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7766778</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibson JE, Hubbard RB, Smith CJP, Tata LJ, Britton JR, Fogarty AW. Use of Self-controlled Analytical Techniques to Assess the Association Between Use of Prescription Medications and the Risk of Motor Vehicle Crashes. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2009;169:761&#x2013;768.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19181876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins RM, Davidian M, Giltinan DM. A Two-Step Approach to Measurement Error in Time-Dependent Covariates in Nonlinear Mixed-Effects Models, With Application to IGF-I Pharmacokinetics. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 1997;92:436&#x2013;348.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Wang CY. Cox Regression With Accurate Covariate Unascertainable: A Nonparametric-Correction Approach. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2000;95:1209&#x2013;1219.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hubbard R, Farrington P, Smith C, Smeeth L, Tattersfield A. Exposure to Tricyclic and Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitor Antidepressants and the Risk of Hip Fracture. American Journal of Epidemiology. 2003;158:77&#x2013;84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12835289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keiding N. Independent Delayed Entry. Survival Analysis: State of the Art. 1992;211:309&#x2013;326.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li Y, Ryan L. Survival Analysis With Heterogeneous Covariate Measurement Error. Journal of the American Statistical Association. 2004;99:724&#x2013;735.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liao X, Zucker DM, Li Y, Spiegelman D. Survival Analysis with Error-Prone Time-Varying Covariates: A Risk Set Calibration Approach. Biometrics. 2011;67:50&#x2013;58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2927810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20486928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macko RF, Ameriso SF, Gruber A, Griffin JH, Fernandez JA, Barndt R, Quismorio FP, Weiner JM, Fisher M. Impairments of the Protein C System and Fibrinolysis in Infection-Associated Stroke. Stroke. 1996;27:2005&#x2013;2011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8898806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mahmoudi M, Curzen N, Gallagher PJ. Atherogenesis: The Role of Inflammation and Infection. Histopathology. 2007;50:535&#x2013;546.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17394488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smeeth L, Thomas SL, Hall AJ, Hubbard R, Farrington P, Vallance P. Risk of Myocardial Infarction and Stroke After Acute Infection or Vaccination. New England Journal of Medicine. 2004;351:2611&#x2013;2618.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15602021</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun H. The Interaction Between Pathogens and the Host Coagulation System. Physiology. 2006;21:281&#x2013;288.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16868317</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsiatis A, Davidian M. Joint Modeling of Longitudinal and Time-to-Event Data: An Overview. Statistica Sinica. 2004;14:809&#x2013;834.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tosteson TD, Buonaccorsi JP, Demidenko E. Covariate Measurement Error and the Estimation of Random Effect Parameters in a Mixed Model for Longitudinal Data. Statistics in Medicine. 1998;17:1959&#x2013;1971.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9777689</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U S Renal Data System, USRDS . Annual Data Report: Atlas of Chronic Kidney Disease and End-Stage Renal Disease in the United States. National Institutes of Health; National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases; Bethesda, MD: 2010. 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walley T, Mantgani A. The UK General Practice Research Database. Lancet. 1997;350:1097&#x2013;1099.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10213569</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitaker HJ, Farrington CP, Spiessens B, Musonda P. Tutorial in Biostatistics: The Self-Controlled Case Series Method. Statistics in Medicine. 2006;25:1768&#x2013;1797.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16220518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Whitaker HJ, Hocine M, Farrington CP. The Methodology of Self-Controlled Case Series Studies. Statistical Methods in Medical Research. 2009;18:7&#x2013;26.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18562396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu J, Quyyumi AA, Norman JE, Csako G, Waclawiw MA, Shearer GM, Epstein SE. Effects of Total Pathogen Burden on Coronary Artery Disease Risk and C-Reactive Protein Levels. American Journal of Cardiology. 2000;85:140&#x2013;146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10955367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>