<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">35287307</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>03</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">0167-2681</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>197</Volume><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>May</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of economic behavior &amp; organization</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Econ Behav Organ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Save lives or save livelihoods? A cross-country analysis of COVID-19 pandemic and economic growth.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>221</StartPage><EndPage>256</EndPage><MedlinePgn>221-256</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jebo.2022.02.027</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This paper studies whether containing COVID-19 pandemic by stringent strategies deteriorates or saves economic growth. Since there are country-specific factors that could affect both economic growth and deaths due to COVID-19, we first start with a cross-country analysis on identifying risk and protective factors on the COVID-19 deaths using large across-country variation. Using data on 100 countries from 3 January to 27 November 2020 and taking into account the possibility of underreporting, we find that for deaths per million population, GDP per capita, population density, and income inequality are the three most important risk factors; government effectiveness, temperature, and hospital beds are the three most important protective factors. Second, inspired by the stochastic frontier literature, we construct a measure of pandemic containment effectiveness (PCE) after controlling for country-specific factors and rank countries by their PCE scores for deaths. Finally, by linking the PCE score with GDP growth data in Quarters 2 and 3 of 2020, we find that PCE is positively associated with economic growth in major economies. Countries with average PCE scores, such as Malaysia, would gain more GDP growth by 3.47 percentage points if they could improve their PCE scores for deaths to South Korea's level in Q2 of 2020. Therefore, there is not a trade-off between lives and livelihood facing by governments. Instead, to save economy, it is important to contain the pandemic first. Our conclusion is also mainly valid for infections due to COVID-19.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2022 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Feng</LastName><ForeName>Qu</ForeName><Initials>Q</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Economics Division, School of Social Sciences, Nanyang Technological University, 48 Nanyang Ave, 639818, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wu</LastName><ForeName>Guiying Laura</ForeName><Initials>GL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Economics Division, School of Social Sciences, Nanyang Technological University, 48 Nanyang Ave, 639818, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yuan</LastName><ForeName>Mengying</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Economics Division, School of Social Sciences, Nanyang Technological University, 48 Nanyang Ave, 639818, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Zhou</LastName><ForeName>Shihao</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Economics Division, School of Social Sciences, Nanyang Technological University, 48 Nanyang Ave, 639818, Singapore.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>J Econ Behav Organ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101086031</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0167-2681</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Economic growth</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemic containment effectiveness (PCE)</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ranking</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Risk and protective factors</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Underreporting</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>None.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>7</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35287307</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8907024</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jebo.2022.02.027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0167-2681(22)00080-4</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Adda J. Economic activity and the spread of viral diseases: evidence from high frequency data. Q. J. Econ. 2016;131(2):891&#x2013;941.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed F., Ahmed N.E., Pissarides C., Stiglitz J. Why inequality could spread COVID-19. Lancet Public Health. 2020;5(5):e240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7270465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32247329</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albani V., Loria J., Massad E., Zubelli J. COVID-19 underreporting and its impact on vaccination strategies. BMC Infect. Dis. 2021;21(1):1&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8552982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34711190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angeli F., Montefusco A. Sensemaking and learning during the COVID-19 pandemic: a complex adaptive systems perspective on policy decision-making. World Dev. 2020;136:105106.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7396147</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834387</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Avery, C., Bossert, W., Clark, A., Ellison, G., &amp; Ellison, S. F. (2020). Policy implications of models of the spread of coronavirus: perspectives and opportunities for economists. In NBER Working Papers No.27007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bannister-Tyrrell, M., Meyer, A., Faverjon, C., &amp; Cameron, A. (2020). Preliminary evidence that higher temperatures are associated with lower incidence of COVID-19, for cases reported globally up to 29th February 2020. In Working Paper.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blundell R., Bond S. GMM estimation with persistent panel data: an application to production functions. Econ. Rev. 2000;19(3):321&#x2013;340.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bommer C., Vollmer S. Average detection rate of SARS-Cov-2 infections is estimated around six percent. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen, Q., He, Z., Hsieh, C., &amp; Song, Z. (2020). Post-lockdown economic recovery in China: April and May. In Becker Friedman Institute, White paper.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coccia M. The relation between length of lockdown, numbers of infected people and deaths of COVID-19, and economic growth of countries: lessons learned to cope with future pandemics similar to covid-19 and to constrain the deterioration of economic system. Sci. Total Environ. 2021;775:145801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dai R., Mookherjee D., Quan Y., Zhang X. Industrial clusters, networks and resilience to the COVID-19 shock in china. J. Econ. Behav. Organ. 2021;183:433&#x2013;455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dingel J.I., Neiman B. How many jobs can be done at home? J. Public Econ. 2020;189:1042351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7346841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards R. Bubble in, bubble out: lessons for the COVID-19 recovery and future crises from the pacific. World Dev. 2020;135:105072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7346778</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834380</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichenbaum, M. S., Rebelo, S., &amp; Trabandt, M. (2020). The macroeconomics of epidemics. In NBER Working Papers No.26882.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elgin C., Basbug G., Yalaman A. Economic policy responses to a pandemic: developing the COVID-19 economic stimulus index. Covid Econ. 2020;1(3):40&#x2013;53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farzanegan, M. R., Feizi, M., &amp; Gholipour, H. F. (2021a). Globalization and outbreak of COVID-19: an empirical analysis. 2020. In Joint Discussion Paper Series in Economics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farzanegan M.R., Gholipour H.F., Feizi M., Nunkoo R., Andargoli A.E. International tourism and outbreak of coronavirus (COVID-19): a cross-country analysis. J. Travel Res. 2021;60(3):687&#x2013;692.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feng Q., Horrace W.C. Alternative technical efficiency measures: skew, bias and scale. J. Appl. Econ. 2012;27(2):253&#x2013;268.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldberg P.K., Reed T. The effects of the coronavirus pandemic in emerging market and developing economies an optimistic preliminary account. Brook. Pap. Econ. Act. 2020;2020(2):161&#x2013;235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene W. Distinguishing between heterogeneity and inefficiency: stochastic frontier analysis of the world health organization&#x2019;s panel data on national health care systems. Health Econ. 2004;13(10):959&#x2013;980.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15455464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greene W. In: The Measurement of Productive Efficiency: Techniques and Applications. Fried H.O., Lovell C.A.K., Schmidt S., editors. University Press; New York: Oxford: 2007. The econometric approach to efficiency analysis.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoarau J.F. Is international tourism responsible for the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic? A cross-country analysis with a special focus on small islands. Rev. World Econ. 2021:1&#x2013;36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hong H., Wang N., Yang J. World Sci.; 2021. Mitigating COVID-19 risks to sustain growth; pp. 25&#x2013;32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Horta&#xe7;su A., Liu J., Schwieg T. Estimating the fraction of unreported infections in epidemics with a known epicenter: an application to COVID-19. J. Econ. 2021;220(1):106&#x2013;129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7476454</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32921876</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsu, W. T., Lin, H. C. L., &amp; Yang, H. (2020). Lives and economy: optimal COVID-19 containment policy in open economies. In Available at SSRN 3705800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10289272</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38620112</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Janiak A., Machado C., Tur&#xe9;n J. Covid-19 contagion, economic activity and business reopening protocols. J. Econ. Behav. Organ. 2021;182:264&#x2013;284.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7759096</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33390632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karlsson M., Nilsson T., Pichler S. The impact of the 1918 Spanish flu epidemic on economic performance in Sweden: an investigation into the consequences of an extraordinary mortality shock. J. Health Econ. 2014;36:1&#x2013;19.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24721206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khalid U., Okafor L.E., Burzynska K. Does the size of the tourism sector influence the economic policy response to the COVID-19 pandemic? Curr. Issues Tour. 2021:1&#x2013;20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K&#xf6;nig M., Winkler A. COVID-19 and economic growth: does good government performance pay off? Intereconomics. 2020;55(4):224&#x2013;231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7385207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834098</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumbhakar S.C., Wang H., Horncastle A.P. University Press; Cambridge: 2015. A Practitioner&#x2019;s Guide to Stochastic Frontier Analysis Using Stata.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lau H., Khosrawipour V., Kocbach P., Mikolajczyk A., Ichii H., Schubert J., Khosrawipour T. Internationally lost COVID-19 cases. J. Microbiol. Immunol. Infect. 2020;53(3):454&#x2013;458.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7102572</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32205091</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee L.F. Consistency and efficiency of least squares estimation for mixed regressive, spatial autoregressive models. Econ. Theory. 2002:252&#x2013;277.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R., Pei S., Chen B., Song Y., Zhang T., Yang W., Shaman J. Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (SARS-COV-2) Science. 2020;368(6490):489&#x2013;4930.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32179701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liang L.L., Tseng C.H., Ho H.J., Wu C.Y. COVID-19 mortality is negatively associated with test number and government effectiveness. Sci. Rep. 2020;10(1):1&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7381657</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32709854</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magazzino C., Mele M., Sarkodie S.A. The nexus between COVID-19 deaths, air pollution and economic growth in new york state: evidence from deep machine learning. J. Environ. Manag. 2021;286:112241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8506015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33667818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mele M., Magazzino C. Pollution, economic growth, and COVID-19 deaths in india: a machine learning evidence. Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. 2021;28(3):2669&#x2013;2677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7472938</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32886309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milani F. COVID-19 outbreak, social response, and early economic effects: a global VAR analysis of cross-country interdependencies. J. Popul. Econ. 2021;34(1):223&#x2013;252.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7437387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32839640</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okafor L.E., Khalid U., Burzynska K. Does the level of a country&#x2019;s resilience moderate the link between the tourism industry and the economic policy response to the COVID-19 pandemic? Curr. Issues Tour. 2021:1&#x2013;16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okoi O., Bwawa T. How health inequality affect responses to the COVID-19 pandemic in sub-saharan africa. World Dev. 2020;135:105067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7351451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32834378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesaran M.H., Zhou Q. Estimation of time-invariant effects in static panel data models. econometric reviews. Econ. Rev. 2018;37(10):1137&#x2013;1171.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmandad, H., Lim, T. Y., &amp; Sterman, J. (2020). Estimating COVID-19 under-reporting across 86 nations: implications for projections and control. In medrxiv.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sebhatu A., Wennberg K., Arora-Jonsson S., Lindberg S.I. Explaining the homogeneous diffusion of COVID-19 nonpharmaceutical interventions across heterogeneous countries. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 2020;117(35):21201&#x2013;21208.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7474611</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32788356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Selvanathan E.A., Jayasinghe M., Selvanathan S. International tourism and infectious disease transmission nexus: a cross-country and regional study. J. Travel Res. 2021 doi:00472875211048932.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shafiullah M., Khalid U., Chaudhry S.M. Do stock markets play a role in determining COVID-19 economic stimulus? A cross-country analysis. World Econ. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8250644</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34230757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stock, J. H., Aspelund, K. M., Droste, M., &amp; Walker, C. D. (2020). Estimates of the undetected rate among the SARS-Cov-2 infected using testing data from Iceland. In Working Paper.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viscusi W.K. Pricing the global health risks of the COVID-19 pandemic. J. Risk Uncertain. 2020;61(2):101&#x2013;128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7604649</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33162671</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Q., Zhang F. What does the China&#x2019;s economic recovery after COVID-19 pandemic mean for the economic growth and energy consumption of other countries? J. Clean. Prod. 2021;295:126265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7874931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33589853</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wimmer A., Min B. From empire to nation-state: explaining wars in the modern world. Am. Sociol. Rev. 2006;71(6):867&#x2013;897.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wright A.L., Sonin K., Driscoll J., Wilson J. Poverty and economic dislocation reduce compliance with COVID-19 shelter-in-place protocols. J. Econ. Behav. Organ. 2020;180:544&#x2013;554.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7568053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33100443</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>