<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">27670635</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>26</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>6</Volume><PubDate><Year>2016</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>27</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Benchmarking Measures of Network Influence.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>34052</StartPage><MedlinePgn>34052</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">34052</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/srep34052</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Identifying key agents for the transmission of diseases (ideas, technology, etc.) across social networks has predominantly relied on measures of centrality on a static base network or a temporally flattened graph of agent interactions. Various measures have been proposed as the best trackers of influence, such as degree centrality, betweenness, and k-shell, depending on the structure of the connectivity. We consider SIR and SIS propagation dynamics on a temporally-extruded network of observed interactions and measure the conditional marginal spread as the change in the magnitude of the infection given the removal of each agent at each time: its temporal knockout (TKO) score. We argue that this TKO score is an effective benchmark measure for evaluating the accuracy of other, often more practical, measures of influence. We find that none of the network measures applied to the induced flat graphs are accurate predictors of network propagation influence on the systems studied; however, temporal networks and the TKO measure provide the requisite targets for the search for effective predictive measures.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bramson</LastName><ForeName>Aaron</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Riken Brain Science Institute, Laboratory for Symbolic Cognitive Development, Wako, 351-0198, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ghent University, Department of General Economics, Ghent, 9000, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of North Carolina at Charlotte, Department of Software and Information Systems, Charlotte, 28223, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vandermarliere</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ghent University, Department of General Economics, Ghent, 9000, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Ghent University, Department of Physics and Astronomy, Ghent, 9000, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2016</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>27</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2016</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>18</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2016</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2016</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2016</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2016</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2016</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27670635</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5037445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/srep34052</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">srep34052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Kempe D., Kleinberg J. &amp; Tardos &#xc9;. Influential nodes in a diffusion model for social networks. In Automata, languages and programming, 1127&#x2013;1138 (Springer, 2005).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang Y., Cong G., Song G. &amp; Xie K. Community-based greedy algorithm for mining top-k influential nodes in mobile social networks. In Proceedings of the 16th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining, 1039&#x2013;1048 (ACM, 2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimura M., Saito K., Nakano R. &amp; Motoda H. Extracting influential nodes on a social network for information diffusion. Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery 20, 70&#x2013;97 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen D., L&#xfc; L., Shang M.-S., Zhang Y.-C. &amp; Zhou T. Identifying influential nodes in complex networks. Physica a: Statistical mechanics and its applications 391, 1777&#x2013;1787 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saito K., Kimura M., Ohara K. &amp; Motoda H. Efficient discovery of influential nodes for sis models in social networks. Knowledge and information systems 30, 613&#x2013;635 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sikic M., Lancic A., Antulov-Fantulin N. &amp; Stefancic H. Epidemic centrality &#x2013; is there an underestimated epidemic impact of network peripheral nodes? The European Physical Journal B 86, 1&#x2013;13 (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y., Paul G., Havlin S., Liljeros F. &amp; Stanley H. E. Finding a better immunization strategy. Physical review letters 101, 058701 (2008).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18764435</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu Y., Berger-Wolf T. Y., Saia J. et al. Finding spread blockers in dynamic networks. In Advances in Social Network Mining and Analysis, 55&#x2013;76 (Springer, 2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhlman C. J., Kumar V. A., Marathe M. V., Ravi S. &amp; Rosenkrantz D. J. Finding critical nodes for inhibiting diffusion of complex contagions in social networks. In Machine Learning and Knowledge Discovery in Databases, 111&#x2013;127 (Springer, 2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman M. E. Spread of epidemic disease on networks. Physical review E 66, 016128 (2002).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12241447</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman M. E., Forrest S. &amp; Balthrop J. Email networks and the spread of computer viruses. Physical Review E 66, 035101 (2002).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12366169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dekker A. H. Network centrality and super-spreaders in infectious disease epidemiology. In <i>20th International Congress on Modelling and Simulation (MODSIM2013)</i> (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Danon L. et al. Networks and the epidemiology of infectious disease. Interdisciplinary perspectives on infectious diseases 2011 (2011).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3062985</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21437001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albert R., Jeong H. &amp; Barab&#xe1;si A.-L. Error and attack tolerance of complex networks. Nature 406, 378&#x2013;382 (2000).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10935628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Callaway D. S., Newman M. E. J., Strogatz S. H. &amp; Watts D. J.
Network robustness and fragility: Percolation on random graphs. Physical Review Letters
85, <b>25</b>, 5468&#x2013;5471 (2000).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11136023</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pastor-Satorras R. &amp; Vespignani A. Immunization of complex networks. Physical Review E 65, 036104 (2002).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11909162</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitsak M. et al. Identification of influential spreaders in complex networks. Nature Physics 6, 888&#x2013;893 (2010).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klemm K., Serrano M., Eguluz V. M. &amp; Miguel M. S. A measure of individual role in collective dynamics. <i>arXiv preprint arXiv:1002.4042</i> (2010).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3289910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22379597</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer F. &amp; Lizier J. T. Identifying influential spreaders and efficiently estimating infection numbers in epidemic models: A walk counting approach. EPL (Europhysics Letters) 99, 68007 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Viana M. P., Batista J. a. L. &amp; Costa L. d. F. Effective number of accessed nodes in complex networks. Physical Review E 85, 036105 (2012).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22587147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawyer G. Understanding the influence of all nodes in a network. Scientific reports 5 (2015).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4345333</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25727453</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hufnagel L., Brockmann D. &amp; Geisel T. Forecast and control of epidemics in a globalized world. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 101, 15124&#x2013;15129 (2004).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC524041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15477600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brockmann D. &amp; Helbing D. The hidden geometry of complex, network-driven contagion phenomena. Science 342, 1337&#x2013;1342 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24337289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holme P. &amp; Saram&#xe4;kid J. Temporal networks. Physics Reports 519, 97&#x2013;125 (2012).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holme P. Modern temporal network theory: a colloquium. The European Physical Journal B 88, 1&#x2013;30 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bramson A. &amp; Vandermarliere B. Dynamical properties of interaction data. Journal of Complex Networks cnv009 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Michail O. An introduction to temporal graphs: An algorithmic perspective. In Algorithms, Probability, Networks, and Games, 308&#x2013;343 (Springer, 2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Speidel L., Takaguchi T. &amp; Masuda N. Community detection in directed acyclic graphs. The European Physical Journal B 88, 1&#x2013;10 (2015).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagberg A. A., Schult D. A. &amp; Swart P. J. Exploring network structure, dynamics, and function using NetworkX. In Proceedings of the 7th Python in Science Conference (SciPy2008), 11&#x2013;15 (Pasadena, CA USA 2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rahmandad H. &amp; Sterman J. Heterogeneity and network structure in the dynamics of diffusion: Comparing agent-based and differential equation models. Management Science 54, 998&#x2013;1014 (2008).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nicosia V.
et al. Graph metrics for temporal networks. <i>arXiv:1306.0493 [physics.soc-ph]</i>
<b>1306</b> (2013).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pfitzner R., Scholtes I., Garas A., Tessone C. J. &amp; Schweitzerk F. Betweenness preference: Quantifying correlations in the topological dynamics of temporal networks. Physical Review Letters 110, 198701 1&#x2013;5 (2013).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23705746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lancic A., Antulov-Fantulin N., Sikic M. &amp; Stefancic H. Phase diagram of epidemic spreading &#x2013; unimodal vs. bimodal probability distributions. Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications 390, 65&#x2013;76 (2011).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>