<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37166329</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>07</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2165-0497</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Microbiology spectrum</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Microbiol Spectr</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Reagent and Virus Benchmarking Panel for a Uniform Analytical Performance Assessment of N Antigen-Based Diagnostic Tests for COVID-19.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0373122</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0373122</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e03731-22</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/spectrum.03731-22</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Rapid diagnostic tests (RDTs) that detect antigen indicative of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection can help in making quick health care decisions and regularly monitoring groups at risk of infection. With many RDT products entering the market, it is important to rapidly evaluate their relative performance. Comparison of clinical evaluation study results is challenged by protocol design variations and study populations. Laboratory assays were developed to quantify nucleocapsid (N) and spike (S) SARS-CoV-2 antigens. Quantification of the two antigens in nasal eluates confirmed higher abundance of N than S antigen. The median concentration of N antigen was 10 times greater than S per genome equivalent. The N antigen assay was used in combination with quantitative reverse transcription (RT)-PCR to qualify a panel composed of recombinant antigens, inactivated virus, and clinical specimen pools. This benchmarking panel was applied to evaluate the analytical performance of the SD Biosensor Standard Q COVID-19 antigen (Ag) test, Abbott Panbio COVID-19 Ag rapid test, Abbott BinaxNOW COVID-19 Ag test, and the LumiraDx SARS-CoV-2 Ag test. The four tests displayed different sensitivities toward the different panel members, but all performed best with the clinical specimen pool. The concentration for a 90% probability of detection across the four tests ranged from 21&#x2009;to 102&#x2009;pg/mL of N antigen in the extracted sample. Benchmarking panels provide a quick way to verify the baseline performance of a diagnostic and enable direct comparisons between diagnostic tests. <b>IMPORTANCE</b> This study reports the results for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-COV-2) nucleocapsid (N) and spike (S) antigen quantification assays and their performance against clinical reverse transcription (RT)-PCR results, thus describing an open-access quantification method for two important SARS-CoV-2 protein analytes. Characterized N antigen panels were used to evaluate the limits of detection of four different rapid tests for SARS-CoV-2 against multiple sources of nucleocapsid antigen, demonstrating proof-of-concept materials and methodology to evaluate SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen detection tests. Quantification of N antigen was used to characterize the relationship between viral count and antigen concentration among clinical samples and panel members of both clinical sample and viral culture origin. This contributes to a deeper understanding of protein antigen and molecular analytes and presents analytical methods complementary to clinical evaluation for characterizing the performance of both laboratory-based and point-of-care rapid diagnostics for SARS-CoV-2.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Golden</LastName><ForeName>Allison</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-6891-5176</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cantera</LastName><ForeName>Jason L</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7665-5458</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lillis</LastName><ForeName>Lorraine</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Phan</LastName><ForeName>Thanh T</ForeName><Initials>TT</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Slater</LastName><ForeName>Hannah</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Webb</LastName><ForeName>Edwin J</ForeName><Initials>EJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Peck</LastName><ForeName>Roger B</ForeName><Initials>RB</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boyle</LastName><ForeName>David S</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Domingo</LastName><ForeName>Gonzalo J</ForeName><Initials>GJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PATH, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Microbiol Spectr</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101634614</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2165-0497</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D007202">Indicators and Reagents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007202" MajorTopicYN="N">Indicators and Reagents</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019985" MajorTopicYN="N">Benchmarking</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003955" MajorTopicYN="N">Diagnostic Tests, Routine</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086742" MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 Testing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">PCR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">genome equivalent</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nucleocapsid antigen</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rapid antigen diagnostic test</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rapid antigen test</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">rapid diagnostic test</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">screening</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">spike antigen</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>8</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>18</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>10</Hour><Minute>6</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37166329</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10269465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.03731-22</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. 2021. Antigen-detection in the diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection. https://www.who.int/publications-detail-redirect/antigen-detection-in-the-diagnosis-of-sars-cov-2infection-using-rapid-immunoassays. Accessed 1 February 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollock NR, Berlin D, Smole SC, Madoff LC, Brown C, Henderson K, Larsen E, Hay J, Gabriel S, Gawande AA, Lennon NJ. 2021. Implementation of SARS-CoV2 screening in K-12 schools using in-school pooled molecular testing and deconvolution by rapid antigen test. J Clin Microbiol 59:e01123-21. doi: 10.1128/JCM.01123-21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.01123-21</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8373013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34191585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revollo B, Blanco I, Soler P, Toro J, Izquierdo-Useros N, Puig J, Puig X, Navarro-P&#xe9;rez V, Casa&#xf1; C, Ruiz L, Perez-Zsolt D, Videla S, Clotet B, Llibre JM. 2021. Same-day SARS-CoV-2 antigen test screening in an indoor mass-gathering live music event: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet Infect Dis 21:1365&#x2013;1372. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00268-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00268-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8457773</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34051886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jimenez A, Rees-Channer RR, Perera R, Gamboa D, Chiodini PL, Gonz&#xe1;lez IJ, Mayor A, Ding XC. 2017. Analytical sensitivity of current best-in-class malaria rapid diagnostic tests. Malar J 16:128. doi: 10.1186/s12936-017-1780-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-017-1780-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5366122</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28340585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Br&#xfc;mmer LE, Katzenschlager S, Gaeddert M, Erdmann C, Schmitz S, Bota M, Grilli M, Larmann J, Weigand MA, Pollock NR, Mac&#xe9; A, Carmona S, Ongarello S, Sacks JA, Denkinger CM. 2021. Accuracy of novel antigen rapid diagnostics for SARS-CoV-2: a living systematic review and meta-analysis. PLoS Med 18:e1003735. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1003735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8389849</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34383750</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinnes J, Deeks JJ, Berhane S, Taylor M, Adriano A, Davenport C, Dittrich S, Emperador D, Takwoingi Y, Cunningham J, Beese S, Domen J, Dretzke J, Ferrante di Ruffano L, Harris IM, Price MJ, Taylor-Phillips S, Hooft L, Leeflang MM, McInnes MD, Spijker R, Van den Bruel A, Cochrane COVID-19 Diagnostic Test Accuracy Group . 2021. Rapid, point-of-care antigen and molecular-based tests for diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 3:Cd013705. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD013705.pub2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD013705.pub2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8078597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33760236</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corman VM, Haage VC, Bleicker T, Schmidt ML, M&#xfc;hlemann B, Zuchowski M, Jo WK, Tscheak P, M&#xf6;ncke-Buchner E, M&#xfc;ller MA, Krumbholz A, Drexler JF, Drosten C. 2021. Comparison of seven commercial SARS-CoV-2 rapid point-of-care antigen tests: a single-centre laboratory evaluation study. Lancet Microbe 2:e311&#x2013;e319. doi: 10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00056-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00056-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8026170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33846704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schroeder LF, Bachman MA, Idoni A, Gegenheimer-Holmes J, Kronick SL, Valdez R, Lephart PR. 2022. Predicting direct-specimen SARS-CoV-2 assay performance using residual patient samples. J Appl Lab Med 7:661&#x2013;673. doi: 10.1093/jalm/jfab159.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jalm/jfab159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8767897</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34755849</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Denzler A, Jacobs ML, Witte V, Schnitzler P, Denkinger CM, Knop M. 2022. Rapid comparative evaluation of SARS-CoV-2 rapid point-of-care antigen tests. Infection 50:1281&#x2013;1293. doi: 10.1007/s15010-022-01810-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s15010-022-01810-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8994089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35397099</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekliz M, Adea K, Essaidi-Laziosi M, Sacks JA, Escadafal C, Kaiser L, Eckerle I. 2022. SARS-CoV-2 antigen-detecting rapid tests for the delta variant. Lancet Microbe 3:e90. doi: 10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00302-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00302-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8612709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34849494</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kontogianni K, Cubas-Atienzar AI, Wooding D, Buist K, Thompson CR, Williams CT, Baldwin L, Escadafal C, Sacks JA, Adams ER, Edwards T. 2021. Lateral flow antigen tests can sensitively detect live cultured virus of the SARS-CoV-2 B1.1.7 lineage. J Infect 83:e1&#x2013;e4. doi: 10.1016/j.jinf.2021.05.033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2021.05.033</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8164512</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34062185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bekliz M, Adea K, Essaidi-Laziosi M, Sacks JA, Escadafal C, Kaiser L, Eckerle I. 2021. SARS-CoV-2 rapid diagnostic tests for emerging variants. Lancet Microbe 2:e351. doi: 10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00147-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2666-5247(21)00147-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8241290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34223400</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanley S, Hamel DJ, Wolf ID, Riedel S, Dutta S, Contreras E, Callahan CJ, Cheng A, Arnaout R, Kirby JE, Kanki PJ. 2022. Limit of detection for rapid antigen testing of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron and Delta variants of concern using live-virus culture. J Clin Microbiol 60:e00140-22. doi: 10.1128/jcm.00140-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/jcm.00140-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9116160</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35440165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sigal GB, Novak T, Mathew A, Chou J, Zhang Y, Manjula N, Bathala P, Joe J, Padmanabhan N, Romero D, Allegri-Machado G, Joerger J, Loftis LL, Schwartz SP, Walker TC, Fitzgerald JC, Tarquinio KM, Zinter MS, Schuster JE, Halasa NB, Cullimore ML, Madduz AB, Staat MA, Irby K, Flori HR, Coates BM, Crandall H, Gertz SJ, Randolph AG, Pollack NR, Overcoming COVID-19 Investigators . 2021. Measurement of SARS-CoV-2 antigens in plasma of pediatric patients with acute COVID-19 or MIS-C using an ultrasensitive and quantitative immunoassay. MedRxiv Prepr Serv Health Sci doi: 10.1101/2021.12.08.21267502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1101/2021.12.08.21267502</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hingrat QL, Visseaux B, Laouenan C, Tubiana S, Bouadma L, Yazdanpanah Y, Duval X, Burdet C, Ichou H, Damond F, Bertine M, Benmalek N, Choquet C, Timsit J-F, Ghosn J, Charpentier C, Descamps D, Houhou-Fidouh N, Genetic . 2020. Detection of SARS-CoV-2 N-antigen in blood during acute COVID-19 provides a sensitive new marker and new testing alternatives. Clin Microbiol Infect 27:789.e1&#x2013;789.e5. doi: 10.1016/j.cmi.2020.11.025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.11.025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7724284</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33307227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pollock NR, Savage TJ, Wardell H, Lee RA, Mathew A, Stengelin M, Sigal GB. 2021. Correlation of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid antigen and RNA concentrations in nasopharyngeal samples from children and adults using an ultrasensitive and quantitative antigen assay. J Clin Microbiol 59:e03077-20. doi: 10.1128/JCM.03077-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.03077-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8092747</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33441395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang H, Hogan CA, Verghese M, Solis D, Sibai M, Huang C, Zehnder J, Sahoo MK, Pinsky BA. 2021. Ultra-sensitive severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) antigen detection for the diagnosis of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in upper respiratory samples. Clin Infect Dis off Publ Infect Dis Soc Am 73:2326&#x2013;2328. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciab063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciab063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8083502</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33830203</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bourassa L, Perchetti GA, Phung Q, Lin MJ, Mills MG, Roychoudhury P, Harmon KG, Reed JC, Greninger AL. 2021. A SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid variant that affects antigen test performance. J Clin Virol 141:104900. doi: 10.1016/j.jcv.2021.104900.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2021.104900</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8219478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34171548</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jian M-J, Chung H-Y, Chang C-K, Lin J-C, Yeh K-M, Chen C-W, Lin D-Y, Chang F-Y, Hung K-S, Perng C-L, Shang H-S. 2022. SARS-CoV-2 variants with T135I nucleocapsid mutations may affect antigen test performance. Int J Infect Dis 114:112&#x2013;114. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2021.11.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.11.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8572148</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34758391</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrera-Avalos C, Luraschi R, Vallejos-Vidal E, Mella-Torres A, Hern&#xe1;ndez F, Figueroa M, Rioseco C, Vald&#xe9;s D, Imarai M, Acu&#xf1;a-Castillo C, Reyes-L&#xf3;pez FE, Sandino AM. 2021. The rapid antigen detection test for SARS-CoV-2 underestimates the identification of COVID-19 positive cases and compromises the diagnosis of the SARS-CoV-2 (K417N/T, E484K, and N501Y) variants. Front Public Health 9:780801. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2021.780801.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.780801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8761676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35047474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bayart J-L, Degosserie J, Favresse J, Gillot C, Didembourg M, Djokoto HP, Verbelen V, Roussel G, Maschietto C, Mullier F, Dogn&#xe9; J-M, Douxfils J. 2022. Analytical sensitivity of six SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen tests for Omicron versus Delta variant. Viruses 14:654. doi: 10.3390/v14040654.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/v14040654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9031584</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35458384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rogier E, Bakari C, Mandara CI, Chiduo MG, Plucinski M, Nace D, Battle N, Chacky F, Rumisha SF, Molteni F, Mandike R, Mkude S, Njau R, Mohamed A, Udhayakumar V, Ishengoma DS. 2022. Performance of antigen detection for HRP2-based malaria rapid diagnostic tests in community surveys: Tanzania, July-November 2017. Malar J 21:361. doi: 10.1186/s12936-022-04383-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-022-04383-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9714097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36457087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plucinski M, Dimbu R, Candrinho B, Colborn J, Badiane A, Ndiaye D, Mace K, Chang M, Lemoine JF, Halsey ES, Barnwell JW, Udhayakumar V, Aidoo M, Rogier E. 2017. Malaria surveys using rapid diagnostic tests and validation of results using post hoc quantification of <i>Plasmodium falciparum</i> histidine-rich protein 2. Malar J
16:451. doi: 10.1186/s12936-017-2101-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12936-017-2101-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5678810</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29115966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CLSI. 2022. EP12A2 | User protocol for evaluation of qualitative test performance. Clinical &amp; Laboratory Standards Institute. https://clsi.org/standards/products/method-evaluation/documents/ep12/. Accessed 1 February 2022.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McKay SL, Tobolowsky FA, Moritz ED, Hatfield KM, Bhatnagar A, LaVoie SP, Jackson DA, Lecy KD, Bryant-Genevier J, Campbell D, Freeman B, Gilbert SE, Folster JM, Medrzycki M, Shewmaker PL, Bankamp B, Radford KW, Anderson R, Bowen MD, Negley J, Reddy SC, Jernigan JA, Brown AC, McDonald LC, Kutty PK, CDC Infection Prevention and Control Team, CDC COVID-19 Surge Laboratory Group . 2021. Performance evaluation of serial SARS-CoV-2 rapid antigen testing during a nursing home outbreak. Ann Intern Med 174:945&#x2013;951. doi: 10.7326/M21-0422.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/M21-0422</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8108910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33900791</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Begum MN, Jubair M, Nahar K, Rahman S, Talha M, Sarker MS, Uddin AKMN, Khaled S, Uddin MS, Li Z, Ke T, Rahman MZ, Rahman M. 2022. Factors influencing the performance of rapid SARS-CoV-2 antigen tests under field condition. J Clin Lab Anal 36:e24203. doi: 10.1002/jcla.24203.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jcla.24203</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8842313</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34942043</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jungnick S, Hobmaier B, Mautner L, Hoyos M, Haase M, Baiker A, Lahne H, Eberle U, Wimmer C, Hepner S, Sprenger A, Berger C, Dangel A, Ippisch S, Hahner S, Wildner M, Liebl B, Ackermann N, Sing A, Fingerle V. 2021. <i>In vitro</i> rapid antigen test performance with the SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern B.1.1.7 (Alpha), B.1.351 (Beta), P.1 (Gamma), and B.1.617.2 (Delta). Microorganisms
9:1967. doi: 10.3390/microorganisms9091967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/microorganisms9091967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8465346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34576862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>ExPASy. ProtParam tool. https://web.expasy.org/protparam/. Accessed 19 May 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Armbruster DA, Pry T. 2008. Limit of blank, limit of detection and limit of quantitation. Clin Biochem Rev 29:S49&#x2013;S52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2556583</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18852857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>B&#xfc;rkner PC. 2017. brms: an R package for Bayesian multilevel models using Stan. J Stat Soft 80:1&#x2013;28. doi: 10.18637/jss.v080.i01.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18637/jss.v080.i01</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>