<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">33428331</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>13</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1863-2378</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>68</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Zoonoses and public health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Zoonoses Public Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Establishment of sentinel surveillance of human clinical campylobacteriosis in Ireland.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>121</StartPage><EndPage>130</EndPage><MedlinePgn>121-130</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/zph.12802</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The aim of this work was the establishment of a national laboratory sentinel surveillance service for human clinical Campylobacter in Ireland. This included detailed genomic molecular epidemiology of Campylobacter for 2019. For February-December 2019, 24 clinical microbiology laboratories in Ireland submitted all PCR/culture-positive clinical Campylobacter spp. specimens to Public Health Laboratory (PHL) Dublin one&#xa0;week out of every four. Antimicrobial susceptibility testing (AST) according to European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (EUCAST) criteria was carried out for Campylobacter spp. isolates for ciprofloxacin, tetracycline and erythromycin. Batch whole genome sequencing (WGS) was carried out on cultures and analysis was performed to determine species, genotype, identify antimicrobial resistance (AMR) and virulence determinants and identify clusters. A total of 75 isolates and 366 PCR-positive stools were received, and 277 isolates recovered (55.7% recovery from stools). Of 257 isolates characterized by WGS, 86.4% (n&#xa0;=&#xa0;222) were Campylobacter jejuni, 11.7% (n&#xa0;=&#xa0;30) Campylobacter coli and 1.9% (n&#xa0;=&#xa0;5) Campylobacter lari. There were 20 clonal complexes with ST-21 clonal complex most prevalent at 26.8% (n&#xa0;=&#xa0;69). 50.5% (n&#xa0;=&#xa0;140) of isolates were susceptible to all three antimicrobials tested. 39.3% (n&#xa0;=&#xa0;109) isolates were ciprofloxacin resistant, 26.3% (n&#xa0;=&#xa0;73) tetracycline resistant and two isolates erythromycin resistant. Congruence between phenotypic and genotypic AST was observed. There was 95.9% and 95.6% sensitivity and specificity for WGS to predict ciprofloxacin sensitivity and 98.6% and 99.5% sensitivity and specificity for WGS to predict tetracycline sensitivity. Virulence factors flaA, racR, ciaB and cdtB were detected in all isolates. WGS identified 31 potential clusters for public health alert. This sentinel surveillance of human campylobacteriosis in Ireland establishes the basis for a national reference service. Linking with other partners in a 'One Health' framework will help us better understand sources of infection to reduce disease burden and the threat of AMR.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2021 Wiley-VCH GmbH.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Brehony</LastName><ForeName>Carina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2967-2762</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Laboratory, Health Service Executive, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>European Public Health Microbiology Training Programme (EUPHEM), European Centre for Disease Control and Prevention, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lanigan</LastName><ForeName>Donal</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Laboratory, Health Service Executive, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carroll</LastName><ForeName>Anne</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Laboratory, Health Service Executive, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McNamara</LastName><ForeName>Eleanor</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Public Health Laboratory, Health Service Executive, Dublin, Ireland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Germany</Country><MedlineTA>Zoonoses Public Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101300786</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1863-1959</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D004269">DNA, Bacterial</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D037521">Virulence Factors</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="N">pharmacology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002167" MajorTopicYN="N">Campylobacter</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000187" MajorTopicYN="N">drug effects</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="Y">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002169" MajorTopicYN="N">Campylobacter Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="Y">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016000" MajorTopicYN="N">Cluster Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004269" MajorTopicYN="N">DNA, Bacterial</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D024881" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Resistance, Bacterial</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015964" MajorTopicYN="N">Gene Expression Regulation, Bacterial</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016680" MajorTopicYN="N">Genome, Bacterial</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005838" MajorTopicYN="N">Genotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007494" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Ireland</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018571" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sentinel Surveillance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D037521" MajorTopicYN="N">Virulence Factors</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000378" MajorTopicYN="N">metabolism</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000073336" MajorTopicYN="N">Whole Genome Sequencing</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Campylobacter</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">AMR</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Ireland</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">WGS</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">laboratory surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">molecular epidemiology</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2020</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2020</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>23</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33428331</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/zph.12802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Babu Rajendran, N., Mutters, N. T., Marasca, G., Conti, M., Sifakis, F., Vuong, C., Voss, A., Ba&#xf1;o, J. R., Tacconelli, E.; COMBACTE-MAGNET-EPI-Net Consortium (2019). Mandatory surveillance and outbreaks reporting of the WHO priority pathogens for research &amp; discovery of new antibiotics in European countries. Clinical Microbiology and Infection, 26(7), 943.e1-943.e6. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2019.11.020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bankevich, A., Nurk, S., Antipov, D., Gurevich, A. A., Dvorkin, M., Kulikov, A. S., Lesin, V. M., Nikolenko, S. I., Pham, S., Prjibelski, A. D., Pyshkin, A. V., Sirotkin, A. V., Vyahhi, N., Tesler, G., Alekseyev, M. A., &amp; Pevzner, P. A. (2012). SPAdes: A new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing. Journal of Computational Biology, 19(5), 455-477. https://doi.org/10.1089/cmb.2012.0021</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barker, C. R., Painset, A., Swift, C., Jenkins, C., Godbole, G., Maiden, M. C. J., &amp; Dallman, T. J. (2020). Microevolution of Campylobacter jejuni during long-term infection in an immunocompromised host. Scientific Reports, 10(1), 10109. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-66771-7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bless, P. J., Schmutz, C., &amp; M&#xe4;usezahl, D. (2017). The recurrent campylobacteriosis epidemic over Christmas and New Year in European countries, 2006-2014. BMC Research Notes, 10(266), 30130. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13104-017-2587-8</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolton, D. J. (2015). Campylobacter virulence and survival factors. Food Microbiology, 48, 99-108. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fm.2014.11.017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bolwell, C. F., Gilpin, B. J., Campbell, D., &amp; French, N. P. (2015). Evaluation of the representativeness of a sentinel surveillance site for campylobacteriosis. Epidemiology and Infection, 143(9), 1990-2002. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0950268814003173</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Broberg, E., Revez, J., Alm, E., Van Walle, I., Palm, D., &amp; Struelens, M. (2019). ECDC strategic framework for the integration of molecular and genomic typing into European surveillance and multi-country outbreak investigations - 2019-2021.. Stockholm: ECDC. https://doi.org/10.2900/805317</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cassini, A., Colzani, E., Pini, A., Mangen, M. J., Plass, D., McDonald, S. A., Maringhini, G., van Lier, A., Haagsma, J. A., Havelaar, A. H., Kramarz, P., Kretzschmar, M. E.; On Behalf Of The BCoDE Consortium (2018). Impact of infectious diseases on population health using incidence-based disability-adjusted life years (DALYs): Results from the Burden of Communicable Diseases in Europe study, European Union and European Economic Area countries, 2009 to 2013. Eurosurveillance, 23(16), 17-00454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chai, S. J., Gu, W., O'Connor, K. A., Richardson, L. C., &amp; Tauxe, R. V. (2019). Incubation periods of enteric illnesses in foodborne outbreaks, United States, 1998-2013. Epidemiology and Infection, 147, e285. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0950268819001651</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Charlo, A., Bry, M., Bujila, I., Chenais, E., Dryselius, R., Eriksson, H., &#x2026; Widgren, S. (2020). Surveillance of infectious diseases in animals and humans in Sweden 2019, SVA:s rapportserie 64 1654-7098. Uppsala, Sweden: National Veterinary Institute (SVA).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cody, A. J., Bray, J. E., Jolley, K. A., McCarthy, N. D., &amp; Maiden, M. C. J. (2017). Core genome multilocus sequence analyses of Campylobacter jejuni and C. coli human disease isolates. Journal of Clinical Microbiology, 55(7), 2086-2097.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cody, A. J., McCarthy, N. D., Van Rensburg, M. J., Isinkaye, T., Bentley, S. D., Parkhill, J., Dingle, K. E., Bowler, I. C., Jolley, K. A. &amp; Maiden, M. C. J. (2013). Real-time genomic epidemiological evaluation of human Campylobacter isolates by use of whole-genome multilocus sequence typing. Journal of Clinical Microbiology, 51(8), 2526-2534. https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.00066-13</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cody, A. J., McCarthy, N. M., Wimalarathna, H. L., Colles, F. M., Clark, L., Bowler, I. C., Maiden, M. C., &amp; Dingle, K. E. (2012). A longitudinal 6-year study of the molecular epidemiology of clinical Campylobacter isolates in Oxfordshire, United Kingdom. Journal of Clinical Microbiology, 50(10), 3193-3201. https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.01086-12</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dever, N., O'Connell, B., &amp; McNamara, E. (2018). Is there loss of epidemiologocal data on campylobacteriosis due to widespread use of molecular diagnostics. Poster presentation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyle, R. M., Sullivan, D. M. O., Aller, S. D., Bruchmann, S., Clark, T., Pelegrin, A. C., Cormican, M., Diez Benavente, E., Ellington, M. J., McGrath, E., Motro, Y., Phuong Thuy Nguyen, T., Phelan, J., Shaw, L. P., Stabler, R. A., van Belkum, A., van Dorp, L., Woodford, N., Moran-Gilad, J., &#x2026; Harris, K. A. (2020). Discordant bioinformatic predictions of antimicrobial resistance from whole-genome sequencing data of bacterial isolates: An inter-laboratory study. Microbial Genomics, 6(2), e000335. https://doi.org/10.1099/mgen.0.000335</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>EFSA/ECDC (2019). The European Union One Health 2018 Zoonoses Report. EFSA Journal, 17(12). http://dx.doi.org/10.2903/j.efsa.2019.5926</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellington, M. J., Ekelund, O., Aarestrup, F. M., Canton, R., Doumith, M., Giske, C., Grundman, H., Hasman, H., Holden, M. T. G., Hopkins, K. L., Iredell, J., Kahlmeter, G., K&#xf6;ser, C. U., MacGowan, A., Mevius, D., Mulvey, M., Naas, T., Peto, T., Rolain, J. M., &#x2026; Woodford, N. (2017). The role of whole genome sequencing in antimicrobial susceptibility testing of bacteria: Report from the EUCAST Subcommittee. Clinical Microbiology and Infection, 23(1), 2-22. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2016.11.012</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (2018). ECDC Surveillance Atlas. https://atlas.ecdc.europa.eu/public/index.aspx</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (2019). In: ECDC. Campylobacteriosis Annual Epidemiological Report for 2017, Stockholm: ECDC. https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/campylobacteriosis-annual-epidemiological-report-2017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (2003). Directive 2003/99/EC European Parliament and of the Council of 17 November 2003. Official Journal of the European Union, 325, 31-40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Commission (2018). Commission Implementing Decision (EU) 2018/945 of 22 June 2018 on the communicable diseases and related special health issues to be covered by epidemiological surveillance as well as relevant case definitions. Official Journal of the European Union, L170(2119), 1-74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (2019). European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing. European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing Breakpoint tables for interpretation of MICs and zone diameters. Version 9.0.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Food and Drug Administration (2009). Guidance for Industry and FDA. Class II special controls guidance document: Antimicrobial susceptibility test (AST) systems, USA: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services Food and Drug Administration Center for Devices and Radiological Health. https://www.fda.gov/medical-devices/guidance-documents-medical-devices-and-radiation-emitting-products/antimicrobial-susceptibility-test-ast-systems-class-ii-special-controls-guidance-industry-and-fda</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G&#xf6;lz, G., Rosner, B., Hofreuter, D., Josenhans, C., Kreienbrock, L., L&#xf6;wenstein, A., Schielke, A., Stark, K., Suerbaum, S., Wieler, L. H., &amp; Alter, T. (2014). Relevance of Campylobacter to public health - The need for a One Health approach. International Journal of Medical Microbiology, 304(7), 817-823. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijmm.2014.08.015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greninger, A. L., Addetia, A., Starr, K., Cybulski, R. J., Stewart, M. K., Salipante, S. J., Bryan, A. B., Cookson, B., Gaudreau, C., Bekal, S., &amp; Fang, F. C. (2019). International spread of multidrug-resistant campylobacter coli in men who have sex with men in Washington State and Quebec. 2015-2018. Clinical Infectious Diseases, 71(8), 1896-1904. https://doi.org/10.1093/cid/ciz1060</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>HSE Health Protection Surveillance Centre (2019). Annual Epidemiological Report. Campylobacter infection in Ireland, 2018, Dublin: HSE HPSC.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hetman, B. M., Mutschall, S. K., Carrillo, C. D., Thomas, J. E., Gannon, V. P. J., Inglis, G. D., &amp; Taboada, E. N. (2020). &#x201c;These Aren't the Strains You're Looking for&#x201d;: Recovery bias of common campylobacter jejuni subtypes in mixed cultures. Frontiers in Microbiology, 11(541), 1-12. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2020.00541</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Humphries, R. M., Ambler, J., Mitchell, S. L., Castanheira, M., Dingle, T., Hindler, J. A., Koeth, L., Sei, K., CLSI Methods Development and Standardization Working Group of the Subcommittee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (2018). CLSI methods development and standardization working group best practices for evaluation of antimicrobial susceptibility tests. Journal of Clinical Microbiology, 56(4), e01934-17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iglesias-Torrens, Y., Mir&#xf3;, E., Guirado, P., Llovet, T., Mu&#xf1;oz, C., Cerd&#xe0;-Cu&#xe9;llar, M.,Madrid, C., Balsalobre, C., &amp; Navarro, F. (2018). Population structure, antimicrobial resistance, and virulence-associated genes in campylobacter jejuni isolated from three ecological niches: Gastroenteritis patients, broilers, and wild birds. Frontiers in Microbiology, 9(AUG), 1-13. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2018.01676</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joensen, K. G., Kiil, K., Gantzhorn, M. R., Nauerby, B., Engberg, J., Holt, H. M., Nielsen, H. L., Petersen, A. M., Kuhn, K. G., Sand&#xf8;, G., Ethelberg, S., &amp; Nielsen, E. M. (2020). Whole-genome sequencing to detect numerous Campylobacter jejuni outbreaks and match patient isolates to sources, Denmark, 2015-2017. Emerging Infectious Diseases, 26(3), 523-532. https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2603.190947</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Joensen, K., Kuhn, K., M&#xfc;ller, L., Bj&#xf6;rkman, J., Torpdahl, M., Engberg, J., Holt, H. M., Nielsen, H. L., Petersen, A. M., Ethelberg, S. &amp; Nielsen, H. (2018). Whole-genome sequencing of Campylobacter jejuni isolated from Danish routine human stool samples reveals surprising degree of clustering. Clinical Microbiology and Infection, 24(2), 201.e5-201.e8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaakoush, N. O., Casta&#xf1;o-Rodr&#xed;guez, N., Mitchell, H. M., &amp; Ming Man, S. (2015). Global epidemiology of campylobacter infection. Clinical Microbiol Reviews, 28(3), 687-720. https://doi.org/10.1128/CMR.00006-15</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kivist&#xf6;, R. I., Kovanen, S., Skarp-De Haan, A., Schott, T., Rahkio, M., Rossi, M., &amp; H&#xe4;nninen, M. L. (2014). Evolution and comparative genomics of Campylobacter jejuni ST-677 clonal complex. Genome Biology and Evolution, 6(9), 2424-2438. https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evu194</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kovanen, S. M., Kivist&#xf6;, R. I., Rossi, M., Schott, T., K&#xe4;rkk&#xe4;inen, U. M., Tuuminen, T., Uksila, J., Rautelin, H. &amp; H&#xe4;nninen, M. L. (2014). Multilocus sequence typing (MLST) and whole-genome MLST of Campylobacter jejuni isolates from human infections in three districts during a seasonal peak in Finland. Journal of Clinical Microbiology, 52(12), 4147-4154. https://doi.org/10.1128/JCM.01959-14</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lake, I. R., Col&#xf3;n-Gonz&#xe1;lez, F. J., Dias, J. G., Semenza, J. C., &amp; Nichols, G. (2019). Exploring Campylobacter seasonality across Europe using The European Surveillance System (TESSy), 2008 to 2016. Eurosurveillance, 24(13), 1800028.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luangtongkum, T., Jeon, B., Han, J., Plummer, P., Logue, C. M., &amp; Zhang, Q. (2009). Antibiotic resistance in Campylobacter: Emergence, transmission and persistence. Future Microbiology, 4(2), 189-200. https://doi.org/10.2217/17460913.4.2.189</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lynch, C. T., Lynch, H., Egan, J., Whyte, P., Bolton, D., Coffey, A., &amp; Lucey, B. (2020). Antimicrobial resistance of Campylobacter isolates recovered from broilers in the Republic of Ireland in 2017 and 2018: an update. British Poultry Science, 61(5), 550-556. https://doi.org/10.1080/00071668.2020.1758300</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCarthy, N., Cody, A., Maiden, M., &amp; Strachan, N. (2019). A systematic review of source attribution of human campylobacteriosis using multi-locus sequence typing. Eurosurveillance, 24(43), 1800696. https://doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2019.24.43.1800696</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muellner, P., Pleydell, E., Pirie, R., Baker, M. G., Campbell, D., Carter, P. E., &amp; French, N. P. (2013). Molecular-based surveillance of campylobacteriosis in New Zealand - From source attribution to genomic epidemiology. Eurosurveillance, 18(3), 1-7. https://doi.org/10.2807/ese.18.03.20365-en</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Connor, L., McKeown, P., Barrasa, A., &amp; Garvey, P. (2020). Epidemiology of Campylobacter infections in Ireland 2004-2016: What has changed? Zoonoses and Public Health, 67(4), 362-369. https://doi.org/10.1111/zph.12695</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Painset, A., Day, M., Doumith, M., Rigby, J., Jenkins, C., Grant, K., Dallman, T. J., Godbole, G., &amp; Swift, C. (2020). Comparison of phenotypic and WGS-derived antimicrobial resistance profiles of Campylobacter jejuni and Campylobacter coli isolated from cases of diarrhoeal disease in England and Wales, 2015-16. Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy, 75(4), 883-889. https://doi.org/10.1093/jac/dkz539</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Redondo, N., Carroll, A., &amp; McNamara, E. (2019). Molecular characterization of Campylobacter causing human clinical infection using wholegenome sequencing: Virulence, antimicrobial resistance and phylogeny in Ireland. PLoS One, 14(7), e0219088. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0219088</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rokney, A., Valinsky, L., Moran-Gilad, J., Vranckx, K., Agmon, V., &amp; Weinberger, M. (2018). Genomic epidemiology of Campylobacter jejuni transmission in Israel. Frontiers in Microbiology, 9(2432), 1-10. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2018.02432</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scanlon, K. A., Cagney, C., Walsh, D., McNulty, D., Carroll, A., McNamara, E. B., McDowell, D. A., &amp; Duffy, G. (2013). Occurrence and characteristics of fastidious Campylobacteraceae species in porcine samples. International Journal of Food Microbiology, 163(1), 6-13. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.02.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheppard, S. K., Dallas, J. F., Strachan, N. J. C., MacRae, M., McCarthy, N. D., Wilson, D. J., Gormley, F. J., Falush, D., Ogden, I. D., &amp; Maiden, M. C. &amp; Forbes, K. J. (2009). Campylobacter genotyping to determine the source of human infection. Clinical Infectious Diseases, 48(8), 1072-1078. https://doi.org/10.1086/597402</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheppard, S. K., &amp; Maiden, M. C. J. (2015). The evolution of Campylobacter jejuni and Campylobacter coli. Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology, 7(8), 1-13. https://doi.org/10.1101/cshperspect.a018119</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tack, D. M., Ray, L., Griffin, P. M., Cieslak, P. R., Dunn, J., Rissman, T., Jervis, R., Lathrop, S., Muse, A., Duwell, M., Smith, K., Tobin-D'Angelo, M., Vugia, D. J., Zablotsky Kufel, J., Wolpert, B. J., Tauxe, R., &amp; Payne, D. C. (2020). Preliminary incidence and trends of infections with pathogens transmitted commonly through food - foodborne diseases active surveillance network, 10 U.S. Sites, 2016-2019. MMWR. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report, 69(17), 509-514. https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6917a1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO (2012). The global view of campylobacteriosis: report of an expert consultation, Utrecht, Netherlands, Geneva: WHO. https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/80751/9789241564601_eng.pdf?sequence=1</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>