<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37027438</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>11</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>12</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>18</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mining and quantitative evaluation of COVID-19 policy tools in China.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0284143</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0284143</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0284143</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0284143</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Policy quantitative analysis can effectively evaluate the government's response to COVID-19 emergency management effect, and provide reference for the government to formulate follow-up policies. The content mining method is used to explore the 301 COVID-19 policies issued by the Central government of China since the outbreak of the epidemic in a multi-dimensional manner and comprehensively analyze the characteristics of epidemic prevention policies. Then, based on policy evaluation theory and data fusion theory, a COVID-19 policy evaluation model based on PMC-AE is established to evaluate quantitatively eight representative COVID-19 policy texts. The results show that: Firstly, China's COVID-19 policies are mainly aimed at providing economic support to enterprises and individuals affected by the epidemic, issued by 49 departments, and include 32.7 percent supply-level and 28.5 percent demand-level, and 25.8 percent environment-level. In addition, strategy-level policies accounted for at least 13 percent. Secondly, according to the principle of openness, authority, relevance and normative principle, eight COVID-19 policies are evaluated by PMC-AE model. Four policies are level &#x2160; policies, three policies are level &#x2161; policies and one policy is level &#x2162; policies. The reason for its low score is mainly affected by four indexes: policy evaluation, incentive measures, policy emphasis and policy receptor. To sum up, China has taken both non-structural and structural measures to prevent and control the epidemic. The introduction of specific epidemic prevention and control policy has realized complex intervention in the whole process of epidemic prevention and control.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright: &#xa9; 2023 Liu et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Liu</LastName><ForeName>Jianzhao</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Economics and Management, Tianjin Chengjian University, Tianjin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Li</LastName><ForeName>Na</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Economics and Management, Tianjin Chengjian University, Tianjin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cheng</LastName><ForeName>Luming</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-0077-9109</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Economics and Management, Tianjin Chengjian University, Tianjin, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058872" MajorTopicYN="Y">Epidemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006291" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Policy</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002681" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">China</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>44</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37027438</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10081750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0284143</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-22-20862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bloom DE, Cadarette D. Infectious disease threats in the twenty-first century: strengthening the global response. Frontiers in immunology. 2019;(10):549. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2019.00549</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.00549</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6447676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30984169</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian ZH, Zhang Z, Ma T, Cheng YF, Ma ZY, Fan HF, et al. Analysis of epidemiological characteristics of public health emergencies in Nanjing between 2006 and 2018. Modern Preventive Medicine. 2020;47(02):348&#x2013;351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma XW, Feng J, Zeng RN, liao XL, Xiao XC, Wang ZW, et al. Epidemiological characteristics of public health emergencies of schools in Guangzhou, 2010&#x2013;2017. Modern Preventive Medicine. 2019;46(19):3483&#x2013;3486.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>He ZT, Ma XL, Li YW. COVID-19 online public opinion analysis and response measures. Journal of News Research. 2020;11(12):9&#x2013;11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo Y, Zhang HT. Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia (COVID-19) and Intelligence wisdom: evaluation and governance on Intelligence ability of disease control emergency work in public health emergencies. Information Science. 2020;38(03):129&#x2013;136.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu H, Zhang SS, Shen L, Xie Q, Jiang SM, Liang SP, et al. Construction of a novel coronavirus pneumonia epidemic prevention and control system in Zhengzhou People&#x2019;s Hospital. Chinese Journal of Hygiene Rescue (Electronic Edition). 2020;6(03):186&#x2013;188.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao XQ, Li TE, Mo CL. Text analysis of polices about enterprises returning to work and restarting production in the context of COVID-19 in China. Information Studies: Theory &amp; Application. 2020;43(08):21&#x2013;28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zang W, Li TT, Xu L. Policy instrument mining and quantitative evaluation of maker space supporting policy of Beijing. Soft Science. 2018;32(09):56&#x2013;61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sokolov A, et al. Quantitative analysis for a better-focused international STI collaboration policy: A case of BRICS. Technological Forecasting and Social Change. 2019;147:221&#x2013;242.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grandia JJ, and Kruyen PMP. Assessing the implementation of sustainable public procurement using quantitative text-analysis tools: A large-scale analysis of Belgian public procurement notices. Journal of Purchasing and Supply Management. 2020;26(04):100627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ewalt JAG, Jennings ET Jr. Administration, governance, and policy tools in welfare policy implementation. Public Administration Review. 2004;64(04):449&#x2013;462.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Redmond WJ. A quantification of policy reform: an application to the Uruguay Round Negotiations on Agriculture. Journal of Policy Modeling. 2003;25(09):893&#x2013;910.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Williamson B. Digital education governance: data visualization, predictive analytics, and &#x2018;real-time&#x2019;policy instruments. Journal of education policy. 2016;31(02):123&#x2013;141.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Logar I. Sustainable tourism management in Crikvenica, Croatia: An assessment of policy instruments. Tourism management. 2010;31(01):125&#x2013;135.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carter T, Fowler L. Establishing green roof infrastructure through environmental policy instruments. Environmental management. 2008;42(01):151&#x2013;164. doi: 10.1007/s00267-008-9095-5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00267-008-9095-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18389306</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hou ZX, Lyu Y. Quantitative research on the policy of regional agricultural products ecommerce&#x2014;tasking Gansu province as the example. China Business and Market. 2017;31(11):45&#x2013;53.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xiong XG. The content analysis and suggestions for Chinese &#x201c;popular entrepreneurship and innovation&#x201d; policy from the perspective of policy tools. Soft Science. 2018;32(12):19&#x2013;23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang XF, Hao L, Qin HB, Su LY, Liu ZN. Textual quantitative analysis of cultivated land ecological management and protection policies in China from the perspective of policy tools. China Land Science. 2018;32(12):15&#x2013;23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang XP, Huang C, Su J. Textual and quantitative research on Chinese science and technology finance development policies based on policy tools. Journal of Intelligence. 2020;39(01):130&#x2013;137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao J, Zhang L. Textual and quantitative research on China&#x2019;s old-age service policy from the perspective of policy tools. Modern Economic Research. 2018;(12):33&#x2013;39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei JY, Wang XX. Content analysis of China&#x2019;s industrial internet policy from the perspective of policy tool. Value Engineering. 2020;39(02):295&#x2013;297.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peng JS, Zhong WG, Sun WX. Policy measurement, policy co-evolution, and economic performance: an empirical study based on innovation policy. Journal of Management World.2008;(09):25&#x2013;36.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li JH, Chang XZ. Innovation policy coordination of China&#x2019;s circulation industry. Journal of Business Economics.2014;(09):5&#x2013;16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang BJ, Zhu R. Evaluation on policy efficacy and effect of industry-university-research cooperative innovation&#x2014;policy quantification on China from 2006 to 2016. Soft Science.2019;33(03):30&#x2013;35+44.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang YA, Yan J. A research on the influences of technology innovation policy on enterprise innovation performance&#x2014;based on the policy text analysis. Science &amp; Technology Progress and Policy. 2016;33(01):108&#x2013;113.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lepskiy V. Evolution of cybernetics: philosophical and methodological analysis. Kybernetes, 2017;47(02):249&#x2013;261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz Estrada MA, Yap SF. The origins and evolution of policy modeling. Journal of Policy Modeling. 2013;35(01):170&#x2013;182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz Estrada MA, Yap SF, Nagaraj S. Beyond the ceteris paribus assumption: Modeling demand and supply assuming omnia mobilis. Social Science Electronic Publishing, 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruize Estrada MA. The policy modeling research consistency index (PMC-index). Social Science Electronic Publishing, 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang YA, Zhou YY. Policy instrument mining and quantitative evaluation of new energy vehicles subsidies. 2017;27(10):188&#x2013;197.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang JF, Yang QY, Zhang YY. Quantitative evaluation of Civil-Military integration policy based on PMC-AE index model. Journal of Intelligence. 2019;38(04):66&#x2013;73.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz Estrada MA. Policy modeling: Definition, classification and evaluation. Journal of Policy Modeling. 2011;33(04): 523&#x2013;536.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Du DL, Yuan L, Gao K. Evaluation on Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei science and technology innovation policy in 2010&#x2013;2017. Forum on Science and Technology in China. 2019;(10):100&#x2013;109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding XJ, Fang YT. Study on the policy of "China&#x2019;s Chip" by text mining tool and quantitative evaluation. Soft Science. 2019;33(04):34&#x2013;39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fang YH, Chen YQ. Quantitative evaluation of the state council&#x2019;s social housing policies: analysis based on 10 social housing policies intelligence. Journal of Intelligence. 2019;38(03):101&#x2013;107.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao LX, Tang J. The quantitative evaluation of China&#x2019;s carbon reduction policies based on the index of PMC model. Forum on Science and Technology in China. 2018;(01):116&#x2013;122+172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu TL, Fu QY. Quantitative evaluation innovation policies and path selection of the Chinese green energy industry. Forum on Science and Technology in China. 2018;(10):82&#x2013;92.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Justicia de la Torre C, S&#xe1;nchez D, Blanco I, Mart&#xed;n-Bautista MJ. Text Mining: Techniques, Applications, and Challenges. International Journal of Uncertainty, Fuzziness and Knowledge-Based Systems.2018;26(4).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lange S, and Riedmiller M. Deep auto-encoder neural networks in reinforcement learning. The 2010 international joint conference on neural networks (IJCNN). IEEE, 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu MX, Li H. Evaluation of the effectiveness of motor vehicle pollution prevention and control policies in Beijing: quantitative analysis based on policy texts from 2013 to 2017. Scientific Decision Making. 2018;(12):74&#x2013;90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo YF, Bai WC. The implementation status of local government efficacy evaluation in China: based on the policy text analysis of 31 provinces. Lanzhou Academic Journal. 2019;(01):164&#x2013;182.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang MM, Li H, Wang F. Chinese public innovation and entrepreneurship policies, development: an evaluation based on policy tools, innovation and entrepreneurship cycles, policy levels. Forum on Science and Technology in China. 2018;(08):25&#x2013;33+57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flanagan K, Uyarra E, Laranja M. "Reconceptualizing the &#x2018;policy mix&#x2019; for innovation. " Research policy. 2011;40(05): 702&#x2013;713.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rothwell R, Zegveld W. Reindusdalization and Technology. London: Logman Group Limited; 1985.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kissler S, Tedijanto C, Lipsitch M, Grad YH. Social distancing strategies for curbing the COVID-19 epidemic. medRxiv. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maharaj S, Kleczkowski A. Controlling epidemic spread by social distancing: Do it well or not at all. BMC Public Health. 2012;12(01):1&#x2013;16. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-12-679</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-679</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3563464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22905965</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maier BF, Brockmann D. Effective containment explains subexponential growth in recent confirmed COVID-19 cases in China. Science. 2020;368(6492):742&#x2013;746. doi: 10.1126/science.abb4557</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.abb4557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164388</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32269067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>K&#xf6;hler J, et al. Robust and optimal predictive control of the COVID-19 outbreak. Annual Reviews in Control. 2021;51:525&#x2013;539. doi: 10.1016/j.arcontrol.2020.11.002</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.arcontrol.2020.11.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7757387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33362428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leopoldina NAW. Dritte Ad-hoc-Stellungnahme: Coronavirus-Pandemie&#x2013;Die Krise nachhaltig &#xfc;berwinden. 2020. Available from https://www.leopoldina.org/uploads/tx_leopublication/2020_04_13_Coronavirus-Pandemie-Die_Krise_nachhaltig_%C3%BCberwinden_final.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu P, Zhang MM, Suo JL. Theme ming and hierarchical diffsuion characteristics analysis of COVID-19 policy based on spatio-temporal big data evolution. Information Studies: Theory &amp; Application. 2023;1&#x2013;13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao S, NI J. The development, current situation and implications of after-school service system in Japan. Journal of Comparative Education. 2023;(01):105&#x2013;117.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu XR, Gong JT. Research on policy construction of rural cultural revitalization from the perspective of policy tools. Library Tribune. 2023;1&#x2013;11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen G, Lin JW. Evolution context, stage characteristics and development trend of China&#x2019;s digital culture industry policy. Journal of Shenzhen University (Humanities &amp; Social Sciences). 2022;39(06):40&#x2013;51.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pierre L; Patrick LG. Introduction: Understanding Public Policy through Its Instruments&#x2014;From the Nature of Instruments to the Sociology of Public Policy Instrumentation. Governance: An International Journal of Policy, Administration, and Institutions. 2007;20(1):1&#x2013;21.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>