<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">22544188</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2012</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>18</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>17</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-6591</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>54 Suppl 4</Volume><Issue>Suppl 4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2012</Year><Month>May</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical infectious diseases : an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>HIV drug resistance early warning indicators in cohorts of individuals starting antiretroviral therapy between 2004 and 2009: World Health Organization global report from 50 countries.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>S280</StartPage><EndPage>S289</EndPage><MedlinePgn>S280-9</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/cid/cis207</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The World Health Organization developed a set of human immunodeficiency virus drug resistance (HIVDR) early warning indicators (EWIs) to assess antiretroviral therapy clinic and program factors associated with HIVDR. EWIs are monitored by abstracting data routinely recorded in clinical records, and the results enable clinics and program managers to identify problems that should be addressed to minimize preventable emergence of HIVDR in clinic populations. As of June 2011, 50 countries monitored EWIs, covering 131 686 patients initiating antiretroviral treatment between 2004 and 2009 at 2107 clinics. HIVDR prevention is associated with patient care (appropriate prescribing and patient monitoring), patient behavior (adherence), and clinic/program management efforts to reduce treatment interruptions (follow up, retention on first-line ART, procurement and supply management of antiretroviral drugs). EWIs measure these factors and the results have been used to optimize patient and population treatment outcomes.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bennett</LastName><ForeName>Diane E</ForeName><Initials>DE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia 30333, USA. dib1@cdc.gov</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jordan</LastName><ForeName>Michael R</ForeName><Initials>MR</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bertagnolio</LastName><ForeName>Silvia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hong</LastName><ForeName>Steven Y</ForeName><Initials>SY</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ravasi</LastName><ForeName>Giovanni</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>McMahon</LastName><ForeName>James H</ForeName><Initials>JH</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Saadani</LastName><ForeName>Ahmed</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kelley</LastName><ForeName>Karen F</ForeName><Initials>KF</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>L30 AI080268-02</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>K23 AI074423</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>K23 AI097010</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>K23 AI074423-05</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>L30 AI080268</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>P30AI4853</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9203213</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1058-4838</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D044966">Anti-Retroviral Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D044966" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Retroviral Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000494" MajorTopicYN="Y">pharmacology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015331" MajorTopicYN="N">Cohort Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003695" MajorTopicYN="N">Delivery of Health Care</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003906" MajorTopicYN="N">Developing Countries</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D024882" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Resistance, Viral</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="Y">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059012" MajorTopicYN="N">Lost to Follow-Up</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010349" MajorTopicYN="N">Patient Compliance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011159" MajorTopicYN="N">Population Surveillance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014944" MajorTopicYN="N">World Health Organization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2012</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2012</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2012</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2013</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22544188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3338314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/cis207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">cis207</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation> UNAIDS. AIDS at 30: nations at a crossroad. Available at:  http://www.unaids.org/unaids_resources/aidsat30/aids-at-30.pdf. Accessed 10 June 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilks CF, Crowley S, Ekpini R, et al. The WHO public-health approach to antiretroviral treatment against HIV in resource-limited settings. Lancet. 2006;368:505&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16890837</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boesecke C, Cooper DA. Toxicity of HIV protease inhibitors: clinical considerations. Curr Opin HIV AIDS. 2008;3:653&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19373038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haubrich RH, Riddler SA, DiRienzo AG, et al. Metabolic outcomes in a randomized trial of nucleoside, nonnucleoside and protease inhibitor-sparing regimens for initial HIV treatment. AIDS. 2009;23:1109&#x2013;18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2739977</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19417580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murphy RA, Sunpath H, Kuritzkes DR, Venter F, Gandhi RT. Antiretroviral therapy-associated toxicities in the resource-poor world: the challenge of a limited formulary. J Infect Dis. 2007;196(Suppl 3):S449&#x2013;56.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18181693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruno R, Sacchi P, Maiocchi L, Patruno S, Filice G. Hepatotoxicity and antiretroviral therapy with protease inhibitors: a review. Dig Liver Dis. 2006;38:363&#x2013;73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16631422</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> M&#xe9;decins Sans Fronti&#xe8;res. Untangling the web of antiretroviral price reductions, special report. Available at:  http://utw.msfaccess.org/. Accessed 20 February 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation> WHO/UNICEF/UNAIDS. Global HIV/AIDS Response: epidemic update and health sector progress towards universal access. Available at:  http://www.who.int/hiv/pub/progress_report2011/en/. Accessed 19 January 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett DE, Bertagnolio S, Sutherland D, Gilks CF. The World Health Organization&#x2019;s global strategy for prevention and assessment of HIV drug resistance. Antivir Ther. 2008;13(Suppl 2):1&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18578063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan MR. Assessments of HIV drug resistance mutations in resource-limited settings. Clin Infect Dis. 2011;52:1058&#x2013;60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21460325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. HIV drug resistance early warning indicators. World Health Organization indicators to monitor HIV drug resistance prevention at antiretroviral treatment sites. June 2010 update. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D&#x2019;Aquila RT, Hughes MD, Johnson VA, et al. Nevirapine, zidovudine, and didanosine compared with zidovudine and didanosine in patients with HIV-1 infection. A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases AIDS Clinical Trials Group Protocol 241 Investigators. Ann Intern Med. 1996;124:1019&#x2013;30.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8633815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammer SM, Katzenstein DA, Hughes MD, et al. A trial comparing nucleoside monotherapy with combination therapy in HIV-infected adults with CD4 cell counts from 200 to 500 per cubic millimeter. AIDS Clinical Trials Group Study 175 Study Team. N Engl J Med. 1996;335:1081&#x2013;90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8813038</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hammer SM, Squires KE, Hughes MD, et al. A controlled trial of two nucleoside analogues plus indinavir in persons with human immunodeficiency virus infection and CD4 cell counts of 200 per cubic millimeter or less. AIDS Clinical Trials Group 320 Study Team. N Engl J Med. 1997;337:725&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9287227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larder BA, Darby G, Richman DD. HIV with reduced sensitivity to zidovudine (AZT) isolated during prolonged therapy. Science. 1989;243:1731&#x2013;4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2467383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montaner JS, Reiss P, Cooper D, et al. A randomized, double-blind trial comparing combinations of nevirapine, didanosine, and zidovudine for HIV-infected patients: the INCAS Trial. Italy, the Netherlands, Canada and Australia Study. JAMA. 1998;279:930&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9544767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nachega JB, Knowlton AR, Deluca A, et al. Treatment supporter to improve adherence to antiretroviral therapy in HIV-infected South African adults. A qualitative study. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2006;43(Suppl 1):S127&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17133196</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pasquet A, Messou E, Gabillard D, et al. Impact of drug stock-outs on death and retention to care among HIV-infected patients on combination antiretroviral therapy in Abidjan, Cote d&#x2019;Ivoire. PLoS One. 2010;5:e13414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2955519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20976211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oyugi JH, Byakika-Tusiime J, Ragland K, et al. Treatment interruptions predict resistance in HIV-positive individuals purchasing fixed-dose combination antiretroviral therapy in Kampala, Uganda. AIDS. 2007;21:965&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17457090</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marcellin F, Boyer S, Protopopescu C, et al. Determinants of unplanned antiretroviral treatment interruptions among people living with HIV in Yaound&#xe9;, Cameroon (EVAL survey, ANRS 12-116) Trop Med Int Health. 2008;13:1470&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19000156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parienti JJ, Das-Douglas M, Massari V, et al. Not all missed doses are the same: sustained NNRTI treatment interruptions predict HIV rebound at low-to-moderate adherence levels. PLoS One. 2008;3:e2783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2467488</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18665246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parienti JJ, Massari V, Descamps D, et al. Predictors of virologic failure and resistance in HIV-infected patients treated with nevirapine- or efavirenz-based antiretroviral therapy. Clin Infect Dis. 2004;38:1311&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15127346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boyer S, Clerc I, Bonono CR, Marcellin F, Bile PC, Ventelou B. Non-adherence to antiretroviral treatment and unplanned treatment interruption among people living with HIV/AIDS in Cameroon: individual and healthcare supply-related factors. Soc Sci Med. 2011;72:1383&#x2013;92.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21470734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMahon J, Jordan M, Kelley K, et al. Pharmacy adherence measures to assess adherence to antiretroviral therapy: review of the literature and implications for treatment monitoring. Clin Infect Dis. 2011;52:493&#x2013;506.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3060901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21245156</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Messou E, Chaix M-L, Gabillard D, et al. Association between medication possession ratio, virologic failure and drug resistance in HIV-1&#x2013;infected adults on antiretroviral therapy in Cote d&#x2019;Ivoire. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2011;56:356&#x2013;64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3050083</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21191309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bisson GP, Gross R, Bellamy S, et al. Pharmacy refill adherence compared with CD4 count changes for monitoring HIV-infected adults on antiretroviral therapy. PLoS Med. 2008;5:e109. Public Library of Science.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2386831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18494555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polisset J, Ametonou F, Arrive E, Aho A, Perez F. Correlates of adherence to antiretroviral therapy in HIV-infected children in Lome, Togo, West Africa. AIDS Behav. 2009;13:23&#x2013;32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18654845</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fassinou P, Elenga N, Rouet F, et al. Highly active antiretroviral therapies among HIV-1-infected children in Abidjan, Cote d&#x2019;Ivoire. AIDS. 2004;18:1905&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15353976</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertagnolio S, Kelley K, Saadani Hassani A, Obeng-Aduasare Y, Jordan M. Programs and abstracts of the 18th Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections. Boston, MA: CROI: 2011. Surveillance of transmitted and acquired HIV drug resistance using WHO surveys in resource-limited settings [abstract 52]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cheeseman SH, Havlir D, McLaughlin MM, et al. Phase I/II evaluation of nevirapine alone and in combination with zidovudine for infection with human immunodeficiency virus. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr Hum Retrovirol. 1995;8:141&#x2013;51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7530585</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jack N, Ravasi G, Schrooten W. Implementing early-warning indicators of HIV drug resistance in the Caribbean. Clin Infect Dis. 2012;54(Suppl 4):S290&#x2013;3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22544189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuller DM, Bangsberg DR, Senkungu J, Ware NC, Emenyonu N, Weiser SD. Transportation costs impede sustained adherence and access to HAART in a clinic population in southwestern Uganda: a qualitative study. AIDS Behav. 2010;14:778&#x2013;84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2888948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19283464</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiser S, Wolfe W, Bangsberg D, et al. Barriers to antiretroviral adherence for patients living with HIV infection and AIDS in Botswana. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2003;34:281&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14600572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brigido LF, Rodrigues R, Casseb J, et al. Impact of adherence to antiretroviral therapy in HIV-1-infected patients at a university public service in Brazil. AIDS Patient Care STDs. 2001;15:587&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11788069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muko KN, Ngwa VC, Chigang LC, Ngwa IG, Meiburg A, Shu EN. Willingness to pay for treatment with highly active antiretroviral (HAART) drugs: a rural case study in Cameroon. SAHARA J. 2004;1:107&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11132610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17601016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey KM, Carrington D, Duncan J, et al. Evaluation of adherence to highly active antiretroviral therapy in adults in Jamaica. West Indian Med J. 2008;57:293&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19583131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Crane JT, Kawuma A, Oyugi JH, et al. The price of adherence: qualitative findings from HIVpositive individuals purchasing fixed-dose combination generic HIV antiretroviral therapy in Kampala, Uganda. AIDS Behav. 2006;10:437&#x2013;42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2386888</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16636892</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chalker JC, Andualem T, Gitau LN, et al. Measuring adherence to antiretroviral treatment in resource-poor settings: the feasibility of collecting routine data for key indicators. BMC Health Serv Res. 2010;10:43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2836318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20170479</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pearson CR, Micek M, Simoni JM, Matediana E, Martin DP, Gloyd S. Modified directly observed therapy to facilitate highly active antiretroviral therapy adherence in Beira, Mozambique. Development and implementation. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2006;43(Suppl 1):S134&#x2013;41.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5096448</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17133197</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mills EJ, Nachega JB, Bangsberg DR, et al. Adherence to HAART: a systematic review of developed and developing nation patient-reported barriers and facilitators. PLoS Med. 2006;3:e438.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1637123</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17121449</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White YR, Pierre RB, Steel-Duncan J, et al. Adherence to antiretroviral drug therapy in children with HIV/AIDS in Jamaica. West Indian Med J. 2008;57:231&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19583121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bussmann H, Wester CW, Thomas A, et al. Response to zidovudine/didanosine-containing combination antiretroviral therapy among HIV-1 subtype C-infected adults in Botswana: two-year outcomes from a randomized clinical trial. Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes: JAIDS 2009; 51:37&#x2013;46.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3066172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19282782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lyagoba F, Dunn DT, Pillay D, et al. Evolution of drug resistance during 48 weeks of zidovudine/lamivudine/tenofovir in the absence of real-time viral load monitoring. Journal of Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndromes: JAIDS 2010; 55:277&#x2013;83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20686411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ndembi N, Goodall RL, Dunn DT, et al. Viral rebound and emergence of drug resistance in the absence of viral load testing: a randomized comparison between zidovudine-lamivudine plus Nevirapine and zidovudine-lamivudine plus Abacavir. J Infect Dis 2010; 201:106&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19938977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation> World Health Organization. Antiretroviral therapy of HIV infection in infants and children: towards universal access: recommendations for a public health approach - 2010 revision. Available at:  http://www.who.int/hiv/pub/paediatric/infants2010/en. Accessed 20 May 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramadhani HO, Thielman NM, Landman KZ, et al. Predictors of incomplete adherence, virologic failure, and antiviral drug resistance among HIV-infected adults receiving antiretroviral therapy in Tanzania. Clin Infect Dis. 2007;45:1492&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17990233</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ma Y, Zhang F, Li H. Monitoring HIV drug resistance using early warning indicators in China: results from a pilot survey conducted in 2008. Clin Infect Dis. 2012;54(Suppl 4):S300&#x2013;2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22544191</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daoni E, Kitur U, Parunga A. Experience in piloting HIV drug resistance early warning indicators to improve the antiretroviral program in Papua New Guinea. Clin Infect Dis. 2012;54(Suppl 4):S303&#x2013;5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22544192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>