<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37202025</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>22</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>18</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2214-109X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Lancet. Global health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet Glob Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Diagnostic yield of urine lipoarabinomannan and sputum tuberculosis tests in people living with HIV: a systematic review and meta-analysis of individual participant data.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e903</StartPage><EndPage>e916</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e903-e916</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/S2214-109X(23)00135-3</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2214-109X(23)00135-3</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Sputum is the most widely used sample to diagnose active tuberculosis, but many people living with HIV are unable to produce sputum. Urine, in contrast, is readily available. We hypothesised that sample availability influences the diagnostic yield of various tuberculosis tests.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">In this systematic review and meta-analysis of individual participant data, we compared the diagnostic yield of point-of-care urine-based lipoarabinomannan tests with that of sputum-based nucleic acid amplification tests (NAATs) and sputum smear microscopy (SSM). We used microbiologically confirmed tuberculosis based on positive culture or NAAT from any body site as the denominator and accounted for sample provision. We searched PubMed, Web of Science, Embase, African Journals Online, and clinicaltrials.gov from database inception to Feb 24, 2022 for randomised controlled trials, cross-sectional studies, and cohort studies that assessed urine lipoarabinomannan point-of-care tests and sputum NAATs for active tuberculosis detection in participants irrespective of tuberculosis symptoms, HIV status, CD4 cell count, or study setting. We excluded studies in which recruitment was not consecutive, systematic, or random; provision of sputum or urine was an inclusion criterion; less than 30 participants were diagnosed with tuberculosis; early research assays without clearly defined cutoffs were tested; and humans were not studied. We extracted study-level data, and authors of eligible studies were invited to contribute deidentified individual participant data. The main outcomes were the tuberculosis diagnostic yields of urine lipoarabinomannan tests, sputum NAATs, and SSM. Diagnostic yields were predicted using Bayesian random-effects and mixed-effects meta-analyses. This study is registered with PROSPERO, CRD42021230337.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS">We identified 844 records, from which 20 datasets and 10&#x2008;202 participants (4561 [45%] male participants and 5641 [55%] female participants) were included in the meta-analysis. All studies assessed sputum Xpert (MTB/RIF or Ultra, Cepheid, Sunnyvale, CA, USA) and urine Alere Determine TB LAM (AlereLAM, Abbott, Chicago, IL, USA) in people living with HIV aged 15 years or older. Nearly all (9957 [98%] of 10&#x2008;202) participants provided urine, and 82% (8360 of 10&#x2008;202) provided sputum within 2 days. In studies that enrolled unselected inpatients irrespective of tuberculosis symptoms, only 54% (1084 of 1993) of participants provided sputum, whereas 99% (1966 of 1993) provided urine. Diagnostic yield was 41% (95% credible interval [CrI] 15-66) for AlereLAM, 61% (95% Crl 25-88) for Xpert, and 32% (95% Crl 10-55) for SSM. Heterogeneity existed across studies in the diagnostic yield, influenced by CD4 cell count, tuberculosis symptoms, and clinical setting. In predefined subgroup analyses, all tests had higher yields in symptomatic participants, and AlereLAM yield was higher in those with low CD4 counts and inpatients. AlereLAM and Xpert yields were similar among inpatients in studies enrolling unselected participants who were not assessed for tuberculosis symptoms (51% vs 47%). AlereLAM and Xpert together had a yield of 71% in unselected inpatients, supporting the implementation of combined testing strategies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERPRETATION">AlereLAM, with its rapid turnaround time and simplicity, should be prioritised to inform tuberculosis therapy among inpatients who are HIV-positive, regardless of symptoms or CD4 cell count. The yield of sputum-based tuberculosis tests is undermined by people living with HIV who cannot produce sputum, whereas nearly all participants are able to provide urine. The strengths of this meta-analysis are its large size, the carefully harmonised denominator, and the use of Bayesian random-effects and mixed-effects models to predict yields; however, data were geographically restricted, clinically diagnosed tuberculosis was not considered in the denominator, and little information exists on strategies for obtaining sputum samples.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FUNDING">FIND, the Global Alliance for Diagnostics.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2023 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an Open Access article under the CC BY 4.0 license. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Broger</LastName><ForeName>Tobias</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease and Tropical Medicine, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Koeppel</LastName><ForeName>Lisa</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease and Tropical Medicine, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Huerga</LastName><ForeName>Helena</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Field Epidemiology Department, Epicentre, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Miller</LastName><ForeName>Poppy</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New Zealand Institute for Plant and Food Research, Auckland, New Zealand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gupta-Wright</LastName><ForeName>Ankur</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Global Health, University College London, London, UK; Clinical Research Department, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Blanc</LastName><ForeName>Fran&#xe7;ois-Xavier</ForeName><Initials>FX</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Service de Pneumologie, l'institut du thorax, Nantes Universit&#xe9;, CHU Nantes, Nantes, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Esmail</LastName><ForeName>Aliasgar</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Lung Infection and Immunity, Division of Pulmonology, Department of Medicine and UCT Lung Institute, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa; South African MRC Centre for the Study of Antimicrobial Resistance, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Reeve</LastName><ForeName>Byron W P</ForeName><Initials>BWP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>DSI-NRF Centre of Excellence for Biomedical Tuberculosis Research, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, Cape Town, South Africa; South African Medical Research Council Centre for Tuberculosis Research, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, Cape Town, South Africa; Division of Molecular Biology and Human Genetics, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Floridia</LastName><ForeName>Marco</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Global Health, Istituto Superiore di Sanit&#xe0;, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kerkhoff</LastName><ForeName>Andrew D</ForeName><Initials>AD</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of HIV, Infectious Diseases and Global Medicine, Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital, San Francisco, CA, USA; Trauma Center, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA; Center for Tuberculosis, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ciccacci</LastName><ForeName>Fausto</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>UniCamillus, International University of Health and Medical Science, Rome, Italy; Community of Sant'Egidio, DREAM programme, Rome, Italy.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Kasaro</LastName><ForeName>Margaret P</ForeName><Initials>MP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Infectious Disease Research in Zambia, Lusaka, Zambia; UNC Global Projects, LLC Zambia, Lusaka, Zambia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thit</LastName><ForeName>Swe Swe</ForeName><Initials>SS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Medicine 2, Yangon, Myanmar.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bastard</LastName><ForeName>Mathieu</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Field Epidemiology Department, Epicentre, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferlazzo</LastName><ForeName>Gabriella</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, M&#xe9;decins Sans Fronti&#xe8;res, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoon</LastName><ForeName>Christina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, Division of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, Zuckerberg San Francisco General Hospital, San Francisco, CA, USA; Center for Tuberculosis, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Van Hoving</LastName><ForeName>Dani&#xeb;l J</ForeName><Initials>DJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Emergency Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa; Division of Emergency Medicine, Stellenbosch University, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sossen</LastName><ForeName>Bianca</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa; Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Garc&#xed;a</LastName><ForeName>Juan Ignacio</ForeName><Initials>JI</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Population Health Program, Tuberculosis Group, Texas Biomedical Research Institute, San Antonio, TX, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cummings</LastName><ForeName>Matthew J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Pulmonary, Allergy, and Critical Care Medicine, Columbia University Irving Medical Center, New York, NY, USA; Center for Infection and Immunity, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wake</LastName><ForeName>Rachel M</ForeName><Initials>RM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Healthcare-Associated Infections, Antimicrobial Resistance and Mycoses, National Institute for Communicable Diseases, Johannesburg, South Africa; Institute for Infection and Immunity, St George's University of London, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hanson</LastName><ForeName>Josh</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Kirby Institute, University of New South Wales, Sydney, NSW, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cattamanchi</LastName><ForeName>Adithya</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Tuberculosis, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA; Department of Medicine, Division of Pulmonary Diseases and Critical Care Medicine, University of California Irvine, Irvine, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Meintjes</LastName><ForeName>Graeme</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa; Wellcome Centre for Infectious Diseases Research in Africa, Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maartens</LastName><ForeName>Gary</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa; Wellcome Centre for Infectious Diseases Research in Africa, Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wood</LastName><ForeName>Robin</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Theron</LastName><ForeName>Grant</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>DSI-NRF Centre of Excellence for Biomedical Tuberculosis Research, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, Cape Town, South Africa; South African Medical Research Council Centre for Tuberculosis Research, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, Cape Town, South Africa; Division of Molecular Biology and Human Genetics, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Dheda</LastName><ForeName>Keertan</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Infectious and Tropical Diseases, Department of Immunology and Infection, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK; Centre for Lung Infection and Immunity, Division of Pulmonology, Department of Medicine and UCT Lung Institute, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa; South African MRC Centre for the Study of Antimicrobial Resistance, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olaru</LastName><ForeName>Ioana Diana</ForeName><Initials>ID</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease and Tropical Medicine, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany; Clinical Research Department, London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Denkinger</LastName><ForeName>Claudia M</ForeName><Initials>CM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Infectious Disease and Tropical Medicine, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany; German Center for Infection Research, partner site, Heidelberg University Hospital, Heidelberg, Germany. Electronic address: claudia.denkinger@uni-heidelberg.de.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><CollectiveName>TBYield Study Consortium</CollectiveName></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>MR/M007375/1</GrantID><Acronym>MRC_</Acronym><Agency>Medical Research Council</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>203135/Z/16/Z</GrantID><Acronym>WT_</Acronym><Agency>Wellcome Trust</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>214321/Z/18/Z</GrantID><Acronym>WT_</Acronym><Agency>Wellcome Trust</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet Glob Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101613665</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2214-109X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C050016">lipoarabinomannan</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D008070">Lipopolysaccharides</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Lancet Glob Health. 2023 Jun;11(6):e809-e810. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(23)00215-2.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">37202010</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013183" MajorTopicYN="N">Sputum</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001499" MajorTopicYN="N">Bayes Theorem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003430" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross-Sectional Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014376" MajorTopicYN="Y">Tuberculosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008070" MajorTopicYN="N">Lipopolysaccharides</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000652" MajorTopicYN="N">urine</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="Y">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012680" MajorTopicYN="N">Sensitivity and Specificity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009169" MajorTopicYN="Y">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>Declaration of interests TB reports patent applications in the field of tuberculosis detection, reports consulting fees from the FINDdx, and is a shareholder of Avelo. GMe was supported by the Wellcome Trust (214321/Z/18/Z and 203135/Z/16/Z) and the South African Research Chairs Initiative of the Department of Science and Technology and National Research Foundation of South Africa (grant number 64787). The opinions, findings, and conclusions expressed in this manuscript reflect those of the authors alone. All other authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement><InvestigatorList><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Oelofse</LastName><ForeName>Suzette</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Laureillard</LastName><ForeName>Didier</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andreotti</LastName><ForeName>Mauro</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chilyabanyama</LastName><ForeName>Obvious Nchimunya</ForeName><Initials>ON</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Welu</LastName><ForeName>Benjamin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Molfino</LastName><ForeName>Lucas</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mathabire R&#xfc;cker</LastName><ForeName>Sekai Chenai</ForeName><Initials>SC</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Szumilin</LastName><ForeName>Elisabeth</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cossa</LastName><ForeName>Loide</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mel&#xe9;ndez</LastName><ForeName>Johanna</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mbuthini</LastName><ForeName>Linda</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>O'Donnell</LastName><ForeName>Max</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jarvis</LastName><ForeName>Joseph N</ForeName><Initials>JN</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ndlangalavu</LastName><ForeName>Gcobisa</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials></Investigator><Investigator ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fielding</LastName><ForeName>Katherine</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials></Investigator></InvestigatorList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>4</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>58</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37202025</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(23)00135-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2214-109X(23)00135-3</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>