<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">25111394</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2016</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>8</Issue><PubDate><Year>2014</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Nowcasting the spread of chikungunya virus in the Americas.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e104915</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e104915</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e104915</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0104915</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">In December 2013, the first locally-acquired chikungunya virus (CHIKV) infections in the Americas were reported in the Caribbean. As of May 16, 55,992 cases had been reported and the outbreak was still spreading. Identification of newly affected locations is paramount to intervention activities, but challenging due to limitations of current data on the outbreak and on CHIKV transmission. We developed models to make probabilistic predictions of spread based on current data considering these limitations.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS AND FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Branching process models capturing travel patterns, local infection prevalence, climate dependent transmission factors, and associated uncertainty estimates were developed to predict probable locations for the arrival of CHIKV-infected travelers and for the initiation of local transmission. Many international cities and areas close to where transmission has already occurred were likely to have received infected travelers. Of the ten locations predicted to be the most likely locations for introduced CHIKV transmission in the first four months of the outbreak, eight had reported local cases by the end of April. Eight additional locations were likely to have had introduction leading to local transmission in April, but with substantial uncertainty.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Branching process models can characterize the risk of CHIKV introduction and spread during the ongoing outbreak. Local transmission of CHIKV is currently likely in several Caribbean locations and possible, though uncertain, for other locations in the continental United States, Central America, and South America. This modeling framework may also be useful for other outbreaks where the risk of pathogen spread over heterogeneous transportation networks must be rapidly assessed on the basis of limited information.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Johansson</LastName><ForeName>Michael A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vector-Borne Diseases, Centers for Diseases Control and Prevention, San Juan, PR.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Powers</LastName><ForeName>Ann M</ForeName><Initials>AM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vector-Borne Diseases, Centers for Diseases Control and Prevention, Fort Collins, Colorado, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pesik</LastName><ForeName>Nicki</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Global Migration and Quarantine, Centers for Diseases Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cohen</LastName><ForeName>Nicole J</ForeName><Initials>NJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Global Migration and Quarantine, Centers for Diseases Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Staples</LastName><ForeName>J Erin</ForeName><Initials>JE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Vector-Borne Diseases, Centers for Diseases Control and Prevention, Fort Collins, Colorado, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2014</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000330" MajorTopicYN="N">Aedes</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D065632" MajorTopicYN="N">Chikungunya Fever</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="Y">transmission</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002646" MajorTopicYN="N">Chikungunya virus</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000472" MajorTopicYN="Y">pathogenicity</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007303" MajorTopicYN="N">Insect Vectors</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009656" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">North America</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013020" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">South America</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014195" MajorTopicYN="N">Travel</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement><b>Competing Interests: </b>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2014</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2014</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2014</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2014</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2016</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2014</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25111394</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4128737</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-14-22376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Leparc-Goffart I, Nougairede A, Cassadou S, Prat C, de Lamballerie X (2014) Chikungunya in the Americas. Lancet 383: 514.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24506907</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sergon K, Yahaya AA, Brown J, Bedja SA, Mlindasse M, et al. (2007) Seroprevalence of Chikungunya virus infection on Grande Comore Island, union of the Comoros, 2005. The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene 76: 1189&#x2013;1193.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17556634</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gerardin P, Guernier V, Perrau J, Fianu A, Le Roux K, et al. (2008) Estimating Chikungunya prevalence in La Reunion Island outbreak by serosurveys: two methods for two critical times of the epidemic. BMC infectious diseases 8: 99.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2528011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18662384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sergon K, Njuguna C, Kalani R, Ofula V, Onyango C, et al. (2008) Seroprevalence of Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) infection on Lamu Island, Kenya, October 2004. The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene 78: 333&#x2013;337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18256441</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (2011) Preparedness and Response for Chikungunya Virus Introduction in the Americas. Washington D.C.: Pan American Health Organization. 149 p.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2014) Chikungunya in the Americas.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Singh KR, Pavri KM (1967) Experimental studies with chikungunya virus in Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus. Acta virologica 11: 517&#x2013;526.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4383887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Turell MJ, Beaman JR, Tammariello RF (1992) Susceptibility of selected strains of Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus (Diptera: Culicidae) to chikungunya virus. Journal of medical entomology 29: 49&#x2013;53.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1313111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsetsarkin KA, Vanlandingham DL, McGee CE, Higgs S (2007) A single mutation in chikungunya virus affects vector specificity and epidemic potential. PLoS pathogens 3: e201.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2134949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18069894</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vazeille M, Moutailler S, Coudrier D, Rousseaux C, Khun H, et al. (2007) Two Chikungunya isolates from the outbreak of La Reunion (Indian Ocean) exhibit different patterns of infection in the mosquito, Aedes albopictus. PloS one 2: e1168.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2064959</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18000540</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dubrulle M, Mousson L, Moutailler S, Vazeille M, Failloux AB (2009) Chikungunya virus and Aedes mosquitoes: saliva is infectious as soon as two days after oral infection. PloS one 4: e5895.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2690823</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19521520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pesko K, Westbrook CJ, Mores CN, Lounibos LP, Reiskind MH (2009) Effects of infectious virus dose and bloodmeal delivery method on susceptibility of Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus to chikungunya virus. Journal of medical entomology 46: 395&#x2013;399.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2716074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19351094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsetsarkin KA, Chen R, Leal G, Forrester N, Higgs S, et al. (2011) Chikungunya virus emergence is constrained in Asia by lineage-specific adaptive landscapes. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 108: 7872&#x2013;7877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3093459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21518887</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johansson MA, Arana-Vizcarrondo N, Biggerstaff BJ, Gallagher N, Marano N, et al. (2012) Assessing the risk of international spread of yellow fever virus: a mathematical analysis of an urban outbreak in Asuncion, 2008. The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene 86: 349&#x2013;358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3269406</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22302873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anderson RM, May RM (1991) Infectious diseases of humans: dynamics and control. Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press. viii, 757 p. p.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalnay E, Kanamitsu M, Kistler R, Collins W, Deaven D, et al. (1996) The NCEP/NCAR 40-year reanalysis project. 77: 437&#x2013;471.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (2014) Cumulative Number of Reported Cases of Chikungunya Fever in the Americas: Epidemiologic Week 1. Pan American Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cire Antilles Guyane (2014) Le chikungunya dans les Antilles-Guyane. Centre d&#x2019;Affaires AGORA. 4 4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (2014) Number of Reported Cases of Chikungunya Fever in the Americas: Epidemiologic Week 5. Pan American Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cire Antilles Guyane (2014) Le chikungunya dans les Antilles-Guyane. Centre d&#x2019;Affaires AGORA. 8 8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (2014) Number of Reported Cases of Chikungunya Fever in the Americas: Epidemiologic Week 9. Pan American Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (2014) Number of Reported Cases of Chikungunya Fever in the Americas: Epidemiologic Week 13. Pan American Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan American Health Organization (2014) Number of Reported Cases of Chikungunya Fever in the Americas: Epidemiologic Week 18. Pan American Health Organization.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Retuya T, Ting DL, Dacula B, Lanada JM, Roque V, et al. (1998) Chikungunya fever outbreak in an agricultural village in Indang, Cavite, Philippines. 27: 93&#x2013;96.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sissoko D, Moendandze A, Malvy D, Giry C, Ezzedine K, et al. (2008) Seroprevalence and risk factors of chikungunya virus infection in Mayotte, Indian Ocean, 2005&#x2013;2006: a population-based survey. PloS one 3: e3066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2518850</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18725980</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moro ML, Gagliotti C, Silvi G, Angelini R, Sambri V, et al. (2010) Chikungunya virus in North-Eastern Italy: a seroprevalence survey. The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene 82: 508&#x2013;511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2829919</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20207883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanciotti RS, Kosoy OL, Laven JJ, Panella AJ, Velez JO, et al. (2007) Chikungunya virus in US travelers returning from India, 2006. Emerging infectious diseases 13: 764&#x2013;767.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2738459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17553261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laurent P, Le Roux K, Grivard P, Bertil G, Naze F, et al. (2007) Development of a sensitive real-time reverse transcriptase PCR assay with an internal control to detect and quantify chikungunya virus. Clinical chemistry 53: 1408&#x2013;1414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17586592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appassakij H, Khuntikij P, Kemapunmanus M, Wutthanarungsan R, Silpapojakul K (2013) Viremic profiles in asymptomatic and symptomatic chikungunya fever: a blood transfusion threat? Transfusion 53: 2567&#x2013;2574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23176378</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chusri S, Siripaitoon P, Silpapojakul K, Hortiwakul T, Charernmak B, et al. (2014) Kinetics of Chikungunya Infections during an Outbreak in Southern Thailand, 2008&#x2013;2009. The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene 90: 410&#x2013;417.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3945684</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24493674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liumbruno GM, Calteri D, Petropulacos K, Mattivi A, Po C, et al. (2008) The Chikungunya epidemic in Italy and its repercussion on the blood system. Blood transfusion&#x200a;=&#x200a;Trasfusione del sangue 6: 199&#x2013;210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2626913</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19112735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudolph KE, Lessler J, Moloney RM, Kmush B, Cummings DA (2014) Incubation periods of mosquito-borne viral infections: a systematic review. The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene 90: 882&#x2013;891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4015582</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24639305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Scott TW, Amerasinghe PH, Morrison AC, Lorenz LH, Clark GG, et al.  (2000) Longitudinal studies of <i>Aedes aegypti</i> (Diptera: Culicidae) in Thailand and Puerto Rico: blood feeding frequency. J Med Entomol
37: 89&#x2013;101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15218911</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chan M, Johansson MA (2012) The incubation periods of dengue viruses. PloS one 7: e50972.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3511440</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23226436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brady OJ, Johansson MA, Guerra CA, Bhatt S, Golding N, et al. (2013) Modelling adult Aedes aegypti and Aedes albopictus survival at different temperatures in laboratory and field settings. Parasites &amp; vectors 6: 351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3867219</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24330720</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boelle PY, Thomas G, Vergu E, Renault P, Valleron AJ, et al. (2008) Investigating transmission in a two-wave epidemic of Chikungunya fever, Reunion Island. Vector borne and zoonotic diseases 8: 207&#x2013;217.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18171107</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Massad E, Ma S, Burattini MN, Tun Y, Coutinho FA, et al. (2008) The risk of chikungunya fever in a dengue-endemic area. Journal of travel medicine 15: 147&#x2013;155.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18494691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yakob L, Clements AC (2013) A mathematical model of chikungunya dynamics and control: the major epidemic on Reunion Island. PloS one 8: e57448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3590184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23554860</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Government of the Virgin Islands (2014) Three Cases Of The Chickungunya Confirmed In The Virgin Islands.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Bortel W, Dorleans F, Rosine J, Blateau A, Rousseau D, et al. (2014) Chikungunya outbreak in the Caribbean region, December 2013 to March 2014, and the significance for the European Union. 19: 13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24721539</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>