<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">19864468</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2010</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>17</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-1719</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>27</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Feb</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Molecular biology and evolution</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Mol Biol Evol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Phylodynamics of HIV-1 from a phase-III AIDS vaccine trial in North America.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>417</StartPage><EndPage>425</EndPage><MedlinePgn>417-25</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/molbev/msp254</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>In 2003, a phase III placebo-controlled trial (VAX004) of a candidate HIV-1 vaccine (AIDSVAX B/B) was completed in 5,403 volunteers at high risk for HIV-1 infection from North America and the Netherlands. A total of 368 individuals became infected with HIV-1 during the trial. The envelope glycoprotein gene (gp120) from the HIV-1 subtype B viruses infecting 349 patients was sequenced from clinical samples taken as close as possible to the time of diagnosis, rendering a final data set of 1,047 sequences (1,032 from North America and 15 from the Netherlands). Here, we used these data in combination with other sequences available in public databases to assess HIV-1 variation as a function of vaccination treatment, geographic region, race, risk behavior, and viral load. Viral samples did not show any phylogenetic structure for any of these factors, but individuals with different viral loads showed significant differences (P = 0.009) in genetic diversity. The estimated time of emergence of HIV-1 subtype B was 1966-1970. Despite the fact that the number of AIDS cases has decreased in North America since the early 90s, HIV-1 genetic diversity seems to have remained almost constant over time. This study represents one of the largest molecular epidemiologic surveys of viruses responsible for new HIV-1 infections in North America and could help the selection of epidemiologically representative vaccine antigens to include in the next generation of candidate HIV-1 vaccines.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>P&#xe9;rez-Losada</LastName><ForeName>Marcos</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>CIBIO, Centro de Investiga&#xe7;&#xe3;o em Biodiversidade e Recursos Gen&#xe9;ticos, Universidade do Porto, Vair&#xe3;o, Portugal. mlosada323@gmail.com</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jobes</LastName><ForeName>David V</ForeName><Initials>DV</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sinangil</LastName><ForeName>Faruk</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Crandall</LastName><ForeName>Keith A</ForeName><Initials>KA</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Posada</LastName><ForeName>David</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Berman</LastName><ForeName>Phillip W</ForeName><Initials>PW</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2009</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Mol Biol Evol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8501455</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0737-4038</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D016915">AIDS Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D015699">HIV Envelope Protein gp120</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016915" MajorTopicYN="Y">AIDS Vaccines</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017326" MajorTopicYN="N">Clinical Trials, Phase III as Topic</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015699" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Envelope Protein gp120</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="Y">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015497" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV-1</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="Y">genetics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="Y">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009656" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">North America</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="Y">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011157" MajorTopicYN="Y">Population Dynamics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2009</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2009</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2009</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19864468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2806245</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/molbev/msp254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">msp254</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Akaike H. A new look at the statistical model identification. IEEE Trans Automat Contr. 1974;19:716&#x2013;723.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Castresana J. Selection of conserved blocks from multiple alignments for their use in phylogenetic analysis. Mol Biol Evol. 2000;17:540&#x2013;552.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10742046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. HIV/AIDS surveillance report. 2007. Atlanta (GA): Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) 2008.  [cited 2009 Dec 4] Available from:  http://www.cdc.gov.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chohan B, Lang D, Sagar M, Korber B, Lavreys L, Richardson B, Overbaugh J. Selection for human immunodeficiency virus type 1 envelope glycosylation variants with shorter V1-V2 loop sequences occurs during transmission of certain genetic subtypes and may impact viral RNA levels. J Virol. 2005;79:6528&#x2013;6531.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1091724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15858037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark SJ, Saag MS, Decker WD, Campbell-Hill S, Roberson JL, Veldkamp PJ, Kappes JC, Hahn BH, Shaw GM. High titers of cytopathic virus in plasma of patients with symptomatic primary HIV-1 infection. New Engl J Med. 1991;324:954&#x2013;960.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1900576</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daar ES, Moudgil T, Meyer RD, Ho DD. Transient high levels of viremia in patients with primary human immunodeficiency virus type 1 infection. New Engl J Med. 1991;324:961&#x2013;964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1823118</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Derdeyn CA, Decker JM, Bibollet-Ruche F, et al. (14 co-authors) Envelope-constrained neutralization-sensitive HIV-1 after heterosexual transmission. Science. 2004;303:2019&#x2013;2022.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15044802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond AJ, Ho SYW, Phillips MJ, Rambaut A. Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence. PLoS Biol. 2006;4:e88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1395354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16683862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond AJ, Rambaut A. BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees. BMC Evol Biol. 2007;7:214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2247476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17996036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond AJ, Rambaut A, Shapiro B, Pybus OG. Bayesian coalescent inference of past population dynamics from molecular sequences. Mol Biol Evol. 2005;22:1185&#x2013;1192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15703244</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein J. Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap. Evolution. 1985;39:783&#x2013;791.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28561359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrante P, Delbue S, Mancuso R. The manifestation of AIDS in Africa: an epidemiological overview. J Neurovirol. 2005;11(Suppl 1):50&#x2013;57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15960239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiebig EW, Wright DJ, Rawal BD, et al. (11 co-authors) Dynamics of HIV viremia and antibody seroconversion in plasma donors: implications for diagnosis and staging of primary HIV infection. AIDS. 2003;17:1871&#x2013;1879.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12960819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flynn NM, Forthal DN, Harro CD, Judson FN, Mayer KH, Para MF. Placebo-controlled phase 3 trial of a recombinant glycoprotein 120 vaccine to prevent HIV-1 infection. J Infect Dis. 2005;191:654&#x2013;665.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15688278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gilbert MT, Rambaut A, Wlasiuk G, Spira TJ, Pitchenik AE, Worobey M. The emergence of HIV/AIDS in the Americas and beyond. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2007;104:18566&#x2013;18570.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2141817</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17978186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gray ES, Moore PL, Choge IA, et al. (13 co-authors) Neutralizing antibody responses in acute human immunodeficiency virus type 1 subtype C infection. J Virol. 2007;81:6187&#x2013;6196.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1900112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17409164</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jaffe HW, Darrow WW, Echenberg DF, et al. (11 co-authors) The acquired immunodeficiency syndrome in a cohort of homosexual men. A six-year follow-up study. Ann Intern Med. 1985;103:210&#x2013;214.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2990275</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jobes DV, Daoust M, Nguyen V, Padua A, Michele S, Lock MD, Chen A, Sinangil F, Berman PW. High incidence of unusual cysteine variants in gp120 envelope proteins from early HIV type 1 infections from a phase 3 vaccine efficacy trial. AIDS Res Hum Retrovir. 2006;22:1014&#x2013;1021.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17067272</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katoh K, Kuma K, Toh H, Miyata T. MAFFT version 5: improvement in accuracy of multiple sequence alignment. Nucleic Acids Res. 2005;33:511&#x2013;518.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC548345</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15661851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keele BF, Giorgi EE, Salazar-Gonzalez JF, et al. (37 co-authors) Identification and characterization of transmitted and early founder virus envelopes in primary HIV-1 infection. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2008;105:7552&#x2013;7557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2387184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18490657</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korber B, Muldoon M, Theiler J, Gao F, Gupta R, Lapedes A, Hahn BH, Wolinsky S, Bhattacharya T. Timing the ancestor of the HIV-1 pandemic strains. Science. 2000;288:1789&#x2013;1796.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10846155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kosakovsky Pond SL, Frost SDW. Not so different after all: a comparison of methods for detecting amino acid sites under selection. Mol Biol Evol. 2005;22:1208&#x2013;1222.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15703242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kosakovsky Pond SL, Frost SDW, Muse SV. HyPhy: hypothesis testing using phylogenies. Bioinformatics. 2005;21:676&#x2013;679.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15509596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McVean G, Awadalla P, Fearnhead P. A coalescent-based method for detecting and estimating recombination from gene sequences. Genetics. 2002;160:1231&#x2013;1241.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1462015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11901136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oelrichs RB, Crowe SM. The molecular epidemiology of HIV-1 in South and East Asia. Curr HIV Res. 2003;1:239&#x2013;248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15043206</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ou CY, Takebe Y, Weniger BG, Luo CC, Kalish ML, Auwanit W, Yamazaki S, Gayle HD, Young NL, Schochetman G. Independent introduction of two major HIV-1 genotypes into distinct high-risk populations in Thailand. Lancet. 1993;341:1171&#x2013;1174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8098076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papathanasopoulos MA, Hunt GM, Tiemessen CT. Evolution and diversity of HIV-1 in Africa&#x2014;a review. Virus Genes. 2003;26:151&#x2013;163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12803467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peeters M, Toure-Kane C, Nkengasong JN. Genetic diversity of HIV in Africa: impact on diagnosis, treatment, vaccine development and trials. AIDS. 2003;17:2547&#x2013;2560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14685049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>P&#xe9;rez-Losada M, Posada D, Arenas M, Jobes DV, Sinangil F, Berman PW, Crandall KA. Ethnic differences in the adaptation rate of HIV gp120 from a vaccine trial. Retrovirology. 2009;6:67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2717047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19604405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Posada D, Crandall KA. Modeltest: testing the model of DNA substitution. Bioinformatics. 1998;14:817&#x2013;818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9918953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quinn TC, Wawer MJ, Sewankambo N, Serwadda D, Li C, Wabwire-Mangen F, Meehan MO, Lutalo T, Gray RH. Viral load and heterosexual transmission of human immunodeficiency virus type 1. Rakai Project Study Group. New Engl. J Med. 2000;342:921&#x2013;929.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10738050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rambaut A, Drummond AJ.  Tracer: MCMC trace analysis tool. Oxford: University of Oxford; 2003.  Available from:  http://evolve.zoo.ox.ac.uk.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Development Core Team. R Foundation for Statistical Computing. Vienna: Austria; 2008. R: a language and environment for statistical computing. Available from: http://www.R-project.org.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richman DD, Wrin T, Little SJ, Petropoulos CJ. Rapid evolution of the neutralizing antibody response to HIV type 1 infection. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2003;100:4144&#x2013;4149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC153062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12644702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ronquist F, Huelsenbeck JP. MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference under mixed models. Bioinformatics. 2003;19:1572&#x2013;1574.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12912839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shankarappa R, Margolick JB, Gange SJ, et al. (12 co-authors) Consistent viral evolutionary changes associated with the progression of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 infection. J Virol. 1999;73:10489&#x2013;10502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC113104</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10559367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevens CE, Taylor PE, Zang EA, Morrison JM, Harley EJ, Rodriguez de Cordoba S, Bacino C, Ting RC, Bodner AJ, Sarngadharan MG. Human T-cell lymphotropic virus type III infection in a cohort of homosexual men in New York City. JAMA. 1986;255:2167&#x2013;2172.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3007789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tavar&#xe9; S. Some probabilistic and statistical problems in the analysis of DNA sequences. In: Miura RM, editor. Some mathematical questions in biology&#x2014;DNA sequence analysis. Vol. 17. Providence (RI): American Mathematical Society; 1986. pp. 57&#x2013;86.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tessier SF, Remy G, Louis JP, Trebucq A. The frontline of HIV1 diffusion in the Central African region: a geographical and epidemiological perspective. Int J Epidemiol. 1993;22:127&#x2013;134.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8449632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tibayrenc M. Bridging the gap between molecular epidemiologists and evolutionists. Trends Microbiol. 2005;13:575&#x2013;580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16214342</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Report on the global HIV/AIDS epidemic. Joint United Nations programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS) 2008. Geneva (Switzerland): WHO Library Cataloguing-in-Publication Data; 2008. p. 362.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watterson GA. On the number of segregating sites in genetical models without recombination. Theor Popul Biol. 1975;7:256&#x2013;276.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1145509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei X, Decker JM, Wang S, et al. (15 co-authors) Antibody neutralization and escape by HIV-1. Nature. 2003;422:307&#x2013;312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12646921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weniger BG, Takebe Y, Ou CY, Yamazaki S. The molecular epidemiology of HIV in Asia. AIDS. 1994;8(Suppl 2):S13&#x2013;S28.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7857556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zwickl DJ.  Genetic algorithm approaches for the phylogenetic analysis of large biological sequence datasets under the maximum likelihood criterion. Austin (TX): The University of Texas at Austin; 2006.  Available from:  http://www.bio.utexas.edu/faculty/antisense/garli/Garli.html.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>