<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">27798403</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2018</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>29</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1076-836X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>66</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2017</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Systematic biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Syst Biol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A Relaxed Directional Random Walk Model for Phylogenetic Trait Evolution.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>299</StartPage><EndPage>319</EndPage><MedlinePgn>299-319</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/sysbio/syw093</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Understanding the processes that give rise to quantitative measurements associated with molecular sequence data remains an important issue in statistical phylogenetics. Examples of such measurements include geographic coordinates in the context of phylogeography and phenotypic traits in the context of comparative studies. A popular approach is to model the evolution of continuously varying traits as a Brownian diffusion process acting on a phylogenetic tree. However, standard Brownian diffusion is quite restrictive and may not accurately characterize certain trait evolutionary processes. Here, we relax one of the major restrictions of standard Brownian diffusion by incorporating a nontrivial estimable mean into the process. We introduce a relaxed directional random walk (RDRW) model for the evolution of multivariate continuously varying traits along a phylogenetic tree. Notably, the RDRW model accommodates branch-specific variation of directional trends while preserving model identifiability. Furthermore, our development of a computationally efficient dynamic programming approach to compute the data likelihood enables scaling of our method to large data sets frequently encountered in phylogenetic comparative studies and viral evolution. We implement the RDRW model in a Bayesian inference framework to simultaneously reconstruct the evolutionary histories of molecular sequence data and associated multivariate continuous trait data, and provide tools to visualize evolutionary reconstructions. We demonstrate the performance of our model on synthetic data, and we illustrate its utility in two viral examples. First, we examine the spatiotemporal spread of HIV-1 in central Africa and show that the RDRW model uncovers a clearer, more detailed picture of the dynamics of viral dispersal than standard Brownian diffusion. Second, we study antigenic evolution in the context of HIV-1 resistance to three broadly neutralizing antibodies. Our analysis reveals evidence of a continuous drift at the HIV-1 population level towards enhanced resistance to neutralization by the VRC01 monoclonal antibody over the course of the epidemic. [Brownian Motion; Diffusion Processes; Phylodynamics; Phylogenetics; Phylogeography; Trait Evolution.].</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s) 2016. Published by Oxford University Press, on behalf of the Society of Systematic Biologists. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gill</LastName><ForeName>Mandev S</ForeName><Initials>MS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Statistics, Columbia University, New York, NY 10027, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tung Ho</LastName><ForeName>Lam Si</ForeName><Initials>LS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, Jonathan and Karin Fielding School of Public Health, University of California, Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Baele</LastName><ForeName>Guy</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Rega Institute, KU Leuven, Minderbroedersstaat 10, 3000, Leuven, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lemey</LastName><ForeName>Philippe</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Rega Institute, KU Leuven, Minderbroedersstaat 10, 3000, Leuven, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suchard</LastName><ForeName>Marc A</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics, Jonathan and Karin Fielding School of Public Health, University of California, Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomathematics, David Geffen School of Medicine at UCLA, University of California, Los Angeles, CA 90095, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Human Genetics, David Geffen School of Medicine at UCLA, Universtiy of California, Los Angeles, CA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI107034</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>T32 AI007370</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 HG006139</GrantID><Acronym>HG</Acronym><Agency>NHGRI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 LM011247</GrantID><Acronym>LM</Acronym><Agency>NLM NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>260864</GrantID><Acronym>ERC_</Acronym><Agency>European Research Council</Agency><Country>International</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Syst Biol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9302532</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1063-5157</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000349" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Africa</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001499" MajorTopicYN="N">Bayes Theorem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002965" MajorTopicYN="N">Classification</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="Y">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="N">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015497" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV-1</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008954" MajorTopicYN="Y">Models, Biological</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010641" MajorTopicYN="N">Phenotype</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010802" MajorTopicYN="Y">Phylogeny</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2015</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2016</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2016</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2018</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>30</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2016</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2018</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27798403</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6075548</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syw093</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">syw093</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Agrawal A.,, Fishbein M. 2008. Phylogenetic escalation and decline of plant defense strategies. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 105:10057&#x2013;10060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2481309</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18645183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrawal A.,, Fishbein M.,, Halitschke R.,, Hastings A.,, Rabosky D.,, Rasmann S. 2009. Evidence for adaptive radiation from a phylogenetic study of plant defenses. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 106:18067&#x2013;18072.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2775318</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19805160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allicock O. M.,, Lemey P.,, Tatem A. J.,, Pybus O. G.,, Bennett S. N.,, Mueller B. A.,, Suchard M. A.,, Foster J. E.,, Rambaut A.,, Carrington C.V. 2012. Phylogeography and population dynamics of dengue viruses in the americas. Mol. Biol. Evol. 29:1533&#x2013;1543.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3529620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22319149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baele G.,, Lemey P.,, Suchard M. A. 2016a. Genealogical working distributions for bayesian model testing with phylogenetic uncertainty. Sys. Biol. 65:250&#x2013;264.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5009437</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26526428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baele G.,, Suchard M. A.,, Rambaut A.,, Lemey, P. 2016b. Emerging concepts of data integration in pathogen phylodynamics. Systematic Biology, in press.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5837209</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28173504</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barouch D. 2008. Challenges in the development of an HIV-1 vaccine. Nature 455:613&#x2013;619.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2572109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18833271</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bartoszek K.,, Pienaar J.,, Mostad P.,, Andersson S.,, Hansen, T. 2012. A phylogenetic comparative method for studying multivariate adaptation. J. Theor. Biol. 314:204&#x2013;215.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22940235</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beaulieu J.,, Jhwueng D.,, Boettiger C.,, O&#x2019;Meara, B. 2012. Modeling stabilizing selection: Expanding the Ornstein&#x2013;Uhlenbeck model of adaptive evolution. Evolution 66:2369&#x2013;2383.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22834738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bedford T.,, Suchard M.,, Lemey P.,, Dudas G.,, Gregory V.,, Hay A.,, McCauley J.,, Russell C.,, Smith D.,, Rambaut, A. 2014. Integrating influenza antigenic dynamics with molecular evolution. Elife 3:e01914.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3909918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24497547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett S.,, Drummond A.,, Kapan D.,, Suchard M.,, Munoz-Jordan J.,, Pybus O.,, Holmes E.,, Gubler D. 2010. Epidemic dynamics revealed in dengue evolution. Mol. Biol. Evol. 27:811&#x2013;818.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2877535</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19965886</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biek R.,, Henderson J.,, Waller L.,, Rupprecht C.,, Real L. 2007. A high-resolution genetic signature of demographic and spatial expansion in epizootic rabies virus. PNAS 104:7993&#x2013;7998.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1876560</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17470818</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bikandou B.,, Ndoundou-Nkodia M.,, Niama F.,, Ekwalanga M.,, Obengui O.,, Taty-Taty R.,, Parra H.,, Saragosti S. 2004. Genetic subtyping of gag and env regions of HIV type 1 isolates in the Republic of Congo. AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses 20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15585087</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bikandou B.,, Takehisa J.,, Mboudjeka I.,, Ido E.,, Kuwata T.,, Miyazaki Y.,, Moriyama H.,, Harada Y.,, Taniguchi Y.,, Ichimura H.,, Ikeda M.,, Ndolo P.,, Nzoukoudi M.,, M&#x2019;Vouenze R.,, M&#x2019;Pandi M.,, Parra H.,, M&#x2019;Pele P.,, Hayami M. 2000. Genetic subtypes of HIV type 1 in Republic of Congo. AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses 16:613&#x2013;619.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10791871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bloomquist E. W.,, Lemey P.,, Suchard M. A. 2010. Three roads diverged? routes to phylogeographic inference. Trends Ecol. &amp; Evol. 25:626&#x2013;632.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2956787</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20863591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boucher F., D&#xe9;mery V. 2016. Inferring bounded evolution in phenotypic characters from phylogenetic comparative data. Syst. Biol. 65:651&#x2013;661.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26865274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouvin-Pley M.,, Morgand M.,, Moreau A.,, Jestin P.,, Simonnet C.,, Tran L.,, Goujard C.,, Meyer L.,, Barin F.,, Braiband M. 2013. Evidence for a continuous drift of the HIV-1 species towards higher resistance to neutralizing antibodies over the course of the epidemic. PLoS Pathog. 9:e1003477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3701719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23853594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown R. 1828. A brief account of microscopial observations made in the months of June, July and August, 1827, on the particles contained in the pollen of plants; and on the general existence of active molecules in organic and inorganic bodies. Philos. Mag. 4:161&#x2013;173.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bunnik E.,, Euler Z.,, Welkers M.,, Boeser-Nunnink B., Grijsen M., Prins J., Schuitemaker H. 2010. Adaptation of HIV-1 envelope gp120 to humoral immunity at a population level. Nat. Med. 16:995&#x2013;997.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20802498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burton D. 2002. Antibodies, viruses and vaccines. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 2:706&#x2013;713.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12209139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burton D. 2004. HIV vaccine design and the neutralizing antibody problem. Nat. Immunol. 5:233&#x2013;236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14985706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butler M., King A. 2004. Phylogenetic comparative analysis: a modeling approach for adaptive evolution. Am. Nat. 164.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29641928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chipman, H.,, George E.,, McCulloch R. 2001. The practical implementation of Bayesian model selection. IMS Lecture Notes - Monograph Series 38:67&#x2013;134.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond A.,, Ho S.,, Phillips M.,, Rambaut A. 2006. Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence. PLoS Biol. 4:e88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1395354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16683862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond A., Suchard M. 2010. Bayesian random local clocks, or one rate to rule them all. BMC Biol. 8:114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2949620</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20807414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Drummond A. J.,, Suchard M. A.,, Xie D.,, Rambaut A. 2012. Bayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 17.. Mol. Biol. Evol. 29:1969&#x2013;1973.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3408070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22367748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eastman J.,, Alfaro M.,, Joyce P.,, Hipp A.,, Harmon L. 2011. A novel comparative method for identifying shifts in the rate of character evolution on trees. Evolution 65:3578&#x2013;89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22133227</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Euler Z.,, Bunnik E.,, Burger J.,, Boeser-Nunnink B.,, Grijsen M.,, Prins J.,, Schuitemaker H. 2011. Activity of broadly neutralizing antibodies, including PG9, PG16, and VRC01, against recently transmitted subtype B HIV-1 variants from early and late in the epidemic. J. Virol. 85:7236&#x2013;7245.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3126573</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21561918</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Faria N.,, Rambaut A.,, Suchard M.,, Baele G.,, Bedford T.,, Ward M.,, Tatem A.,, Sousa J.,, Arinaminpathy N.,, Pepin J.,, Posada D.,, Peeters M.,, Pybus O.,, Lemey P. 2014. The early spead and epidemic ignition of HIV-1 in human populations. Science 346:56&#x2013;61.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4254776</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25278604</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein J. 1973. Maximum-likelihood estimation of evolutionary trees from continuous characters. Am. J. Hum. Genet. 25:471&#x2013;492.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1762641</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4741844</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein J. 1981. Evolutionary trees from DNA sequences: a maximum likelihood approach. J. Mol. Evol. 13:93&#x2013;104.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7288891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein J. 1985. Phylogenies and the comparative method. Am. Nat. 125:1&#x2013;15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Felsenstein J. 1988. Phylogenies and quantitative characters. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 19:445&#x2013;471.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freckleton R.,, Harvey P.,, Pagel M. 2002. Phylogenetic analysis and comparative data: A test and review of evidence. Am. Nat. 160:712&#x2013;726.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18707460</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>George E.,, McCulloch R. 1993. Variable selection via Gibbs sampling. JASA 88:881&#x2013;889.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gill M.,, Lemey P.,, Bennett S.,, Biek R.,, Suchard M. 2016. Understanding past population dynamics: Bayesian coalescent-based modeling with covariates. Syst. Biol. 65:1041&#x2013;1056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5066065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27368344</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gill M.,, Lemey P.,, Faria N.,, Rambaut A.,, Shapiro B.,, Suchard M. 2013. Improving Bayesian population dynamics inference: a coalescent-based model for multiple loci. Mol. Biol. Evol. 30:713&#x2013;724.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3563973</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23180580</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grenfell B.,, Pybus O.,, Gog J.,, Wood J.,, Daly J.,, Mumford J.,, Holmes E. 2004. Unifying the epidemiological and evolutionary dynamics of pathogens. Science 303:327&#x2013;332.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14726583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen T. 1997. Stabilizing selection and the comparative analysis of adaptation. Evolution 52:1341&#x2013;1351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28568616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen T.,, Martins E. 1996. Translating between microevolutionary process and macroevolutionary patterns: the correlation structure of interspecific data. Evolution 50:1404&#x2013;1417.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28565714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hansen T.,, Pienaar J.,, Orzack S. 2008. A comparative method for studying adaptation to a randomly evolving environment. Evolution 62:1965&#x2013;1967.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18452574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey P.,, Pagel M. 1991. The comparative method in evolutionary biology. Oxford, UK:Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hasegawa M.,, Kishino H.,, Yano T. 1985. Dating the human-ape splitting by a molecular clock of mitochondrial DNA. J. Mol. Evol. 22:160&#x2013;174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3934395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hastings W. 1970. Monte Carlo sampling methods using Markov chains and their applications. Biometrika 57:97&#x2013;109.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huelsenbeck J.,, Rannala B. 2003. Detecting correlation between characters in a comparative analysis with uncertain phylogeny. Evolution 57:1237&#x2013;1247.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12894932</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt G. 2006. Fitting and comparing models of phyletic evolution: Random walks and beyond. Paleobiology 32:578&#x2013;601.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hunt G. 2007. The relative importance of directional change, random walks, and stasis in the evolution of fossil lineages. Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. USA 104:18404&#x2013;18408.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2141789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18003931</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeffreys H. 1935. Some tests of significance, treated by the theory of probability. Math. Proc. Cambridge Philos. Soc. 31:203&#x2013;222.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeffreys H. 1961. Theory of Probability. Oxford, UK:Oxford University Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnston, M.,, Fauci A. 2007. An HIV vaccine: evolving concepts. N. Eng. J. Med. 356:2073&#x2013;2080.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17507706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalish M.,, Robbins K.,, Pieniazek D.,, Schaefer A.,, Nzilambi N.,, Quinn T.,, Louis M. S.,, Youngpairoj A.,, Phillips J.,, Jaffe H.,, Folks T. 2004. Recombinant viruses and early global HIV-1 epidemic. Emerg. Infect. Diseases 10:1227&#x2013;1234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3323344</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15324542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kass R., Raftery A. 1995. Bayes factors. JASA 90:773&#x2013;795.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kimura M. 1980. A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences. J. Mol. Evol. 16:111&#x2013;120.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7463489</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kita K.,, Ndembi N.,, Ekwalanga M.,, Ido E.,, Kazadi R.,, Bikandou B.,, Takehisa J.,, Takemura T.,, Kageyama S.,, Tanaka J.,, Parra H.,, Hayami M.,, Ichimura H. 2004. Genetic diversity of HIV type 1 in Likasi, southeast of the Democratic Republic of Congo. AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses 20:1352&#x2013;1357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15650428</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuo L.,, Mallick B. 1998. Variable selection for regression models. Sankhya B 60:65&#x2013;81.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lartillot N.,, Poujol R. 2011. A phylogenetic model for investigating correlated evolution of subsitution rates and continuous phenotypic characters. Mol. Biol. Evol. 28:729&#x2013;744.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20926596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemey P.,, Rambaut A.,, Drummond A.,, Suchard M. 2009a. Bayesian phylogeography finds its roots. PLoS Comput. Biol. 5:e1000520.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2740835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19779555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemey P.,, Rambaut A.,, Welch J.,, Suchard M. 2010. Phylogeography takes a relaxed random walk in continuous space and time. Mole. Biol. Evol. 27:1877&#x2013;1885.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2915639</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20203288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lemey P.,, Suchard M.,, Rambaut A. 2009b. Reconstructing the initial global spread of a human influenza pandemic: A Bayesian spatial-temporal model for the global spread of H1N1pdm. PLoS Curr. 1:RRN1031.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2762761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20029613</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Martins E. 1999. Estimation of ancestral states of continuous characters: a computer simulation study. Syst. Biol. 48:642&#x2013;650.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mascola J.,, Montefiori D. 2010. The role of antibodies in HIV vaccines. Ann. Rev. Immun. 28:413&#x2013;444.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20192810</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mello F.,, Araujo O.,, Lago B.,, Motta-Castro A.,, Moraes M.,, Gomes S.,, Bello G.,, Araujo N. 2013. Phylogeography and evolutionary history of hepatitis B virus genotype F in Brazil. Virol. J. 10:236.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3751091</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23855930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metropolis N.,, Rosenbluth A.,, Rosenbluth M.,, Teller A.,, Teller E. 1953. Equation of state calculation by fast computing machines. J. Chem. Phys. 21:1087&#x2013;1092.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Niama F.,, Toure-Kane C.,, Vidal N.,, Obengui P.,, Bikandou B.,, Ndoundou-Nkodia M.,, Montavon C.,, Diop-Ndiaye H.,, Mombouli J.,, Mokondzimobe E.,, Diallo A.,, Delaporte E.,, Parra H.,, Peeters M.,, Mboup S. 2006. HIV-1 subtypes and recombinants in the Republic of Congo. Infect., Genet. Evol. 6:337&#x2013;343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16473564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oakley T.,, Cunningham C. 2000. Independent contrasts succeed where ancestor reconstruction fails in a known bacteriophage phylogeny. Evolution 54:397&#x2013;405.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10937216</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O&#x2019;Meara B.,, Ane C.,, Sanderson M.,, Wainwright P. 2006. Testing for different rates of continuous trait evolution using likelihood. Evolution 60:922&#x2013;933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16817533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pagel M. 1999. The maximum likelihood approach to reconstructing ancestral character states of discrete characters on phylogenies. Syst. Biol. 48:612&#x2013;622.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pant S.,, Goswami A.,, Finarelli J. 2014. Complex body size trends in the evolution of sloths (Xenarthra: Pilosa). BMC Evol. Biol. 14:184.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4243956</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25319928</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pybus O.,, Suchard M.,, Lemey P.,, Bernardin F.,, Rambaut A.,, Crawford F.,, Gray R.,, Arinaminpathy N.,, Stramer S.,, Busch M.,, Delwart E. 2012. Unifying the spatial epidemiology and molecular evolution of emerging epidemics. Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. USA 109:15066&#x2013;15071.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3443149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22927414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pybus O.,, Tatem A.,, Lemey P. 2015. Virus evolution and transmission in an ever more connected world. Proc. Roy. Soc. B 282:20142878.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4707738</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26702033</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revell L.,, Harmon L. 2008. Testing quantitative genetic hypotheses about the evolutionary rate matrix for continuous characters. Evol. Ecol. Res. 10:311&#x2013;331.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Revell L.,, Mahler D.,, Peres-Neto P.,, Redelings B. 2012. A new phylogenetic method for identifying exceptional phenotypic diversification. Evolution 66:135&#x2013;146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22220870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ronquist F. 2004. Bayesian inference of character evolution. Trends Ecol. Evol. 19:475&#x2013;481.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16701310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seetahal J.,, Velasco-Billa A.,, Allicock O.,, Adesiyun A.,, Bissessar J.,, Amour K.,, Phillip-Hosein A.,, Marston D.,, McElhinney L.,, Shi M.,, Wharwood C.,, Fooks A.,, Carrington C. 2013. Evolutionary history and phylogeography of rabies viruses associated with outbreaks in Trinidad. PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis. 7:e2365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3749974</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23991230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sinsheimer J.,, Lake J.,, Little R. 1996. Bayesian hypothesis testing of four-taxon topologies using molecular sequence data. Biometrics 52:193&#x2013;210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8934592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slater G.,, Harmon L.,, Alfaro M. 2012a. Integrating fossils with molecular phylogenies improves inference of trait evolution. Evolution 66:3931&#x2013;3944.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23206147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Slater G.,, Harmon L.,, Wegmann D.,, Joyce P.,, Revell L.,, Alfaro M. 2012b. Fitting models of continuous trait evolution to incompletely sampled comparative data using approximate Bayesian computation. Evolution 66:752&#x2013;762.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22380438</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sookias R., Butler R., Benson R.. 2012. Rise of dinosaurs reveals major body-size transitions are driven by passive processes of trait evolution. Proc. Roy. Soc. B 279:2180&#x2013;2187.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3321709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22298850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suchard M.,, Weiss R.,, Sinsheimer J. 2005. Models for estimating Bayes factors with applications to phylogeny and tests of monophyly. Biometrics 61:665&#x2013;673.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16135017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thomas G.,, Freckleton R.,, Szekely T. 2006. Comparative analyses of the influence of developmental mode on phenotypic diversification rates in shorebirds. Proc. Roy. Soc. B 273:1619&#x2013;1624.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1634920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16769632</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidal N.,, Mulanga C.,, Bazepeo S.,, Mwamba J.,, Tshimpaka J.,, Kashi M.,, Mama N.,, Laurent C.,, Lepira F.,, Delaporte E.,, Peeters M. 2005. Distribution of HIV-1 variants in the Democratic Republic of Congo suggests increase of subtype C in Kinshasa between 1997 and 2002. J. Acquir. Immune Defic. Syndr. 40:456&#x2013;462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16280702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vidal N.,, Peeters M.,, Mulanga-Kabeya C.,, Nzilambi N.,, Robertson D.,, Ilunga W.,, Sema H.,, Tshimanga K.,, Bongo B.,, Delaporte E. 2000. Unprecedented degree of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) group M genetic diversity in the Democratic Republic of Congo suggests that the HIV-1 pandemic originated in Central Africa. J. Virol. 74:10498&#x2013;10507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC110924</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11044094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vrancken B.,, Lemey P.,, Rambaut A.,, Bedford T.,, Longdon B.,, G&#xfc;nthard H.F.,, Suchard M. A. 2015. Simultaneously estimating evolutionary history and repeated traits phylogenetic signal: applications to viral and host phenotypic evolution. Methods Ecol. Evol. 6:67&#x2013;82.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4358766</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25780554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker B.,, Burton D. 2008. Toward an AIDS vaccine. Science 320:760&#x2013;764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18467582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walker L.,, Phogat S.,, Chan-Hui P.,, Wagner D.,, Phung P.,, Goss J.,, Wrin T.,, Simek M.,, Fling S.,, Mitcham J.,, Lehrman J.,, Priddy F.,, Olsen O.,, Frey S.,, Hammond P.,, Investigators P.G.P.,, Kaminsky S.,, Zamb T.,, Moyle M.,, Koff W.,, Poignard P.,, Burton D. 2009. Broad and potent neutralizing antibodies from an African donor reveal a new HIV-1 vaccine target. Science 326:285&#x2013;289.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3335270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19729618</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weiss R.,, Clapham P.,, Cheingsong-Popov R.,, Dalgleish A.,, Carne C.,, Weller I.,, Tedder R. 1985. Neutralization of human T-lymphocyte virus type III by sera of AIDS and AIDS-risk patients. Nature 316:69&#x2013;72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2989706</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wiener N. 1958. Nonlinear problems in random theory. Cambridge (MA), MIT Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woolhouse M.,, Rambaut A.,, Kellam P. 2015. Lessons from Ebola: Improving infectious disease surveillance to inform outbreak management. Sci. Transl. Med. 7:307rv5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5819730</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26424572</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang C.,, Li M.,, Mokili J.,, Winter J.,, Lubaki N.,, Mwandagalirwa K.,, Kasali M.,, Losoma A.,, Quinn T.,, Bollinger R.,, Lal R. 2005. Genetic diversification and recombination of HIV type 1 group M in Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo. AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses 21:661&#x2013;666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16060838</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Z. 1994. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic estimation from DNA sequences with variable rates over sites: approximate methods. J. Mol. Evol. 39:306&#x2013;314.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7932792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou T.,, Georgiev I.,, Wu X.,, Yang Z.,, Dai K.,, Finzi A.,, Kwon Y.,, Scheid J.,, Shi W.,, Xu L.,, Yang Y.,, Zhu J.,, Nussenzweig M.,, Sodroski J.,, Shapiro L.,, Nabel G.,, Mascola J.,, Kwong P. 2010. Structural basis for broad and potent neutralization of HIV-1 by antibody VRC01. Science 329:811&#x2013;817.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2981354</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20616231</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>