<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37838198</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>09</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-0953</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>240</Volume><Issue>Pt 2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Environmental research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Environ Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Predictive power of wastewater for nowcasting infectious disease transmission: A retrospective case study of five sewershed areas in Louisville, Kentucky.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>117395</StartPage><MedlinePgn>117395</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.envres.2023.117395</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0013-9351(23)02199-0</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Epidemiological nowcasting traditionally relies on count surveillance data. The availability and quality of such count data may vary over time, limiting representation of true infections. Wastewater data correlates with traditional surveillance data and may provide additional value for nowcasting disease trends.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">We obtained SARS-CoV-2 case, death, wastewater, and serosurvey data for Jefferson County, Kentucky (USA), between August 2020 and March 2021, and parameterized an existing nowcasting model using combinations of these data. We assessed the predictive performance and variability at the sewershed level and compared the effects of adding or replacing wastewater data to case and death reports.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS">Adding wastewater data minimally improved the predictive performance of nowcasts compared to a model fitted to case and death data (Weighted Interval Score (WIS) 0.208 versus 0.223), and reduced the predictive performance compared to a model fitted to deaths data (WIS 0.517 versus 0.500). Adding wastewater data to deaths data improved the nowcasts agreement to estimates from models using cases and deaths data. These findings were consistent across individual sewersheds as well as for models fit to the aggregated total data of 5 sewersheds. Retrospective reconstructions of epidemiological dynamics created using different combinations of data were in general agreement (coverage &gt;75%).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERPRETATION">These findings show wastewater data may be valuable for infectious disease nowcasting when clinical surveillance data are absent, such as early in a pandemic or in low-resource settings where systematic collection of epidemiologic data is difficult.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2023 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Klaassen</LastName><ForeName>Fayette</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Health and Population, Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA. Electronic address: fklaassen@hsph.harvard.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Holm</LastName><ForeName>Rochelle H</ForeName><Initials>RH</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Christina Lee Brown Envirome Institute, School of Medicine, University of Louisville, Louisville, KY, USA. Electronic address: rochelle.holm@louisville.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Smith</LastName><ForeName>Ted</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Christina Lee Brown Envirome Institute, School of Medicine, University of Louisville, Louisville, KY, USA. Electronic address: ted.smith@louisville.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cohen</LastName><ForeName>Ted</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology of Microbial Diseases and Public Health Modeling Unit, Yale School of Public Health, New Haven, CT, USA. Electronic address: theodore.cohen@yale.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bhatnagar</LastName><ForeName>Aruni</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Christina Lee Brown Envirome Institute, School of Medicine, University of Louisville, Louisville, KY, USA. Electronic address: aruni.bhatnagar@louisville.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Menzies</LastName><ForeName>Nicolas A</ForeName><Initials>NA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Health and Population, Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA; Center for Health Decision Science, Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA. Electronic address: nmenzies@hsph.harvard.edu.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>P30 ES030283</GrantID><Acronym>ES</Acronym><Agency>NIEHS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>UL1 TR001863</GrantID><Acronym>TR</Acronym><Agency>NCATS NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>HHSD200201691779I</GrantID><Acronym>CC</Acronym><Agency>CDC HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>NU38OT000297</GrantID><Acronym>CC</Acronym><Agency>CDC HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>U01 CA261277</GrantID><Acronym>CA</Acronym><Agency>NCI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Environ Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0147621</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0013-9351</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D062065">Wastewater</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007629" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Kentucky</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062065" MajorTopicYN="Y">Wastewater</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Communicable Diseases</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058873" MajorTopicYN="N">Pandemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiological nowcasting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Infectious disease</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Predictive performance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Public health</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">SARS-CoV-2</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Wastewater surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declaration of competing interest The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Fayette Klaassen reports financial support was provided by Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Fayette Klaassen reports financial support was provided by Council of State and Territorial Epidemiologists. Nicolas Menzies reports financial support was provided by Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Nicolas Menzies reports financial support was provided by Council of State and Territorial Epidemiologists. Ted Cohen reports financial support was provided by Council of State and Territorial Epidemiologists. Rochelle H Holm reports financial support was provided by Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Ted Smith reports financial support was provided by Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Aruni Bhatnagar reports financial support was provided by Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Rochelle H Holm reports financial support was provided by Louisville-Jefferson County Metro Government. Ted Smith reports financial support was provided by Louisville-Jefferson County Metro Government. Aruni Bhatnagar reports financial support was provided by Louisville-Jefferson County Metro Government. Rochelle Holm reports financial support was provided by James Graham Brown Foundation. Ted Smith reports financial support was provided by James Graham Brown Foundation. Aruni Bhatnagar reports financial support was provided by James Graham Brown Foundation. Rochelle H Holm reports financial support was provided by Owsley Brown II Family Foundation. Ted Smith reports financial support was provided by Owsley Brown II Family Foundation. Aruni Bhatnagar reports financial support was provided by Owsley Brown II Family Foundation. Rochelle H Holm reports financial support was provided by Welch Family. Ted Smith reports financial support was provided by Welch Family. Aruni Bhatnagar reports financial support was provided by Welch Family. Rochelle H Holm reports financial support was provided by Jewish Heritage Fund. Ted Smith reports financial support was provided by Jewish Heritage Fund. Aruni Bhatnagar reports financial support was provided by Jewish Heritage Fund. Rochelle H Holm reports financial support was provided by University of Louisville Center for Predictive Medicine for Biodefense and Emerging Infectious Diseases. Ted Smith reports financial support was provided by University of Louisville Center for Predictive Medicine for Biodefense and Emerging Infectious Diseases. Aruni Bhatnagar reports financial support was provided by University of Louisville Center for Predictive Medicine for Biodefense and Emerging Infectious Diseases.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2023</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>21</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>46</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>19</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37838198</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">NIHMS1941163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10863376</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2023.117395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0013-9351(23)02199-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Wu JT, Leung K, Lam TTY, Ni MY, Wong CKH, Peiris JSM, et al. Nowcasting epidemics of novel pathogens: lessons from COVID-19. Nat Med. 2021;27(3):388&#x2013;95. doi: 10.1038/s41591-021-01278-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01278-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33723452</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rossman H, Segal E. Nowcasting the spread of SARS-CoV-2. Nature Microbiology. 2022;7(1):16&#x2013;7. doi: 10.1038/s41564-021-01035-2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41564-021-01035-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34972824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pitzer VE, Chitwood M, Havumaki J, Menzies NA, Perniciaro S, Warren JL, et al. The Impact of Changes in Diagnostic Testing Practices on Estimates of COVID-19 Transmission in the United States. Am J Epidemiol. 2021;190(9):1908&#x2013;17. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwab089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kwab089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8083380</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33831148</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bilal U, Tabb LP, Barber S, Diez Roux AV. Spatial Inequities in COVID-19 Testing, Positivity, Confirmed Cases, and Mortality in 3 U.S. Cities. Ann Intern Med. 2021;174(7):936&#x2013;44. doi: 10.7326/M20-3936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/M20-3936</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8029592</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33780289</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lauer SA, Grantz KH, Bi Q, Jones FK, Zheng Q, Meredith HR, et al. The Incubation Period of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) From Publicly Reported Confirmed Cases: Estimation and Application. Ann Intern Med. 2020;172(9):577&#x2013;82. doi: 10.7326/m20-0504.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/m20-0504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7081172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32150748</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kilaru P, Hill D, Anderson K, Collins MB, Green H, Kmush BL, et al. Wastewater Surveillance for Infectious Disease: A Systematic Review. Am J Epidemiol. 2022;192(2):305&#x2013;22. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwac175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kwac175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9620728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36227259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shah S, Gwee SXW, Ng JQX, Lau N, Koh J, Pang J. Wastewater surveillance to infer COVID-19 transmission: A systematic review. Sci Total Environ. 2022;804:150060. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8423771</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34798721</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith T, Holm RH, Keith RJ, Amraotkar AR, Alvarado CR, Banecki K, et al. Quantifying the relationship between sub-population wastewater samples and community-wide SARS-CoV-2 seroprevalence. Sci Total Environ. 2022;853:158567. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158567</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9444845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36084773</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu F, Xiao A, Zhang J, Moniz K, Endo N, Armas F, et al. SARS-CoV-2 RNA concentrations in wastewater foreshadow dynamics and clinical presentation of new COVID-19 cases. Sci Total Environ. 2022;805:150121. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150121.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.150121</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8416286</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34534872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pulicharla R, Kaur G, Brar SK. A year into the COVID-19 pandemic: Rethinking of wastewater monitoring as a preemptive approach. Journal of Environmental Chemical Engineering. 2021;9(5):106063. doi: 10.1016/j.jece.2021.106063.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jece.2021.106063</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8282934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34307017</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. COVID Data Tracker: Wastewater Surveillance [webpage]. Atlanta, GA: US Department of Health and Human Services, CDC; 2023.  [Accessed: April 10, 2023]. Available from: https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biobot Analytics. Data on Covid-19 and Mpox Wastewater Monitoring [webpage]. Cambridge, MA:  [Accessed: May 12, 2023]. Available from: https://biobot.io/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schenk H, Heidinger P, Insam H, Kreuzinger N, Markt R, N&#xe4;gele F, et al. Prediction of hospitalisations based on wastewater-based SARS-CoV-2 epidemiology. Sci Total Environ. 2023;873:162149. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162149.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.162149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9911153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36773921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phan T, Brozak S, Pell B, Gitter A, Xiao A, Mena KD, et al. A simple SEIR-V model to estimate COVID-19 prevalence and predict SARS-CoV-2 transmission using wastewater-based surveillance data. Sci Total Environ. 2023;857:159326. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159326.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.159326</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9547654</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36220466</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jeng HA, Singh R, Diawara N, Curtis K, Gonzalez R, Welch N, et al. Application of wastewater-based surveillance and copula time-series model for COVID-19 forecasts. Sci Total Environ. 2023;885:163655. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163655.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.163655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10122554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37094677</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farkas K, Hillary LS, Malham SK, McDonald JE, Jones DL. Wastewater and public health: the potential of wastewater surveillance for monitoring COVID-19. Current Opinion in Environmental Science &amp; Health. 2020;17:14&#x2013;20. doi: 10.1016/j.coesh.2020.06.001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.coesh.2020.06.001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7291992</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32835157</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed W, Simpson SL, Bertsch PM, Bibby K, Bivins A, Blackall LL, et al. Minimizing errors in RT-PCR detection and quantification of SARS-CoV-2 RNA for wastewater surveillance. Sci Total Environ. 2022;805:149877. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.149877.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2021.149877</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8386095</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34818780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rondeau Nicole C, Rose Oliver J, Alt Ellen R, Ariyan Lina A, Elikan Annabelle B, Everard Jenna L, et al. Building-Level Detection Threshold of SARS-CoV-2 in Wastewater. Microbiology Spectrum. 2023;11(2):e0292922. doi: 10.1128/spectrum.02929-22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/spectrum.02929-22</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10100851</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36975999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keith RJ, Holm RH, Amraotkar AR, Bezold MM, Brick JM, Bushau-Sprinkle AM, et al. Stratified Simple Random Sampling Versus Volunteer Community-Wide Sampling for Estimates of COVID-19 Prevalence. Am J Public Health. 2023:e1&#x2013;e10. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2023.307303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2023.307303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10262242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37200600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holm RH, Mukherjee A, Rai JP, Yeager RA, Talley D, Rai SN, et al. SARS-CoV-2 RNA abundance in wastewater as a function of distinct urban sewershed size. Environmental Science: Water Research &amp; Technology. 2022;8(4):807&#x2013;19. doi: 10.1039/D1EW00672J.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1039/D1EW00672J</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rouchka EC, Chariker JH, Saurabh K, Waigel S, Zacharias W, Zhang M, et al. The Rapid Assessment of Aggregated Wastewater Samples for Genomic Surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 on a City-Wide Scale. Pathogens. 2021;10(10). doi: 10.3390/pathogens10101271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/pathogens10101271</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8541652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34684220</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holm RH, Nagarkar M, Yeager RA, Talley D, Chaney AC, Rai JP, et al. Surveillance of RNase P, PMMoV, and CrAssphage in wastewater as indicators of human fecal concentration across urban sewer neighborhoods, Kentucky. FEMS Microbes. 2022;3:xtac003. doi: 10.1093/femsmc/xtac003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/femsmc/xtac003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10117713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37228897</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kanneganti D, Reinersman LE, Holm RH, Smith T. Estimating sewage flow rate in Jefferson County, Kentucky, using machine learning for wastewater-based epidemiology applications. Water Supply. 2022;22(12):8434&#x2013;9. doi: 10.2166/ws.2022.395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2166/ws.2022.395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chitwood MH, Russi M, Gunasekera K, Havumaki J, Klaassen F, Pitzer VE, et al. Reconstructing the course of the COVID-19 epidemic over 2020 for US states and counties: Results of a Bayesian evidence synthesis model. PLoS Comput Biol. 2022;18(8):e1010465. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010465.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010465</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9467347</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36040963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klaassen F, Chitwood MH, Cohen T, Pitzer VE, Russi M, Swartwood NA, et al. Changes in Population Immunity Against Infection and Severe Disease From Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) Omicron Variants in the United States Between December 2021 and November 2022. Clin Infect Dis. 2023:ciad210. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciad210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciad210</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10425195</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37074868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bracher J, Ray EL, Gneiting T, Reich NG. Evaluating epidemic forecasts in an interval format. PLoS Comput Biol. 2021;17(2):e1008618. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008618.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008618</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7880475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33577550</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cramer EY, Huang Y, Wang Y, Ray EL, Cornell M, Bracher J, et al. The United States COVID-19 Forecast Hub dataset. Scientific Data. 2022;9(1):462. doi: 10.1038/s41597-022-01517-w.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41597-022-01517-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9342845</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35915104</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dong E, Du H, Gardner L. An interactive web-based dashboard to track COVID-19 in real time. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2020;20(5):533&#x2013;4. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30120-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30120-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7159018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32087114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>covidestim: COVID-19 nowcasting [webpage]. 2022.  [Accessed: March 13, 2023]. Available from: https://legacy.covidestim.org/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. 2021. R Foundation for Statistical Computing:Vienna, Austria.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stan Development Team. RStan: the R interface to Stan. 2020. R package version 2.21.2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wickham H. ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis. 2016. Springer-Verlag, New York.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maal-Bared R, Qiu Y, Li Q, Gao T, Hrudey SE, Bhavanam S, et al. Does normalization of SARS-CoV-2 concentrations by Pepper Mild Mottle Virus improve correlations and lead time between wastewater surveillance and clinical data in Alberta (Canada): comparing twelve SARS-CoV-2 normalization approaches. Sci Total Environ. 2023;856(Pt 1):158964. doi: 10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158964.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.158964</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9508694</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36167131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Greenwald HD, Kennedy LC, Hinkle A, Whitney ON, Fan VB, Crits-Christoph A, et al. Tools for interpretation of wastewater SARS-CoV-2 temporal and spatial trends demonstrated with data collected in the San Francisco Bay Area. Water Research X. 2021;12:100111. doi: 10.1016/j.wroa.2021.100111.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wroa.2021.100111</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8325558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34373850</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang G, Wu J, Weidhaas J, Li X, Chen Y, Mueller J, et al. Artificial neural network-based estimation of COVID-19 case numbers and effective reproduction rate using wastewater-based epidemiology. Water Res. 2022;218:118451. doi: 10.1016/j.watres.2022.118451.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2022.118451</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9006161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35447417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arts Peter J, Kelly JD, Midgley Claire M, Anglin K, Lu S, Abedi Glen R, et al. Longitudinal and quantitative fecal shedding dynamics of SARS-CoV-2, pepper mild mottle virus, and crAssphage. mSphere. 2023;0(0):e00132&#x2013;23. doi: 10.1128/msphere.00132-23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/msphere.00132-23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10506459</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37338211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>