<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20562627</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2010</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1531-5487</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>21</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Epidemiology (Cambridge, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Epidemiology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Estimating the proportion of pneumonia attributable to pneumococcus in Kenyan adults: latent class analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>719</StartPage><EndPage>725</EndPage><MedlinePgn>719-25</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/EDE.0b013e3181e4c4d5</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">Community-acquired pneumonia is a common cause of hospitalization among African adults, and Streptococcus pneumoniae is assumed to be a frequent cause. Pneumococcal conjugate vaccine is currently being introduced into childhood immunization programs in Africa. The case for adult vaccination is dependent on the contribution of the pneumococcus to the hospital pneumonia burden.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Pneumococcal diagnosis is complex because there is no gold standard, and culture methods are invalidated by antibiotic use. We used latent class analysis to estimate the proportion of pneumonia episodes caused by pneumococcus. Furthermore, we extended this methodology to evaluate the effect of antimicrobial treatment on test accuracies and the prevalence of the disease. The study combined data from 5 validation studies of pneumococcal diagnostic tests performed on 281 Kenyan adults with pneumonia.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">The proportion of pneumonia episodes attributable to pneumococcus was 0.46 (95% confidence interval = 0.36-0.57). Failure to account for the effect of antimicrobial exposure underestimates this proportion as 0.32. A history of antibiotic exposure was a poor predictor of antimicrobial activity in patients' urine. Blood culture sensitivity for pneumococcus was estimated at 0.24 among patients with antibiotic exposure, and 0.75 among those without.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The large contribution of pneumococcus to adult pneumonia provides a strong case for the investigation of pneumococcal vaccines in African adults.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jokinen</LastName><ForeName>Jukka</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Vaccination and Immune Protection, National Institute for Health and Welfare, Helsinki, Finland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Scott</LastName><ForeName>J Anthony G</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>061089</GrantID><Acronym>WT_</Acronym><Agency>Wellcome Trust</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>081835</GrantID><Acronym>WT_</Acronym><Agency>Wellcome Trust</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Epidemiology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9009644</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1044-3983</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000900">Anti-Bacterial Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000900" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-Bacterial Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016009" MajorTopicYN="N">Chi-Square Distribution</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016001" MajorTopicYN="N">Confidence Intervals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007630" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Kenya</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016013" MajorTopicYN="N">Likelihood Functions</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008828" MajorTopicYN="N">Microbiological Techniques</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011014" MajorTopicYN="N">Pneumonia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011018" MajorTopicYN="N">Pneumonia, Pneumococcal</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012680" MajorTopicYN="N">Sensitivity and Specificity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012703" MajorTopicYN="N">Serotyping</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><OtherID Source="NLM">UKMS31178</OtherID></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2011</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20562627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="mid">UKMS31178</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2923075</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e3181e4c4d5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Williams EH, Hayes RJ, Smith PG. Admissions to a rural hospital in the West Nile District of Uganda over a 27 year period. J Trop Med Hyg. 1986;89:193&#x2013;211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3783813</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pneumonia and influenza death rates&#x2013;United States, 1979-1994. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 1995;44:535&#x2013;537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7603429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Macfarlane JT, Adegboye DS, Warrell MJ. Mycoplasma pneumoniae and aetiology of lobar pneumonia in northern Nigeria. Thorax. 1979;34:713&#x2013;719.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC471172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">120616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sow O, Frechet M, Diallo AA, et al. Community acquired pneumonia in adults: a study comparing clinical features and outcome in Africa (Republic of Guinea) and Europe (France) Thorax. 1996;51:385&#x2013;388.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1090673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8733490</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JA, Hall AJ, Muyodi C, et al. Aetiology, outcome, and risk factors for mortality among adults with acute pneumonia in Kenya. Lancet. 2000;355:1225&#x2013;1230.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10770305</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mulholland K, Hilton S, Adegbola R, et al. Randomised trial of Haemophilus influenzae type-b tetanus protein conjugate vaccine [corrected] for prevention of pneumonia and meningitis in Gambian infants. Lancet. 1997;349:1191&#x2013;1197.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9130939</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cutts FT, Zaman SMA, Enwere G, et al. Efficacy of nine-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine against pneumonia and invasive pneumococcal disease in The Gambia: randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2005;365:1139&#x2013;1146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15794968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fedson DS, Scott JAG. The burden of pneumococcal disease among adults in developed and developing countries: what is and is not known. Vaccine. 1999;17:S11&#x2013;18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10471174</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koulla-Shiro S, Kuaban C, Belec L. Acute community-acquired bacterial pneumonia in Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infected and non-HIV-infected adult patients in Cameroon: aetiology and outcome. Tuber Lung Dis. 1996;77:47&#x2013;51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8733414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marrie TJ, Durant H, Yates L. Community-acquired pneumonia requiring hospitalization: 5-year prospective study. Rev Infect Dis. 1996;11:586&#x2013;599.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2772465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>British Thoracic Society Research Committee, the Public Health Laboratory Service Community-acquired pneumonia in adults in British hospitals in 1982&#x2013;1983; A survey of aetiology, mortality, prognostic factors and outcome. Q J Med. 1987;62:195&#x2013;200.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">3116595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JAG, Hall AJ. The value and complications of percutaneous transthoracic lung aspiration for the etiologic diagnosis of community acquired pneumonia. Chest. 1999;116:1716&#x2013;1732.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10593800</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butler JC, Bosshardt SC, Phelan M, et al. Classical and Latent Class Analysis Evaluation of Sputum Polymerase Chain Reaction and Urine Antigen Testing for Diagnosis of Pneumococcal Pneumonia in Adults. J Infect Dis. 2003;187:1416&#x2013;1423.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12717623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allen SC. Lobar pneumonia in Northern Zambia: Clinical study of 502 patients. Thorax. 1984;39:612&#x2013;616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1020516</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">6474390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koulla-Shiro S, Kuaban C, Auckenthaler R, Belec L, Ngu JL. Adult response to initial treatment with ampicillin in community acquired pneumonia in Yaounde, Cameroon. Cent Afr J Med. 1993;39:188&#x2013;192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8020088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoshimine H, Oishi K, Mubiru F, et al. Community-acquired pneumonia in Ugandan adults: short-term parenteral ampicillin therapy for bacterial pneumonia. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2001;64:172&#x2013;177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11442214</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JAG, Hannington A, Marsh K, Hall AJ. Diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia in epidemiological studies: Evaluation in Kenyan adults of a serotype-specific urine latex agglutination assay. Clin Infect Dis. 1999;28:764&#x2013;769.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10825036</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JA, Hall AJ, Leinonen M. Validation of immune-complex enzyme immunoassays for diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia among adults in Kenya. Clin Diagn Lab Immunol. 2000;7:64&#x2013;67.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC95824</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10618279</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JA, Obiero J, Hall AJ, Marsh K. Validation of immunoglobulin G enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay for antibodies to pneumococcal surface adhesin A in the diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia among adults in Kenya. J Infect Dis. 2002;186:220&#x2013;226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12134258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JA, Marston EL, Hall AJ, Marsh K. Diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia by PsaA PCR analysis of lung aspirates from adult patients in Kenya. J Clin Microbiol. 2003;41:2554&#x2013;2559.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC156539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12791880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scott JA, Hall AJ, Hannington A, et al. Serotype distribution and prevalence of resistance to benzylpenicillin in three representative populations of Streptococcus pneumoniae isolates from the coast of Kenya. Clin Infect Dis. 1998;27:1442&#x2013;1450.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9868658</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding RMZ, Nohynek H, Ruutu P, Leinonen M. Evaluation of a new tube latex agglutination test for detection of type-specific pneumococcal antigen in urine. J Clin Microbiol. 1991;29:1818&#x2013;1821.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC270217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1774301</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tharpe JA, Russell H, Leinonen M, et al. Comparison of a pneumococcal common protein (PsaA) antibody ELISA and a PsaA immune complex ELISA for detection of pneumococcal serum antibody. Pathobiology. 1998;66:77&#x2013;83.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9645631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Morrison KE, Lake D, Crook J, et al. Confirmation of PsaA in all 90 serotypes of Streptococcus pneumoniae by PCR and potential of this assay for identification and diagnosis. J Clin Microbiol. 2000;38:434&#x2013;437.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC88744</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10618136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Formann A, Kohlmann T. Latent class analysis in medical research. Stat Meth Med Res. 1996;5:179&#x2013;211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8817797</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albert PS, McShane LM, Shih JH. Latent Class modeling approaches for assessing diagnostic error without a gold standard: With applications to p53 Immunohistochemical Assays in Bladder Tumors. Biometrics. 2001;57:610&#x2013;619.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11414591</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albert PS, Dodd LE. A Cautionary Note on the Robustness of Latent Class Models for Estimating Diagnostic Error without Gold Standard. Biometrics. 2004;60:427&#x2013;435.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15180668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hagenaars JA. Latent Structure Models with Direct Effects Between Indicators. Sociol Meth Res. 1988;16:379&#x2013;405.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonzo TA, Pepe MS. Using a combination of reference tests to asses the accuracy of a new diagnostic test. Stat Med. 1999;18:2987&#x2013;3003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10544302</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Little RJA, Rubin DB. Statistical analysis with missing data. 2nd ed. Wiley-Interscience; New York: 2002.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schafer JL, Graham JW. Missing Data: Our view of the State of Art. Psychol Methods. 2002;7:47&#x2013;177.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12090408</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Collins LM, Schafer JL, Kam CM. A comparison of inclusive and restrictive strategies in modern missing-data procedures. Psychol Methods. 2001;6:330&#x2013;351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11778676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wheeler J, Murphy OM, Freeman R, Kearns AM, Steward M, Lee MJ. PCR can add to detection of pneumococcal disease in pneumonic patients receiving antibiotics at admission. J Clin Microbiol. 2000;38:3907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC87511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11184177</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musher DM, Mediwala R, Phan HM, Chen G, Baughn RE. Nonspecificity of assaying for IgG antibody to pneumolysin in circulating immune complexes as a means to diagnose pneumococcal pneumonia. Clin Infect Dis. 2001;32:534&#x2013;538.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11181114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fuchs C. Maximum Likelihood Estimation and Model Selection in Contingency Tables with Missing Data. JASA. 1982;77:270&#x2013;278.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roson B, Fernandez-Sabe N, Carratala J, et al. Contribution of a urinary antigen assay (Binax NOW) to the early diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia. Clin Infect Dis. 2004;38:222&#x2013;226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14699454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rudolph KM, Parkinson AJ, Black CM, Mayer LW. Evaluation of polymerase chain reaction for diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia. J Clin Microbiol. 1993;31:2661&#x2013;2666.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC265966</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8253962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorente ML, Falguera M, Nogues A, Gonzalez AR, Merino MT, Caballero MR. Diagnosis of pneumococcal pneumonia by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in whole blood: a prospective clinical study. Thorax. 2000;55:133&#x2013;137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1745670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10639531</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murdoch DR, Anderson TP, Beynon KA, et al. Evaluation of a PCR assay for detection of Streptococcus pneumoniae in respiratory and nonrespiratory samples from adults with community-acquired pneumonia. J Clin Microbiol. 2003;41:63&#x2013;66.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC149569</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12517826</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Haeften R, Palladino S, Kay I, Keil T, Heath C, Waterer GW. A quantitative LightCycler PCR to detect Streptococcus pneumoniae in blood and CSF. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2003;47:407&#x2013;414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14522514</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>