<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20053861</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2010</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>24</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>20</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1098-660X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>48</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Mar</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Journal of clinical microbiology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Clin Microbiol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Use of the normalized absorbance ratio as an internal standardization approach to minimize measurement error in enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays for diagnosis of human papillomavirus infection.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>791</StartPage><EndPage>796</EndPage><MedlinePgn>791-6</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1128/JCM.00844-09</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The serological detection of antibodies against human papillomavirus (HPV) antigens is a useful tool to determine exposure to genital HPV infection and in predicting the risk of infection persistence and associated lesions. Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (ELISAs) are commonly used for seroepidemiological studies of HPV infection but are not standardized. Intra- and interassay performance variation is difficult to control, especially in cohort studies that require the testing of specimens over extended periods. We propose the use of normalized absorbance ratios (NARs) as a standardization procedure to control for such variations and minimize measurement error. We compared NAR and ELISA optical density (OD) values for the strength of the correlation between serological results for paired visits 4 months apart and HPV-16 DNA positivity in cervical specimens from a cohort investigation of 2,048 women tested with an ELISA using HPV-16 virus-like particles. NARs were calculated by dividing the mean blank-subtracted (net) ODs by the equivalent values of a control serum pool included in the same plate in triplicate, using different dilutions. Stronger correlations were observed with NAR values than with net ODs at every dilution, with an overall reduction in nonexplained regression variability of 39%. Using logistic regression, the ranges of odds ratios of HPV-16 DNA positivity contrasting upper and lower quintiles at different dilutions and their averages were 4.73 to 5.47 for NARs and 2.78 to 3.28 for net ODs, with corresponding significant improvements in seroreactivity-risk trends across quintiles when NARs were used. The NAR standardization is a simple procedure to reduce measurement error in seroepidemiological studies of HPV infection.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ramanakumar</LastName><ForeName>Agnihotram V</ForeName><Initials>AV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Cancer Epidemiology, McGill University, Montreal, QC, Canada.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Thomann</LastName><ForeName>Patricia</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Candeias</LastName><ForeName>Joao M</ForeName><Initials>JM</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferreira</LastName><ForeName>Silvaneide</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Villa</LastName><ForeName>Luisa L</ForeName><Initials>LL</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Franco</LastName><ForeName>Eduardo L</ForeName><Initials>EL</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 CA070269</GrantID><Acronym>CA</Acronym><Agency>NCI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>49396</GrantID><Acronym>CAPMC</Acronym><Agency> CIHR</Agency><Country>Canada</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>CA70269</GrantID><Acronym>CA</Acronym><Agency>NCI NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>83320</GrantID><Acronym>CAPMC</Acronym><Agency> CIHR</Agency><Country>Canada</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D023362">Evaluation Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>J Clin Microbiol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>7505564</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0095-1137</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000914">Antibodies, Viral</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000914" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Viral</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="Y">blood</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019411" MajorTopicYN="N">Clinical Laboratory Techniques</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000592" MajorTopicYN="Y">standards</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004797" MajorTopicYN="N">Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000592" MajorTopicYN="N">standards</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D027383" MajorTopicYN="N">Papillomaviridae</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000302" MajorTopicYN="N">isolation &amp; purification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D030361" MajorTopicYN="N">Papillomavirus Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="Y">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015203" MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility of Results</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>8</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20053861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2832464</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00844-09</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">JCM.00844-09</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation><b>Bauer, H. M., Y. Ting, C. E. Greer, J. C. Chambers, C. J. Tashiro, J. Chimera, A. Reingold, and M. M. Manos.</b> 1991. Genital human papillomavirus infection in female university students as determined by a PCR-based method. JAMA 265<b>:</b>2809-2810.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1845912</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Bontkes, H. J., T. D. de Gruijl, J. M. Walboomers, J. T. Schiller, J. Dillner, T. J. Helmerhorst, R. H. Verheijen, R. J. Scheper, and C. J. Meijer.</b> 1999. Immune responses against human papillomavirus (HPV) type 16 virus-like particles in a cohort study of women with cervical intraepithelial neoplasia. II. Systemic but not local IgA responses correlate with clearance of HPV-16. J. Gen. Virol. 80(Pt. 2)<b>:</b>409-417.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10073701</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Carter, J. J., L. A. Koutsky, J. P. Hughes, S. K. Lee, J. Kuypers, N. Kiviat, and D. A. Galloway.</b> 2000. Comparison of human papillomavirus types 16, 18, and 6 capsid antibody responses following incident infection. J. Infect. Dis. 181<b>:</b>1911-1919.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10837170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Franco, E. L., L. Villa, T. Rohan, et al.</b> 1999. Design and methods of the Ludwig-McGill longitudinal study of the natural history of human papillomavirus infection and cervical neoplasia in Brazil. Rev. Panam. Salud Publica 6<b>:</b>223-233.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10572472</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Gravitt, P. E., C. L. Peyton, T. Q. Alessi, C. M. Wheeler, F. Coutl&#xe9;e, A. Hildesheim, M. H. Schiffman, D. R. Scott, and R. J. Apple.</b> 2000. Improved amplification of genital human papillomaviruses. J. Clin. Microbiol. 38<b>:</b>357-361.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC88724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10618116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Karem, K. L., A. C. Poon, C. Bierl, R. Nisenbaum, and E. Unger.</b> 2002. Optimization of a human papillomavirus-specific enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. Clin. Diagn. Lab. Immunol. 9<b>:</b>577-582.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC120007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11986263</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Kirnbauer, R., J. Taub, H. Greenstone, R. Roden, M. D&#xfc;rst, L. Gissmann, D. R. Lowy, and J. T. Schiller.</b> 1993. Efficient self-assembly of human papillomavirus type 16 L1 and L1-L2 into virus-like particles. J. Virol. 67<b>:</b>6929-6936.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC238150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8230414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Kirnbauer, R., N. L. Hubbert, C. M. Wheeler, T. M. Becker, D. R. Lowy, and J. T. Schiller.</b> 1994. A virus like particle enzyme linked immunosorbent assay detects serum antibodies in a majority of women infected with human papillomavirus type 16. J. Natl. Cancer Inst. 86<b>:</b>494-499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3935441</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8133532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Nonnenmacher, B., J. Pintos, M. C. Bozzetti, I. Mielzinska-Lohnas, A. T. Lorincz, N. Ikuta, G. Schwartsmann, L. L. Villa, J. T. Schiller, and E. Franco.</b> 2003. Epidemiologic correlates of antibody response to human papillomavirus among women at low risk of cervical cancer. Int. J. STD AIDS 14<b>:</b>258-265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12716496</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Palefsky, J. M.</b> 1995. Serologic detection of human papillomavirus-related anogenital disease: new opportunities and challenges. J. Natl. Cancer Inst. 87<b>:</b>437-440.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7861455</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Petter, A., K. Heim, M. Guger, A. C.-K. Nig, N. Christensen, M. Sarcletti, U. Wieland, H. Pfister, R. Zangerle, and R. H&#xf6;pfl.</b> 2000. Specific serum IgG, IgM and IgA antibodies to human papillomavirus types 6, 11, 16, 18 and 31 virus-like particles in human immunodeficiency virus-seropositive women. J. Gen. Virol. 81(Pt. 3)<b>:</b>701-708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10675407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Schlecht, N. F., S. Kulaga, J. Robitaille, S. Ferreira, M. Santos, R. A. Miyamura, E. Duarte-Franco, T. E. Rohan, A. Ferenczy, L. L. Villa, and E. L. Franco.</b> 2001. Persistent human papillomavirus infection as a predictor of cervical intraepithelial neoplasia. JAMA 286<b>:</b>3106-3114.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11754676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Studentsov, Y. Y., M. Schiffman, H. D. Strickler, G. Y. Ho, Y. Y. Pang, J. Schiller, R. Herrero, and R. D. Burk.</b> 2002. Enhanced enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay for detection of antibodies to virus-like particles of human papillomavirus. J. Clin. Microbiol. 40<b>:</b>1755-1760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC130949</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11980956</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Tabrizi, S. N., I. H. Frazer, and S. M. Garland.</b> 2006. Serologic response to human papillomavirus 16 among Australian women with high-grade cervical intraepithelial neoplasia. Int. J. Gynecol. Cancer 16<b>:</b>1032-1035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16803481</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Trottier, H., S. Mahmud, J. C. Prado, J. S. Sobrinho, M. C. Costa, T. E. Rohan, L. L. Villa, and E. L. Franco.</b> 2008. Type-specific duration of human papillomavirus infection: implications for human papillomavirus screening and vaccination. J. Infect. Dis. 197<b>:</b>1436-1447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7889327</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18419547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>van Doornum, G., M. Prins, A. Andersson-Ellstr&#xf6;m, and J. Dillner.</b> 1998. Immunoglobulin A, G, and M responses to L1 and L2 capsids of human papillomavirus types 6, 11, 16, 18, and 33 L1 after newly acquired infection. Sex. Transm. Infect. 74<b>:</b>354-360.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1758137</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10195032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Wang, S. S., M. Schiffman, R. Herrero, J. Carreon, A. Hildesheim, A. C. Rodriguez, M. C. Bratti, M. E. Sherman, J. Morales, D. Guillen, M. Alfaro, B. Clayman, R. D. Burk, and R. P. Viscidi.</b> 2004. Determinants of human papillomavirus 16 serological conversion and persistence in a population-based cohort of 10 000 women in Costa Rica. Br. J. Cancer 91<b>:</b>1269-1274.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2409899</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15292929</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Wang, Z. H., L. Kjellberg, H. Abdalla, F. Wiklund, C. Eklund, P. Knekt, M. Lehtinen, I. Kallings, P. Lenner, G. Hallmans, C. G. M&#xe4;hlck, G. Wadell, and J. Schiller.</b> 2000. Type specificity and significance of different isotypes of serum antibodies to human papillomavirus capsids. J. Infect. Dis. 181<b>:</b>456-462.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10669326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation><b>Wideroff, L., M. H. Schiffman, B. Nonnenmacher, N. Hubbert, R. Kirnbauer, C. E. Greer, D. Lowy, A. T. Lorincz, M. M. Manos, A. G. Glass, et al.</b> 1995. Evaluation of seroreactivity to human papillomavirus type 16 virus-like particles in an incident case-control study of cervical neoplasia. J. Infect. Dis. 172<b>:</b>1425-1430.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7594698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>