<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">27884172</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2017</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>26</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1756-3305</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>9</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2016</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>25</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Parasites &amp; vectors</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Parasit Vectors</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Spatial distribution and trypanosome infection of tsetse flies in the sleeping sickness focus of Zimbabwe in Hurungwe District.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>605</StartPage><MedlinePgn>605</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">605</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">In Zimbabwe, cases of human African trypanosomiasis (HAT) are caused by the unicellular protozoan Trypanosoma brucei, sub-species T. b. rhodesiense. They are reported from the tsetse-infested area in the northern part of the country, broadly corresponding to the valley of the Zambezi River. Tsetse-transmitted trypanosomes, in particular T. congolense and T. vivax, also cause morbidity and mortality in livestock, thus generating poverty and food insecurity. Two species of tsetse fly, Glossina morsistans morsitans and G. pallidipes, are known to be present in the Zambezi Valley, although their distributional patterns and densities have not been investigated in detail. The present study tries to address this gap by providing some insight into the dynamics of trypanosomiasis in humans and livestock.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">Tsetse distribution and trypanosome infections were studied using traps and fixed fly rounds located at 10&#xa0;km intervals along a 110&#xa0;km long transect straddling the southern escarpment of the Zambezi Valley. Three km long fly rounds were conducted on 12 sites, and were repeated 11 times over a 7-month period. Additional traps were deployed and monitored in selected sites. Microscopic examination of 2092 flies for trypanosome infections was conducted.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">Surveys confirmed the presence of G. morsitans morsitans and G. pallidipes in the Zambezi Valley floor. Moving south, the apparent density of tsetse flies appears to peak in the vicinity of the escarpment, then drops on the highlands. Only one fly was caught south of the old game fence separating protected and settled areas. A trypanosome infection rate of 6.31% was recorded in tsetse flies dissected. Only one infection of the T. brucei-type was detected.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">Tsetse fly distribution in the study area appears to be driven by ecological factors such as variation in land use and altitude-mediated climatic patterns. Although targeted control of tsetse flies have played a role in determining distribution, no major control operations have been implemented in the area for 15&#xa0;years. Trypanosome infections in tsetse flies are consistent with HAT epidemiological data, which considers the situation to be generally 'low risk'. Nonetheless, underreporting is likely to conceal the true epidemiological picture, and efforts are needed to strengthen the diagnostic capacities of health facilities.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shereni</LastName><ForeName>William</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9427-4349</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tsetse Control Division, Department of Livestock and Veterinary Services, Ministry of Agriculture, Mechanization and Irrigation Development, Harare, Zimbabwe. shereni2005@yahoo.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Anderson</LastName><ForeName>Neil E</ForeName><Initials>NE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Royal (Dick) School of Veterinary Studies and the Roslin Institute, University of Edinburgh, Easter Bush Campus, Roslin, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nyakupinda</LastName><ForeName>Learnmore</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tsetse Control Division, Department of Livestock and Veterinary Services, Ministry of Agriculture, Mechanization and Irrigation Development, Harare, Zimbabwe.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cecchi</LastName><ForeName>Giuliano</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Sub-Regional Office for Eastern Africa, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2016</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>25</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Parasit Vectors</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101462774</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1756-3305</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007303" MajorTopicYN="N">Insect Vectors</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="Y">parasitology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014346" MajorTopicYN="Y">Trypanosoma brucei brucei</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014353" MajorTopicYN="N">Trypanosomiasis, African</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="N">parasitology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000662" MajorTopicYN="N">veterinary</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014370" MajorTopicYN="N">Tsetse Flies</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000469" MajorTopicYN="Y">parasitology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015030" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Zimbabwe</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">African animal trypanosomiasis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Glossina</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sleeping sickness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Tsetse</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Zimbabwe</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2016</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2016</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2016</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2016</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2017</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2016</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27884172</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5123324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13071-016-1879-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s13071-016-1879-5</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Steverding D. The history of African trypanosomiasis. Parasit Vectors. 2008;1(1):3. doi: 10.1186/1756-3305-1-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-1-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2270819</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18275594</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ford J. The role of the trypanosomiases in African ecology. A study of the tsetse fly problem. Oxford: Clarendon Press; 1971.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Phelps RJ, Lovemore DF. Vectors: Tsetse flies. In: Coetzer JAW, Thomson GR, Tustin RC, editors. Infectious diseases of livestock with special reference to southern Africa. Cape Town: Oxford University Press; 1994. p. 25&#x2013;52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jordan A. Trypanosomiasis control and African rural development. London: Longman; 1986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jack RW. Tsetse fly and big game in Southern Rhodesia. Bull Entomol Res. 1914;5(02):97&#x2013;110. doi: 10.1017/S0007485300033940.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0007485300033940</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cecchi G, Paone M, Feldmann U, Vreysen MJB, Diall O, Mattioli RC. Assembling a geospatial database of tsetse-transmitted animal trypanosomosis for Africa. Parasit Vectors. 2014;7:39. doi: 10.1186/1756-3305-7-39.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-7-39</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4015763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24447638</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cecchi G, Paone M, Argiles Herrero R, Vreysen MJ, Mattioli RC. Developing a continental atlas of the distribution and trypanosomal infection of tsetse flies (Glossina species) Parasit Vectors. 2015;8:284. doi: 10.1186/s13071-015-0898-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13071-015-0898-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4448735</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25994757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed SK. The spatial distribution of bovine trypanosomosis, tsetse and tabanids flies in Sudan: an epidemiological update. Khartoum: Sudan Academy of Sciences; 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO . Control and surveillance of human African trypanosomiasis. In: Technical Report Series. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24552089</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simarro PP, Cecchi G, Paone M, Franco JR, Diarra A, Ruiz JA, et al. The Atlas of human African trypanosomiasis: a contribution to global mapping of neglected tropical diseases. Int J Health Geogr. 2010;9:57. doi: 10.1186/1476-072X-9-57.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-9-57</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2988709</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21040555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simarro PP, Franco JR, Cecchi G, Paone M, Diarra A, Ruiz JA, et al. Human African trypanosomiasis in non-endemic countries (2000&#x2013;2010) J Travel Med. 2012;19(1):44&#x2013;53. doi: 10.1111/j.1708-8305.2011.00576.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1708-8305.2011.00576.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22221811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vale G. Responses of tsetse flies (Diptera: Glossinidae) to vegetation in Zimbabwe: implications for population distribution and bait siting. Bull Entomol Res. 1998;88:S10&#x2013;59.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Potts W. A contribution to the study of numbers of tsetse fly (Glossina morsitans Westw.) by quantitative methods. S Afr J Sci. 1930;27:491&#x2013;497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ford J, Glasgow J, Johns D, Welch J. Transect fly-rounds in field studies of Glossina. Bull Entomol Res. 1959;50(02):275&#x2013;285. doi: 10.1017/S0007485300054584.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0007485300054584</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shereni W. The use of cloth screens and acetone vapour as alternatives to a bait-ox for sampling populations of tsetse flies (Diptera: Glossinidae) Trans Zimb Sci Assoc. 1984;62:22&#x2013;27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brady J. Spontaneous, circadian components of tsetse fly activity. J Insect Physiol. 1972;18(3):471&#x2013;484. doi: 10.1016/0022-1910(72)90078-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0022-1910(72)90078-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5045295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leak GA, Tsetse biology and ecology: Their role in epidemiology and control of trypanosomosis. Nairobi: ILRI (aka ILCA and ILRAD); 1999.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torr S, Hall D, Phelps R, Vale G. Methods for dispensing odour attractants for tsetse flies (Diptera: Glossinidae) Bull Entomol Res. 1997;87(03):299&#x2013;311. doi: 10.1017/S0007485300037251.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0007485300037251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lloyd L, Johnson W. The trypanosome infections of tsetse-flies in Northern Nigeria and a new method of estimation. Bull Entomol Res. 1924;14:265&#x2013;288.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Minitab 17 Statistical Software. [Computer software]. State College, PA: Minitab, Inc. (2010). (http://www.minitab.com)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. (2014). URL http://www.R-project.org/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>StatSoft, Inc. STATISTICA (data analysis software system), (2008) version 8.0 http://www.statsoft.com. Accessed 10 Nov 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van den Bossche P. Some general aspects of the distribution and epidemiology of bovine trypanosomosis in southern Africa. Int J Parasitol. 2001;31(5):592&#x2013;598. doi: 10.1016/S0020-7519(01)00146-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0020-7519(01)00146-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11334947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouyer J, Bouyer F, Donadeu M, Rowan T, Napier G. Community-and farmer-based management of animal African trypanosomosis in cattle. Trends Parasitol. 2013;29(11):519&#x2013;522. doi: 10.1016/j.pt.2013.08.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2013.08.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24012356</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ducheyne E, Mweempa C, De Pus C, Verniuwe H, De Deken R, Hendrickx G, et al. The impact of habitat fragmentation on tsetse abundance on the plateau of eastern Zambia. Prev Vet Med. 2009;91:11&#x2013;18. doi: 10.1016/j.prevetmed.2009.05.009.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2009.05.009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2722901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19523702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munang&#x2019;andu HM, Siamudaala V, Munyeme M, Nalubamba KS. A review of ecological factors associated with the epidemiology of wildlife trypanosomiasis in the Luangwa and Zambezi Valley ecosystems of Zambia. Interdiscip Perspect Infect Dis. 2012:2012;372523.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3368204</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22693499</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leak SGE, Ejigu D, Vreysen MJB. Collection of entomological baseline data for tsetse area-wide integrated pest management programmes. Rome: Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vale GA. Tsetse control - a new method holds exciting prospects. Tobacco Forum. 1974;2:19&#x2013;23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simarro PP, Cecchi G, Franco JR, Paone M, F&#xe8;vre EM, Diarra A, et al. Estimating and mapping the population at risk of sleeping sickness. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2012;6(10):e1859. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0001859.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0001859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3493382</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23145192</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simarro PP, Cecchi G, Franco JR, Paone M, Diarra A, Ruiz-Postigo JA, et al. Mapping the capacities of fixed health facilities to cover people at risk of gambiense human African trypanosomiasis. Int J Health Geogr. 2014;13:4. doi: 10.1186/1476-072X-13-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-13-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3938140</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24517513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouyer J, Dicko AH, Cecchi G, Ravel S, Guerrini L, Solano P, et al. Mapping landscape friction to locate isolated tsetse populations that are candidates for elimination. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2015;112(47):14575&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4664298</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26553973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>