<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">35232491</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2397-7523</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>6</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>02</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Diagnostic and prognostic research</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Diagn Progn Res</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The comparative interrupted time series design for assessment of diagnostic impact: methodological considerations and an example using point-of-care C-reactive protein testing.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>3</StartPage><MedlinePgn>3</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">3</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s41512-022-00118-w</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">In diagnostic evaluation, it is necessary to assess the clinical impact of a new diagnostic as well as its diagnostic accuracy. The comparative interrupted time series design has been proposed as a quasi-experimental approach to evaluating interventions. We show how it can be used in the design of a study to evaluate a point-of-care diagnostic test for C-reactive protein in out-of-hours primary care services, to guide antibiotic prescribing among patients presenting with possible respiratory tract infection. This study consisted of a retrospective phase that used routinely collected monthly antibiotic prescribing data from different study sites, and a prospective phase in which antibiotic prescribing rates were monitored after the C-reactive protein diagnostic was introduced at some of the sites.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Of 8 study sites, 3 were assigned to receive the diagnostic and 5 were assigned as controls. We obtained retrospective monthly time series of respiratory tract targeted antibiotic prescriptions at each site. Separate ARIMA models at each site were used these to forecast monthly prescription counts that would be expected in the prospective phase, using simulation to obtain a set of 1-year predictions alongside their standard errors. We show how these forecasts can be combined to test for a change in prescription rates after introduction of the diagnostic and estimate power to detect this change.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Fitted time series models at each site were stationary and showed second-order annual seasonality, with a clear December peak in prescriptions, although the timing and extent of the peak varied between sites and between years. Mean one-year predictions of antibiotic prescribing rates based on the retrospective time series analysis differed between sites assigned to receive the diagnostic and those assigned to control. Adjusting for the trend in the retrospective time series at each site removed these differences.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Quasi-experimental designs such as comparative interrupted time series can be used in diagnostic evaluation to estimate effect sizes before conducting a full randomised controlled trial or if a randomised trial is infeasible. In multi-site studies, existing retrospective data should be used to adjust for underlying differences between sites to make outcome data from different sites comparable, when possible.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2022. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fanshawe</LastName><ForeName>Thomas R</ForeName><Initials>TR</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9928-8934</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, OX2 6GG, UK. thomas.fanshawe@phc.ox.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Turner</LastName><ForeName>Philip J</ForeName><Initials>PJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, OX2 6GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gillespie</LastName><ForeName>Marjorie M</ForeName><Initials>MM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Practice Plus Group, Hawker House, 5-6 Napier Court, Napier Road, Reading, Berkshire, England, RG1 8BW, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hayward</LastName><ForeName>Gail N</ForeName><Initials>GN</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Nuffield Department of Primary Care Health Sciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, OX2 6GG, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>MIC-2016-018</GrantID><Agency>national institute for health research (nihr) community healthcare medtech and in vitro diagnostics co-operative at oxford health nhs foundation trust</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>02</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Diagn Progn Res</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101718985</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2397-7523</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">ARIMA</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">C-reactive protein</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Diagnostic</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Point-of-care</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Quasi-experimental</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Time series</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Not applicable. Competing interests. All authors declare that they have no competing interests. All authors declare that they have no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>13</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>45</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35232491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8888027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s41512-022-00118-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s41512-022-00118-w</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Lord SJ, Irwig L, Simes RJ. When is measuring sensitivity and specificity sufficient to evaluate a diagnostic test, and when do we need randomized trials. Ann Intern Med. 2006;144(11):850&#x2013;855. doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-144-11-200606060-00011.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-144-11-200606060-00011</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16754927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verbakel JY, Turner PJ, Thompson MJ, Pl&#xfc;ddemann A, Price CP, Shinkins B, van den Bruel A. Common evidence gaps in point-of-care diagnostic test evaluation: a review of horizon scan reports. BMJ Open. 2017;7(9):e015760. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2016-015760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-015760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5588931</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28864692</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shinkins B, Yang Y, Abel L, Fanshawe TR. Evidence synthesis to inform model-based cost-effectiveness evaluations of diagnostic tests: a methodological review of health technology assessments. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2017;17(1):56. doi: 10.1186/s12874-017-0331-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12874-017-0331-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5391551</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28410588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Abel L, Buchanan J, Fanshawe T, Shinkins B. Use of decision modelling in economic evaluations of diagnostic tests: an appraisal and review of Health Technology Assessments in the UK. Pharmacoecon Open. 2019;3(3):281&#x2013;291. doi: 10.1007/s41669-018-0109-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s41669-018-0109-9</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6710311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30552651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bossuyt PM, Lijmer JG, Mol BW. Randomised comparisons of medical tests: sometimes invalid, not always efficient. Lancet. 2000;356(9244):1844&#x2013;1847. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(00)03246-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(00)03246-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11117930</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van den Bruel A, Cleemput I, Aertgeerts B, Ramaekers D, Buntinx F. The evaluation of diagnostic tests: evidence on technical and diagnostic accuracy, impact on patient outcome and cost-effectiveness is needed. J Clin Epidemiol. 2007;60(11):1116&#x2013;1122. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2007.03.015.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2007.03.015</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17938052</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steyerberg EW, Moons KG, van der Windt DA, Hayden JA, Perel P, Schroter S, et al. Prognosis Research Strategy (PROGRESS) 3: prognostic model research. PLoS Med. 2013;10(2):e1001381. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1001381.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1001381</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3564751</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23393430</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Regulation (EU) 2017/746 of the European Parliament and of the Council, L117/176. https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:32017R0746&amp;from=EN. Accessed 11 June 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deeks JJ, Dinnes J, D'Amico R, Sowden AJ, Sakarovitch C, Song F, et al. Evaluating non-randomised intervention studies. Health Technol Assess. 2003;7(27):iii-x. doi: 10.3310/hta7270.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3310/hta7270</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14499048</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrante di Ruffano L, Deeks JJ. Test-treatment RCTs are sheep in wolves' clothing. J Clin Epidemiol. 2016;69:266&#x2013;267. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.06.013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.06.013</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26130595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wagner AK, Soumerai SB, Zhang F, Ross-Degnan D. Segmented regression analysis of interrupted time series studies in medication use research. J Clin Pharm Ther. 2002;27(4):299&#x2013;309. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-2710.2002.00430.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2710.2002.00430.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12174032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bernal JL, Cummins S, Gasparrini A. Interrupted time series regression for the evaluation of public health interventions: a tutorial. Int J Epidemiol. 2017;46(1):348&#x2013;355. doi: 10.1093/ije/dyw098.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ije/dyw098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5407170</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27283160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bjerrum L, Cots JM, Llor C, Molist N, Munck A. Effect of intervention promoting a reduction in antibiotic prescribing by improvement of diagnostic procedures: a prospective, before and after study in general practice. Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2006;62(11):913&#x2013;918. doi: 10.1007/s00228-006-0187-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00228-006-0187-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16967300</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cals JW, Ebell MH. C-reactive protein: guiding antibiotic prescribing decisions at the point of care. Br J Gen Pract. 2018;68(668):112&#x2013;113. doi: 10.3399/bjgp18X694901.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/bjgp18X694901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5819954</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29472204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ward C. Point-of-care C-reactive protein testing to optimise antibiotic use in a primary care urgent care centre setting. BMJ Open Quality. 2018;7(4):e000391. doi: 10.1136/bmjoq-2018-000391.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjoq-2018-000391</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6203029</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30397661</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hayward GN, Fisher RFR, Spence GT, Lasserson DS. Increase in antibiotic prescriptions in out-of-hours primary care in contrast to in-hours primary care prescriptions: service evaluation in a population of 600&#x200a;000 patients. J Antimicrob Chemoth. 2016;71(9):2612&#x2013;2619. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkw189.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/dkw189</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4992853</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27287234</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang Y, Chen R, Wu T, Wei X, Guo A. Association between point-of-care CRP testing and antibiotic prescribing in respiratory tract infections: a systematic review and meta-analysis of primary care studies. Br J Gen Pract. 2013;63(616):e787&#x2013;e794. doi: 10.3399/bjgp13X674477.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3399/bjgp13X674477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3809432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24267862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Out-of-hours services (OOH). https://www.careukhealthcare.com/our-services/out-of-hours-services. Accessed 11 June 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kontopantelis E, Doran T, Springate DA, Buchan I, Reeves D. Regression based quasi-experimental approach when randomisation is not an option: interrupted time series analysis. BMJ. 2015;350(jun09 5):h2750. doi: 10.1136/bmj.h2750.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.h2750</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4460815</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26058820</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hudson J, Fielding S, Ramsay CR. Methodology and reporting characteristics of studies using interrupted time series design in healthcare. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2019;19(1):137. doi: 10.1186/s12874-019-0777-x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12874-019-0777-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6609377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31272382</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Biglan A, Ary D, Wagenaar AC. The value of interrupted time-series experiments for community intervention research. Prev Sci. 2000;1(1):31&#x2013;49. doi: 10.1023/A:1010024016308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1023/A:1010024016308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4553062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11507793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacob R, Somers M-A, Zhu P, Bloom H. The validity of the comparative interrupted time series design for evaluating the effect of school-level interventions. Evaluation Rev. 2016;40(3):167&#x2013;198. doi: 10.1177/0193841X16663414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/0193841X16663414</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27553034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cruz M, Gillen DL, Bender M, Ombao H. Assessing health care interventions via an interrupted time series model: Study power and design considerations. Stat Med. 2019;38(10):1734&#x2013;1752. doi: 10.1002/sim.8067.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/sim.8067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7959401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30616298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang F, Wagner AK, Ross-Degnan D. Simulation-based power calculation for designing interrupted time series analyses of health policy interventions. J Clin Epidemiol. 2011;64(11):1252&#x2013;1261. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2011.02.007.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2011.02.007</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21640554</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chatfield C. The analysis of time series: an introduction. 6. Chapman &amp; Hall/CRC: Boca Raton; 2003.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fretheim A, Zhang F, Ross-Degnan D, Oxman AD, Cheyne H, Foy R, Goodacre S, Herrin J, Kerse N, McKinlay RJ, Wright A, Soumerai SB. A reanalysis of cluster randomized trials showed interrupted time-series studies were valuable in health system evaluation. J Clin Epidemiol. 2015;68(3):324&#x2013;333. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.10.003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2014.10.003</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25499983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fanshawe TR, Diggle PJ, Rushton S, Sanderson R, Lurz PWW, Glinianaia SV, Pearce MS, Parker L, Charlton M, Pless-Mulloli T. Modelling spatio-temporal variation in exposure to particulate matter: a two-stage approach. Environmetrics. 2008;19(6):549&#x2013;566. doi: 10.1002/env.889.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/env.889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyndman RJ, Khandakar Y. Automatic time series forecasting: the forecast package for R. J Stat Softw. 2008;27(3):1&#x2013;22. doi: 10.18637/jss.v027.i03.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18637/jss.v027.i03</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harvey AC, McKenzie CR. Algorithm AS 182: finite sample prediction from ARIMA processes. J R Stat Soc C - App. 1982;31(2):180&#x2013;187.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Durbin J, Koopman SJ. Time series analysis by state space methods. 2. Oxford: Oxford University Press; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hyndman R, Athanasopoulos G, Bergmeir C, Caceres G, Chhay L, O'Hara-Wild M, et al. forecast: Forecasting functions for time series and linear models. R package version 8.12. 2020. https://pkg.robjhyndman.com/forecast.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weatherburn CE. A first course in mathematical statistics. 2. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; 1968.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Elseviers MM, Ferech M, Vander Stichele RH, Goossens H, ESAC Project Group Antibiotic use in ambulatory care in Europe (ESAC data 1997&#x2013;2002): trends, regional differences and seasonal fluctuations. Pharmacoepidem Dr S. 2007;16(1):115&#x2013;123. doi: 10.1002/pds.1244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/pds.1244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16700079</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Curtis HJ, Walker AJ, Mahtani KR, Goldacre B. Time trends and geographical variation in prescribing of antibiotics in England 1998&#x2013;2017. J Antimicrob Chemoth. 2018;74(1):242&#x2013;250. doi: 10.1093/jac/dky377.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/dky377</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30239809</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fleming DM, Ross AM, Cross KW, Kendall H. The reducing incidence of respiratory tract infection and its relation to antibiotic prescribing. Br J Gen Pract. 2003;53(495):778&#x2013;783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1314710</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14601353</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>St. Clair T, Cook TD, Hallberg K. Examining the internal validity and statistical precision of the comparative interrupted time series design by comparison with a randomized experiment. Am J Eval. 2014;35(3):311&#x2013;327. doi: 10.1177/1098214014527337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/1098214014527337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrante di Ruffano L, Dinnes J, Sitch AJ, Hyde C, Deeks JJ. Test-treatment RCTs are susceptible to bias: a review of the methodological quality of randomized trials that evaluate diagnostic tests. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2017;17(1):35. doi: 10.1186/s12874-016-0287-z.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12874-016-0287-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5326492</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28236806</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edelstein M, Agbebiyi A, Ashiru-Oredope D, Hopkins S. Trends and patterns in antibiotic prescribing among out-of-hours primary care providers in England, 2010&#x2013;14. J Antimicrob Chemoth. 2017;72(12):3490&#x2013;3495. doi: 10.1093/jac/dkx323.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jac/dkx323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5890685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28961983</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>