<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">24723276</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2015</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>28</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>28</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1537-6591</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>59</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2014</Year><Month>Jul</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Clinical infectious diseases : an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Clin Infect Dis</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Prevention of central line-associated bloodstream infections through quality improvement interventions: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>96</StartPage><EndPage>105</EndPage><MedlinePgn>96-105</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/cid/ciu239</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>This systematic review and meta-analysis examines the impact of quality improvement interventions on central line-associated bloodstream infections in adult intensive care units. Studies were identified through Medline and manual searches (1995-June 2012). Random-effects meta-analysis obtained pooled odds ratios (ORs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs). Meta-regression assessed the impact of bundle/checklist interventions and high baseline rates on intervention effect. Forty-one before-after studies identified an infection rate decrease (OR, 0.39 [95% CI, .33-.46]; P &lt; .001). This effect was more pronounced for trials implementing a bundle or checklist approach (P = .03). Furthermore, meta-analysis of 6 interrupted time series studies revealed an infection rate reduction 3 months postintervention (OR, 0.30 [95% CI, .10-.88]; P = .03). There was no difference in infection rates between studies with low or high baseline rates (P = .18). These results suggest that quality improvement interventions contribute to the prevention of central line-associated bloodstream infections. Implementation of care bundles and checklists appears to yield stronger risk reductions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Infectious Diseases Society of America. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Blot</LastName><ForeName>Koen</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Ghent University.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bergs</LastName><ForeName>Jochen</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Economics and Patient Safety, Hasselt University, Hasselt, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vogelaers</LastName><ForeName>Dirk</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Ghent University General Internal Medicine, Ghent University Hospital, Ghent.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Blot</LastName><ForeName>Stijn</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Ghent University Burns, Trauma and Critical Care Research Centre, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vandijck</LastName><ForeName>Dominique</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Ghent University General Internal Medicine, Ghent University Hospital, Ghent Health Economics and Patient Safety, Hasselt University, Hasselt, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2014</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>09</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Clin Infect Dis</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9203213</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1058-4838</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001521" MajorTopicYN="N">Behavior Therapy</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="Y">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055499" MajorTopicYN="N">Catheter-Related Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="Y">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003428" MajorTopicYN="N">Cross Infection</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="Y">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058996" MajorTopicYN="Y">Quality Improvement</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018805" MajorTopicYN="N">Sepsis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="Y">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">catheter-related bloodstream infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">central line&#x2013;associated bloodstream infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">meta-analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">quality improvement intervention</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2014</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2014</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2015</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2015</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24723276</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4305144</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciu239</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ciu239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Central line&#x2013;associated bloodstream infection (CLABSI) event protocol. 2014. pp. 1&#x2013;10. Available at: http://www.cdc.gov.  Accessed 9 February 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Atlanta, GA: CDC; 2014. NHSN key terms. pp. 1&#x2013;16. Available at: http://www.cdc.gov.  Accessed 22 March 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blot SI, Depuydt P, Annemans L, et al. Clinical and economic outcomes in critically ill patients with nosocomial catheter-related bloodstream infections. Clin Infect Dis. 2005;41:1591&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16267731</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Umscheid CA, Mitchell MD, Doshi JA, Agarwal R, Williams K, Brennan PJ. Estimating the proportion of healthcare-associated infections that are reasonably preventable and the related mortality and costs. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2011;32:101&#x2013;14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21460463</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenthal VD. Central line&#x2013;associated bloodstream infections in limited-resource countries: a review of the literature. Clin Infect Dis. 2009;49:1899&#x2013;907.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19911941</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olaechea PM, Palomar M, &#xc1;lvarez-Lerma F, et al. Morbidity and mortality associated with primary and catheter-related bloodstream infections in critically ill patients. Rev Esp Quimioter. 2013;26:21&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23546458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Januel JM, Harbarth S, Allard R, et al. Estimating attributable mortality due to nosocomial infections acquired in intensive care units. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2010;31:388&#x2013;94.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20156064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marra AR, Cal RG, Durao MS, et al. Impact of a program to prevent central line-associated bloodstream infection in the zero tolerance era. Am J Infect Control. 2010;38:434&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20226570</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pronovost PJ, Goeschel CA, Colantuoni E, et al. Sustaining reductions in catheter related bloodstream infections in Michigan intensive care units: observational study. BMJ. 2010;340:c309.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2816728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20133365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Grady NP, Alexander M, Burns LA, et al. Guidelines for the prevention of intravascular catheter-related infections. Clin Infect Dis. 2011;52:e162&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3106269</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21460264</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yokoe DS, Mermel LA, Anderson DJ, et al. Executive summary: a compendium of strategies to prevent healthcare-associated infections in acute care hospitals. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2008;29:S12&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18840084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Maki DG, Kluger DM, Crnich CJ. The risk of bloodstream infection in adults with different intravascular devices: a systematic review of 200 published prospective studies. Mayo Clin Proc. 2006;81:1159&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16970212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blot S, Vandijck D, Vogelaers D, Labeau S. Bridging the gap between theory and practice. ICU Management. 2011;11:40&#x2013;11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Labeau SO, Vandijck DM, Rello J, et al. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention guidelines for preventing central venous catheter-related infection: results of a knowledge test among 3405 European intensive care nurses. Crit Care Med. 2009;37:320&#x2013;23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19050628</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cabana MD, Rand CS, Powe NR, et al. Why don't physicians follow clinical practice guidelines? A framework for improvement. JAMA. 1999;282:1458&#x2013;65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10535437</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ranji SR, Shetty K, Posley KA, et al. Rockville, MD: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality; 2007. Closing the quality gap: a critical analysis of quality improvement strategies. Vol 6: Prevention of healthcare&#x2013;associated infections.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20734530</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Downs SH, Black N. The feasibility of creating a checklist for the assessment of the methodological quality both of randomised and non-randomised studies of health care interventions. J Epidemiol Community Health. 1998;52:377&#x2013;84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1756728</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9764259</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraher MH, Collins CJ, Bourke J, Phelan D, Lynch M. Cost-effectiveness of employing a total parenteral nutrition surveillance nurse for the prevention of catheter-related bloodstream infections. J Hosp Infect. 2009;73:129&#x2013;34.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19709776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flodgren G, Conterno LO, Mayhew A, Omar O, Pereira CR, Shepperd S. Interventions to improve professional adherence to guidelines for prevention of device-related infections. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013 doi:10.1002/14651858.CD006559.pub2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23543545</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coopersmith CM, Rebmann TL, Zack JE, et al. Effect of an education program on decreasing catheter-related bloodstream infections in the surgical intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 2002;30:59&#x2013;64.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11902288</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pronovost P, Needham D, Berenholtz S, et al. An intervention to decrease catheter-related bloodstream infections in the ICU. N Engl J Med. 2006;355:2725&#x2013;32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17192537</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Coopersmith CM, Zack JE, Ward MR, et al. The impact of bedside behavior on catheter-related bacteremia in the intensive care unit. Arch Surg. 2004;139:131&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14769568</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richardson J, Tjoelker R. Beyond the central line-associated bloodstream infection bundle: the value of the clinical nurse specialist in continuing evidence-based practice changes. Clin Nurse Spec. 2012;26:205&#x2013;11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22678186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenthal VD, Maki DG, Rodrigues C, et al. Impact of International Nosocomial Infection Control Consortium (INICC) strategy on central line&#x2013;associated bloodstream infection rates in the intensive care units of 15 developing countries. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2010;31:1264&#x2013;72.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21029008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berenholtz SM, Pronovost PJ, Lipsett PA, et al. Eliminating catheter-related bloodstream infections in the intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 2004;32:2014&#x2013;20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15483409</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cherry-Bukowiec JR, Denchev K, Dickinson S, et al. Prevention of catheter-related blood stream infection: back to basics? Surg Infect (Larchmt) 2011;12:27&#x2013;32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21171811</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longmate AG, Ellis KS, Boyle L, et al. Elimination of central-venous-catheter-related bloodstream infections from the intensive care unit. BMJ Qual Saf. 2011;20:174&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21303772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller RS, Norris PR, Jenkins JM, et al. Systems initiatives reduce healthcare-associated infections: a study of 22,928 device days in a single trauma unit. J Trauma. 2010;68:23&#x2013;31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20065753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munoz-Price LS, Dezfulian C, Wyckoff M, et al. Effectiveness of stepwise interventions targeted to decrease central catheter-associated bloodstream infections. Crit Care Med. 2012;40:1464&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22511128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ong A, Dysert K, Herbert C, et al. Trends in central line&#x2013;associated bloodstream infections in a trauma-surgical intensive care unit. Arch Surg. 2011;146:302&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21422361</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ramos ER, Reitzel R, Jiang Y, et al. Clinical effectiveness and risk of emerging resistance associated with prolonged use of antibiotic-impregnated catheters: more than 0.5 million catheter days and 7 years of clinical experience. Crit Care Med. 2011;39:245&#x2013;51.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21057308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Royer T. Implementing a better bundle to achieve and sustain a zero central line-associated bloodstream infection rate. J Infus Nurs. 2010;33:398&#x2013;406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21079468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seddon ME, Hocking CJ, Mead P, Simpson C. Aiming for zero: decreasing central line associated bacteraemia in the intensive care unit. N Z Med J. 2011;124:9&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21952326</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gastmeier P, Geffers C, Brandt C, et al. Effectiveness of a nationwide nosocomial infection surveillance system for reducing nosocomial infections. J Hosp Infect. 2006;64:16&#x2013;22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16820247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McLaws ML, Burrell AR. Zero risk for central line-associated bloodstream infection: are we there yet? Crit Care Med. 2012;40:388&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22020239</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonello RS, Fletcher CE, Becker WK, et al. An intensive care unit quality improvement collaborative in nine Department of Veterans Affairs hospitals: reducing ventilator-associated pneumonia and catheter-related bloodstream infection rates. Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf. 2008;34:639&#x2013;45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19025084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koll BS, Straub TA, Jalon HS, Block R, Heller KS, Ruiz RE. The CLABs collaborative: a regionwide effort to improve the quality of care in hospitals. Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf. 2008;34:713&#x2013;23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19119725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Render ML, Hasselbeck R, Freyberg RW, Hofer TP, Sales AE, Almenoff PL. Reduction of central line infections in Veterans Administration intensive care units: an observational cohort using a central infrastructure to support learning and improvement. BMJ Qual Saf. 2011;20:725&#x2013;32.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21460392</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bijma R, Girbes AR, Kleijer DJ, Zwaveling JH. Preventing central venous catheter-related infection in a surgical intensive-care unit. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 1999;20:618&#x2013;20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10501261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dixon JM, Carver RL. Daily chlorohexidine gluconate bathing with impregnated cloths results in statistically significant reduction in central line-associated bloodstream infections. Am J Infect Control. 2010;38:817&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21093698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duane TM, Brown H, Borchers CT, et al. A central venous line protocol decreases bloodstream infections and length of stay in a trauma intensive care unit population. Am Surg. 2009;75:1166&#x2013;70.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19999905</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frankel HL, Crede WB, Topal JE, Roumanis SA, Devlin MW, Foley AB. Use of corporate Six Sigma performance-improvement strategies to reduce incidence of catheter-related bloodstream infections in a surgical ICU. J Am Coll Surg. 2005;201:349&#x2013;58.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16125067</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Galpern D, Guerrero A, Tu A, Fahoum B, Wise L. Effectiveness of a central line bundle campaign on line-associated infections in the intensive care unit. Surgery. 2008;144:492&#x2013;5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18847630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gozu A, Clay C, Younus F. Hospital-wide reduction in central line-associated bloodstream infections: a tale of two small community hospitals. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2011;32:619&#x2013;22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21558777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guerin K, Wagner J, Rains K, Bessesen M. Reduction in central line-associated bloodstream infections by implementation of a postinsertion care bundle. Am J Infect Control. 2010;38:430&#x2013;3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20570395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higuera F, Rosenthal VD, Duarte P, Ruiz J, Franco G, Safdar N. The effect of process control on the incidence of central venous catheter-associated bloodstream infections and mortality in intensive care units in Mexico. Crit Care Med. 2005;33:2022&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16148475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim JS, Holtom P, Vigen C. Reduction of catheter-related bloodstream infections through the use of a central venous line bundle: epidemiologic and economic consequences. Am J Infect Control. 2011;39:640&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21641088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lopez AC. A quality improvement program combining maximal barrier precaution compliance monitoring and daily chlorhexidine gluconate baths resulting in decreased central line bloodstream infections. Dimens Crit Care Nurs. 2011;30:293&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21841426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosenthal VD, Guzman S, Pezzotto SM, Crnich CJ. Effect of an infection control program using education and performance feedback on rates of intravascular device-associated bloodstream infections in intensive care units in Argentina. Am J Infect Control. 2003;31:405&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14639436</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santana SL, Furtado GH, Wey SB, Medeiros EA. Impact of an education program on the incidence of central line-associated bloodstream infection in 2 medical-surgical intensive care units in Brazil. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2008;29:1171&#x2013;3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18956978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Seguin P, Laviolle B, Isslame S, Coue A, Malledant Y. Effectiveness of simple daily sensitization of physicians to the duration of central venous and urinary tract catheterization. Intensive Care Med. 2010;36:1202&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20237761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shannon RP, Frndak D, Grunden N, et al. Using real-time problem solving to eliminate central line infections. Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf. 2006;32:479&#x2013;87.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17987871</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsuchida T, Makimoto K, Toki M, Sakai K, Onaka E, Otani Y. The effectiveness of a nurse-initiated intervention to reduce catheter-associated bloodstream infections in an urban acute hospital: an intervention study with before and after comparison. Int J Nurs Stud. 2007;44:1324&#x2013;33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16996516</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Venkatram S, Rachmale S, Kanna B. Study of device use adjusted rates in health care-associated infections after implementation of &#x2018;bundles&#x2019; in a closed-model medical intensive care unit. J Crit Care. 2010;25:174.e11&#x2013;18.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19682846</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wall RJ, Ely EW, Elasy TA, et al. Using real time process measurements to reduce catheter related bloodstream infections in the intensive care unit. Qual Saf Health Care. 2005;14:295&#x2013;302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1744064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16076796</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warren DK, Cosgrove SE, Diekema DJ, et al. A multicenter intervention to prevent catheter-associated bloodstream infections. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2006;27:662&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16807839</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoo S, Ha M, Choi D, Pai H. Effectiveness of surveillance of central catheter-related bloodstream infection in an ICU in korea. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2001;22:433&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11583212</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zingg W, Imhof A, Maggiorini M, Stocker R, Keller E, Ruef C. Impact of a prevention strategy targeting hand hygiene and catheter care on the incidence of catheter-related bloodstream infections. Crit Care Med. 2009;37:2167&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19487942</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chua C, Wisniewski T, Ramos A, Schlepp M, Fildes JJ, Kuhls DA. Multidisciplinary trauma intensive care unit checklist: impact on infection rates. J Trauma Nurs. 2010;17:163&#x2013;6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20838165</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lobo RD, Levin AS, Gomes LM, et al. Impact of an educational program and policy changes on decreasing catheter-associated bloodstream infections in a medical intensive care unit in Brazil. Am J Infect Control. 2005;33:83&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15761407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warren DK, Zack JE, Cox MJ, Cohen MM, Fraser VJ. An educational intervention to prevent catheter-associated bloodstream infections in a nonteaching, community medical center. Crit Care Med. 2003;31:1959&#x2013;63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12847389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berriel-Cass D, Adkins FW, Jones P, Fakih MG. Eliminating nosocomial infections at Ascension Health. Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf. 2006;32:612&#x2013;20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17120920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peredo R, Sabatier C, Villagra A, et al. Reduction in catheter-related bloodstream infections in critically ill patients through a multiple system intervention. Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis. 2010;29:1173&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20533071</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perez Parra A, Cruz Menarguez M, Perez Granda MJ, Tomey MJ, Padilla B, Bouza E. A simple educational intervention to decrease incidence of central line-associated bloodstream infection (CLABSI) in intensive care units with low baseline incidence of CLABSI. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2010;31:964&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20658936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Warren DK, Zack JE, Mayfield JL, et al. The effect of an education program on the incidence of central venous catheter-associated bloodstream infection in a medical ICU. Chest. 2004;126:1612&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15539735</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lobo RD, Levin AS, Oliveira MS, et al. Evaluation of interventions to reduce catheter-associated bloodstream infection: continuous tailored education versus one basic lecture. Am J Infect Control. 2010;38:440&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20123149</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Safdar N, Abad C. Educational interventions for prevention of healthcare-associated infection: a systematic review. Crit Care Med. 2008;36:933&#x2013;40.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18431283</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aboelela SW, Stone PW, Larson EL. Effectiveness of bundled behavioural interventions to control healthcare-associated infections: a systematic review of the literature. J Hosp Infect. 2007;66:101&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17320242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eccles M, Grimshaw J, Campbell M, Ramsay C. Research designs for studies evaluating the effectiveness of change and improvement strategies. Qual Saf Health Care. 2003;12:47&#x2013;52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1743658</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12571345</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prior M, Guerin M, Grimmer-Somers K. The effectiveness of clinical guideline implementation strategies&#x2014;a synthesis of systematic review findings. J Eval Clin Pract. 2008;14:888&#x2013;97.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19018923</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>