<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">37580359</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>16</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2023</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>19</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2045-2322</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>13</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>Aug</Month><Day>14</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Scientific reports</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Sci Rep</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Construction and effectiveness evaluation of a knowledge-based infectious disease monitoring and decision support system.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>13202</StartPage><MedlinePgn>13202</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">13202</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1038/s41598-023-39931-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>To improve the hospital's ability to proactively detect infectious diseases, a knowledge-based infectious disease monitoring and decision support system was established based on real medical records and knowledge rules. The effectiveness of the system was evaluated using interrupted time series analysis. In the system, a monitoring and alert rule library for infectious diseases was generated by combining infectious disease diagnosis guidelines with literature and a real medical record knowledge map. The system was integrated with the electronic medical record system, and doctors were provided with various types of real-time warning prompts when writing medical records. The effectiveness of the system's alerts was analyzed from the perspectives of false positive rates, rule accuracy, alert effectiveness, and missed case rates using interrupted time series analysis. Over a period of 12&#xa0;months, the system analyzed 4,497,091 medical records, triggering a total of 12,027 monitoring alerts. Of these, 98.43% were clinically effective, while 1.56% were invalid alerts, mainly owing to the relatively rough rules generated by the guidelines leading to several false alarms. In addition, the effectiveness of the system's alerts, distribution of diagnosis times, and reporting efficiency of doctors were analyzed. 89.26% of infectious disease cases could be confirmed and reported by doctors within 5&#xa0;min of receiving the alert, and 77.6% of doctors could complete the filling of 33 items of information within 2&#xa0;min, which is a reduction in time compared to the past. The timely reminders from the system reduced the rate of missed cases by doctors; the analysis using interrupted time series method showed an average reduction of 4.4037% in the missed-case rate. This study proposed a knowledge-based infectious disease decision support system based on real medical records and knowledge rules, and its effectiveness was verified. The system improved the management of infectious diseases, increased the reliability of decision-making, and reduced the rate of underreporting.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2023. Springer Nature Limited.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Mengying</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Information Management and Big Data Center, Peking University Third Hospital, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Jia</LastName><ForeName>Mo</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Information Management and Big Data Center, Peking University Third Hospital, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wei</LastName><ForeName>Zhenhao</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Goodwill Hessian Health Technology Co. Ltd, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wang</LastName><ForeName>Wei</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Goodwill Hessian Health Technology Co. Ltd, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shang</LastName><ForeName>Yafei</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Goodwill Hessian Health Technology Co. Ltd, Beijing, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ji</LastName><ForeName>Hong</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Information Management and Big Data Center, Peking University Third Hospital, Beijing, China. puh3_imc@bjmu.edu.cn.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>14</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Sci Rep</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101563288</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2045-2322</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015203" MajorTopicYN="N">Reproducibility of Results</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D020000" MajorTopicYN="Y">Decision Support Systems, Clinical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012984" MajorTopicYN="N">Software</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008499" MajorTopicYN="N">Medical Records</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Communicable Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2023</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>23</Hour><Minute>19</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37580359</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10425425</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41598-023-39931-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1038/s41598-023-39931-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Jang H, Park AL, Lee Y-R, Ryu S, Lee J-Y, Kim J-M, Kim S-W, Kang Y-S. Relationship between economic loss and anxiety during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic: Moderating effects of knowledge, gratitude, and perceived stress. Front. Psychiatry. 2022;13:904449. doi: 10.3389/fpsyt.2022.904449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2022.904449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9234110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35770062</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Gong W, Wu X, Zhao W. Estimating economic losses caused by COVID-19 under multiple control measure scenarios with a coupled infectious disease-economic model: A case study in Wuhan, China. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 2021;18(22):11753. doi: 10.3390/ijerph182211753.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/ijerph182211753</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8621982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34831508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakamoto S, Terashita D, Balter S. Liaison public health nurse project: Innovative public health approach to combat infectious disease in hospitals. J. Public Health Manag. Pract. 2020;26(6):557&#x2013;561. doi: 10.1097/PHH.0000000000001068.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PHH.0000000000001068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31688736</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M, Lee C, Wang W, Yang Y, Yang C. Early warning of infectious diseases in hospitals based on multi-self-regression deep neural network. J. Healthc. Eng. 2022;2022:1&#x2013;13. doi: 10.1155/2022/4509612.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1155/2022/4509612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9410942</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36032546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nestor CC, Donnelly M, Connors S, Morrison P, Boylan J. Early warning scores and critical care transfer&#x2014;Patient heterogeneity, low sensitivity, high mortality. Ir. J. Med. Sci. 2022;191(1):119&#x2013;126. doi: 10.1007/s11845-021-02558-7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11845-021-02558-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8789627</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33689132</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li W, Lu S, Cui Z, Cui J, Zhou H, Wang Y, Shao Z, Ye C, Kan B, Xu J. PulseNet China, a model for future laboratory-based bacterial infectious disease surveillance in China. Front. Med. 2012;6(4):366&#x2013;375. doi: 10.1007/s11684-012-0214-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11684-012-0214-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23124882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saperstein, Y., Ong, S. Y., Al-Bermani, T., Park, J., Saperstein, Y., Olayinka, J., Jaiman, A., Winer, A., Salifu, M. O., McFarlane, S. I. COVID-19 guidelines changing faster than the virus: Implications of a clinical decision support app. <i>Int. J. Clin. Res. Trials.</i><b>5</b>(2) (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Souza AA, de Almeida DC, Barcelos TS, Bortoletto RC, Munoz R, Waldman H, Goes MA, Silva LA. Simple hemogram to support the decision-making of COVID-19 diagnosis using clusters analysis with self-organizing maps neural network. Soft Comput. 2021;27:3295&#x2013;3306. doi: 10.1007/s00500-021-05810-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00500-021-05810-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8127503</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34025211</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Albin JS, Lazarus JE, Hysell KM, Rubins DM, Germaine L, Dugdale CM, Heller HM, Hohmann EL, Baugh JJ, Shenoy ES. Development and implementation of a clinical decision support system tool for the evaluation of suspected monkeypox infection. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2022;29(12):2124&#x2013;2127. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocac151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocac151</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9667162</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36036367</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumann LA, Baker J, Elshaug AG. The impact of electronic health record systems on clinical documentation times: A systematic review. Health Policy. 2018;122(8):827&#x2013;836. doi: 10.1016/j.healthpol.2018.05.014.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.healthpol.2018.05.014</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29895467</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>dos Santos, H. D. P., Damasio, J. O., Ulbrich, A. H. D. P. S., Vieira, R. Opportunities and challenges in fall risk management using EHRs and artificial intelligence: A systematic review. In <i>23rd International Conference on Enterprise Information Systems (ICEIS): 2021 Apr 26&#x2013;28 2021; Electr Network</i>. 626&#x2013;633 (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang T, Wang Q, Wang Y, Bai G, Dai R, Luo L. Early surveillance and public health emergency responses between novel coronavirus disease 2019 and avian influenza in China: A case-comparison study. Front. Public Health. 2021;9:629295. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2021.629295.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.629295</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8383042</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34447733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S, Wu J, Ding C, Cui Y, Zhou Y, Li Y, Deng M, Wang C, Xu K, Ren J, et al. Epidemiological features of and changes in incidence of infectious diseases in China in the first decade after the SARS outbreak: An observational trend study. Lancet Infect. Dis. 2017;17(7):716&#x2013;725. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30227-X.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30227-X</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7164789</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28412150</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walsh S, de Jong EEC, van Timmeren JE, Ibrahim A, Compter I, Peerlings J, Sanduleanu S, Refaee T, Keek S, Larue RTHM, et al. Decision support systems in oncology. Jco Clin. Cancer Inform. 2019;3:1&#x2013;9. doi: 10.1200/CCI.18.00001.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1200/CCI.18.00001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6873918</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30730766</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sutton RT, Pincock D, Baumgart DC, Sadowski DC, Fedorak RN, Kroeker KI. An overview of clinical decision support systems: Benefits, risks, and strategies for success. NPJ Digit. Med. 2020;3(1):17. doi: 10.1038/s41746-020-0221-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/s41746-020-0221-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7005290</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32047862</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ronan CE, Crable EL, Drainoni M-L, Walkey AJ. The impact of clinical decision support systems on provider behavior in the inpatient setting: A systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Hosp. Med. 2022;17(5):368&#x2013;383. doi: 10.1002/jhm.12825.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jhm.12825</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35514024</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jing X, Min H, Gong Y, Biondich P, Robinson D, Law T, Nohr C, Faxvaag A, Rennert L, Hubig N, et al. Ontologies applied in clinical decision support system rules: Systematic review. JMIR Med. Inform. 2023;11:e43053&#x2013;e43053. doi: 10.2196/43053.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/43053</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9896360</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36534739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dalal AK, Schaffer A, Gershanik EF, Papanna R, Eibensteiner K, Nolido NV, Yoon CS, Williams D, Lipsitz SR, Roy CL, et al. The impact of automated notification on follow-up of actionable tests pending at discharge: A cluster-randomized controlled trial. J. Gen. Intern. Med. 2018;33(7):1043&#x2013;1051. doi: 10.1007/s11606-018-4393-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s11606-018-4393-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6025668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29532297</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan BA, Calvo-Ayala E, Campbell N, Perkins A, Ionescu R, Tricker J, Campbell T, Zawahiri M, Buckley JD, Farber MO, et al. Clinical decision support system and incidence of delirium in cognitively impaired older adults transferred to intensive care. Am. J. Crit. Care. 2013;22(3):257&#x2013;262. doi: 10.4037/ajcc2013447.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4037/ajcc2013447</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3752665</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23635936</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tao L, Zhang C, Zeng L, Zhu S, Li N, Li W, Zhang H, Zhao Y, Zhan S, Ji H. Accuracy and effects of clinical decision support systems integrated with BMJ best practice-aided diagnosis: Interrupted time series study. JMIR Med. Inform. 2020;8(1):56&#x2013;70. doi: 10.2196/16912.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/16912</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6997922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31958069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chien SC, Chen YL, Chien CH, Chin YP, Yoon CH, Chen CY, Yang HC, Li YC. Alerts in clinical decision support systems (CDSS): A bibliometric review and content analysis. Healthcare. 2022;10(4):601. doi: 10.3390/healthcare10040601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/healthcare10040601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9028311</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35455779</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park H, Chae MK, Jeong W, Yu JY, Jung W, Chang HS, Cha WC. Appropriateness of alerts and physicians' responses with a medication-related clinical decision support system: Retrospective observational study. JMIR Med. Inform. 2022;10(10):e40511. doi: 10.2196/40511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/40511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9579928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36194461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binh-Phi, N., Reese, T., Decker, S., Malone, D., Boyce, R. D., Beyan, O. Implementation of clinical decision support services to detect potential drug-drug interaction using clinical quality language. In <i>17th World Congress of Medical and Health Informatics (MEDINFO): 2019 Aug 25&#x2013;30 2019; Int Med Informat Assoc, Lyon, FRANCE</i>. 724&#x2013;728 (2019).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31438019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang M, Wei Z, Jia M, Chen L, Ji H. Deep learning model for multi-classification of infectious diseases from unstructured electronic medical records. BMC Med. Inform. Decis. Making. 2022;22(1):1&#x2013;13. doi: 10.1186/s12911-022-01776-y.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12911-022-01776-y</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8848865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35168624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dissanayake PI, Colicchio TK, Cimino JJ. Using clinical reasoning ontologies to make smarter clinical decision support systems: A systematic review and data synthesis. J. Am. Med. Inform. Assoc. 2020;27(1):159&#x2013;174. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocz169.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamia/ocz169</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6913230</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31592534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han C, Li M, Haihambo N, Cao Y, Zhao X. Enlightenment on oscillatory properties of 23 class B notifiable infectious diseases in the mainland of China from 2004 to 2020. PLoS&#xa0;One. 2021;16(6):e0252803. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0252803.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0252803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8189525</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34106977</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Wang Y, Jin S, Wu Z, Chin DP, Koplan JP, Wilson ME. Health system reform in China 2 Emergence and control of infectious diseases in China. Lancet. 2008;372(9649):1598&#x2013;1605. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61365-3.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(08)61365-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7138027</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18930534</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou J, Guo X, Duan L, Yao Y, Shang Y, Wang Y, Xing B. Moving toward a standardized diagnostic statement of pituitary adenoma using an information extraction model: A real-world study based on electronic medical records. BMC Med. Inform. Decis. Making. 2022;22(1):319. doi: 10.1186/s12911-022-02031-0.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12911-022-02031-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9727982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36476365</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen T, Xu R, He Y, Wang X. Improving sentiment analysis via sentence type classification using BiLSTM-CRF and CNN. Expert Syst. Appl. 2017;72:221&#x2013;230. doi: 10.1016/j.eswa.2016.10.065.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.eswa.2016.10.065</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, L., Hou, L. IEEE: Combined attention mechanism for named entity recognition in chinese electronic medical records. In <i>7th IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics (ICHI): 2019 Jun 10&#x2013;13 2019; Xian, PEOPLES R CHINA</i>. 476&#x2013;477 (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>https://github.com/grapheco/InteractiveGraph/releases/tag/0.3.1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen B, Wang M, Huang X, Xie M, Pan L, Liu H, Liu Z, Zhou P. Changes in incidence of notifiable infectious diseases in China under the prevention and control measures of COVID-19. Front. Public Health. 2021;9:728768. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2021.728768.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2021.728768</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8553983</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34722440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Degli Esposti M, Spreckelsen T, Gasparrini A, Wiebe DJ, Bonander C, Yakubovich AR, Humphreys DK. Can synthetic controls improve causal inference in interrupted time series evaluations of public health interventions? Int. J. Epidemiol. 2020;49(6):2010&#x2013;2020. doi: 10.1093/ije/dyaa152.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/ije/dyaa152</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33005920</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wei L, Liu N, Chen J, Sun J. Topic evolution of Chinese COVID-19 policies based on co-occurrence clustering network analysis. Sustainability. 2022;14(4):2411. doi: 10.3390/su14042411.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3390/su14042411</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chai M, Shi Q. The effect of anti-cancer and anti-tuberculosis treatments in lung cancer patients with active tuberculosis: A retrospective analysis. BMC Cancer. 2020;20(1):1&#x2013;7. doi: 10.1186/s12885-020-07622-6.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12885-020-07622-6</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7678174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33213414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lu Y, Xie R, Zhou X, Zhou Z, Xu J, He W, Guo L, Ning F. CT imaging of coexisting pulmonary tuberculosis and lung cancer. Chin. J. Radiol. 2013;47(1):8&#x2013;12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen SY, Chiang WC, Ma MHM, Su CP, Hsu CY, Ko PCI, Tsai KC, Yen ZS, Shih FY, Chen SC, et al. Sequential symptomatic analysis in probable severe acute respiratory syndrome cases. Ann. Emerg. Med. 2004;43(1):27&#x2013;33. doi: 10.1016/j.annemergmed.2003.10.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2003.10.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7124244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14707937</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bowyer RCE, Huggins C, Toms R, Shaw RJ, Hou B, Thompson EJ, Kwong ASF, Williams DM, Kibble M, Ploubidis GB, et al. Characterising patterns of COVID-19 and long COVID symptoms: Evidence from nine UK longitudinal studies. Eur. J. Epidemiol. 2023;374:1648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9860244</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36680646</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mengying, W. Research of infectious disease early warning system in real scene of hospital-based on big data. <i>Chin. Hosp. Manag. 42</i>(3) (2022).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiyanbo. Underreporting and report quality analysis of statutory infectious diseases in Yunnan Province in 2019. <i>Mod. Prev. Med. 48</i>(8) (2021).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen J, Chen L, Liao N, Wang J, Qi X, Zhang H, Sun L, Zhang R. Practice and consideration of foodborne disease surveillance in Zhejiang Province. Chin. J. Food Hyg. 2021;33(1):47&#x2013;52.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ambika M, Raghuraman G, SaiRamesh L. Enhanced decision support system to predict and prevent hypertension using computational intelligence techniques. Soft. Comput. 2020;24(17):13293&#x2013;13304. doi: 10.1007/s00500-020-04743-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00500-020-04743-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Natalia, K., Mikhail, B., Michael, K., Anna, D., Igor, I. Convolutional neural networks application in cardiovascular decision support systems. In <i>2nd International Conference on Image and Video Processing, and Artificial Intelligence (IPVAI): 2019 Aug 23&#x2013;25 2019; Shanghai, Peoples R China</i>. (2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gong K, Xu X, Yao J, Ye S, Yu X, Tu H, Lan Y, Fan Y-C, Shi Y. Acute hepatitis of unknown origin in children: A combination of factors. Front. Pharmacol. 2022;13:1056385. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2022.1056385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.1056385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9698116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36438816</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tilashalski FP, Sillence EM, Newton AE, Biggerstaff GK. Enhancing response to foodborne disease outbreaks: Findings of the foodborne diseases centers for outbreak response enhancement (FoodCORE), 2010&#x2013;2019. J. Public Health Manag. Pract. 2022;28(4):E702&#x2013;E710. doi: 10.1097/PHH.0000000000001470.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/PHH.0000000000001470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11027903</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34939601</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Deng, Y.-h., Wu, L.-m., Lu, Q.-w. Application and design of data communication mechanism of information systems based on MQ. In <i>2nd International Conference on Computer and Automation Engineering (ICCAE): 2010 Feb 26&#x2013;28 2010; Singapore, Singapore</i>. 451&#x2013;454 (2010).</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>