<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20056004</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2010</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>21</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>10</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1742-4682</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>07</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Theoretical biology &amp; medical modelling</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Theor Biol Med Model</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Pros and cons of estimating the reproduction number from early epidemic growth rate of influenza A (H1N1) 2009.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1</StartPage><MedlinePgn>1</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/1742-4682-7-1</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">In many parts of the world, the exponential growth rate of infections during the initial epidemic phase has been used to make statistical inferences on the reproduction number, R, a summary measure of the transmission potential for the novel influenza A (H1N1) 2009. The growth rate at the initial stage of the epidemic in Japan led to estimates for R in the range 2.0 to 2.6, capturing the intensity of the initial outbreak among school-age children in May 2009.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">An updated estimate of R that takes into account the epidemic data from 29 May to 14 July is provided. An age-structured renewal process is employed to capture the age-dependent transmission dynamics, jointly estimating the reproduction number, the age-dependent susceptibility and the relative contribution of imported cases to secondary transmission. Pitfalls in estimating epidemic growth rates are identified and used for scrutinizing and re-assessing the results of our earlier estimate of R.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Maximum likelihood estimates of R using the data from 29 May to 14 July ranged from 1.21 to 1.35. The next-generation matrix, based on our age-structured model, predicts that only 17.5% of the population will experience infection by the end of the first pandemic wave. Our earlier estimate of R did not fully capture the population-wide epidemic in quantifying the next-generation matrix from the estimated growth rate during the initial stage of the pandemic in Japan.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">In order to quantify R from the growth rate of cases, it is essential that the selected model captures the underlying transmission dynamics embedded in the data. Exploring additional epidemiological information will be useful for assessing the temporal dynamics. Although the simple concept of R is more easily grasped by the general public than that of the next-generation matrix, the matrix incorporating detailed information (e.g., age-specificity) is essential for reducing the levels of uncertainty in predictions and for assisting public health policymaking. Model-based prediction and policymaking are best described by sharing fundamental notions of heterogeneous risks of infection and death with non-experts to avoid potential confusion and/or possible misuse of modelling results.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nishiura</LastName><ForeName>Hiroshi</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>PRESTO, Japan Science and Technology Agency, Honcho 4-1-8, Kawaguchi, Saitama, 332-0012, Japan. h.nishiura@uu.nl</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chowell</LastName><ForeName>Gerardo</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Safan</LastName><ForeName>Muntaser</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Castillo-Chavez</LastName><ForeName>Carlos</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016421">Editorial</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>07</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Theor Biol Med Model</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101224383</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1742-4682</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="Y">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D053118" MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza A Virus, H1N1 Subtype</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000254" MajorTopicYN="Y">growth &amp; development</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007251" MajorTopicYN="N">Influenza, Human</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000635" MajorTopicYN="N">transmission</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000821" MajorTopicYN="Y">virology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="Y">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013997" MajorTopicYN="N">Time Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2009</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>23</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20056004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2821365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1742-4682-7-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">1742-4682-7-1</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Fraser C, Donnelly CA, Cauchemez S, Hanage WP, Van Kerkhove MD, Hollingsworth TD, Griffin J, Baggaley RF, Jenkins HE, Lyons EJ, Jombart T, Hinsley WR, Grassly NC, Balloux F, Ghani AC, Ferguson NM, Rambaut A, Pybus OG, Lopez-Gatell H, Alpuche-Aranda CM, Chapela IB, Zavala EP, Guevara DM, Checchi F, Garcia E, Hugonnet S, Roth C. WHO Rapid Pandemic Assessment Collaboration. Pandemic potential of a strain of influenza A (H1N1): early findings. Science. 2009;324:1557&#x2013;1561. doi: 10.1126/science.1176062.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1176062</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3735127</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19433588</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bo&#xeb;lle PY, Bernillon P, Desenclos JC. A preliminary estimation of the reproduction ratio for new influenza A(H1N1) from the outbreak in Mexico, March-April 2009. Euro Surveill. 2009;14(19) pii: 19205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19442402</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang Y, Sugimoto JD, Halloran ME, Basta NE, Chao DL, Matrajt L, Potter G, Kenah E, Longini IM Jr. The transmissibility and control of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) virus. Science. 2009;326:729&#x2013;733. doi: 10.1126/science.1177373.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1126/science.1177373</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2880578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19745114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>White LF, Wallinga J, Finelli L, Reed C, Riley S, Lipsitch M, Pagano M. Estimation of the reproductive number and the serial interval in early phase of the 2009 influenza A/H1N1 pandemic in the USA. Influenza Other Respi Viruses. 2009;3:267&#x2013;276. doi: 10.1111/j.1750-2659.2009.00106.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-2659.2009.00106.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2782458</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19903209</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Castillo-Chavez C, Safan M, Chowell G. Transmission potential of the new influenza A(H1N1) virus and its age-specificity in Japan. Euro Surveill. 2009;14(19) pii: 19205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19497256</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Wilson N, Baker MG. Estimating the reproduction number of the novel influenza A virus (H1N1) in a Southern Hemisphere setting: preliminary estimate in New Zealand. N Z Med J. 2009;122:73&#x2013;77.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19684651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Balcan D, Hu H, Goncalves B, Bajardi P, Poletto C, Ramasco JJ, Paolotti D, Perra N, Tizzoni M, Broeck W Van den, Colizza V, Vespignani A. Seasonal transmission potential and activity peaks of the new influenza A(H1N1): a Monte Carlo likelihood analysis based on human mobility. BMC Med. 2009;7:45. doi: 10.1186/1741-7015-7-45.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-7-45</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2755471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19744314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Munayco CV, Gomez J, Laguna-Torres VA, Arrasco J, Kochel TJ, Fiestas V, Garcia J, Perez J, Torres I, Condori F, Nishiura H, Chowell G. Epidemiological and transmissibility analysis of influenza A(H1N1)v in a southern hemisphere setting: Peru. Euro Surveill. 2009;14(32) pii: 19299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19679037</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McBryde E, Bergeri I, van Gemert C, Rotty J, Headley E, Simpson K, Lester R, Hellard M, Fielding J. Early transmission characteristics of influenza A(H1N1)v in Australia: Victorian state, 16 May - 3 June 2009. Euro Surveill. 2009;14 pii = 19363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19883544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Silva UC, Warachit J, Waicharoen S, Chittaganpitch M. A preliminary analysis of the epidemiology of influenza A(H1N1)v virus infection in Thailand from early outbreak data, June-July 2009. Euro Surveill. 2009;14 pii = 19292.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19660247</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pourbohloul B, Ahued A, Davoudi B, Meza R, Meyers LA, Skowronski DM, Villase&#xf1;or I, Galv&#xe1;n F, Cravioto P, Earn DJ, Dushoff J, Fisman D, Edmunds WJ, Hupert N, Scarpino SV, Trujillo J, Lutzow M, Morales J, Contreras A, Ch&#xe1;vez C, Patrick DM, Brunham RC. Initial human transmission dynamics of the pandemic (H1N1) 2009 virus in North America. Influenza Other Respi Viruses. 2009;3:215&#x2013;222. doi: 10.1111/j.1750-2659.2009.00100.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1750-2659.2009.00100.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3122129</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19702583</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tuite AR, Greer AL, Whelan M, Winter AL, Lee B, Yan P, Wu J, Moghadas S, Buckeridge D, Pourbohloul B, Fisman DN. Estimated epidemiologic parameters and morbidity associated with pandemic H1N1 influenza. CMAJ. 2009. in press .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1503/cmaj.091807</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2817319</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19959592</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Busenberg S, Castillo-Chavez C. A general solution of the problem of mixing of subpopulations and its application to risk- and age-structured epidemic models for the spread of AIDS. IMA J Math Appl Med Biol. 1991;8:1&#x2013;29. doi: 10.1093/imammb/8.1.1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/imammb/8.1.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1875096</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Mathematical modelling of the pandemic H1N1 2009. Wkly Epidemiol Rec. 2009;84:341&#x2013;348.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19702014</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brauer F, Feng Z, Castillo-Chavez C. Discrete epidemic models. Math Biosci Eng. 2010;7:1&#x2013;15. doi: 10.3934/mbe.2010.7.1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3934/mbe.2010.7.1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20104945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Lipsitch M. How generation intervals shape the relationship between growth rates and reproductive numbers. Proc R Soc Lond Ser B. 2007;274:599&#x2013;604. doi: 10.1098/rspb.2006.3754.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rspb.2006.3754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1766383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17476782</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Transmission dynamics and impact of pandemic influenza A (H1N1) 2009 virus. Wkly Epidemiol Rec. 2009;84:481&#x2013;484.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19928298</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mikolajczyk RT, Akmatov MK, Rastin S, Kretzschmar M. Social contacts of school children and the transmission of respiratory-spread pathogens. Epidemiol Infect. 2008;136:813&#x2013;822. doi: 10.1017/S0950268807009181.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268807009181</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2870867</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17634160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare, Japan. Influenza A(H1N1) Tokyo: Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare; http://www.mhlw.go.jp/english/topics/influenza_a/index.html (accessed on 10 December 2009)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diekmann O, Heesterbeek JAP. Mathematical Epidemiology of Infectious Diseases: Model Building, Analysis and Interpretation. Chichester: John Wiley and Son; 2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diekmann O, Heesterbeek JA, Metz JA. On the definition and the computation of the basic reproduction ratio R0 in models for infectious diseases in heterogeneous populations. J Math Biol. 1990;28:365&#x2013;382. doi: 10.1007/BF00178324.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/BF00178324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2117040</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hahn&#xe9; S, Donker T, Meijer A, Timen A, van Steenbergen J, Osterhaus A, van der Sande M, Koopmans M, Wallinga J, Coutinho R. Dutch New Influenza A(H1N1)v Investigation Team. Epidemiology and control of influenza A(H1N1)v in the Netherlands: the first 115 cases. Euro Surveill. 2009;14(27) pii: 19267.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19589332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Teunis P, Kretzschmar M. Using data on social contacts to estimate age-specific transmission parameters for respiratory-spread infectious agents. Am J Epidemiol. 2006;164:936&#x2013;944. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwj317.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/aje/kwj317</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16968863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smieszek T. A mechanistic model of infection: why duration and intensity of contacts should be included in models of disease spread. Theor Biol Med Model. 2009;6:25. doi: 10.1186/1742-4682-6-25.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1742-4682-6-25</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2780993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19919678</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H. Time variations in the transmissibility of pandemic influenza in Prussia, Germany, from 1918-19. Theor Biol Med Model. 2007;4:20. doi: 10.1186/1742-4682-4-20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1742-4682-4-20</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1892008</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17547753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Hoye B, Klaassen M, Bauer S, Heesterbeek H. How to find natural reservoir hosts from endemic prevalence in a multi-host population: A case study of influenza in waterfowl. Epidemics. 2009;1:118&#x2013;128. doi: 10.1016/j.epidem.2009.04.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2009.04.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21352759</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Serum cross-reactive antibody response to a novel influenza A (H1N1) virus after vaccination with seasonal influenza vaccine. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2009;58:521&#x2013;524.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19478718</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Itoh Y, Shinya K, Kiso M, Watanabe T, Sakoda Y, Hatta M, Muramoto Y, Tamura D, Sakai-Tagawa Y, Noda T, Sakabe S, Imai M, Hatta Y, Watanabe S, Li C, Yamada S, Fujii K, Murakami S, Imai H, Kakugawa S, Ito M, Takano R, Iwatsuki-Horimoto K, Shimojima M, Horimoto T, Goto H, Takahashi K, Makino A, Ishigaki H, Nakayama M, Okamatsu M, Takahashi K, Warshauer D, Shult PA, Saito R, Suzuki H, Furuta Y, Yamashita M, Mitamura K, Nakano K, Nakamura M, Brockman-Schneider R, Mitamura H, Yamazaki M, Sugaya N, Suresh M, Ozawa M, Neumann G, Gern J, Kida H, Ogasawara K, Kawaoka Y. In vitro and in vivo characterization of new swine-origin H1N1 influenza viruses. Nature. 2009;460:1021&#x2013;1025.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2748827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19672242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reichert T, Chowell G, Nishiura H, Christensen RA, McCullers JA. Does Glycosylation as a modifier of Original Antigenic Sin explain the case age distribution and unusual toxicity in pandemic novel H1N1 influenza? BMC Infect Dis. 2010;10:5. doi: 10.1186/1471-2334-10-5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-10-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3003248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20059763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton T, Nordvik MK, Liljeros F. Modelling sexually transmitted infections: the effect of partnership activity and number of partners on R0. Theor Popul Biol. 2007;72:389&#x2013;399. doi: 10.1016/j.tpb.2007.06.006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tpb.2007.06.006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17707873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Newman MEJ. The structure and function of complex networks. SIAM Review. 2003;45:167&#x2013;256. doi: 10.1137/S003614450342480.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1137/S003614450342480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hethcote HW, Yorke JA. Gonorrhea Transmission Dynamics and Control (Lecture Notes in Biomathematics, 56) Berlin:Springer-Verlag; 1980.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldstein E, Apolloni A, Lewis B, Miller JC, Macauley M, Eubank S, Lipsitch M, Wallinga J. Distribution of vaccine/antivirals and the 'least spread line' in a stratified population. J R Soc Interface. 2009. in press .</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/?rsif.2009.0393</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2874227</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19828505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Chowell G, Heesterbeek H, Wallinga J. The ideal reporting interval for an epidemic to objectively interpret the epidemiological time course. J R Soc Interface. 2010;7:297&#x2013;307. doi: 10.1098/rsif.2009.0153.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1098/rsif.2009.0153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2842610</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19570792</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeling M. The implications of network structure for epidemic dynamics. Theor Popul Biol. 2005;67:1&#x2013;8. doi: 10.1016/j.tpb.2004.08.002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.tpb.2004.08.002</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15649519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smieszek T, Fiebig L, Scholz RW. Models of epidemics: when contact repetition and clustering should be included. Theor Biol Med Model. 2009;6:11. doi: 10.1186/1742-4682-6-11.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1742-4682-6-11</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2709892</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19563624</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurevich KG. Formal kinetics of H1N1 epidemic. Theor Biol Med Model. 2009;6:23. doi: 10.1186/1742-4682-6-23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1742-4682-6-23</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2751748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19754945</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chowell G, Castillo-Chavez C. In: Bioterrorism: Mathematical and Modeling Applications in Homeland Security, (Frontiers in Applied Mathematics 28) Banks T, Castillo-Chavez C, editor. Philadelphia, PA: Society for Industrial Mathematics; 2003. Worst-Case scenarios and epidemics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bettencourt LMA, Ribeiro RM, Chowell G, Lant T, Castillo-Chavez C. Intelligence and Security Informatics: Biosurveillance (Lecture Notes in Computer Science, volume 4506) Berlin: Springer; 2009. Towards Real Time Epidemiology: Data Assimilation, Modeling and Anomaly Detection of Health Surveillance Data Streams.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ball F, Clancy D. The final size and severity of a generalised stochastic multitype epidemic model. Adv Appl Prob. 1993;25:721&#x2013;736. doi: 10.2307/1427788.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2307/1427788</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistics Bureau, Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications. Population estimates. Tokyo: Statistics Bureau (in Japanese) http://www.stat.go.jp/data/nihon/02.htm (accessed on 10 December 2009)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Longini IM, Ackerman E, Elveback LR. An optimization model for influenza A epidemics. Math Biosci. 1978;38:141&#x2013;157. doi: 10.1016/0025-5564(78)90023-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/0025-5564(78)90023-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Britton T. On critical vaccination coverage in multitype epidemics. J Appl Prob. 1998;35:1003&#x2013;1006. doi: 10.1239/jap/1032438395.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1239/jap/1032438395</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garske T, Legrand J, Donnelly CA, Ward H, Cauchemez S, Fraser C, Ferguson NM, Ghani AC. Assessing the severity of the novel influenza A/H1N1 pandemic. BMJ. 2009;339:b2840. doi: 10.1136/bmj.b2840.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmj.b2840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19602714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nishiura H, Klinkenberg D, Roberts M, Heesterbeek JA. Early epidemiological assessment of the virulence of emerging infectious diseases: a case study of an influenza pandemic. PLoS ONE. 2009;4:e6852. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0006852.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2729920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19718434</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Presanis AM, De Angelis D. New York City Swine Flu Investigation Team; Hagy A, Reed C, Riley S, Cooper BS, Finelli L, Biedrzycki P, Lipsitch M. The severity of pandemic H1N1 influenza in the United States, from April to July 2009: a Bayesian analysis. PLoS Med. 2009;6:e1000207. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1000207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2784967</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19997612</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>