<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38968067</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>07</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>30</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1531-5487</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>35</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>01</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Epidemiology (Cambridge, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Epidemiology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A New Criterion for Determining a Cutoff Value Based on the Biases of Incidence Proportions in the Presence of Non-differential Outcome Misclassifications.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>618</StartPage><EndPage>627</EndPage><MedlinePgn>618-627</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/EDE.0000000000001756</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>When conducting database studies, researchers sometimes use an algorithm known as "case definition," "outcome definition," or "computable phenotype" to identify the outcome of interest. Generally, algorithms are created by combining multiple variables and codes, and we need to select the most appropriate one to apply to the database study. Validation studies compare algorithms with the gold standard and calculate indicators such as sensitivity and specificity to assess their validities. As the indicators are calculated for each algorithm, selecting an algorithm is equivalent to choosing a pair of sensitivity and specificity. Therefore, receiver operating characteristic curves can be utilized, and two intuitive criteria are commonly used. However, neither was conceived to reduce the biases of effect measures (e.g., risk difference and risk ratio), which are important in database studies. In this study, we evaluated two existing criteria from perspectives of the biases and found that one of them, called the Youden index always minimizes the bias of the risk difference regardless of the true incidence proportions under nondifferential outcome misclassifications. However, both criteria may lead to inaccurate estimates of absolute risks, and such property is undesirable in decision-making. Therefore, we propose a new criterion based on minimizing the sum of the squared biases of absolute risks to estimate them more accurately. Subsequently, we apply all criteria to the data from the actual validation study on postsurgical infections and present the results of a sensitivity analysis to examine the robustness of the assumption our proposed criterion requires.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2024 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Suzuki</LastName><ForeName>Norihiro</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7913-8595</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Health Data Science, Tokyo Medical University, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taguri</LastName><ForeName>Masataka</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the Department of Health Data Science, Tokyo Medical University, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Research Center for Medical and Health Data Science, The Institute of Statistical Mathematics, Tokyo, Japan.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Epidemiology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9009644</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1044-3983</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015982" MajorTopicYN="Y">Bias</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000465" MajorTopicYN="Y">Algorithms</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015994" MajorTopicYN="N">Incidence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012372" MajorTopicYN="N">ROC Curve</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012680" MajorTopicYN="N">Sensitivity and Specificity</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016208" MajorTopicYN="N">Databases, Factual</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors report no conflicts of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>7</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>12</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38968067</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11309335</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/EDE.0000000000001756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">00001648-202409000-00005</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Loke YK. Use of databases for clinical research. Arch Dis Child. 2014;99:587&#x2013;589.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24489362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook JA, Collins GS. The rise of big clinical databases. Br J Surg. 2015;102:e93&#x2013;e101.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25627139</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baumfeld Andre E, Reynolds R, Caubel P, Azoulay L, Dreyer NA. Trial designs using real-world data: the changing landscape of the regulatory approval process. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2020;29:1201&#x2013;1212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7687110</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31823482</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feinberg BA, Gajra A, Zettler ME, Phillips TD, Phillips EG, Kish JK. Use of real-world evidence to support FDA approval of oncology drugs. Value Health. 2020;23:1358&#x2013;1365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33032780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arondekar B, Duh MS, Bhak RH, et al. Real-world evidence in support of oncology product registration: a systematic review of new drug application and biologics license application approvals from 2015-2020. Clin Cancer Res. 2022;28:27&#x2013;35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9401526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34667027</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hern&#xe1;n MA, Robins JM. Using big data to emulate a target trial when a randomized trial is not available. Am J Epidemiol. 2016;183:758&#x2013;764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4832051</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26994063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele SR, Brady JT, Cao Z, et al. Evaluation of healthcare use and clinical outcomes of alvimopan in patients undergoing bowel resection: a propensity score-matched analysis. Dis Colon Rectum. 2018;61:1418&#x2013;1425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30312222</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration. Best practices for conducting and reporting pharmacoepidemiologic safety studies using electronic healthcare data sets. Available at: https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/best-practices-conducting-and-reporting-pharmacoepidemiologic-safety-studies-using-electronic. Accessed May 12, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richesson RL, Hammond WE, Nahm M, et al. Electronic health records based phenotyping in next-generation clinical trials: a perspective from the NIH health care systems collaboratory. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2013;20:e226&#x2013;e231.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3861929</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23956018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chubak J, Pocobelli G, Weiss NS. Tradeoffs between accuracy measures for electronic health care data algorithms. J Clin Epidemiol. 2012;65:343&#x2013;349.e2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3264740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22197520</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration. Real-world data: Assessing electronic health records and medical claims data to support regulatory decision-making for drug and biological products. Available at: https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/real-world-data-assessing-electronic-health-records-and-medical-claims-data-support-regulatory. Accessed May 12, 2023.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9320939</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35471704</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pharmaceuticals and Medical Device Agency. Basic concept on implementing validations of outcome definitions used in post-marketing database surveys [in Japanese]. Available at: https://www.mhlw.go.jp/web/t_doc?dataId=00tc5226&amp;dataType=1&amp;pageNo=1. Accessed May 12, 2023.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weinstein EJ, Ritchey ME, Lo Re V, 3rd. Core concepts in pharmacoepidemiology: validation of health outcomes of interest within real-world healthcare databases. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2023;32:1&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9772105</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36057777</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akobeng AK. Understanding diagnostic tests 3: receiver operating characteristic curves. Acta Paediatr. 2007;96:644&#x2013;647.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17376185</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandrekar JN. Receiver operating characteristic curve in diagnostic test assessment. J Thorac Oncol. 2010;5:1315&#x2013;1316.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20736804</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Youden WJ. Index for rating diagnostic tests. Cancer. 1950;3:32&#x2013;35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15405679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perkins NJ, Schisterman EF. The inconsistency of &#x201c;optimal&#x201d; cutpoints obtained using two criteria based on the receiver operating characteristic curve. Am J Epidemiol. 2006;163:670&#x2013;675.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1444894</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16410346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruth MP, Mitchell HG. Absolute risk: methods and applications in clinical management and public health. New York: Chapman and Hall/CRC; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, G&#xf8;tzsche PC, Vandenbroucke JP; STROBE Initiative. The strengthening the reporting of observational Studies in epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. Int J Surg. 2014;12:1495&#x2013;1499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25046131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yamana H, Tsuchiya A, Horiguchi H, et al. Validity of a model using routinely collected data for identifying infections following gastric, colon, and liver cancer surgeries. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2022;31:452&#x2013;460.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34800063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lash TL, VanderWeele TJ, Rothman K. Measurement and measurement error. In: Lash TL, VanderWeele TJ, Haneause S, Rothman K, eds. Modern Epidemiology. 4th ed. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2020:287&#x2013;314.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brenner H, Savitz DA. The effects of sensitivity and specificity of case selection on validity, sample size, precision, and power in hospital-based case-control studies. Am J Epidemiol. 1990;132:181&#x2013;192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2192549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cantor SB, Sun CC, Tortolero-Luna G, Richards-Kortum R, Follen M. A comparison of C/B ratios from studies using receiver operating characteristic curve analysis. J Clin Epidemiol. 1999;52:885&#x2013;892.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10529029</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Copeland KT, Checkoway H, McMichael AJ, Holbrook RH. Bias due to misclassification in the estimation of relative risk. Am J Epidemiol. 1977;105:488&#x2013;495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">871121</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flegal KM, Keyl PM, Nieto FJ. Differential misclassification arising from nondifferential errors in exposure measurement. Am J Epidemiol. 1991;134:1233&#x2013;1244.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1746532</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Numata M, Godai T, Shirai J, et al. A prospective randomized controlled trial of subcutaneous passive drainage for the prevention of superficial surgical site infections in open and laparoscopic colorectal surgery. Int J Colorectal Dis. 2014;29:353&#x2013;358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24385026</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox MP, Lash TL, Greenland S. A method to automate probabilistic sensitivity analyses of misclassified binary variables. Int J Epidemiol. 2005;34:1370&#x2013;1376.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16172102</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lash TL, Mor V, Wieland D, Ferrucci L, Satariano W, Silliman RA. Methodology, design, and analytic techniques to address measurement of comorbid disease. J Gerontol A Biol Sci Med Sci. 2007;62:281&#x2013;285.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2645650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17389725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shaw PA, Deffner V, Keogh RH, et al. ; Measurement Error and Misclassification Topic Group (TG4) of the STRATOS Initiative. Epidemiologic analyses with error-prone exposures: review of current practice and recommendations. Ann Epidemiol. 2018;28:821&#x2013;828.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6734186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30316629</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walraven CV. A comparison of methods to correct for misclassification bias from administrative database diagnostic codes. Int J Epidemiol. 2018;47:605&#x2013;616.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29253160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lash TL, Olshan AF. EPIDEMIOLOGY announces the &#x201c;Validation Study&#x201d; submission category. Epidemiology. 2016;27:613&#x2013;614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27388372</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jurek AM, Maldonado G, Greenland S, Church TR. Exposure-measurement error is frequently ignored when interpreting epidemiologic study results. Eur J Epidemiol. 2006;21:871&#x2013;876.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17186399</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neuhaus JM. Bias and efficiency loss due to misclassified responses in binary regression. Biometrika. 1999;86:843&#x2013;855.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>