<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">33720030</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>13</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2369-2960</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Mar</Month><Day>15</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JMIR public health and surveillance</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JMIR Public Health Surveill</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Hybrid Approach to Estimation of Underreporting of Tuberculosis Case Notification in High-Burden Settings With Weak Surveillance Infrastructure: Design and Implementation of an Inventory Study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e22352</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e22352</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e22352</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.2196/22352</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">The greatest risk of infectious disease undernotification occurs in settings with limited capacity to detect it reliably. World Health Organization guidance on the measurement of misreporting is paradoxical, requiring robust, independent systems to assess surveillance rigor. Methods are needed to estimate undernotification in settings with incomplete, flawed, or weak surveillance systems. This study attempted to design a tuberculosis (TB) inventory study that balanced rigor with feasibility for high-need settings.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE">This study aims to design a hybrid TB inventory study for contexts without World Health Organization preconditions. We estimated the proportion of TB cases that were not reported to the Ministry of Health in 2015. The study sought to describe TB surveillance coverage and quality at different levels of TB care provision. Finally, we aimed to identify structural-, facility-, and provider-level barriers to notification and reasons for underreporting, nonreporting, and overreporting.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">Retrospective partial digitalization of paper-based surveillance and facility records preceded deterministic and probabilistic record linkage; a hybrid of health facilities and laboratory census with a stratified sampling of HFs with no capacity to notify leveraged a priori knowledge. Distinct extrapolation methods were applied to the sampled health facilities to estimate bacteriologically confirmed versus clinical TB. In-depth interviews and focus groups were used to identify causal factors responsible for undernotification and test the acceptability of remedies.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">The hybrid approach proved viable and instructive. High-specificity verification of paper-based records in the field was efficient and had minimal errors. Limiting extrapolation to clinical cases improved precision. Probabilistic record linkage is computationally intensive, and the choice of software influences estimates. Record absence, decay, and overestimation of the private sector TB treatment behavior threaten validity, meriting mitigation. Data management demands were underestimated. Treatment success was modest in all sectors (R=37.9%-72.0%) and did not align with treatment success reported by the state (6665/8770, 75.99%). One-fifth of TB providers (36/178, 20%) were doubtful that the low volume of patients with TB treated in their facility merited mastery of the extensive TB notification forms and procedures.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">Subnational inventory studies can be rigorous, relevant, and efficient in countries that need them even in the absence of World Health Organization preconditions, if precautions are taken. The use of triangulation techniques, with minimal recourse to sampling and extrapolation, and the privileging of practical information needs of local decision makers yield reasonable misreporting estimates and viable policy recommendations.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9;Ellen M H Mitchell, Olusola Adedeji Adejumo, Hussein Abdur-Razzaq, Chidubem Ogbudebe, Nkem Chukwueme, Samson Bamidele Olorunju, Mustapha Gidado. Originally published in JMIR Public Health and Surveillance (http://publichealth.jmir.org), 15.03.2021.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Mitchell</LastName><ForeName>Ellen M H</ForeName><Initials>EMH</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-2824-3499</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tropical Infectious Diseases, Department of Public Health, Institute for Tropical Medicine, Antwerp, Belgium.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Adejumo</LastName><ForeName>Olusola Adedeji</ForeName><Initials>OA</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-8946-3244</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mainland Hospital, Yaba Lagos, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Abdur-Razzaq</LastName><ForeName>Hussein</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4946-3415</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Health Research Unit, Lagos State Ministry of Health, Lagos, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ogbudebe</LastName><ForeName>Chidubem</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-9616-0695</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>KNCV TB Foundation Nigeria, Abuja, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chukwueme</LastName><ForeName>Nkem</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7848-375X</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>New York Medical College, New York, NY, United States.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Olorunju</LastName><ForeName>Samson Bamidele</ForeName><Initials>SB</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-5486-5964</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology and Medical Statistics, Faculty of Public Health, University of Ibadan, Ibadan, Nigeria.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gidado</LastName><ForeName>Mustapha</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1798-7281</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>KNCV TB Foundation, Koninklijke Centrale Vereniging tot bestrijding der Tuberculose (KNCV), The Hague, Netherlands.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013486">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, Non-P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Canada</Country><MedlineTA>JMIR Public Health Surveill</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101669345</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2369-2960</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018563" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Notification</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="Y">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009549" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Nigeria</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D062486" MajorTopicYN="N">Public Health Surveillance</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="Y">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014376" MajorTopicYN="N">Tuberculosis</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014944" MajorTopicYN="N">World Health Organization</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious disease notification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious disease reporting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">integrated disease surveillance reporting</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">inventory study</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">notification</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">private sector</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">public health surveillance</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">tuberculosis</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Conflicts of Interest: None declared.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2020</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2020</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>8</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2020</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>13</Hour><Minute>5</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33720030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8088841</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2196/22352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">v7i3e22352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ansumana R, Keitell S, Roberts GM, Ntoumi F, Petersen E, Ippolito G, Zumla A. Impact of infectious disease epidemics on tuberculosis diagnostic, management, and prevention services: experiences and lessons from the 2014&#x2013;2015 Ebola virus disease outbreak in West Africa. International Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2017 Mar;56:101&#x2013;104. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2016.10.010.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2016.10.010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7110799</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27818362</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Marston BJ, Dokubo EK, van Steelandt A, Martel L, Williams D, Hersey S, Jambai A, Keita S, Nyenswah TG, Redd JT. Ebola Response Impact on Public Health Programs, West Africa, 2014&#x2013;2017. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2017 Dec;23(13) doi: 10.3201/eid2313.170727.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid2313.170727</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5711323</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29155674</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell BP, Damon IK, Jernigan DB, Kenyon TA, Nichol ST, O'Connor John P, Tappero JW. Overview, Control Strategies, and Lessons Learned in the CDC Response to the 2014-2016 Ebola Epidemic. MMWR Suppl. 2016 Jul 08;65(3):4&#x2013;11. doi: 10.15585/mmwr.su6503a2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.15585/mmwr.su6503a2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27389903</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization . Assessing Tuberculosis Under-Reporting Through Inventory Studies. Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anyaehie U, Nwakoby B, Chikwendu C, Dim C, Uguru N, Oluka C, Ogugua C. Constraints, challenges and prospects of public-private partnership in health-care delivery in a developing economy. Ann Med Health Sci Res. 2014 Jan;4(1):61&#x2013;6. doi: 10.4103/2141-9248.126615.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/2141-9248.126615</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3952299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24669333</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Omoleke SA, Ajibola O, Ajiboye JO, Raji RO. Quagmire of epidemic disease outbreaks reporting in Nigeria. BMJ Glob Health. 2018 Feb 15;3(1):e000659. doi: 10.1136/bmjgh-2017-000659.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2017-000659</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5841526</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29527352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abubakar A, Idris S, Nguku P, Sabitu K, Sambo M. Assessment of integrated disease surveillance and response strategy implementation in selected Local Government Areas of Kaduna state. Ann Nigerian Med. 2013;7(1):14. doi: 10.4103/0331-3131.119981.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0331-3131.119981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nnebue C, Onwasigwe C, Onyeonoro U, Adogu PU. Awareness and knowledge of disease surveillance and notification by health-care workers and availability of facility records in Anambra state, Nigeria. Niger Med J. 2012;53(4):220. doi: 10.4103/0300-1652.107557.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0300-1652.107557</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3640243</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23661882</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwu A, Diwe K, Duru C, Uwakwe K. Assessment of disease reporting among health care workers in a South Eastern State, Nigeria. Int J Community Med Public Health. 2016:2766&#x2013;2774. doi: 10.18203/2394-6040.ijcmph20163359.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18203/2394-6040.ijcmph20163359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aruna O, Nsofor I, Oyediran K. Tuberculosis in Nigeria Rapid Assessment of Infectious Disease Surveillance and Reporting. Chapel Hill, USA. www.measureevaluation.org. 2018.   https://www.measureevaluation.org/resources/publications/tr-18-292.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  . Global Tuberculosis Report 2015. Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2015. Mar 24,  [2015-03-24]. Global Tuberculosis Report 2015.  http://www.who.int/tb/publications/global_report/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nigeria Private Health Sector Assessment. SHOPS Project. 2012.  [2021-02-08].   https://www.shopsplusproject.org/sites/default/files/resources/Nigeria%20Private%20Health%20Sector%20Assessment%2009_10_2012.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hotchkiss DR, Eisele TP, Djibuti M, Silvestre EA, Rukhadze N. Health system barriers to strengthening vaccine-preventable disease surveillance and response in the context of decentralization: evidence from Georgia. BMC Public Health. 2006 Jul 05;6(1):175. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-6-175.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-6-175</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1526426</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16822316</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Agency for the Control of AIDS  . Federal Republic of Nigeria: GLOBAL AIDS RESPONSE Country Progress Report, Nigeria GARPR 2014. Abuja, Nigeria: Federal Republic of Nigeria; 2014. Jan 01,   http://www.unaids.org/sites/default/files/country/documents/NGA_narrative_report_2014.pdf.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gulma K, Abubakar M, Mohammed B, Musa B, Nata'ala S, Yusuf M. Stock status assessment of health commodities used in the management of HIV/AIDS and tuberculosis in kano state, Nigeria. J Pharma Res. 2015;14(2):33&#x2013;41. doi: 10.18579/jpcrkc/2015/14/2/79075.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.18579/jpcrkc/2015/14/2/79075</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Daniel OJ, Adedeji Adejumo O, Abdur-Razzaq HA, Ngozi Adejumo E, Salako AA. Public-private mix for TB and TB-HIV care in Lagos, Nigeria. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2013 Sep 01;17(9):1195&#x2013;8. doi: 10.5588/ijtld.12.0759.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5588/ijtld.12.0759</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23928168</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adejumo O, Daniel O, Abdur-Razzaq H, Shogbamimu Y, Femi-Adebayo T, Adepoju V, Adebayo Bisola I, Sodipo Oluwajimi O. Trend of tuberculosis case notification and treatment outcome in Lagos State, Nigeria: a 5-year retrospective study. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2017 Jul 01;111(7):300&#x2013;307. doi: 10.1093/trstmh/trx060.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/trstmh/trx060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29165702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adejumo O, Daniel O, Adejumo E, Oluwole E, Olumuyiwa O. Treatment Outcomes of Tuberculosis Patients Managed at the Public and Private Dots Facilities in Lagos Nigeria. IJTDH. 2015 Jan 10;10(2):1&#x2013;9. doi: 10.9734/ijtdh/2015/19933.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.9734/ijtdh/2015/19933</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adejumo OA, Daniel OJ, Gidado M, Otesanya AF, Adejumo EN, O. Jaiyesimi E, Esther Idowu O, O. Odusanya O. Are Tuberculosis Patients Managed According to the National Guidelines in Lagos State Nigeria? IJCM. 2016;07(01):16&#x2013;24. doi: 10.4236/ijcm.2016.71003.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4236/ijcm.2016.71003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Public Health . Guidelines for Community Tuberculosis Care in Nigeria National Tuberculosis and Leprosy. Abuja, Nigeria: Federal Republic of Nigeria; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnson D, Woodman B, Baruwa S, Toriola M, Chatterji M, Kinnan C. A Census of Private Health Facilities in Six States of Nigeria. Bethesda, Maryland USA: Strengthening Health Outcomes through the Private Sector Project, Abt Associates; 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gale NK, Heath G, Cameron E, Rashid S, Redwood S. Using the framework method for the analysis of qualitative data in multi-disciplinary health research. BMC Med Res Methodol. 2013 Sep 18;13:117. doi: 10.1186/1471-2288-13-117.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2288-13-117</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3848812</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24047204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacPherson P, Houben RM, Glynn JR, Corbett EL, Kranzer K. Pre-treatment loss to follow-up in tuberculosis patients in low- and lower-middle-income countries and high-burden countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Bull. World Health Organ. 2013 Nov 22;92(2):126&#x2013;138. doi: 10.2471/blt.13.124800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2471/blt.13.124800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3949536</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24623906</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beyeler N, Liu J, Sieverding M. A systematic review of the role of proprietary and patent medicine vendors in healthcare provision in Nigeria. PLoS One. 2015 Jan 28;10(1):e0117165. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0117165.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117165</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4309565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25629900</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Micallef L, Rodgers P. eulerAPE: drawing area-proportional 3-Venn diagrams using ellipses. PLoS One. 2014 Jul 17;9(7):e101717. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0101717.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0101717</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4102485</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25032825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heberle H, Meirelles GV, da Silva FR, Telles GP, Minghim R. InteractiVenn: a web-based tool for the analysis of sets through Venn diagrams. BMC Bioinformatics. 2015 May 22;16(1):169. doi: 10.1186/s12859-015-0611-3.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12859-015-0611-3</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4455604</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25994840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bardou P, Mariette J, Escudi&#xe9; Fr&#xe9;d&#xe9;ric, Djemiel C, Klopp C. jvenn: an interactive Venn diagram viewer. BMC Bioinformatics. 2014 Aug 29;15(1):293. doi: 10.1186/1471-2105-15-293.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-15-293</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4261873</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25176396</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Straetemans M, Bakker M, Alba S, Mergenthaler C, Rood E, Andersen P, Schimmel Henrieke, Simunovic Aleksandar, Svetina Petra, Carvalho Carlos, Lyytik&#xe4;inen Outi, Abubakar Ibrahim, Harris Ross J, K&#xf6;dm&#xf6;n Csaba, van der Werf Marieke J, van Hest Rob. Completeness of tuberculosis (TB) notification: inventory studies and capture-recapture analyses, six European Union countries, 2014 to 2016. Euro Surveill. 2020 Mar;25(12):10. doi: 10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2020.25.12.1900568.  </Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2020.25.12.1900568</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7118341</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32234122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>