<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">36217424</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2590-1362</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>12</Volume><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Vaccine: X</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Vaccine X</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Trust is the common denominator for COVID-19 vaccine acceptance: A literature review.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100213</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100213</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">100213</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jvacx.2022.100213</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Vaccine hesitancy and refusal to be vaccinated are major reasons why mass vaccination strategies do not reach the intended coverage, even if adequate vaccine supply has been achieved. The main objective of this study is to explore the role and contribution of trust in public willingness to accept COVID-19 vaccinations. The study utilised a qualitative synthesis of literature around hesitancy, willingness to accept vaccination, and the role of trust. Data were extracted from the literature and first categorised using a deductive approach, and later analysed in QSR NVivo using a mix of deductive and inductive approaches. The impact of trust was mostly borne out in the willingness to accept a vaccine, but details on what trust is, how and why it affects willingness or lack of it, was not frequently reported. Three types of trust were identified: 1) Trust in the quality and safety of vaccines; 2) Institutional trust; and 3) Interpersonal trust in the professionals who communicate about and administer the vaccine. Trust in the vaccines' quality and safety, and institutional affiliation significantly contributed towards willingness to be vaccinated. The bulk of the literature focused on how interpersonal trust and personal attributes of potential vaccinees affected the willingness to accept the vaccine. This complex relationship included a fragility of beliefs and perceptions at an individual level, with a bidirectional relationship to societal perceptions. Perceptions of vaccines had a predominant role in decision-making, in contrast to more science-based decision-making. Although globally, the perceptions and beliefs contributing to trust had commonalities and relevance, trust was often found to be dependent on factors embedded in local social, cultural, institutional, and individual attributes and experiences. Understanding different types of trust offers potential approaches to motivate undecided people to receive vaccine; and vaccine refusers to revisit their decisions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2022 The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adhikari</LastName><ForeName>Bipin</ForeName><Initials>B</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mahidol Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit, Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Tropical Medicine and Global Health, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yeong Cheah</LastName><ForeName>Phaik</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mahidol Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit, Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Tropical Medicine and Global Health, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>von Seidlein</LastName><ForeName>Lorenz</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mahidol Oxford Tropical Medicine Research Unit, Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Centre for Tropical Medicine and Global Health, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Acronym>WT_</Acronym><Agency>Wellcome Trust</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2022</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Vaccine X</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101748769</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2590-1362</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19 vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Institutional trust</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Perceptions</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Trust</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Vaccine hesitancy</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Willingness to take vaccine</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>17</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>30</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>47</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>12</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2022</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36217424</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9536059</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jvacx.2022.100213</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2590-1362(22)00073-0</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Gilson L. Trust and the development of health care as a social institution. Soc Sci Med. 2003;56(7):1453&#x2013;1468.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12614697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ozawa S., Paina L., Qiu M. Exploring pathways for building trust in vaccination and strengthening health system resilience. BMC Health Serv Res. 2016;16:639.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5123384</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28185595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson H.J., Clarke R.M., Jarrett C., Eckersberger E., Levine Z., Schulz W.S., et al. Measuring trust in vaccination: A systematic review. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2018;14(7):1599&#x2013;1609.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6067893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29617183</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>N O. Science Isn&#x2019;t Always Perfect&#x2014;But We Should Still Trust It. Available online at https://time.com/5709691/why-trust-science/ (Accessed on 13th April, 2021). 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilholt T. Epistemic trust in science. The British Journal for the Philosophy of Science. 2013;64(2):233&#x2013;253.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldenberg M.J. and the War on Science: University of Pittsburgh Press; 2021. Vaccine Hesitancy: Public Trust, Expertise.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Molyneux C.S., Peshu N., Marsh K. Trust and informed consent: insights from community members on the Kenyan coast. Soc Sci Med. 2005;61(7):1463&#x2013;1473.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16005781</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasiah S., Jaafar S., Yusof S., Ponnudurai G., Chung K.P.Y., Amirthalingam S.D. A study of the nature and level of trust between patients and healthcare providers, its dimensions and determinants: a scoping review protocol. BMJ Open. 2020;10(1):e028061.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7044948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31980505</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Larson H.J., Jarrett C., Schulz W.S., Chaudhuri M., Zhou Y., Dube E., et al. Measuring vaccine hesitancy: The development of a survey tool. Vaccine. 2015;33(34):4165&#x2013;4175.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25896384</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Butler R, MacDonald NE, Hesitancy SWGoV. Diagnosing the determinants of vaccine hesitancy in specific subgroups: The Guide to Tailoring Immunization Programmes (TIP). Vaccine. 2015;33:4176-9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25896376</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MacDonald NE, Hesitancy SWGoV. Vaccine hesitancy: Definition, scope and determinants. Vaccine. 2015;33:4161-4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25896383</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lazarus J.V., Ratzan S.C., Palayew A., Gostin L.O., Larson H.J., Rabin K., et al. A global survey of potential acceptance of a COVID-19 vaccine. Nat Med. 2021;27(2):225&#x2013;228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7573523</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33082575</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dub&#xe9; E., Laberge C., Guay M., Bramadat P., Roy R., Bettinger J.A. Vaccine hesitancy: an overview. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2013;9(8):1763&#x2013;1773.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3906279</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23584253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaehler N., Adhikari B., Cheah P.Y., von Seidlein L., Day N.P.J., Dondorp A.M., et al. Community engagement for malaria elimination in the Greater Mekong Sub-region: a qualitative study among malaria researchers and policymakers. Malar J. 2022;21(1)</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8845385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35164770</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Latkin C.A., Dayton L., Yi G., Konstantopoulos A., Boodram B. Trust in a COVID-19 vaccine in the U.S.: A social-ecological perspective. Soc Sci Med. 2021;270:113684.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834519</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33485008</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verger P., Dub&#xe9; E. Restoring confidence in vaccines in the COVID-19 era. Expert review of vaccines. 2020;19(11):991&#x2013;993.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32940574</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robbins B.G. What is trust? A multidisciplinary review, critique, and synthesis. Sociology compass. 2016;10(10):972&#x2013;986.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scharff D.P., Mathews K.J., Jackson P., Hoffsuemmer J., Martin E., Edwards D. More than Tuskegee: understanding mistrust about research participation. J Health Care Poor Underserved. 2010;21:879&#x2013;897.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4354806</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20693733</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bajaj S.S., Stanford F.C. Beyond Tuskegee - Vaccine Distrust and Everyday Racism. N Engl J Med. 2021;384(5):e12.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9908408</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33471971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sherman S.M., Smith L.E., Sim J., Amlot R., Cutts M., Dasch H., et al. COVID-19 vaccination intention in the UK: results from the COVID-19 vaccination acceptability study (CoVAccS), a nationally representative cross-sectional survey. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2020:1&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8115754</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33242386</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adhikari B., Cheah P.Y. Vaccine hesitancy in the COVID-19 era. Lancet Infect Dis. 2021;21:1086.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8248943</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34217431</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Blume S. Immunization: how vaccines became controversial. Reaktion Books. 2017</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferrari R. Writing narrative style literature reviews. Medical Writing. 2015;24:230&#x2013;235.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Akarsu B, Canbay &#xd6;zdemir D, Ayhan Baser D, Aksoy H, Fidanc&#x131; &#x130;, Cankurtaran M. While studies on COVID-19 vaccine is ongoing, the public's thoughts and attitudes to the future COVID-19 vaccine. Int J Clin Pract. 2020:e13891.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7883065</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33278857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen M., Li Y., Chen J., Wen Z., Feng F., Zou H., et al. An online survey of the attitude and willingness of Chinese adults to receive COVID-19 vaccination. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2021:1&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8189089</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33522405</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kose S., Mandiracioglu A., Sahin S., Kaynar T., Karbus O., Ozbel Y. Vaccine hesitancy of the COVID-19 by health care personnel. Int J Clin Pract. 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kreps S., Prasad S., Brownstein J.S., Hswen Y., Garibaldi B.T., Zhang B., et al. Factors Associated With US Adults' Likelihood of Accepting COVID-19 Vaccination. JAMA Netw Open. 2020;3:e2025594.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7576409</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33079199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Leng A.L., Maitland E., Wang S.Y., Nicholas S., Liu R.G., Wang J. Individual preferences for COVID-19 vaccination in China. Vaccine. 2021;39:247&#x2013;254.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7719001</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33328140</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin Y.L., Hu Z.J., Zhao Q.J., Alias H., Danaee M., Wong L.P. Understanding COVID-19 vaccine demand and hesitancy: A nationwide online survey in China. PLoS NeglTrop Dis. 2020;14</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7775119</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33332359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lucia V.C., Kelekar A., Afonso N.M. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy among medical students. J Public Health (Oxf) 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7799040</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33367857</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pogue K., Jensen J.L., Stancil C.K., Ferguson D.G., Hughes S.J., Mello E.J., et al. Influences on Attitudes Regarding Potential COVID-19 Vaccination in the United States. Vaccines (Basel) 2020;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7711655</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33022917</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Popa G.L., Muntean A.A., Muntean M.M., Popa M.I. Knowledge and Attitudes on Vaccination in Southern Romanians: A Cross-Sectional Questionnaire. Vaccines. 2020;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7765821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33352835</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao S., Tam C.C., Li X. Risk exposures, risk perceptions, negative attitudes toward general vaccination, and COVID-19 vaccine acceptance among college students in South Carolina. medRxiv. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34164998</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reiter P.L., Pennell M.L., Katz M.L. Acceptability of a COVID-19 vaccine among adults in the United States: How many people would get vaccinated? Vaccine. 2020;38:6500&#x2013;6507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7440153</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32863069</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Verger P., Scronias D., Dauby N., Adedzi K.A., Gobert C., Bergeat M., et al. Attitudes of healthcare workers towards COVID-19 vaccination: a survey in France and French-speaking parts of Belgium and Canada, 2020. Euro Surveill. 2021;26</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7848677</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33478623</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoda T., Katsuyama H. Willingness to Receive COVID-19 Vaccination in Japan. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7828811</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33466675</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bell S., Clarke R., Mounier-Jack S., Walker J.L., Paterson P. Parents' and guardians' views on the acceptability of a future COVID-19 vaccine: A multi-methods study in England. Vaccine. 2020;38:7789&#x2013;7798.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7569401</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33109389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman D., Loe B.S., Chadwick A., Vaccari C., Waite F., Rosebrock L., et al. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in the UK: The Oxford coronavirus explanations, attitudes, and narratives survey (Oceans) II. Psychol Med. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7804077</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33305716</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gagneux-Brunon A., Detoc M., Bruel S., Tardy B., Rozaire O., Frappe P., et al. Intention to get vaccinations against COVID-19 in French healthcare workers during the first pandemic wave: a cross-sectional survey. J Hosp Infect. 2021;108:168&#x2013;173.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7699157</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33259883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ruiz J.B., Bell R.A. Predictors of intention to vaccinate against COVID-19: Results of a nationwide survey. Vaccine. 2021;39:1080&#x2013;1086.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7794597</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33461833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K, Wong EL, Ho KF, Cheung AW, Yau PS, Dong D, et al. Change of Willingness to Accept COVID-19 Vaccine and Reasons of Vaccine Hesitancy of Working People at Different Waves of Local Epidemic in Hong Kong, China: Repeated Cross-Sectional Surveys. Vaccines (Basel). 2021;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832291</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33477725</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang K., Wong E.L.Y., Ho K.F., Cheung A.W.L., Chan E.Y.Y., Yeoh E.K., et al. Intention of nurses to accept coronavirus disease 2019 vaccination and change of intention to accept seasonal influenza vaccination during the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic: A cross-sectional survey. Vaccine. 2020;38:7049&#x2013;7056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7834255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32980199</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abedin M., Islam M.A., Rahman F.N., Reza H.M., Hossain M.Z., Hossain M.A., et al. Willingness to vaccinate against COVID-19 among Bangladeshi adults: Understanding the strategies to optimize vaccination coverage. PLoS ONE. 2021;16:e0250495.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8078802</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33905442</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cerda A.A., Garc&#xed;a L.Y. Hesitation and Refusal Factors in Individuals' Decision-Making Processes Regarding a Coronavirus Disease 2019 Vaccination. Front Public Health. 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8096991</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33968880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malesza M., Wittmann E. Acceptance and Intake of COVID-19 Vaccines among Older Germans. J Clin Med. 2021;10</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8036445</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33808414</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Momplaisir F., Haynes N., Nkwihoreze H., Nelson M., Werner R.M., Jemmott J. Understanding Drivers of COVID-19 Vaccine Hesitancy Among Blacks. Clin Infect Dis. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7929035</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33560346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qattan A.M.N., Alshareef N., Alsharqi O., Al Rahahleh N., Chirwa G.C., Al-Hanawi M.K. Acceptability of a COVID-19 Vaccine Among Healthcare Workers in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. Front Med (Lausanne) 2021;8</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7959705</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33732723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rabi R., Maraqa B., Nazzal Z., Zink T. Factors affecting nurses' intention to accept the COVID-9 vaccine: A cross-sectional study. Public Health Nurs. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8251396</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33844870</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robertson E., Reeve K.S., Niedzwiedz C.L., Moore J., Blake M., Green M., et al. Predictors of COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in the UK household longitudinal study. Brain Behav Immun. 2021;94:41&#x2013;50.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7946541</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33713824</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saied SM, Saied EM, Kabbash IA, Abdo SA. Vaccine hesitancy: Beliefs and barriers associated with COVID-19 vaccination among Egyptian medical students. Journal of Medical Virology.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8013865</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33644891</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vall&#xe9;e A., Fourn E., Majerholc C., Touche P., Zucman D. COVID-19 Vaccine Hesitancy among French People Living with HIV. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8063788</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33804808</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gan L., Chen Y., Hu P., Wu D., Zhu Y., Tan J., et al. Willingness to Receive SARS-CoV-2 Vaccination and Associated Factors among Chinese Adults: A Cross Sectional Survey. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7922368</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33670821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wong M.C.S., Wong E.L.Y., Huang J., Cheung A.W.L., Law K., Chong M.K.C., et al. Acceptance of the COVID-19 vaccine based on the health belief model: A population-based survey in Hong Kong. Vaccine. 2021;39:1148&#x2013;1156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832076</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33461834</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin C., Tu P., Beitsch L.M. Confidence and Receptivity for COVID-19 Vaccines: A Rapid Systematic Review. Vaccines (Basel) 2020;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7823859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33396832</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dinga J.N., Sinda L.K., Titanji V.P.K. Assessment of Vaccine Hesitancy to a COVID-19 Vaccine in Cameroonian Adults and Its Global Implication. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7922050</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33669659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agley J., Xiao Y. Misinformation about COVID-19: evidence for differential latent profiles and a strong association with trust in science. BMC Public Health. 2021;21:89.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7789893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33413219</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eichengreen B., Aksoy C.G., Saka O. Revenge of the experts: Will COVID-19 renew or diminish public trust in science? Journal of Public Economics. 2021;193</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8486491</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34629566</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palamenghi L., Barello S., Boccia S., Graffigna G. Mistrust in biomedical research and vaccine hesitancy: the forefront challenge in the battle against COVID-19 in Italy. Eur J Epidemiol. 2020;35:785&#x2013;788.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7431109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32808095</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Qiao S., Friedman D.B., Tam C.C., Zeng C., Li X. Vaccine acceptance among college students in South Carolina: Do information sources and trust in information make a difference? medRxiv. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11915207</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35427458</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Allington D., McAndrew S., Moxham-Hall V., Duffy B. Coronavirus conspiracy suspicions, general vaccine attitudes, trust and coronavirus information source as predictors of vaccine hesitancy among UK residents during the COVID-19 pandemic. Psychol Med. 2021;1&#x2013;12</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8111194</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33843509</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Attwell K., Lake J., Sneddon J., Gerrans P., Blyth C., Lee J. Converting the maybes: Crucial for a successful COVID-19 vaccination strategy. PLoS ONE. 2021;16</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7817004</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33471821</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doherty I.A., Pilkington W., Brown L., Billings V., Hoffler U., Paulin L., et al. COVID-19 Vaccine Hesitancy in Underserved Communities of North Carolina. medRxiv. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8559933</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34723973</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soares P., Rocha J.V., Moniz M., Gama A., Laires P.A., Pedro A.R., et al. Factors Associated with COVID-19 Vaccine Hesitancy. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8004673</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33810131</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards B., Biddle N., Gray M., Sollis K. COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy and resistance: Correlates in a nationally representative longitudinal survey of the Australian population. PLoS ONE. 2021;16:e0248892.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7990228</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33760836</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catalan-Matamoros D., El&#xed;as C. Vaccine Hesitancy in the Age of Coronavirus and Fake News: Analysis of Journalistic Sources in the Spanish Quality Press. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2020;17</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7662702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33158059</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gr&#xfc;ner S., Kr&#xfc;ger F. The intention to be vaccinated against COVID-19: stated preferences before vaccines were available. Applied Economics Letters. 2020</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nzaji M.K., Ngombe L.K., Mwamba G.N., Ndala D.B.B., Miema J.M., Lungoyo C.L., et al. Acceptability of Vaccination Against COVID-19 Among Healthcare Workers in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Pragmatic and Observational Research. 2020;11:103&#x2013;109.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7605960</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33154695</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prati G. Intention to receive a vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 in Italy and its association with trust, worry and beliefs about the origin of the virus. Health Educ Res. 2020;35:505&#x2013;511.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7799056</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33367772</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilson S.L., Wiysonge C. Social media and vaccine hesitancy. BMJ Glob. Health. 2020;5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7590343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33097547</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao E., Wu Q., Crimmins E.M., Ailshire J.A. Media trust and infection mitigating behaviours during the COVID-19 pandemic in the USA. BMJ Glob. Health. 2020;5</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7545496</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33037063</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kourlaba G., Kourkouni E., Maistreli S., Tsopela C.G., Molocha N.M., Triantafyllou C., et al. Willingness of Greek general population to get a COVID-19 vaccine. Global Health Research and Policy. 2021;6</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7843240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33509291</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Mohaithef M., Padhi B.K. Determinants of COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance in Saudi Arabia: A Web-Based National Survey. J Multidiscip Healthc. 2020;13:1657&#x2013;1663.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7686470</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33262600</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bogart L.M., Ojikutu B.O., Tyagi K., Klein D.J., Mutchler M.G., Dong L., et al. COVID-19 Related Medical Mistrust, Health Impacts, and Potential Vaccine Hesitancy Among Black Americans Living With HIV. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2021;86:200&#x2013;207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7808278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33196555</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bokemper S.E., Huber G.A., Gerber A.S., James E.K., Omer S.B. Timing of COVID-19 vaccine approval and endorsement by public figures. Vaccine. 2021;39:825&#x2013;829.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7744009</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33390295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>OECD. Enhancing public trust in COVID-19 vaccination: The role of governments. Available online at https://bit.ly/2RIWfno (Accessed on 23 May 2021). 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Caserotti M., Girardi P., Rubaltelli E., Tasso A., Lotto L., Gavaruzzi T. Associations of COVID-19 risk perception with vaccine hesitancy over time for Italian residents. Soc Sci Med. 2021;272</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7788320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33485215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Metwali B.Z., Al-Jumaili A.A., Al-Alag Z.A., Sorofman B. Exploring the acceptance of COVID-19 vaccine among healthcare workers and general population using health belief model. J Eval Clin Pract. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8242385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33960582</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huynh G., Tran T.T., Nguyen H.T.N., Pham L.A. COVID-19 vaccination intention among healthcare workers in Vietnam. Asian Pacific journal of tropical medicine. 2021;14:159&#x2013;164.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlAwadhi E., Zein D., Mallallah F., Bin Haider N., Hossain A. Monitoring COVID-19 Vaccine Acceptance in Kuwait During the Pandemic: Results from a National Serial Study. Risk Manag Healthc Policy. 2021;14:1413&#x2013;1429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8041648</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33854390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Detoc M., Bruel S., Frappe P., Tardy B., Botelho-Nevers E., Gagneux-Brunon A. Intention to participate in a COVID-19 vaccine clinical trial and to get vaccinated against COVID-19 in France during the pandemic. Vaccine. 2020;38:7002&#x2013;7006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7498238</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32988688</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorman C, Perera A, Condon C, Chau C, Qian J, Kalk K, et al. Factors Associated with Willingness to be Vaccinated Against COVID-19 in a Large Convenience Sample. Journal of Community Health.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8033546</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33835369</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Machida M., Nakamura I., Kojima T., Saito R., Nakaya T., Hanibuchi T., et al. Acceptance of a COVID-19 Vaccine in Japan during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8002097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33802285</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grech V., Gauci C. Vaccine hesitancy in the University of Malta Faculties of Health Sciences, Dentistry and Medicine vis-&#xe0;-vis influenza and novel COVID-19 vaccination. Early Hum Dev. 2020;105258</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7658558</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33213966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alfageeh E.I., Alshareef N., Angawi K., Alhazmi F., Chirwa G.C. Acceptability of a COVID-19 Vaccine among the Saudi Population. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7999879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33807732</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Papagiannis D., Rachiotis G., Malli F., Papathanasiou I.V., Kotsiou O., Fradelos E.C., et al. Acceptability of COVID-19 Vaccination among Greek Health Professionals. Vaccines (Basel) 2021;9</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7997202</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33670913</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gatwood J., McKnight M., Fiscus M., Hohmeier K.C., Chisholm-Burns M. Factors influencing likelihood of COVID-19 vaccination: A survey of Tennessee adults. Am J Health Syst Pharm. 2021;78:879&#x2013;889.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7989652</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33954426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olagoke AA, Olagoke OO, Hughes AM. Intention to Vaccinate Against the Novel 2019 Coronavirus Disease: The Role of Health Locus of Control and Religiosity. Journal of Religion &amp; Health.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7596314</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33125543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alley S.J., Stanton R., Browne M., To Q.G., Khalesi S., Williams S.L., et al. As the Pandemic Progresses, How Does Willingness to Vaccinate against COVID-19 Evolve? Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2021;18</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7832839</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33477825</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu D., Luo L., Xie F., Yu Z., Ma Z.F., Wang Y., et al. Factors associated with the willingness and acceptance of SARS-CoV-2 vaccine from adult subjects in China. Hum Vaccin Immunother. 2021:1&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8475565</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33759691</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dror A.A., Eisenbach N., Taiber S., Morozov N.G., Mizrachi M., Zigron A., et al. Vaccine hesitancy: the next challenge in the fight against COVID-19. Eur J Epidemiol. 2020;35:775&#x2013;779.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8851308</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32785815</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Earnshaw V.A., Eaton L.A., Kalichman S.C., Brousseau N.M., Hill E.C., Fox A.B. COVID-19 conspiracy beliefs, health behaviors, and policy support. Transl Behav Med. 2020;10:850&#x2013;856.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7499784</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32910819</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ecker F., Kutalek R. &#x2018;I&#x2019;m not an anti-vaxer!&#x2019;&#x2014;vaccine hesitancy among physicians: a qualitative study. Eur J Pub Health. 2021</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8675240</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34580713</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ostergaard S.D., Schmidt M., Horvath-Puho E., Thomsen R.W., Sorensen H.T. Thromboembolism and the Oxford-AstraZeneca COVID-19 vaccine: side-effect or coincidence? Lancet. 2021;397:1441&#x2013;1443.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8009607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33798498</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harford T. Daniel Kahneman: &#x2018;Everything I&#x2019;ve done has been collaborative&#x2019;. Available online https://www.ft.com/content/7cf78f4f-d40a-44f1-9946-e78eccb3da57 (Accessed on 12th May, 2021). Financial Times. 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kahneman D. Thinking, fast and slow: Macmillan; 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldenberg M.J. Public misunderstanding of science? Reframing the problem of vaccine hesitancy. Perspect Sci. 2016;24:552&#x2013;581.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mechanic D., Meyer S. Concepts of trust among patients with serious illness. Soc Sci Med. 2000;51:657&#x2013;668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10975226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20:875.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van der Linden S., Dixon G., Clarke C., Cook J. Inoculating against COVID-19 vaccine misinformation. EClinicalMedicine. 2021;33</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7908879</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33655205</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Group MQR. Medical Product Quality Report &#x2013; COVID-19 vaccine issues. Available online at https://bit.ly/3zRKVp2 (Accessed on 29th September 2021). 2021.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rackimuthu S., Narain K., Lal A., Nawaz F.A., Mohanan P., Essar M.Y., et al. Redressing COVID-19 vaccine inequity amidst booster doses: charting a bold path for global health solidarity, together. Global Health. 2022;18:23.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8862404</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35193616</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burt C.H., Simons R.L., Gibbons F.X. Racial Discrimination, Ethnic-Racial Socialization, and Crime: A Micro-sociological Model of Risk and Resilience. Am Sociol Rev. 2012;77:648&#x2013;677.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3777442</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24058204</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stuck L.HJ. Oxford University Press; 2020. How Vaccine Rumors Start&#x2013;and Why They Don't Go Away.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hao F., Wang B., Tan W., Husain S.F., McIntyre R.S., Tang X., et al. Attitudes toward COVID-19 vaccination and willingness to pay: comparison of people with and without mental disorders in China. BJPsych Open. 2021;7:e146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8365102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34422295</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>