<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">38620813</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>06</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2542-6605</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>14</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Internet of things (Amsterdam, Netherlands)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Internet Things (Amst)</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>iCovidCare: Intelligent health monitoring framework for COVID-19 using ensemble random forest in edge networks.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>100385</StartPage><MedlinePgn>100385</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.iot.2021.100385</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>The COVID-19 outbreak is in its growing stage due to the lack of standard diagnosis for the patients. In recent times, various models with machine learning have been developed to predict and diagnose novel coronavirus. However, the existing models fail to take an instant decision for detecting the COVID-19 patient immediately and cannot handle multiple medical sensor data for disease prediction. To handle such challenges, we propose an intelligent health monitoring and prediction framework, namely the iCovidCare model for predicting the health status of COVID-19 patients using the ensemble Random Forest (eRF) technique in edge networks. In the proposed framework, a rule-based policy is designed on the local edge devices to detect the risk factor of a patient immediately using monitoring Temperature sensor values. The real-time health monitoring parameters of different medical sensors are transmitted to the centralized cloud servers for future health prediction of the patients. The standard eRF technique is used to predict the health status of the patients using the proposed data fusion and feature selection strategy by selecting the most significant features for disease prediction. The proposed iCovidCare model is evaluated with a synthetic COVID-19 dataset and compared with the standard classification models based on various performance matrices to show its effectiveness. The proposed model has achieved 95.13% accuracy, which is higher than the standard classification models.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2021 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Adhikari</LastName><ForeName>Mainak</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Mobile &amp; Cloud Lab, Institute of Computer Science, University of Tartu, Estonia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Munusamy</LastName><ForeName>Ambigavathi</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of ECE, CEG Campus, Anna University, Chennai, India.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>10</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Internet Things (Amst)</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9918608588406676</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2542-6605</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">COVID-19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Disease prediction</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Edge networks</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Feature selection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Health monitoring</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">eRF classification model</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>9</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>15</Day><Hour>14</Hour><Minute>50</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38620813</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7943395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.iot.2021.100385</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2542-6605(21)00029-9</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Rogers J.P., Chesney E., Oliver D., Pollak T.A., McGuire P., Fusar-Poli P., Zandi M.S., Lewis G., David A.S. Psychiatric and neuropsychiatric presentations associated with severe coronavirus infections: a systematic review and meta-analysis with comparison to the COVID-19 pandemic. Lancet Psychiatry. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7234781</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32437679</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peiris J., Lai S., Poon L., Guan Y., Yam L., Lim W., Nicholls J., Yee W., Yan W., Cheung M., et al. Coronavirus as a possible cause of severe acute respiratory syndrome. Lancet. 2003;361(9366):1319&#x2013;1325.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7112372</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12711465</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>H.S. Maghdid, A.T. Asaad, K.Z. Ghafoor, A.S. Sadiq, M.K. Khan, Diagnosing COVID-19 pneumonia from X-ray and CT images using deep learning and transfer learning algorithms, arXiv preprint arXiv:2004.00038(2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>W.H. Organization, et&#xa0;al., Novel coronavirus (2019-ncov): situation report, 3 (2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yao H., Chen J.-H., Xu Y.-F. Rethinking online mental health services in china during the COVID-19 epidemic. Asian J. Psychiatry. 2020;50:1&#x2013;2.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7271098</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32247261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roosa K., Lee Y., Luo R., Kirpich A., Rothenberg R., Hyman J., Yan P., Chowell G. Real-time forecasts of the COVID-19 epidemic in China from february 5th to february 24th, 2020. Infect. Dis. Model. 2020;5:256&#x2013;263.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7033348</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32110742</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hassen H.B., Ayari N., Hamdi B. A home hospitalization system based on the Internet of Things, fog computing and cloud computing. Inform. Med. Unlocked. 2020;20:100368.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7282767</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32537483</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taiwo O., Ezugwu A.E. Smart healthcare support for remote patient monitoring during COVID-19 quarantine. Inform. Med. Unlocked. 2020;20:100428.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7490242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32953970</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meng T., Jing X., Yan Z., Pedrycz W. A survey on machine learning for data fusion. Inf. Fusion. 2020;57:115&#x2013;129.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nweke H.F., Teh Y.W., Mujtaba G., Al-Garadi M.A. Data fusion and multiple classifier systems for human activity detection and health monitoring: review and open research directions. Inf. Fusion. 2019;46:147&#x2013;170.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jonnagaddala J., Liaw S.-T., Ray P., Kumar M., Chang N.-W., Dai H.-J. Coronary artery disease risk assessment from unstructured electronic health records using text mining. J. Biomed. Inform. 2015;58:S203&#x2013;S210.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4985289</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26319542</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jain D., Singh V. Feature selection and classification systems for chronic disease prediction: a review. Egypt. Inform. J. 2018;19(3):179&#x2013;189.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ahmed H., Younis E.M., Hendawi A., Ali A.A. Heart disease identification from patients social posts, machine learning solution on spark. Future Gener. Comput. Syst. 2020;111:714&#x2013;722.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Garate-Escamilla A.K., Hassani A.H.E., Andres E. Classification models for heart disease prediction using feature selection and PCA. Inform. Med. Unlocked. 2020:1&#x2013;11.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Binkhonain M., Zhao L. A review of machine learning algorithms for identification and classification of non-functional requirements. Expert Syst. Appl. X. 2019;1:1&#x2013;13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Uddin S., Khan A., Hossain M.E., Moni M.A. Comparing different supervised machine learning algorithms for disease prediction. BMC Med. Inform. Decis. Mak. 2019;19(1):1&#x2013;16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6925840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31864346</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbas S.A., Rehman A.U., Majeed F., Majid A., Malik M.S.A., Kazmi Z.H., Zafar S. Performance analysis of classification algorithms on birth dataset. IEEE Access. 2020;8:102146&#x2013;102154.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sen P.C., Hajra M., Ghosh M. Emerging Technology in Modelling and Graphics. Springer; 2020. Supervised classification algorithms in machine learning: a survey and review; pp. 99&#x2013;111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdar M., Zomorodi-Moghadam M., Das R., Ting I.-H. Performance analysis of classification algorithms on early detection of liver disease. Expert Syst. Appl. 2017;67:239&#x2013;251.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dogan N., Tanrikulu Z. A comparative analysis of classification algorithms in data mining for accuracy, speed and robustness. Inf. Technol. Manag. 2013;14(2):105&#x2013;124.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>AlJame M., Ahmad I., Imtiaz A., Mohammed A. Ensemble learning model for diagnosing COVID-19 from routine blood tests. Inform. Med. Unlocked. 2020;21:100449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7572278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33102686</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>S. Aktar, M. Ahamad, M. Rashed-Al-Mahfuz, A. Azad, S. Uddin, A. Kamal, S.A. Alyami, P.-I. Lin, S.M.S. Islam, J.M. Quinn, et&#xa0;al., Predicting patient COVID-19 disease severity by means of statistical and machine learning analysis of blood cell transcriptome data, arXiv preprint arXiv:2011.10657(2020).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhammad L., Algehyne E.A., Usman S.S., Ahmad A., Chakraborty C., Mohammed I. Supervised machine learning models for prediction of COVID-19 infection using epidemiology dataset. SN Comput. Sci. 2021;2(1):1&#x2013;13.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7694891</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33263111</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alam M.Z., Rahman M.S., Rahman M.S. A random forest based predictor for medical data classification using feature ranking. Inform. Med. Unlocked. 2019;15:1&#x2013;12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li R., Shen S., Zhang X., Li R., Wang S., Zhou B., Wang Z. Proceedings of the International Conference on Healthcare Science and Engineering. Springer; 2018. Cardiovascular disease risk prediction based on random forest; pp. 31&#x2013;43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iwendi C., Bashir A.K., Peshkar A., Sujatha R., Chatterjee J.M., Pasupuleti S., Mishra R., Pillai S., Jo O. COVID-19 patient health prediction using boosted random forest algorithm. Front. Public Health. 2020;8:1&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7350612</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32719767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muhammad L., Islam M.M., Sharif U.S., Ayon S.I. Predictive data mining models for novel coronavirus (COVID-19) infected patients recovery. SN Comput. Sci. 2020;206:1&#x2013;7.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7306186</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33063049</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Din S., Paul A. Smart health monitoring and management system: toward autonomous wearable sensing for internet of things using big data analytics. Future Gener. Comput. Syst. 2019;91:611&#x2013;619.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul A.K., Shill P.C., Rabin M.R.I., Murase K. Adaptive weighted fuzzy rule-based system for the risk level assessment of heart disease. Appl. Intell. 2018;48(7):1739&#x2013;1756.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Narayan S., Sathiyamoorthy E. A novel recommender system based on FFT with machine learning for predicting and identifying heart diseases. Neural Comput. Appl. 2019;31(1):93&#x2013;102.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kabir W., Ahmad M.O., Swamy M. Normalization and weighting techniques based on genuine-impostor score fusion in multi-biometric systems. IEEE Trans. Inf. Forensics Secur. 2018;13(8):1989&#x2013;2000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petrilli C.M., Jones S.A., Yang J., Rajagopalan H., ODonnell L., Chernyak Y., Tobin K.A., Cerfolio R.J., Francois F., Horwitz L.I. Factors associated with hospital admission and critical illness among 5279 people with coronavirus disease 2019 in New York city: prospective cohort study. BMJ. 2020;369</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7243801</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32444366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tharakan S., Nomoto K., Miyashita S., Ishikawa K. Body temperature correlates with mortality in COVID-19 patients. Crit. Care. 2020;24(1):298. doi: 10.1186/s13054-020-03045-8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s13054-020-03045-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7274509</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32503659</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Liu F.-Y., Sun X.-L., Zhang Y., Ge L., Wang J., Liang X., Li J.-F., Wang C.-L., Xing Z.-T., Chhetri J.K., et al. Evaluation of the risk prediction tools for patients with coronavirus disease 2019 in Wuhan, China: a single-centered, retrospective, observational study. Crit. Care Med. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7448719</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32897668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Virgeniya S., Ramaraj E. Predictive analytics using rule based classification and hybrid logistic regression(hlr) algorithm for decision making. Int. J. Sci. Technol. Res. 2019;8:1509&#x2013;1513.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kumar Y., Sahoo G. Prediction of different types of liver diseases using rule based classification model. Technol. Health Care. 2013;21(5):417&#x2013;432.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23963359</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christopher J. Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Cloud Computing, Data Science Engineering (Confluence) 2019. The science of rule-based classifiers; pp. 299&#x2013;303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1109/CONFLUENCE.2019.8776954</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>