<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">32920842</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>25</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>25</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1541-0420</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>77</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Dec</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Biometrics</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Biometrics</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>A marginal moment matching approach for fitting endemic-epidemic models to underreported disease surveillance counts.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1202</StartPage><EndPage>1214</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1202-1214</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/biom.13371</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Count data are often subject to underreporting, especially in infectious disease surveillance. We propose an approximate maximum likelihood method to fit count time series models from the endemic-epidemic class to underreported data. The approach is based on marginal moment matching where underreported processes are approximated through completely observed processes from the same class. Moreover, the form of the bias when underreporting is ignored or taken into account via multiplication factors is analyzed. Notably, we show that this leads to a downward bias in model-based estimates of the effective reproductive number. A marginal moment matching approach can also be used to account for reporting intervals which are longer than the mean serial interval of a disease. The good performance of the proposed methodology is demonstrated in simulation studies. An extension to time-varying parameters and reporting probabilities is discussed and applied in a case study on weekly rotavirus gastroenteritis counts in Berlin,&#xa0;Germany.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2020 The International Biometric Society.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bracher</LastName><ForeName>Johannes</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-3777-1410</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Prevention Institute, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Held</LastName><ForeName>Leonhard</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Epidemiology, Biostatistics and Prevention Institute, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2020</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>28</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Biometrics</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370625</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0006-341X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015982" MajorTopicYN="N">Bias</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003141" MajorTopicYN="Y">Communicable Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003198" MajorTopicYN="N">Computer Simulation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058872" MajorTopicYN="Y">Epidemics</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="N">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011336" MajorTopicYN="N">Probability</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">count time series analysis</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">effective reproductive number</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">moment matching</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">temporal aggregation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">underreporting</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2019</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>42</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32920842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/biom.13371</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Atkins, K.E., Shim, E., Pitzer, V.E. and Galvani, A.P. (2012) Impact of rotavirus vaccination on epidemiological dynamics in England and Wales. Vaccine, 30(3), 552-564.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Azmon, A., Faes, C. and Hens, N. (2014) On the estimation of the reproduction number based on misreported epidemic data. Statistics in Medicine, 33(7), 1176-1192.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bailey, T., Carvalho, M., Lapa, T., Souza, W. and Brewer, M. (2005) Modeling of under-detection of cases in disease surveillance. Annals of Epidemiology, 15(5), 335-343.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bauer, C. and Wakefield, J. (2018) Stratified space-time infectious disease modelling, with an application to hand, foot and mouth disease in China. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C (Applied Statistics), 67(5), 1379-1398.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker, A.D. and Grenfell, B.T. (2017) tsir: an R package for time-series susceptible-infected-recovered models of epidemics. PLOS One, 12(9), 1-10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker, N. (2015) Modeling to Inform Infectious Disease Control. Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bracher, J. (2019) Comment on &#x201c;Under-reported data analysis with INAR-hidden Markov chains.&#x201d; Statistics in Medicine, 38(5), 893-898.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bracher, J. and Held, L. (2020) Endemic-epidemic models with discrete-time serial interval distributions for infectious disease prediction. International Journal of Forecasting. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03090.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Br&#xe4;nn&#xe4;s, K., Hellstr&#xf6;m, J. and Nordstr&#xf6;m, J. (2002) A new approach to modelling and forecasting monthly guest nights in hotels. International Journal of Forecasting, 18(1), 19-30.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bundesagentur f&#xfc;r Arbeit (2020) Pendleratlas. Available at https://statistik.arbeitsagentur.de/DE/Navigation/Statistiken/Interaktive-Angebote/Pendleratlas/Pendleratlas-Nav.html. Accessed September 22, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cauchemez, S. and Ferguson, N.M. (2008) Likelihood-based estimation of continuous-time epidemic models from time-series data: application to measles transmission in London. Journal of the Royal Society Interface, 5(25), 885-897.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cui, Y. and Zheng, Q. (2017) Conditional maximum likelihood estimation for a class of observation-driven time series models for count data. Statistics and Probability Letters, 123, 193-201.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dorigatti, I., Cauchemez, S., Pugliese, A. and Ferguson, N.M. (2012) A new approach to characterising infectious disease transmission dynamics from sentinel surveillance: application to the Italian 2009-2010 A/H1N1 influenza pandemic. Epidemics, 4(1), 9-21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dvorzak, M. and Wagner, H. (2016) Sparse Bayesian modelling of underreported count data. Statistical Modelling, 16(1), 24-46.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferland, R., Latour, A. and Oraichi, D. (2006) Integer-valued GARCH process. Journal of Time Series Analysis, 27(6), 923-942.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fern&#xe1;ndez-Fontelo, A., Caba&#xf1;a, A., Puig, P. and Mori&#xf1;a, D. (2016) Under-reported data analysis with INAR-hidden Markov chains. Statistics in Medicine, 35(26), 4875-4890.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fern&#xe1;ndez-Fontelo, A., Caba&#xf1;a, A., Joe, H., Puig, P. and Mori&#xf1;a, D. (2019) Untangling serially dependent underreported count data for gender-based violence. Statistics in Medicine, 38(22), 4404-4422.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fintzi, J., Cui, X., Wakefield, J. and Minin, V.N. (2017) Efficient data augmentation for fitting stochastic epidemic models to prevalence data. Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics, 26(4), 918-929.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fokianos, K. (2016) Statistical analysis of count time series models: a GLM perspective. In: Davis, R., Holan, S., Lund, R. and Ravishanker, N. (Eds.) Handbook of Discrete-Valued Time Series. Boca Raton, FL: Wiley, pp. 3-28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fraser, C., Donnelly, C.A., Cauchemez, S., Hanage, W.P. and Van Kerkhove, M. D. (2009) Pandemic potential of a strain of Influenza A (H1N1): early findings. Science, 324(5934), 1557-1561.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamado, K.M., Streftaris, G. and Zachary, S. (2014) Modelling under-reporting in epidemics. Journal of Mathematical Biology, 69(3), 737-765.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibbons, C.L., Mangen, M.-J.J., Plass, D., Havelaar, A.H., Brooke, R.J. and Kramarz, P. (2014) Measuring underreporting and under-ascertainment in infectious disease datasets: a comparison of methods. BMC Public Health, 14(1), 1-17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>G&#xf3;mez-Rubio, V., Palmi&#xed;-Perales, F., L&#xf3;pez-Abente, G., Ramis-Prieto, R. and Fern&#xe1;ndez-Navarro, P. (2019) Bayesian joint spatio-temporal analysis of multiple diseases. SORT-Statistics and Operations Research Transactions, 43(1), 51-74.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grimwood, K., Abbott, G.D., Fergusson, D.M., Jennings, L.C. and Allan, J.M. (1983) Spread of rotavirus within families: a community based study. British Medical Journal, 287(6392), 575-577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Held, L., H&#xf6;hle, M. and Hofmann, M. (2005) A statistical framework for the analysis of multivariate infectious disease surveillance counts. Statistical Modelling, 5(3), 187-199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Held, L., Meyer, S. and Bracher, J. (2017) Probabilistic forecasting in infectious disease epidemiology: the 13th Armitage lecture. Statistics in Medicine, 36(22), 3443-3460.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Held, L. and Paul, M. (2012) Modeling seasonality in space-time infectious disease surveillance data. Biometrical Journal, 54(6), 824-843.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heymann, D. (Ed.) (2015) Control of Communicable Diseases Manual, 20th edition. Washington, DC: APHA Press.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jandarov, R., Haran, M., Bj&#xf8;rnstad, O. and Grenfell, B. (2014) Emulating a gravity model to infer the spatiotemporal dynamics of an infectious disease. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series C (Applied Statistics), 63(3), 423-444.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>King, A., Nguyen, D. and Ionides, E. (2016) Statistical inference for partially observed Markov processes via the R package pomp. Journal of Statistical Software, 69(12), 1-43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Magal, P. and Webb, G. (2018) The parameter identification problem for SIR epidemic models: identifying unreported cases. Journal of Mathematical Biology, 77(6), 1629-1648.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer, S. and Held, L. (2014) Power-law models for infectious disease spread. Annals of Applied Statistics, 8(3), 1612-1639.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer, S. and Held, L. (2017) Incorporating social contact data in spatio-temporal models for infectious disease spread. Biostatistics, 18(2), 338-351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Noufaily, A. (2019) Underreporting and reporting delays. In: Held, L., Hens, N., O'Neill, P. and Wallinga, J. (Eds.) Handbook of Infectious Disease Data Analysis. London, UK: Chapman and Hall/CRC, pp. 437-454.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oliveira, G.L., Loschi, R.H. and Assun&#xe7;&#xe3;o, R.M. (2017) A random-censoring Poisson model for underreported data. Statistics in Medicine, 36(30), 4873-4892.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paul, M., Held, L. and Toschke, A.M. (2008) Multivariate modelling of infectious disease surveillance data. Statistics in Medicine, 27(29), 6250-6267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plummer, M. (2015) Cuts in Bayesian graphical models. Statistics and Computing, 25(1), 37-43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert Koch Institute (2020) Survstat@rki 2.0. Web-based query on data reported under the German Protection against Infection Act. https://survstat.rki.de/ [Accessed 03 September 2020] .</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharmin, S., Glass, K., Viennet, E. and Harley, D. (2018a) A Bayesian approach for estimating under-reported dengue incidence with a focus on non-linear associations between climate and dengue in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Statistical Methods in Medical Research, 27(4), 991-1000.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharmin, S., Glass, K., Viennet, E. and Harley, D. (2018b) Geostatistical mapping of the seasonal spread of under-reported dengue cases in Bangladesh. PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases, 12(11), 1-13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Silvestrini, A. and Veredas, D. (2008) Temporal aggregation of univariate and multivariate time series models: a survey. Journal of Economic Surveys, 22(3), 458-497.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Staudenmayer, J. and Buonaccorsi, J.P. (2005) Measurement error in linear autoregressive models. Journal of the American Statistical Association, 100(471), 841-852.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stocks, T., Britton, T. and H&#xf6;hle, M. (2018) Model selection and parameter estimation for dynamic epidemic models via iterated filtering: application to rotavirus in Germany. Biostatistics, 21(3), 400-416.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoner, O., Economou, T. and Drummond, G. (2019) A hierarchical framework for correcting under-reporting in count data. Journal of the American Statistical Association, 114, 1481-1492.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tam, C.C., Rodrigues, L.C., Viviani, L., Dodds, J.P., Evans, M.R., Hunter, P.R., et&#xa0;al. (2012) Longitudinal study of infectious intestinal disease in the UK (IID2 study): incidence in the community and presenting to general practice. Gut, 61(1), 69-77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>van Gaalen, R., van de Kassteele, J., Hahn&#xe9;, S., Bruijning-Verhagen, P. and Wallinga, J. (2017) Determinants of rotavirus transmission. A lag nonlinear time series analysis. Epidemiology, 28(4), 503-513.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wakefield, J., Dong, Q. and Minin, V.N. (2019) Spatio-temporal analysis of surveillance data. In: Held, L., Hens, N., O'Neill, P. and Wallinga, J. (Eds.) Handbook of Infectious Disease Data Analysis. London, UK: Chapman and Hall/CRC, pp. 455-476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang, Y., Feng, Z., Yang, Y., Self, S., Gao, Y., Longini, I.M., et&#xa0;al., (2011) Hand, foot, and mouth disease in China: patterns of spread and transmissibility. Epidemiology, 22(6), 781-792.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weidemann, F., Dehnert, M., Koch, J., Wichmann, O. and H&#xf6;hle, M. (2014) Bayesian parameter inference for dynamic infectious disease modelling: rotavirus in Germany. Statistics in Medicine, 33(9), 1580-1599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White, L.F. and Pagano, M. (2010) Reporting errors in infectious disease outbreaks, with an application to pandemic influenza A/H1N1. Epidemiologic Perspectives and Innovations, 7(1), 1-12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Woudenberg, T., Woonink, F., Kerkhof, J., Cox, K., Ruijs, W., van Binnendijk, R., et&#xa0;al. (2019) The tip of the iceberg: incompleteness of measles reporting during a large outbreak in The Netherlands in 2013-2014. Epidemiology and Infection, 147, e23.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhu, F. (2011) A negative binomial integer-valued GARCH model. Journal of Time Series Analysis, 32(1), 54-67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zucchini, W. and MacDonald, I. (2009) Hidden Markov Models for Time Series. New York, NY: Chapman and Hall/CRC.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>