<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">26828366</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2016</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1932-6203</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>11</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2016</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PloS one</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS One</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Population Size Estimation of Men Who Have Sex with Men in Tbilisi, Georgia; Multiple Methods and Triangulation of Findings.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e0147413</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e0147413</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e0147413</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pone.0147413</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="INTRODUCTION">An accurate estimation of the population size of men who have sex with men (MSM) is critical to the success of HIV program planning and to monitoring of the response to epidemic as a whole, but is quite often missing. In this study, our aim was to estimate the population size of MSM in Tbilisi, Georgia and compare it with other estimates in the region.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">In the absence of a gold standard for estimating the population size of MSM, this study reports a range of methods, including network scale-up, mobile/web apps multiplier, service and unique object multiplier, network-based capture-recapture, Handcock RDS-based and Wisdom of Crowds methods. To apply all these methods, two surveys were conducted: first, a household survey among 1,015 adults from the general population, and second, a respondent driven sample of 210 MSM. We also conducted a literature review of MSM size estimation in Eastern European and Central Asian countries.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">The median population size of MSM generated from all previously mentioned methods was estimated to be 5,100 (95% Confidence Interval (CI): 3,243~9,088). This corresponds to 1.42% (95%CI: 0.9%~2.53%) of the adult male population in Tbilisi.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION">Our size estimates of the MSM population (1.42% (95%CI: 0.9%~2.53%) of the adult male population in Tbilisi) fall within ranges reported in other Eastern European and Central Asian countries. These estimates can provide valuable information for country level HIV prevention program planning and evaluation. Furthermore, we believe, that our results will narrow the gap in data availability on the estimates of the population size of MSM in the region.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sulaberidze</LastName><ForeName>Lela</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Curatio International Foundation, Tbilisi, Georgia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mirzazadeh</LastName><ForeName>Ali</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Global Health Sciences, University of California San Francisco, San Francisco, California, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Regional Knowledge Hub, and WHO Collaborating Centre for HIV Surveillance, Institute for Futures Studies in Health, Kerman University of Medical Sciences, Kerman, Iran.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Chikovani</LastName><ForeName>Ivdity</ForeName><Initials>I</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Curatio International Foundation, Tbilisi, Georgia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shengelia</LastName><ForeName>Natia</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Curatio International Foundation, Tbilisi, Georgia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsereteli</LastName><ForeName>Nino</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Information and Counseling on Reproductive Health-Tanadgoma, Tbilisi, Georgia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Gotsadze</LastName><ForeName>George</ForeName><Initials>G</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Curatio International Foundation, Tbilisi, Georgia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><DataBankList CompleteYN="Y"><DataBank><DataBankName>Dryad</DataBankName><AccessionNumberList><AccessionNumber>10.5061/dryad.CB574</AccessionNumber></AccessionNumberList></DataBank></DataBankList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2016</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS One</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101285081</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1932-6203</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005845" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Georgia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018451" MajorTopicYN="N">Homosexuality, Male</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="Y">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011156" MajorTopicYN="Y">Population Density</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012944" MajorTopicYN="N">Social Support</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement><b>Competing Interests: </b>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2015</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2016</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2016</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2016</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2016</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>20</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2016</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26828366</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4734621</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0147413</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">PONE-D-15-11315</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>AIDSinfo Online Database. 2014. Ref Type: Online Source</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Global AIDS Response Progress Report, GEORGIA, Country Progress Report. 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO, Regional Knowledge Hub for HIV/AIDS Surveillance, Kerman University of Medical Sciences KI. Network Scale-up Method Workshop Manual. 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS, the US Office of the Global AIDS Coordinator. Consultation on Network scale-up and other size estimation methods from general population surveys. New York City; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salganik MJ, Mello MB, Abdo AH, Bertoni N, Fazito D, Bastos FI. The Game of Contacts: Estimating the Social Visibility of Groups. Soc Networks 2011. January 1;33(1):70&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3035387</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21318126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W, Bao S, Lin W, Wu G, Zhang W, Hladik W, et al. Estimating the size of HIV key affected populations in Chongqing, China, using the network scale-up method. PLOS One 2013;8(8):e71796 10.1371/journal.pone.0071796</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0071796</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3742468</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23967246</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ezoe S, Morooka T, Noda T, Sabin ML, Koike S. Population size estimation of men who have sex with men through the network scale-up method in Japan. PLOS One 2012;7(1):e31184 10.1371/journal.pone.0031184</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0031184</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3341925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22563366</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Killworth PD, McCarty C, Bernard HR, Shelley GA, Johnsen EC. Estimation of seroprevalence, rape, and homelessness in the United States using a social network approach. Eval Rev 1998. April;22(2):289&#x2013;308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10183307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johnston LG, Prybylski D, Raymond HF, Mirzazadeh A, Manopaiboon C, McFarland W. Incorporating the service multiplier method in respondent-driven sampling surveys to estimate the size of hidden and hard-to-reach populations: case studies from around the world. Sex Transm Dis 2013. April;40(4):304&#x2013;10. 10.1097/OLQ.0b013e31827fd650</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/OLQ.0b013e31827fd650</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23486495</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abdul-Quader AS, Baughman AL, Hladik W. Estimating the size of key populations: current status and future possibilities. Curr Opin HIV AIDS 2014. March;9(2):107&#x2013;14. 10.1097/COH.0000000000000041</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/COH.0000000000000041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6787402</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24393694</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Burrell ER, Pines HA, Robbie E, Coleman L, Murphy RD, Hess KL, et al. Use of the location-based social networking application GRINDR as a recruitment tool in rectal microbicide development research. AIDS Behav 2012. October;16(7):1816&#x2013;20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3692292</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22851153</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>RDS Analyst: Software for the analysis of Respondent-Driven Sampling Data, Version 0.42 [computer program]. 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dombrowski K, Khan B, Wendel T, McLean K, Misshula E, Curtis R. Estimating the Size of the Methamphetamine-Using Population in New York City Using Network Sampling Techniques. Adv Appl Sociol 2012. December 1;2(4):245&#x2013;52.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3963163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24672746</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Handcock MS, Gile KJ, Mar CM. Estimating the size of populations at high risk for HIV using respondent-driven sampling data. Biometrics 2015. March;71(1):258&#x2013;66. 10.1111/biom.12255</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/biom.12255</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4418439</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25585794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okal J, Geibel S, Muraguri N, Musyoki H, Tun W, Broz D, et al. Estimates of the size of key populations at risk for HIV infection: men who have sex with men, female sex workers and injecting drug users in Nairobi, Kenya. Sex Transm Infect 2013. August;89(5):366&#x2013;71.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4784698</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23761166</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lorenz J, Rauhut H, Schweitzer F, Helbing D. How social influence can undermine the wisdom of crowd effect. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2011. May 31;108(22):9020&#x2013;5. 10.1073/pnas.1008636108</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1008636108</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3107299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21576485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee MD, Zhang S, Shi J. The wisdom of the crowd playing The Price Is Right. Mem Cognit 2011. July;39(5):914&#x2013;23. 10.3758/s13421-010-0059-7</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3758/s13421-010-0059-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3120971</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21264578</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rastegari A, Haji-Maghsoudi S, Haghdoost A, Shatti M, Tarjoman T, Baneshi MR. The estimation of active social network size of the Iranian population. Glob J Health Sci 2013. July;5(4):217&#x2013;27. 10.5539/gjhs.v5n4p217</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.5539/gjhs.v5n4p217</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4776847</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23777738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rwanda Biomedical Center/Institute of HIV/AIDS, Disease Prevention and Control Department (RBC/IHDPC), School of Public Health (SPH), UNAIDS aII. Estimating the Size of Populations though a Household Survey. Calverton, Maryland, USA; 2012 Feb.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tsereteli N, Chikovani I, Shengelia N, Chkhaidze N. HIV risk and prevention behaviour among Men who have Sex with Men in Tbilisi, Georgia; Bio-behavioral Surveillance Survey. Curatio International Foundation, Center for Information and Counseling on Reproductive Health&#x2014;Tanadgoma; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Development of the software packages, EPP v2 and Spectrum, and Measuring and tracking the epidemic in countries where HIV is concentrated among populations at high risk of HIV. Report of a meeting of the UNAIDS Reference Group for Estimates, Modeling and Projections held in Sintra. 2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Global AIDS Response Progress Report, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Country Progress Report. 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Global AIDS Response Progress Report, Republic of Moldova, Country Progress Report. 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Global AIDS Response Progress Report, Serbia, Country Progress Report. 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Comiskey C, Dempsey O, Simic D, Baros S. Injecting drug users, sex workers and men who have sex with men: a national cross-sectional study to develop a framework and prevalence estimates for national HIV/AIDS programmes in the Republic of Serbia. BMJ Open 2013;3(5).</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3646171</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23645910</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berleva G, Dumchev K, Kasianchuk M, NIkolko M, Saliuk T, Shvab I, et al. Estimation of the Size of Populations Most-at-Risk for HIV Infection in Ukraine as of 2012 based on the results of 2011 survey. 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Global AIDS Response Progress Report, Azerbaijan, Country Progress Report. 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>UNAIDS. Global AIDS Response Progress Report, Kazakhstan, Country Progress Report. 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu E, Terlikbayeva A, Hunt T, Primbetova S, El-Bassel N, Gilbert L. Estimation of the Population Size of Men Who Have Sex with Men (MSM) in Kazakhstan: Implications for HIV Testing and Surveillance. San Diego 2013.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28005454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McGill R, Tukey WJ, Larsen AW. Variations of Box Plots. The American Statistician 1978;32(1):12&#x2013;6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Paniotto V, Petrenko T, Kupriyanov V, Pakhok O. Estimating the Size of Populations with High Risk for HIV Using the Network Scale-up Method Kiev: Kiev International Institute of Sociology; 2009.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manikandan S. Measures of central tendency: The mean. J Pharmacol Pharmacother 2011. April;2(2):140&#x2013;2. 10.4103/0976-500X.81920</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0976-500X.81920</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3127352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21772786</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Manikandan S. Measures of central tendency: Median and mode. J Pharmacol Pharmacother 2011. July;2(3):214&#x2013;5. 10.4103/0976-500X.83300</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4103/0976-500X.83300</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3157145</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21897729</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Politch JA, Mayer KH, Welles SL, O'Brien WX, Xu C, Bowman FP, et al. Highly active antiretroviral therapy does not completely suppress HIV in semen of sexually active HIV-infected men who have sex with men. AIDS 2012. July 31;26(12):1535&#x2013;43. 10.1097/QAD.0b013e328353b11b</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QAD.0b013e328353b11b</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3806452</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22441253</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hosein SR, Wilson DP. Antiretroviral therapy in men who have sex with men. Lancet Infect Dis 2013. August;13(8):654&#x2013;5.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23886331</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muessig KE, Smith MK, Powers KA, Lo YR, Burns DN, Grulich AE, et al. Does ART prevent HIV transmission among MSM? AIDS 2012. November 28;26(18):2267&#x2013;73. 10.1097/QAD.0b013e328355713d</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/QAD.0b013e328355713d</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3499670</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22569019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quaye S, Fisher RH, Atuahene K, Amenyah R, Aberle-Grasse J, McFarland W, et al. Critique and lessons learned from using multiple methods to estimate population size of men who have sex with men in Ghana. AIDS Behav 2015. February;19 Suppl 1:S16&#x2013;S23. 10.1007/s10461-014-0943-4</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10461-014-0943-4</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25704987</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vallejo A, Muniesa A, Ferreira C, de Blas I. New method to estimate the sample size for calculation of a proportion assuming binomial distribution. Res Vet Sci 2013. October;95(2):405&#x2013;9. 10.1016/j.rvsc.2013.04.005</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2013.04.005</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23623739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>