<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">30683242</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2020</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>05</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2020</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>05</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2214-109X</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>2</Issue><PubDate><Year>2019</Year><Month>Feb</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Lancet. Global health</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Lancet Glob Health</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Effect of pneumococcal conjugate vaccine introduction on childhood pneumonia mortality in Brazil: a retrospective observational study.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e249</StartPage><EndPage>e256</EndPage><MedlinePgn>e249-e256</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30455-8</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S2214-109X(18)30455-8</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Understanding the real-world effect of pneumococcal conjugate vaccines (PCVs) on pneumonia mortality is crucial because of the expectation that increased PCV use will substantially reduce the burden of pneumonia deaths in children younger than 5 years. However, few post-vaccine introduction studies have estimated the benefits of PCV use on childhood mortality and results have been inconsistent. Therefore, we set out to assess the effect of introduction of ten-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV10) on pneumonia mortality in children in Brazil.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">In this retrospective observational study, we used publicly available mortality data of children aged 3-59 months in Brazil. We separated data by age group (3-11 months, 3-23 months, and 3-59 months) and stratified data by three different socioeconomic factors of Brazilian municipalities (in 2010): Human Development Index, proportion of children living in extreme poverty, and proportion of mothers with no primary education. We first examined long-term trends in childhood pneumonia mortality in Brazil (from 1980 to 2014). We then assessed the effect of PCV10-introduced in Brazil in 2010-both nationally and in municipalities stratified by socioeconomic status, with a synthetic control approach as our primary analytical method.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FINDINGS">Between 1980 and 2010, a period during which Brazil's Human Development Index rose substantially, national pneumonia mortality in children younger than 5 years decreased from about 150 to 15 deaths per 100&#x2008;000 children younger than 5 years. Despite rapid uptake of PCV10 after its introduction in 2010, we observed a further vaccine-associated decline of about 10% in national childhood pneumonia mortality with our primary analytical method, with a high degree of uncertainty in the estimates. We observed larger reductions in municipal childhood pneumonia mortality in all three age groups (3-11 months, 3-23 months, and 3-59 months) in municipalities with a high percentage of extreme childhood poverty and mothers with no primary education, with the largest decrease observed in children aged 3-23 months in municipalities with low maternal education (24%, 95% credible interval 7-35).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="INTERPRETATION">The large reduction observed from 1980 to 2010 in national pneumonia mortality in children younger than 5 years underscores that improvements in nutrition, hygiene, education, and health care have an important role in reducing pneumonia mortality. Although the PCV-associated reduction in childhood pneumonia mortality at the national level was modest, we found that PCV led to larger reductions in low-income municipalities. Similarly, large benefits might occur when PCVs are introduced in other low-income settings.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="FUNDING">Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation and National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2019 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an Open Access article under the CC BY 4.0 license. Published by Elsevier Ltd.. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schuck-Paim</LastName><ForeName>Cynthia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sage Analytica, Portland, ME, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Taylor</LastName><ForeName>Robert J</ForeName><Initials>RJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Sage Analytica, Portland, ME, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alonso</LastName><ForeName>Wladimir J</ForeName><Initials>WJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Genetics and Evolutionary Biology, University of S&#xe3;o Paulo, S&#xe3;o Paulo, Brazil.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weinberger</LastName><ForeName>Daniel M</ForeName><Initials>DM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology of Microbial Diseases, Yale University School of Public Health, New Haven, CT, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simonsen</LastName><ForeName>Lone</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Health, George Washington University, Washington, DC, USA; Department of Science and Environment, Roskilde University, Roskilde, Denmark. Electronic address: lonesimo@ruc.dk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>R01 AI123208</GrantID><Acronym>AI</Acronym><Agency>NIAID NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D064888">Observational Study</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Lancet Glob Health</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101613665</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2214-109X</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C586648">10-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D022242">Pneumococcal Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Lancet Glob Health. 2019 Feb;7(2):e173-e174. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30540-0.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">30683228</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001938" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Brazil</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D022242" MajorTopicYN="N">Pneumococcal Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="Y">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011014" MajorTopicYN="N">Pneumonia</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="Y">mortality</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011018" MajorTopicYN="N">Pneumonia, Pneumococcal</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="Y">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2018</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2018</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>7</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2018</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2019</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2019</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2019</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30683242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6344339</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30455-8</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S2214-109X(18)30455-8</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Liu L, Oza S, Hogan D. Global, regional, and national causes of under-5 mortality in 2000&#x2013;15: an updated systematic analysis with implications for the Sustainable Development Goals. Lancet. 2016;388:3027&#x2013;3035.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5161777</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27839855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Troeger C, Forouzanfar M, Rao PC. Estimates of global, regional, and national morbidity, mortality, and aetiologies of diarrhoeal diseases: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2015. Lancet Infect Dis. 2017;17:909&#x2013;948.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5589208</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28579426</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health. International Vaccine Access Center  State of PCV use and impact evaluations: a strategic gap analysis of the global evidence from published and ongoing impact studies evaluating routine PCV use. 2016. http://www.jhsph.edu/ivac/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/PCVImpactAnalysis_PublicVersion_2017feb28.pdf</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haasis MA, Ceria JA, Kulpeng W, Teerawattananon Y, Alejandria M. Do pneumococcal conjugate vaccines represent good value for money in a lower-middle income country? A cost-utility analysis in the Philippines. PLoS One. 2015;10:e0131156.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4488861</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26131961</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Loo JD, Conklin L, Fleming-Dutra KE. Systematic review of the effect of pneumococcal conjugate vaccine dosing schedules on prevention of pneumonia. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2014;33(suppl 2):S140&#x2013;S151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3944478</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24336056</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>De Oliveira LH, Camacho LAB, Coutinho ESF. Impact and effectiveness of 10 and 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccines on hospitalization and mortality in children aged less than 5 years in Latin American countries: a systematic review. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0166736.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5152835</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27941979</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feikin DR, Kagucia EW, Loo JD. Serotype-specific changes in invasive pneumococcal disease after pneumococcal conjugate vaccine introduction: a pooled analysis of multiple surveillance sites. PLoS Med. 2013;10:e1001517.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3782411</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24086113</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO  Ending preventable child deaths from pneumonia and diarrhoea by 2025: the integrated Global Action Plan for Pneumonia and Diarrhoea (GAPPD) 2013. http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/79200/1/9789241505239_eng.pdf</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25613963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Pneumococcal vaccines WHO position paper&#x2014;2012&#x2014;recommendations. Vaccine. 2012;30:4717&#x2013;4718.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22621828</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brazilian Ministry of Health  Mortality Information System (SIM) 2015. http://www2.datasus.gov.br/DATASUS/index.php?area=060701 (in Portuguese).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation  GBD compare data visualization. 2017. http://vizhub.healthdata.org/gbd-compare/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brazilian Ministry of Health  Indicadores e Dados B&#xe1;sicos&#x2014;Brazil. 2010. http://tabnet.datasus.gov.br/cgi/idb2010/matriz.htm</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Program for Development  Brazilian atlas of development (census data 2010) 2010. http://www.br.undp.org/content/brazil/pt/home/idh0/rankings/idhm-municipios-2010.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brazilian Institute of Geography and Statistics  Available at: http://www.ibge.gov.br/home/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>United Nations Development Programme  Atlas of human development in Brazil. http://www.atlasbrasil.org.br/2013/en/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wonodi CB, Deloria-Knoll M, Feikin DR. Evaluation of risk factors for severe pneumonia in children: the pneumonia etiology research for child health study. Clin Infect Dis. 2012;54(suppl 2):S124&#x2013;S131.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3297552</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22403226</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alonso WJ, Lopez D, Schuck-Paim C. Popweaver: a program for interpolation and visualization of census and other sparsely collected data. J Popul Res. 2017;34:303&#x2013;311.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brazilian Ministry of Health  National Immunization Program information system (PNI) http://pni.datasus.gov.br/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>SINASC  No Title. 2016. http://www2.datasus.gov.br/DATASUS/index.php?area=0901</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schuck-Paim C, Taylor R, Lindley D, Klugman KP, Simonsen L. Use of near-real-time medical claims data to generate timely vaccine coverage estimates in the US: the dynamics of PCV13 vaccine uptake. Vaccine. 2013;31:5983&#x2013;5988.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24144470</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bruhn CAW, Hetterich S, Schuck-Paim C. Estimating the population-level impact of vaccines using synthetic controls. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2017;114:1524&#x2013;1529.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5321019</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28154145</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Frias PG, Szwarcwald CL, de Souza PRB, da Silva de Almeida W, Lira PIC. Correcting vital information: estimating infant mortality, Brazil, 2000&#x2013;2009. Rev Saude Publica. 2013;47:1048&#x2013;1058.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4206109</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24626543</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cutts FT, Zaman SMA, Enwere G. Efficacy of nine-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine against pneumonia and invasive pneumococcal disease in The Gambia: randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2002;365:1139&#x2013;1146.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15794968</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kupek E, Vieira ILV. O impacto da vacina pneumoc&#xf3;cica PCV10 na redu&#xe7;&#xe3;o da mortalidade por pneumonia em crian&#xe7;as menores de um ano em Santa Catarina, Brasil. Cad Saude Publica. 2016;32:e00131414.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27049314</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Diaz J, Terrazas S, Bierrenbach AL. Effectiveness of the 10-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV-10) in children in Chile: a nested case-control study using nationwide pneumonia morbidity and mortality surveillance data. PLoS One. 2016;11:e0153141.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4825990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27058873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker-Dreps S, Amaya E, Liu L. Changes in childhood pneumonia and infant mortality rates following introduction of the 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in Nicaragua. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2014;33:637&#x2013;642.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24445827</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Becker-Dreps S, Blette B, Brice&#xf1;o R. Changes in the incidence of pneumonia, bacterial meningitis, and infant mortality 5 years following introduction of the 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in a &#x201c;3+0&#x201d; schedule. PLoS One. 2017;12:e0183348.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5558986</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28813518</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Suarez V, Michel F, Toscano CM. Impact of pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in children morbidity and mortality in Peru: time series analyses. Vaccine. 2016;34:4738&#x2013;4743.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27521230</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Klugman KP, Madhi SA, Huebner RE, Kohberger R, Mbelle N, Pierce N. A Trial of a 9-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in children with and those without HIV infection. N Engl J Med. 2003;349:1341&#x2013;1348.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14523142</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tregnaghi MW, S&#xe1;ez-Llorens X, L&#xf3;pez P. Efficacy of pneumococcal nontypable Haemophilus influenzae protein D conjugate vaccine (PHiD-CV) in young Latin American children: a double-blind randomized controlled trial. PLoS Med. 2014;11:e1001657.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4043495</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24892763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Santa-Ana-Tellez Y, Mantel-Teeuwisse AK, Dreser A, Leufkens HGM, Wirtz VJ. Impact of over-the-counter restrictions on antibiotic consumption in Brazil and Mexico. PLoS One. 2013;8:e75550.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3797702</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24146761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>