<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">41272576</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2025</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>30</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1471-2377</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>25</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2025</Year><Month>Nov</Month><Day>22</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BMC neurology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>BMC Neurol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Construction and effectiveness test of multimodal data fusion prediction model for intracranial infection after severe craniocerebral injury in children based on deep learning.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>517</StartPage><MedlinePgn>517</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">517</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1186/s12883-025-04502-z</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">To develop and validate a multimodal data fusion prediction model based on deep learning for the early postoperative identification of intracranial infection in pediatric patients with severe traumatic brain injury (TBI).</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">A total of 203 pediatric TBI patients who underwent surgery at Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine between March 2022 and May 2025 were included as the internal validation cohort. These patients were stratified into infection group (46 cases) and non-infection group (157 cases) based on the occurrence of postoperative infection. General clinical data were compared between the two groups, and multivariate logistic regression analysis was performed to identify risk factors for postoperative infection. Radiomic features and deep learning features were extracted and screened. Additionally, 101 pediatric patients who underwent surgery during the same period were selected as the temporal validation cohort (25 infected cases and 76 non-infected cases). Four predictive models were constructed for the internal temporal validation cohort: a radiomics model, a clinical model, a deep learning model, and a combined model. The predictive performance of these models was evaluated using receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves, clinical decision curve analysis, and calibration curves.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Statistically significant differences (P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) were observed between the infection and non-infection groups in terms of operative duration, preoperative Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) score, external ventricular drainage (EVD), incisional cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) leakage, incisional effusion, number of surgeries, hypersensitive C-reactive protein (hs-CRP), procalcitonin (PCT), and blood lactate levels. Logistic regression analysis identified EVD, incisional effusion, hs-CRP, incisional CSF leakage, and PCT as independent risk factors for postoperative intracranial infection in pediatric TBI patients (P&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). A total of 9 radiomic features and 20 deep learning features were retained. ROC and DCA analyses demonstrated that the combined prediction model exhibited superior predictive performance and greater clinical net benefit compared to the clinical, radiomics, and deep learning models alone.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">The multimodal data fusion prediction model integrating deep learning, radiomics, and clinical data demonstrates excellent performance in the early postoperative monitoring and identification of intracranial infection in pediatric severe TBI.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2025. The Author(s).</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Peiliang</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, 3333 Bingsheng Road, Binjiang District, Hangzhou City, 310052, Zhejiang Province, China. chenkeran789170@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y" EqualContrib="Y"><LastName>Zhang</LastName><ForeName>Wenbo</ForeName><Initials>W</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, 3333 Bingsheng Road, Binjiang District, Hangzhou City, 310052, Zhejiang Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Weng</LastName><ForeName>Jianbin</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, 3333 Bingsheng Road, Binjiang District, Hangzhou City, 310052, Zhejiang Province, China.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shen</LastName><ForeName>Zhipeng</ForeName><Initials>Z</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Neurosurgery, Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, 3333 Bingsheng Road, Binjiang District, Hangzhou City, 310052, Zhejiang Province, China. zhangshiwen625551@163.com.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>BMC Neurol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>100968555</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1471-2377</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000077321" MajorTopicYN="Y">Deep Learning</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000070642" MajorTopicYN="Y">Brain Injuries, Traumatic</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000601" MajorTopicYN="N">surgery</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011183" MajorTopicYN="Y">Postoperative Complications</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012189" MajorTopicYN="N">Retrospective Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006259" MajorTopicYN="Y">Craniocerebral Trauma</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000150" MajorTopicYN="N">complications</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000601" MajorTopicYN="N">surgery</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012307" MajorTopicYN="N">Risk Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Deep learning</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Intracranial infection</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Multimodal data</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Pediatric</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Prediction model</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Severe traumatic brain injury</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>Declarations. Ethics approval and consent to participate: The study was conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki.This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Children's Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine. Informed consent was obtained from the guardians of the patients. Consent for publication: Not applicable. Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2025</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>31</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2025</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>28</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2025</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>31</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>33</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>29</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day><Hour>0</Hour><Minute>11</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2025</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">41272576</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC12755010</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12883-025-04502-z</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">10.1186/s12883-025-04502-z</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Ben Abdeljelil A. Freire GC,Yanchar N,et al.Pediatric moderate and severe traumatic brain injury: a systematic review of clinical practice guideline recommendations. J Neurotrauma. 2023;40(21&#x2013;22):2270&#x2013;81.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1089/neu.2023.0149</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37341019</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agrawal S, Placek MM, White D, et al. Studying Trends of Auto-Regulation in Severe Head Injury in Paediatrics (STARSHIP): protocol to study cerebral autoregulation in a prospective multicentre observational research database study. BMJ Open. 2023,13(3):e071800.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2023-071800</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10008199</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36898758</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S,Yang XH, Guo EK, et al. Analysis of risk factors for postoperative intracranial infection in pediatric neurosurgery. Hebei Medicine. 2022;44(20):3096-9. 10.3969/j.issn.1002-7386.2022.20.012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Serag I, Azzam AY,Hassan AK, et al. Multimodal diagnostic tools and advanced data models for detection of prodromal parkinson&#x2019;s disease: a scoping review. BMC Med Imaging. 2025;25(1):103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12880-025-01620-5</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11951780</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">40155878</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo W, Liu J, Dong F, et al. Review of machine learning and deep learning models for toxicity prediction. Exp Biol Med (Maywood). 2023;248(21):1952-1973. 10.1177/15353702231209421.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1177/15353702231209421</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10798180</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38057999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadzadeh I, Niroomand B, Hajikarimloo B, et al. Can we rely on machine learning algorithms as a trustworthy predictor for recurrence in high-grade glioma? A systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Neurol Neurosurg. 2025;249:108762.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2025.108762</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39884144</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mohammadzadeh I, Niroomand B, Shahnazian Z, et al. Machine learning for predicting poor outcomes in aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage: A systematic review and meta-analysis involving 8445 participants. Clin Neurol Neurosurg. 2025;249:108668.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2024.108668</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39667223</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carney N, Totten AM, O'Reilly C, et al. Guidelines for the management of severe traumatic brain injury, fourth edition. Neurosurgery. 2017,80(1):6-15.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1227/NEU.0000000000001432</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27654000</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chinese Medical Association Department of Neurosurgery, Chinese Neurosurgical Intensive Care Management Collaboration Group. Consensus on diagnosis and treatment of infection in neurosurgical intensive care patients in China (2017). Natl Med J China. 2017;97(21):1607&#x2013;14.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teasdale G, Jennett B. Assessment of coma and impaired consciousness. A practical scale. Lancet. 1974;2(7872):81&#x2013;4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(74)91639-0</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4136544</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann I, Lewis ER, Marini C, et al. Venous thromboembolism risk among pediatric patients with traumatic brain injury: a nationwide study of 44,128 patients. J Neurosurg Pediatr. 2023;32(3):285&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3171/2023.4.PEDS23102</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37243563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Naseri Alavi SA, Habibi MA, Majdi A, et al. Investigating the safety and efficacy of therapeutic hypothermia in pediatric severe traumatic brain injury: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Children (Basel). 2024;11(6):701.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11201645</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38929280</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li S, Yang XH,Guo EK, et al. Analysis of risk factors for postoperative intracranial infection in pediatric neurosurgery. Hebei Med J. 2022;44(20):3096&#x2013;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oksuz E, Demir O. Evaluating the effectiveness of minimally invasive surgery using external ventricular drainage systems in draining chronic subdural hematomas. Turk Neurosurg. 2023,33(2):224-228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">36482847</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang ZY, Wu YX, Zhao XL, et al. The insertion and management of an external ventricular drain in pediatric patients with hydrocephalus associated with medulloblastoma. Neurosurg Rev. 2023;46(1):170.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10143-023-02080-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37433938</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu YX, Xue YF, He JQ, et al. The incidence and risk factors of unplanned reoperation in endoscopic endonasal surgeries: a single center study. Neurosurg Rev. 2023;46(1):224.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10143-023-02134-w</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37665381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stevens AR, Gilbody H, Greig J, et al. Cerebrospinal fluid diversion for refractory intracranial hypertension in traumatic brain injury: a single center experience. World Neurosurg. 2023;176(8):e265-e272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.wneu.2023.05.047</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37207724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang S, Zhu ZY, Chen G, et al. Efficacy of a novel drainage catheter in the treatment of CSF leak after posterior spine surgery: A retrospective cohort study. Open Med (Wars). 2025;20(1):20251211.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1515/med-2025-1211</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC12130775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">40463485</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hanif S, Yousaf I,Iqbal M, et al. Brain herniation and subsequent complications following partial resection of high-grade glioma: A case report. Clin Case Rep. 2024;12(1):e8407.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/ccr3.8407</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10762324</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38173889</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hargarten JC, Anjum SH, Ssebambulidde K, et al. Tocilizumab as a potential adjunctive therapy to corticosteroids in Cryptococcal post-infectious inflammatory response syndrome (PIIRS): a report of two cases. J Clin Immunol. 2023;43(8):2146&#x2013;55.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s10875-023-01592-7</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37814084</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shi JJ, Chen JH, Hu LQ, et al. Retrospective analysis of pulmonary cryptococcosis and extrapulmonary cryptococcosis in a Chinese tertiary hospital. BMC Pulm Med. 2023;23(1):277.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12890-023-02578-2</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10375642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37501136</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lin M, Fang Q. Comparison of changes in PCT and NSE levels in serum and cerebrospinal fluid in children with intracranial infection of different etiologies. Chin J New Clin Med. 2019;12(3):305&#x2013;8.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Samuel O, Saliba W, Stein N, et al. Emerging clinical features of acute mastoiditis in israel: a registry based cohort. Pediatr Infect Dis J. 2024;43(7):620-625.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/INF.0000000000004325</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38564738</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fiordelisi A, Soldovieri S, Trinci M, et al. Clinical characteristics and predictive factors of thrombotic complications in children with acute mastoiditis: a single center retrospective study. Eur J Pediatr. 2025;184(2):142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1007/s00431-024-05965-x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39820761</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xing XW, Li LP, Sun MX, et al. Deep-learning-based 3D super-resolution CT radiomics model: Predict the possibility of the micropapillary/solid component of lung adenocarcinoma. Heliyon. 2024;10(13):e34163.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e34163</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11279278</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39071606</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xia TY, Zhao B, Li BR, et al. MRi-based radiomics and deep learning in biological characteristics and prognosis of hepatocellular carcinoma: opportunities and challenges. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2024;59(3):767-783.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/jmri.28982</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37647155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao ZY, Liu YQ, Ling HZ, et al. Prediction of ATRX mutation status in Lower-Grade gliomas based on MRI radiomics and deep learning features. J Clin Radiol. 2025;44(06):988&#x2013;93.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lan TJ, Kuang SJ, Liang PS, et al. MRI-based deep learning and radiomics for prediction of occult cervical lymph node metastasis and prognosis in early-stage oral and oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma: a diagnostic study. Int J Surg. 2024;110(8):4648&#x2013;59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/JS9.0000000000001578</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC11325978</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38729119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>