<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">29372115</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Print">2167-8359</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Print"><Volume>5</Volume><PubDate><Year>2017</Year></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PeerJ</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PeerJ</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Benchmark datasets for phylogenomic pipeline validation, applications for foodborne pathogen surveillance.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e3893</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e3893</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e3893</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.7717/peerj.3893</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">As next generation sequence technology has advanced, there have been parallel advances in genome-scale analysis programs for determining evolutionary relationships as proxies for epidemiological relationship in public health. Most new programs skip traditional steps of ortholog determination and multi-gene alignment, instead identifying variants across a set of genomes, then summarizing results in a matrix of single-nucleotide polymorphisms or alleles for standard phylogenetic analysis. However, public health authorities need to document the performance of these methods with appropriate and comprehensive datasets so they can be validated for specific purposes, e.g., outbreak surveillance. Here we propose a set of benchmark datasets to be used for comparison and validation of phylogenomic pipelines.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We identified four well-documented foodborne pathogen events in which the epidemiology was concordant with routine phylogenomic analyses (reference-based SNP and wgMLST approaches). These are ideal benchmark datasets, as the trees, WGS data, and epidemiological data for each are all in agreement. We have placed these sequence data, sample metadata, and "known" phylogenetic trees in publicly-accessible databases and developed a standard descriptive spreadsheet format describing each dataset. To facilitate easy downloading of these benchmarks, we developed an automated script that uses the standard descriptive spreadsheet format.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Our "outbreak" benchmark datasets represent the four major foodborne bacterial pathogens (<i>Listeria monocytogenes</i>, <i>Salmonella enterica</i>, <i>Escherichia coli</i>, and <i>Campylobacter jejuni</i>) and one simulated dataset where the "known tree" can be accurately called the "true tree". The downloading script and associated table files are available on GitHub: https://github.com/WGS-standards-and-analysis/datasets.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These five benchmark datasets will help standardize comparison of current and future phylogenomic pipelines, and facilitate important cross-institutional collaborations. Our work is part of a global effort to provide collaborative infrastructure for sequence data and analytic tools-we welcome additional benchmark datasets in our recommended format, and, if relevant, we will add these on our GitHub site. Together, these datasets, dataset format, and the underlying GitHub infrastructure present a recommended path for worldwide standardization of phylogenomic pipelines.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Timme</LastName><ForeName>Ruth E</ForeName><Initials>RE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition, US Food and Drug Administration, College Park, MD, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Rand</LastName><ForeName>Hugh</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition, US Food and Drug Administration, College Park, MD, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shumway</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology Information, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Trees</LastName><ForeName>Eija K</ForeName><Initials>EK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Diseases Laboratory Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simmons</LastName><ForeName>Mustafa</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety and Inspection Service, US Department of Agriculture, Athens, GA, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Agarwala</LastName><ForeName>Richa</ForeName><Initials>R</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology Information, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Davis</LastName><ForeName>Steven</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition, US Food and Drug Administration, College Park, MD, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tillman</LastName><ForeName>Glenn E</ForeName><Initials>GE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety and Inspection Service, US Department of Agriculture, Athens, GA, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Defibaugh-Chavez</LastName><ForeName>Stephanie</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Food Safety and Inspection Service, US Department of Agriculture, Wahington, D.C., United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Carleton</LastName><ForeName>Heather A</ForeName><Initials>HA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Diseases Laboratory Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Klimke</LastName><ForeName>William A</ForeName><Initials>WA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Center for Biotechnology Information, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Katz</LastName><ForeName>Lee S</ForeName><Initials>LS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Enteric Diseases Laboratory Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Center for Food Safety, College of Agricultural and Environmental Sciences, University of Georgia, Griffin, GA, United States of America.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2017</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>06</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PeerJ</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101603425</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2167-8359</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Benchmark datasets</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">E. coli</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Foodborne outbreak</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Listeria</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Phylogenomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Validation</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">WGS</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2017</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>21</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2017</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2018</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2018</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2018</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>27</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2017</Year><Month>10</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29372115</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5782805</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj.3893</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">3893</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Allard MW, Strain E, Melka D, Bunning K, Musser SM, Brown EW, Timme R. Practical value of food pathogen traceability through building a whole-genome sequencing network and database. Journal of Clinical Microbiology. 2016;54:1975&#x2013;1983. doi: 10.1128/JCM.00081-16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/JCM.00081-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4963501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27008877</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bertels F, Silander OK, Pachkov M, Rainey PB, Van Nimwegen E. Automated reconstruction of whole-genome phylogenies from short-sequence reads. Molecular Biology and Evolution. 2014;31:1077&#x2013;1088. doi: 10.1093/molbev/msu088.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu088</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3995342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24600054</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC  Multistate outbreak of Salmonella Bareilly and Salmonella Nchanga infections associated with a raw scraped ground tuna product (final update) 2012. https://www.cdc.gov/salmonella/bareilly-04-12/  [1 December 2016]. https://www.cdc.gov/salmonella/bareilly-04-12/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC  Multistate outbreak of Shiga toxin-producing Escherichia coli O121 infections linked to raw clover sprouts (final update) 2014. https://www.cdc.gov/ecoli/2014/o121-05-14/index.html.  [1 December 2016]. https://www.cdc.gov/ecoli/2014/o121-05-14/index.html</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>CDC Center for Disense Control nnd PreventionAnnual Report to the Secretary, Department of Health and Human Services. 2015</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Burall LS, Luo Y, Timme R, Melka D, Muruvanda T, Payne J, Wang C, Kastanis G, Maounounen-Laasri A, De Jesus AJ, Curry PE, Stones R, Kaluoch O, Liu E, Salter M, Hammack TS, Evans PS, Parish M, Allard MW, Datta A, Strain EA, Brown EW. Listeria monocytogenes in stone fruits linked to a multistate outbreak: enumeration of cells and whole-genome sequencing. Applied and Environmental Microbiology. 2016;82:7030&#x2013;7040. doi: 10.1128/AEM.01486-16.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.01486-16</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5118914</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27694232</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Luo Y, Carleton H, Timme R, Melka D, Muruvanda T, Wang C, Kastanis G, Katz LS, Turner L, Fritzinger A, Moore T, Stones R, Blankenship J, Salter M, Parish M, Hammack TS, Evans PS, Tarr CL, Allard MW, Strain EA, Brown EW. Whole genome and core genome multilocus sequence typing and single nucleotide polymorphism analyses of Listeria monocytogenes isolates associated with an outbreak linked to cheese, United States, 2013. Applied and Environmental Microbiology. 2017a;83:e00633-17. doi: 10.1128/AEM.00633-17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1128/AEM.00633-17</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5514676</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28550058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Luo Y, Curry P, Timme R, Melka D, Doyle M, Parish M, Hammack TS, Allard MW, Brown EW, Strain EA. Assessing the genome level diversity of Listeria monocytogenes from contaminated ice cream and environmental samples linked to a listeriosis outbreak in the United States. PLOS ONE. 2017b;12:e0171389. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0171389.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0171389</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5293252</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28166293</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis S, Pettengill JB, Luo Y, Payne J, Shpuntoff Al, Rand H, Strain E. CFSAN SNP Pipeline: an automated method for constructing SNP matrices from next-generation sequence data. PeerJ Computer Science. 2015;1:e20. doi: 10.7717/peerj-cs.20.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.7717/peerj-cs.20</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Eyre DW, Cule ML, Wilson DJ, Griffiths D, Vaughan A, O&#x2019;Connor L, Ip CLC, Golubchik T, Batty EM, Finney JM, Wyllie DH, Didelot X, Piazza P, Bowden R, Dingle KE, Harding RM, Crook DW, Wilcox MH, Peto TEA, Walker AS. Diverse sources of C. difficile infection identified on whole-genome sequencing. The New England Journal of Medicine. 2013;369:1195&#x2013;1205. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1216064.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1216064</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3868928</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24066741</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gardner SN, Hall BG. When whole-genome alignments just won&#x2019;t work: kSNP v2 software for alignment-free SNP discovery and phylogenetics of hundreds of microbial genomes. PLOS ONE. 2013;8:e81760. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0081760.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0081760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3857212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24349125</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Global Microbial Identifier  2011. http://www.globalmicrobialidentifier.org.  [28 August 2017]. http://www.globalmicrobialidentifier.org</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hinchliff CE, Smith SA, Allman JF, Burleigh JG, Chaudhary R, Coghill LM, Crandall KA, Deng J, Drew BT, Gazis R, Gude K, Hibbett DS, Katz LA, Laughinghouse HD, McTavish EJ, Midford PE, Owen CL, Ree RH, Rees JA, Soltis DE, Williams T, Cranston KA. Synthesis of phylogeny and taxonomy into a comprehensive tree of life. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 2015;112:12764&#x2013;12769. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1423041112.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1073/pnas.1423041112</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4611642</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26385966</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann M, Luo Y, Monday SR, Gonzales-Escalona N, Ottesen AR, Muruvanda T, Wang C, Kastanis G, Keys C, Janies D, Senturk IF, Catalyurek UV, Wang H, Hammack TS, Wolfgang WJ, Schoonmaker-Bopp D, Chu A, Myers R, Haendiges J, Evans PS, Meng J, Strain EA, Allard MW, Brown EW. Tracing origins of the Salmonella Bareilly strain causing a foodborne outbreak in the United States. The Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2015;213:502&#x2013;508. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jiv297.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiv297</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25995194</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jackson BR, Tarr C, Strain E, Jackson KA, Conrad A, Carleton H, Katz LS, Stroika S, Gould LH, Mody RK, Silk BJ, Beal J, Chen Y, Timme R, Doyle M, Fields A, Wise M, Tillman G, Defibaugh-Chavez S, Kucerova Z, Sabol A, Roache K, Trees E, Simmons M, Wasilenko J, Kubota K, Pouseele H, Klimke W, Besser J, Brown E, Allard M, Gerner-Smidt P. Implementation of nationwide real-time whole-genome sequencing to enhance listeriosis outbreak detection and investigation. Clinical Infectious Diseases. 2016;63:380&#x2013;386. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciw242.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/cid/ciw242</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4946012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27090985</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Karsch-Mizrachi I, Nakamura Y, Cochrane G, International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration The International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration. Nucleic Acids Research. 2012;40:D33&#x2013;D37. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkr1006.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr1006</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3244996</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22080546</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Katz LS, Griswold T, Williams-Newkirk AJ, Wagner D, Petkau A, Sieffert C, Van Domselaar G, Deng X, Carleton HA. A comparative analysis of the Lyve-SET phylogenomics pipeline for genomic epidemiology of foodborne pathogens. Frontiers in Microbiology. 2017;8:1&#x2013;13. doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2017.00375.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.00375</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5346554</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28348549</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>MarlerClark  Hendricks&#x2019; farm and dairy raw milk. http://www.outbreakdatabase.com/details/hendricks-farm-and-dairy-raw-milk-2008.  [27 January 2017];2008 </Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McTavish EJ, Pettengill J, Davis S, Rand H, Strain E, Allard M, Timme RE. TreeToReads&#x2014;a pipeline for simulating raw reads from phylogenies. BMC Bioinformatics. 2017;18:178. doi: 10.1186/s12859-017-1592-1.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/s12859-017-1592-1</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5359950</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28320310</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moura A, Criscuolo A, Pouseele H, Maury MM, Leclercq A, Tarr C, Bj&#xf6;rkman JT, Dallman T, Reimer A, Enouf V, Larsonneur E, Carleton H, Bracq-Dieye H, Katz LS, Jones L, Touchon M, Tourdjman M, Walker M, Stroika S, Cantinelli T, Chenal-Francisque V, Kucerova Z, Rocha Eduardo PC, Nadon C, Grant K, Nielsen EM, Pot B, Gerner-Smidt P, Lecuit M, Brisse S. Whole genome-based population biology and epidemiological surveillance of Listeria monocytogenes. Nature Microbiology. 2016;2:16185. doi: 10.1038/nmicrobiol.2016.185.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1038/nmicrobiol.2016.185</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8903085</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27723724</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>NCBI  Pathogen detection homepage. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pathogens/ 2017.  [16 August 2017]. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pathogens/</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Petkau A, Mabon P, Sieffert C, Knox NC, Cabral J, Iskander M, Iskander M, Weedmark K, Zaheer R, Katz LS, Nadon C, Reimer A, Taboada E, Beiko RG, Hsiao W, Brinkman F, Graham M, Van Domselaar G. SNVPhyl: a single nucleotide variant phylogenomics pipeline for microbial genomic epidemiology. Microbial Genomics. 2017;3:1&#x2013;11. doi: 10.1099/mgen.0.000116.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000116</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5628696</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29026651</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quick J, Ashton P, Calus S, Chatt C, Gossain S, Hawker J, Nair GB, Neal K, Nye K, Peters T, De Pinna E, Robinson KS, Struthers K, Webber M, Catto A, Dallman T, Hawkey PM, Loman NJ. Rapid draft sequencing and real-time nanopore sequencing in a hospital outbreak of Salmonella. Genome Biology. 2015;16:1&#x2013;14.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4702336</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26025440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sahl JW, Lemmer D, Travis J, Schupp JM, Gillece JD, Aziz M, Driebe EM, Drees KP, Hicks ND, Williamson CHD, Hepp CM, Smith DE, Roe C, Engelthaler DM, Wagner DM, Keim P. NASP: an accurate, rapid method for the identification of SNPs in WGS datasets that supports flexible input and output formats. Microbial Genomics. 2016;2:e000074. doi: 10.1099/mgen.0.000074.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000074</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5320593</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28348869</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Swaminathan B, Barrett TJ, Hunter SB, Tauxe RV, CDC PulseNet Task Force PulseNet: the molecular subtyping network for foodborne bacterial disease surveillance, United States. Emerging Infectious Diseases. 2001;7:382&#x2013;389. doi: 10.3201/eid0703.010303.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3201/eid0703.010303</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2631779</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11384513</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Treangen TJ, Ondov BD, Koren S, Phillippy AM. The Harvest suite for rapid core-genome alignment and visualization of thousands of intraspecific microbial genomes. Genome Biology. 2014;15:524&#x2013;539. doi: 10.1186/PREACCEPT-2573980311437212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1186/PREACCEPT-2573980311437212</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4262987</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25410596</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Belkum A, Tassios PT, Dijkshoorn L, Haeggman S, Cookson B, Fry NK, Fussing V, Green J, Feil E, Gerner-Smidt P, Brisse S, Struelens M, European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases (ESCMID) Study Group on Epidemiological Markers (ESGEM) Guidelines for the validation and application of typing methods for use in bacterial epidemiology. Clinical Microbiology and Infection. 2007;13(Suppl 3):1&#x2013;46. doi: 10.1111/j.1469-0691.2007.01786.x.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2007.01786.x</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17716294</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zwickl D. PhD dissertation. 2006. Genetic algorithm approaches for the phylogenetic analysis of large biological sequence datasets under the maximum likelihood criterion.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>