<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">25061922</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2015</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>23</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1531-5487</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>25</Volume><Issue>5</Issue><PubDate><Year>2014</Year><Month>Sep</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Epidemiology (Cambridge, Mass.)</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Epidemiology</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Regression discontinuity designs in epidemiology: causal inference without randomized trials.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>729</StartPage><EndPage>737</EndPage><MedlinePgn>729-37</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1097/EDE.0000000000000138</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>When patients receive an intervention based on whether they score below or above some threshold value on a continuously measured random variable, the intervention will be randomly assigned for patients close to the threshold. The regression discontinuity design exploits this fact to estimate causal treatment effects. In spite of its recent proliferation in economics, the regression discontinuity design has not been widely adopted in epidemiology. We describe regression discontinuity, its implementation, and the assumptions required for causal inference. We show that regression discontinuity is generalizable to the survival and nonlinear models that are mainstays of epidemiologic analysis. We then present an application of regression discontinuity to the much-debated epidemiologic question of when to start HIV patients on antiretroviral therapy. Using data from a large South African cohort (2007-2011), we estimate the causal effect of early versus deferred treatment eligibility on mortality. Patients whose first CD4 count was just below the 200 cells/&#x3bc;L CD4 count threshold had a 35% lower hazard of death (hazard ratio = 0.65 [95% confidence interval = 0.45-0.94]) than patients presenting with CD4 counts just above the threshold. We close by discussing the strengths and limitations of regression discontinuity designs for epidemiology.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bor</LastName><ForeName>Jacob</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>From the aDepartment of Global Health, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, MA; bAfrica Centre for Health and Population Studies, Somkhele, South Africa; cDepartment of Global Health and Population, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA; and dFaculty of Medicine, University of Southampton, Southampton, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moscoe</LastName><ForeName>Ellen</ForeName><Initials>E</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mutevedzi</LastName><ForeName>Portia</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Newell</LastName><ForeName>Marie-Louise</ForeName><Initials>ML</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>B&#xe4;rnighausen</LastName><ForeName>Till</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><GrantID>097410</GrantID><Acronym>WT_</Acronym><Agency>Wellcome Trust</Agency><Country>United Kingdom</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 HD058482-01</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 HD058482</GrantID><Acronym>HD</Acronym><Agency>NICHD NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>1R01MH083539-01</GrantID><Acronym>MH</Acronym><Agency>NIMH NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant><Grant><GrantID>R01 MH083539</GrantID><Acronym>MH</Acronym><Agency>NIMH NIH HHS</Agency><Country>United States</Country></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D052061">Research Support, N.I.H., Extramural</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013486">Research Support, U.S. Gov't, Non-P.H.S.</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Epidemiology</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>9009644</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1044-3983</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D019380">Anti-HIV Agents</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><CommentsCorrectionsList><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Epidemiology. 2014 Sep;25(5):738-41. doi: 10.1097/EDE.0000000000000145.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">25076150</PMID></CommentsCorrections><CommentsCorrections RefType="CommentIn"><RefSource>Epidemiology. 2015 Mar;26(2):e28-30; discussion e30. doi: 10.1097/EDE.0000000000000256.</RefSource><PMID Version="1">25643120</PMID></CommentsCorrections></CommentsCorrectionsList><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019380" MajorTopicYN="N">Anti-HIV Agents</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000627" MajorTopicYN="N">therapeutic use</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D018791" MajorTopicYN="N">CD4 Lymphocyte Count</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015984" MajorTopicYN="Y">Causality</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015331" MajorTopicYN="N">Cohort Studies</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003627" MajorTopicYN="Y">Data Interpretation, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004334" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Administration Schedule</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015340" MajorTopicYN="Y">Epidemiologic Research Design</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015658" MajorTopicYN="N">HIV Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000401" MajorTopicYN="N">mortality</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015233" MajorTopicYN="Y">Models, Statistical</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012044" MajorTopicYN="Y">Regression Analysis</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016896" MajorTopicYN="N">Treatment Outcome</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2014</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2014</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2015</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>24</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25061922</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4162343</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1097/EDE.0000000000000138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Editorial. Associations are not effects. Am J Epidemiol. 1991;133:101&#x2013;102.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1985440</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee DS, Lemieux T. Regression discontinuity designs in economics. J Econ Lit. 2010;48:281&#x2013;355.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thistlewaite D, Campbell D. Regression discontinuity analysis: an alternative to the ex-post facto experiment. J Educ Psych. 1960;51:309&#x2013;317.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell DT, Stanley JC. Experimental and quasi-experimental designs for research on teaching. In: Gage NL, editor. In: Handbook of Research on Teaching. Chicago, IL: Rand McNally &amp; Company; 1963. pp. 61&#x2013;64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Campbell DT. Reforms as experiments. Am Psychol. 1969;24:409&#x2013;429.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trochim W. Research Design for Program Evaluation: The Regression Discontinuity Design. Beverly Hills, CA: Sage Publications; 1984.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trochim W. The Regression Discontinuity Design. In: Sechrest L, Perrin E, Bunker J, editors. In: Agency for Health Care Policy and Research Conference Proceedings: Research Methodology: Strengthening Causal Interpretations of Nonexperimental Data. Washington, D.C.: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services; 1990. pp. 119&#x2013;140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Imbens GW, Lemieux T. Regression discontinuity designs: a guide to practice. J Econom. 2008;142:615&#x2013;635.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook TD. &#x201c;Waiting for life to arrive&#x201d;: a history of the regression discontinuity design in psychology, statistics and economics. J Econom. 2008;1422:636&#x2013;654.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Almond D, Doyle JJ, Kowalski AE, Williams H. Estimating marginal returns to medical care: evidence from at-risk newborns. Q J Econ. 2010;125:591&#x2013;634.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2903901</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20634927</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Card D, Dobkin C, Maestas N. Does medicare save lives? Q J Econ. 2009;124:597&#x2013;636.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2777733</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19920880</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carpenter C, Dobkin C. The effect of alcohol consumption on mortality: regression discontinuity evidence from the minimum drinking age. Am Econ J Appl Econ. 2009;1:164&#x2013;182.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2846371</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20351794</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhao M, Konishi Y, Glewwe P. Does information on health status lead to a healthier lifestyle? Evidence from China on the effect of hypertension diagnosis on food consumption. J Health Econ. 2013;32:367&#x2013;385.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23334058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ludwig J, Miller DL. Does Head Start improve children&#x2019;s life chances? Evidence from a regression discontinuity design. Q J Econ. 2007;122:159&#x2013;208.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Snyder SE, Evans WN. The effect of income on mortality: evidence from the Social Security Notch. Rev Econ Stat. 2006;88:482&#x2013;495.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Neidell M. Information, avoidance behavior, and health: the effect of ozone on asthma hospitalizations. J. Hum Resour. 2009;44:450&#x2013;478.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moscoe E, Bor J, B&#xe4;rnighausen T. Regression discontinuity designs in medicine, epidemiology, and public health: a review of current and best practice. J Clinical Epidemiology. In press.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25579639</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization (WHO) Antiretroviral Therapy for HIV Infection in Adults and Adolescents: Recommendations for a Public Health Approach: 2013 Revision. Geneva: WHO; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bor J. In: Essays on the Economics of HIV/AIDS in Rural South Africa [dissertation] Boston: Harvard University, School of Public Health; 2013. Cash transfers and teen pregnancy in an HIV endemic setting: a regression discontinuity study. pp. 91&#x2013;150.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen Y, Ebenstein A, Greenstone M, Li H. Evidence on the impact of sustained exposure to air pollution on life expectancy from China&#x2019;s Huai River policy. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013;110:12936&#x2013;12941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3740827</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23836630</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finkelstein MO, Levin B, Robbins H. Clinical and prophylactic trials with assured new treatment for those at greater risk: II. Examples. Am J Public Health. 1996;86:696&#x2013;705.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1380479</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8629722</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeGruttola V, Lange N, Dafni U. Modeling the progression of HIV infection. J Am Stat Assoc. 1991;86:569&#x2013;577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hughes MD, Stein DS, Gundacker HM, Valentine FT, Phair JP, Volberding PA. Within-subject variation in CD4 lymphocyte count in asymptomatic human immunodeficiency virus infection: implications for patient monitoring. J Infect Dis. 1994;169:28&#x2013;36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7903975</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin D. Estimating causal effects of treatments in randomized and nonrandomized studies. J Educ Psych. 1974;66:688&#x2013;701.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hahn J, Todd P, van der Klaauw W. Identification and estimation of treatment effects with a regression discontinuity design. Econometrica. 2001;69:201&#x2013;209.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee DS. Randomized experiments from non-random selection in U.S. House elections. J Econom. 2008;142:675&#x2013;697.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angrist JD, Imbens GW, Rubin DB. Identification of causal effects using instrumental variables. J Am Stat Assoc. 1996;91:444&#x2013;455.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robins JM, Tsiatis AA. Correcting for non-compliance in randomized trials using rank preserving structural failure time models. Commun. Statist. Theory Meth. 1991;20:2609&#x2013;2631.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rubin DB. Assignment to treatment group on the basis of a covariate. J Educ Stat. 1977;2:1&#x2013;26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fan J, Gijbels I. Local Polynomial Modelling and its Applications. London: Chapman and Hall; 1996.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCrary J. Manipulation of the running variable in the regression discontinuity design: a density test. J Econom. 2008;142:698&#x2013;714.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berk RA, Rauma D. Capitalizing on nonrandom assignment to treatments: a regression discontinuity evaluation of a crime-control program, J Am Stat Assoc. 1983;78:21&#x2013;27.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Berk AR, de Leeuw J. An evaluation of California&#x2019;s inmate classification system using a generalized regression discontinuity design. J Am Stat Assoc. 1999;94:1045&#x2013;1052.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nelder JA, Wedderburn RWM. Generalized linear models. J Royal Stat Soc Ser A. 1972;135:370&#x2013;384.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Frandsen BR, Fr&#xf6;lich M, Melly B. Quantile treatment effects in the regression discontinuity design. J Econom. 2012;168:382&#x2013;395.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Angrist JD. Estimation of limited dependent variable models with dummy endogenous regressors. J Bus Econ Stat. 2001;19:2&#x2013;28.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hern&#xe1;n MA, Robins JM. Instruments for causal inference: an epidemiologist&#x2019;s dream? Epidemiology. 2006;17:360&#x2013;372.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16755261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullahy J. Instrumental-variable estimation of count data models: applications to models of cigarette smoking behavior. Rev Econ Stat. 1997;79:586&#x2013;593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clarke PS, Windmeijer F. Instrumental variable estimators for binary outcomes. J Am Stat Assoc. 2012;107:1638&#x2013;1652.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbring JH, van den Berg GJ. Social experiments and instrumental variables with duration outcomes.. Tinbergen Institute Discussion Paper 2005-047/3.2005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Severe P, Juste MA, Ambroise A, et al. Early versus standard antiretroviral therapy for HIV-infected adults in Haiti. N Engl J Med. 2010;363:257&#x2013;265.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3676927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20647201</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen MS, Chen YQ, McCauley M, et al. HPTN 052 Study Team. Prevention of HIV-1 infection with early antiretroviral therapy. N Engl J Med. 2011;365:493&#x2013;505.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3200068</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21767103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Palella FJ, Jr, Deloria-Knoll M, Chmiel JS, et al. HIV Outpatient Study Investigators. Survival benefit of initiating antiretroviral therapy in HIV-infected persons in different CD4+ cell strata. Ann Intern Med. 2003;138:620&#x2013;626.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12693883</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ford N, Kranzer K, Hilderbrand K, et al. Early initiation of antiretroviral therapy and associated reduction in mortality, morbidity and defaulting in a nurse-managed, community cohort in Lesotho. AIDS. 2010;24:2645&#x2013;2650.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20980868</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitahata MM, Gange SJ, Abraham AG, et al. NA-ACCORD Investigators. Effect of early versus deferred antiretroviral therapy for HIV on survival. N Engl J Med. 2009;360:1815&#x2013;1826.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2854555</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19339714</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sterne JA, May M, Costagliola D, et al. Timing of initiation of antiretroviral therapy in AIDS-free HIV-1-infected patients: a collaborative analysis of 18 HIV cohort studies. Lancet. 2009;373:1352&#x2013;1363.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2670965</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19361855</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fox MP, Sanne IM, Conradie F, et al. Initiating patients on antiretroviral therapy at CD4 cell counts above 200 cells/microl is associated with improved treatment outcomes in South Africa. AIDS. 2010;24:2041&#x2013;2050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2914833</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20613459</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Houlihan CF, Bland RM, Mutevedzi PC, et al. Cohort profile: Hlabisa HIV treatment and care programme. Int J Epidemiol. 2011;40:318&#x2013;326.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3195268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20154009</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bor J, Herbst AJ, Newell ML, B&#xe4;rnighausen T. Increases in adult life expectancy in rural South Africa: valuing the scale-up of HIV treatment. Science. 2013;339:961&#x2013;965.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3860268</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23430655</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanser F, Hosegood V, B&#xe4;rnighausen T, et al. Cohort profile: Africa Centre Demographic Information System (ACDIS) and population-based HIV survey. Int J Epidemiol. 2008;37:956&#x2013;962.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2557060</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17998242</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bor J, B&#xe4;rnighausen T, Newell C, Tanser F, Newell ML. Social exposure to an antiretroviral treatment programme in rural KwaZulu-Natal. Trop Med Int Health. 2011;16:988&#x2013;994.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4295018</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21615631</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Goldberger AS. Selection bias in evaluating treatment effects: some formal illustrations. Madison, WI: Institute for Research on Poverty, University of Wisconsin - Madison: 1972. Discussion Paper.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luft HS. In: Agency for Health Care Policy and Research Conference Proceedings: Research Methodology: Strengthening Causal Interpretations of Nonexperimental Data. Washington, DC: U.S. Department of Health and Human Services; 1990. The applicability of the regression discontinuity design in health services research. pp. 140&#x2013;143.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reichardt CS, Trochim W, Cappelleri J. Reports of the death of the regression discontinuity design are greatly exaggerated. Eval Rev. 1995;19:39&#x2013;63.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanley TD, Robinson A. Sifting statistical significance from the artifact of RD design. Eval Rev. 1990;14:166&#x2013;181.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>