<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Curated"><PMID Version="1">34119859</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>04</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1873-1716</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>193</Volume><PubDate><Year>2021</Year><Month>Aug</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Preventive veterinary medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Prev Vet Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Multiple model triangulation to identify factors associated with lameness in British sheep flocks.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>105395</StartPage><MedlinePgn>105395</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">105395</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2021.105395</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0167-5877(21)00139-2</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Identification of factors associated with an outcome can be challenging when the number of explanatory variables is large in relation to the number of observations. Multiple model triangulation, where results from several model types are combined, improves the likelihood of identifying true predictor variables. The aim of this study was to use triangulation to identify covariates likely to be truly associated with the prevalence of lameness in sheep flocks in Great Britain. Data were collected using a questionnaire sent to 3200 sheep farmers in Great Britain in 2018. The useable response rate was 14.1 %. The geometric mean prevalence of lameness was 1.4 % (95 % CI 1.2-1.7) for ewes, and 0.6 % (95 % CI 0.5-0.9) for lambs, however, approximately 60 % flocks had &gt;2% prevalence of lameness in ewes. Four model types were investigated, two generalised linear models (negative binomial and quasi-Poisson) built using stepwise selection, and two elastic net models (Poisson and Gaussian distributions) refined with selection stability estimation. Triangulated covariates were those selected in three or all four models - 10 for ewes and 12 for lambs. Higher prevalence of lameness in ewes was associated with 5-100% feet bleeding during routine foot trimming compared with not foot trimming, footbathing the flock to treat severe footrot (SFR) and always using formalin in footbaths, both compared with not footbathing, using FootVax&#x2122; for &lt;1 year compared with not using FootVax&#x2122;, and never quarantining new or returning sheep to the farm for &gt;3 weeks compared with always. Lower prevalence of lameness in ewes was associated with vaccinating with FootVax&#x2122; for &gt;5 years compared with not vaccinating, peat soil compared with no peat soil, and having no lame ewes to treat. Higher prevalence of lameness in lambs was associated with 5-100% feet bleeding during routine foot trimming, always foot trimming ewes with SFR, not knowingly selecting replacement ewes from ewes that were never lame compared with always, replacement sheep purchased and homebred compared with only homebred, treating lambs &gt;3 days after recognition of lameness compared with 0-3 days and footbathing the flock to treat interdigital dermatitis compared with not footbathing at all. Lower prevalence of lameness in lambs was associated with peat soil, flocks in Scotland versus England, an altitude of &gt;230-500 m compared with &#x2264;230 m, never using antibiotic injection to treat lambs with SFR compared with always, and having no lame lambs to treat. We conclude triangulation identified reliable management practices for farmers to implement to minimise lameness in sheep.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2021 The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lewis</LastName><ForeName>K E</ForeName><Initials>KE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Gibbet Hill, Warwick University, Coventry, United Kingdom. Electronic address: k.lewis.1@warwick.ac.uk.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Green</LastName><ForeName>M J</ForeName><Initials>MJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Veterinary Medicine and Science, University of Nottingham, Sutton Bonington Campus, Leicestershire, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Witt</LastName><ForeName>J</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>School of Life Sciences, Gibbet Hill, Warwick University, Coventry, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Green</LastName><ForeName>L E</ForeName><Initials>LE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute of Microbiology and Infection, College of Life and Environmental Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, United Kingdom.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2021</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>01</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>Netherlands</Country><MedlineTA>Prev Vet Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8217463</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0167-5877</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000822" MajorTopicYN="N">Animal Husbandry</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005535" MajorTopicYN="N">Foot Rot</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007794" MajorTopicYN="Y">Lameness, Animal</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015995" MajorTopicYN="N">Prevalence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012756" MajorTopicYN="N">Sheep</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012757" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sheep Diseases</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006113" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">United Kingdom</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Footrot</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lambs</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Lameness</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Modelling</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Sheep</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Statistical triangulation</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The authors report no declarations of interest.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>14</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>25</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2021</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>29</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>14</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>5</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2021</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>13</Day><Hour>20</Hour><Minute>48</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2021</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">34119859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC8326248</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2021.105395</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0167-5877(21)00139-2</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Angell J.W., Duncan J.S., Carter S.D., Grove-White D.H. Farmer reported prevalence and factors associated with contagious ovine digital dermatitis in Wales: a questionnaire of 511 sheep farmers. Prev. Vet. Med. 2014;113:132&#x2013;138.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24207114</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Austin P.C., Tu J.V. Bootstrap methods for developing predictive models. Am. Stat. 2004;58:131&#x2013;137.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Belsley D.A., Kuh E., Weich R.E. Wiley; New York: 1980. Regression Diagnostics: Identifying Influential Data and Sources of Collinearity.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Best C.M., Roden J., Pyatt A.Z., Behnke M., Phillips K. Uptake of the lameness five-point plan and its association with farmer-reported lameness prevalence: a cross-sectional study of 532 UK sheep farmers. Prev. Vet. Med. 2020</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32593081</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Botvinik-Nezer R., Holzmeister F., Camerer C.F., Dreber A., Huber J., Johannesson M. Variability in the analysis of a single neuroimaging dataset by many teams. Nature. 2020;582:84&#x2013;88.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7771346</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32483374</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cameron A.C., Trivedi P.K. Cambridge University Press; Cambridge: 2013. Regression Analysis of Count Data.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clifton R., Giebel K., Liu N., Purdy K.J., Green L.E. Sites of persistence of Fusobacterium necrophorum and Dichelobacter nodosus: a paradigm shift in understanding the epidemiology of footrot in sheep. Sci. Rep. 2019;9:14429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6783547</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31594981</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cox D.R., Wermuth N. Chapman &amp; Hall; London: 1996. Multivariate Dependences-Models, Analysis and Interpretation.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Desboulets L. A review on variable selection in regression analysis. Econometrics. 2018:6.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dickins A., Clark C.C., Kaler J., Ferguson E., O&#x2019;kane H., Green L.E. Factors associated with the presence and prevalence of contagious ovine digital dermatitis: a 2013 study of 1136 random English sheep flocks. Prev. Vet. Med. 2016;130:86&#x2013;93.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27435650</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dohoo I., Martin W., Strythn H. AVC Inc; Charlottetown: 2003. Veterinary Epidemiologic Research.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farm Animal Welfare Council . 2011. Opinions on Lameness in Sheep, London.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman J., Hastie T., Tibshirani R. 2009. glmnet: Lasso and Elastic-Net Regularized Generalized Linear Models, R Package Version 1.1-4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman J., Hastie T., Tibshirani R. Regularization paths for generalized linear models via coordinate descent. J. Stat. Softw. 2010:33.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2929880</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20808728</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Graham N.P., Egerton J.R. Pathogenesis of ovine foot-rot: the role of some environmental factors. Aust. Vet. J. 1968;44:235&#x2013;240.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">5690158</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grant C., Kaler J., Ferguson E., O&#x2019;kane H., Green L.E. A comparison of the efficacy of three intervention trial types: postal, group, and one-to-one facilitation, prior management and the impact of message framing and repeat messages on the flock prevalence of lameness in sheep. Prev. Vet. Med. 2018;149:82&#x2013;91.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29290304</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hastie T., Tibshirani R., Mainwright M. Chapman and Hall/CRC; 2015. Statistical Learning With Sparsity: The Lasso and Generalisations.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Heinze G., Wallisch C., Dunkler D. Variable selection - a review and recommendations for the practicing statistician. Biom. J. 2018;60:431&#x2013;449.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5969114</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29292533</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaler J., Green L.E. Farmers&#x2019; practices and factors associated with the prevalence of all lameness and lameness attributed to interdigital dermatitis and footrot in sheep flocks in England in 2004. Prev. Vet. Med. 2009;92:52&#x2013;59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19735953</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaler J., Daniels S.L.S., Wright J.L., Green L.E. Randomized clinical trial of long-acting oxytetracycline, foot trimming, and flunixine meglumine on time to recovery in sheep with footrot. J. Vet. Intern. Med. 2010;24:420&#x2013;425.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20051002</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaplan J. 2020. FastDummies: Fast Creation of Dummy (Binary) Columns and Rows From Categorical Variables. R Package Version 1.6.1.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kassambara A. sthda; 2018. Machine Learning Essentials: Practical Guide in R.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhn M.  2020. Caret: Classification and Regression Training. R Package Version 6.0-85.https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=caret</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuhn M., Johnson K. Springer Science+Business; 2013. Applied Predictive Modelling.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lawlor D.A., Tilling K., Davey Smith G. Triangulation in aetiological epidemiology. Int. J. Epidemiol. 2016;45:1866&#x2013;1886.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5841843</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28108528</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lewis K., Green L. Management Practices Associated With Prevalence of Lameness in Lambs in 2012&#x2013;2013 in 1,271 English Sheep Flocks. Front. Vet. Sci. 2020;7 doi: 10.3389/fvets.2020.519601.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.519601</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7653190</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33195508</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima E., Davies P., Kaler J., Lovatt F., Green M. Variable selection for inferential models with relatively high-dimensional data: between method heterogeneity and covariate stability as adjuncts to robust selection. Sci. Rep. 2020;10:8002.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7224285</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">32409668</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima E., Green M., Lovatt F., Davies P., King L., Kaler J. Use of bootstrapped, regularised regression to identify factors associated with lamb-derived revenue on commercial sheep farms. Prev. Vet. Med. 2020;174</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31778947</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lima E., Hyde R., Green M. Model selection for inferential models with high dimensional data: synthesis and graphical representation of multiple techniques. Sci. Rep. 2021;11:412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC7801732</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">33431921</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meinshausen N., B&#xfc;hlmann P. Stability selection. J. R. Stat. Soc.: Ser. B (Stat. Methodol.) 2010;72:417&#x2013;473.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Met Office . 2018. Met Office Past Weather Events: Summer 2018. [Online].  https://www.metoffice.gov.uk/weather/learn-about/past-uk-weather-events#y2018: Met Office. [Accessed 20.04.2020]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muzafar M., Calvo-Bado L.A., Green L.E., Smith E.M., Russell C.L., Grogono-Thomas R., Wellington E.M.H. The role of the environment in transmission of Dichelobacter nodosus between ewes and their lambs. Vet. Microbiol. 2015;179:53&#x2013;59.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4518504</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25953734</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nieuwhof G.J., Conington J., Bunger L., Haresign W., Bishop S.C. Genetic and phenotypic aspects of foot lesion scores in sheep of different breeds and ages. Animal. 2008;2:1289&#x2013;1296.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22443817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Prosser N.S., Purdy K.J., Green L.E. Increase in the flock prevalence of lameness in ewes is associated with a reduction in farmers using evidence-based management of prompt treatment: a longitudinal observational study of 154 English sheep flocks 2013-2015. Prev. Vet. Med. 2019;173</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6899501</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31683188</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>R Core Team . 2019. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing, R Foundation for Statistical Computing. Vienna, Austria.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Raadsma H., Egerton J., Wood D., Kristo C., Nicholas F. Disease resistance in Merino sheep III. Genetic variation in resistance to footrot following challenge and subsequent vaccination with an homologous rDNA pilus vaccine under both induced and natural conditions. J. Anim. Breed. Genet. 1994;111:367&#x2013;390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21395787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Reeves M.C., Prosser N.S., Monaghan E.M., Green L.E. Footbathing, formalin and foot trimming: The 3Fs associated with granulomas and shelly hoof in sheep. Vet. J. 2019;250:28&#x2013;35.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31383417</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sheep Veterinary Society . 2013. Advice on Best Practice for Treating and Controlling Footrot. [Online]. Available: https://www.sheepvetsoc.org.uk/technical/advice-best-practice-treating-and-controlling-foot-rot [Accessed 26.03.2021]</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shtatland E.S., Cain E., Barton M.B. The perils of stepwise logistic regression and how to escape them using information criteria and the output delivery system. Proceedings of the Twenty-Sixth Annual SAS Users Group International Conference; SAS Institute Inc., Long Beach, California; 2008. pp. 222&#x2013;226. Paper.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skerman T.M., Johnson D., Kane D.W., Clarke J.N. Clinical footscald and footrot in a New Zealand Romney flock: phenotypic and genetic parameters. Aust. J. Agric. Res. 1988:39.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith E.M., Green O.D., Calvo-Bado L.A., Witcomb L.A., Grogono-Thomas R., Russell C.L., Brown J.C., Medley G.F., Kilbride A.L., Wellington E.M., Green L.E. Dynamics and impact of footrot and climate on hoof horn length in 50 ewes from one farm over a period of 10 months. Vet. J. 2014;201:295&#x2013;301.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4168150</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24973007</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steyerberg E.W. Clinical Prediction Models; 2019. Overfitting and Optimism in Prediction Models.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tercerio M. The statistical properties of recreational catch rate data for some fish stocks off the northeast U.S. coast. Fish. Bull. 2003;101:653&#x2013;672.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ver Hoef J.M., Boveng P.L. Quasi-poisson vs. negative binomial regression: how should we model over-dispersed count data? Ecology. 2007;88:2766&#x2013;2772.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18051645</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wassink G.J., Grogono-Thomas R., Moore L.J., Green L.E. Risk factors associated with the prevalence of footrot in sheep from 1999 to 2000. Vet. Rec. 2003;152:351&#x2013;358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12678258</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wassink G.J., Grogono-Thomas R., Moore L.J., Green L.E. Risk factors associated with the prevalence of interdigital dermatitis in sheep from 1999 to 2000. Vet. Rec. 2004;154:551&#x2013;555.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15143999</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wassink G.J., George T.R., Kaler J., Green L.E. Footrot and interdigital dermatitis in sheep: farmer satisfaction with current management, their ideal management and sources used to adopt new strategies. Prev. Vet. Med. 2010;96:65&#x2013;73.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20594602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wassink G.J., King E.M., Grogono-Thomas R., Brown J.C., Moore L.J., Green L.E. A within farm clinical trial to compare two treatments (parenteral antibacterials and hoof trimming) for sheep lame with footrot. Prev. Vet. Med. 2010;96:93&#x2013;103.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20627343</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wheeler D.M., Sparling G.P., Roberts A.H.C. Trends in some soil test data over a 14&#x2010;year period in New Zealand. N. Z. J. Agric. Res. 2010;47:155&#x2013;166.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Winter J.R., Kaler J., Ferguson E., Kilbride A.L., Green L.E. Changes in prevalence of, and risk factors for, lameness in random samples of English sheep flocks: 2004&#x2013;2013. Prev. Vet. Med. 2015;122:121&#x2013;128.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26435034</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Witt J., Green L. Development and assessment of management practices in a flock-specific lameness control plan: a stepped-wedge trial on 44 English sheep flocks. Prev. Vet. Med. 2018;157:125&#x2013;133.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">30086840</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>