<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">38422989</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2024</Year><Month>04</Month><Day>19</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2025</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>02</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1097-0258</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>43</Volume><Issue>10</Issue><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>May</Month><Day>10</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Statistics in medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Stat Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Inference under superspreading: Determinants of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in Germany.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1933</StartPage><EndPage>1954</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1933-1954</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/sim.10046</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Superspreading, under-reporting, reporting delay, and confounding complicate statistical inference on determinants of disease transmission. A model that accounts for these factors within a Bayesian framework is estimated using German Covid-19 surveillance data. Compartments based on date of symptom onset, location, and age group allow to identify age-specific changes in transmission, adjusting for weather, reported prevalence, and testing and tracing. Several factors were associated with a reduction in transmission: public awareness rising, information on local prevalence, testing and tracing, high temperature, stay-at-home orders, and restaurant closures. However, substantial uncertainty remains for other interventions including school closures and mandatory face coverings. The challenge of disentangling the effects of different determinants is discussed and examined through a simulation study. On a broader perspective, the study illustrates the potential of surveillance data with demographic information and date of symptom onset to improve inference in the presence of under-reporting and reporting delay.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024 The Authors. Statistics in Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Schmidt</LastName><ForeName>Patrick W</ForeName><Initials>PW</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-4425-0154</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Psychology, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>SNF</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>02</Month><Day>29</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Stat Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8215016</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0277-6715</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086402" MajorTopicYN="Y">SARS-CoV-2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000086382" MajorTopicYN="Y">COVID-19</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D001499" MajorTopicYN="N">Bayes Theorem</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003198" MajorTopicYN="N">Computer Simulation</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005858" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Germany</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">Covid&#x2010;19</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">infectious diseases</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">instantaneous reproductive number</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">nonpharmaceutical interventions</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2022</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>3</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>10</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>1</Day><Hour>1</Hour><Minute>22</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>2</Month><Day>29</Day><Hour>18</Hour><Minute>21</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">38422989</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/sim.10046</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Lloyd&#x2010;Smith JO, Schreiber SJ, Kopp PE, Getz WM. Superspreading and the effect of individual variation on disease emergence. Nature. 2005;438(7066):355&#x2010;359.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Riley S, Fraser C, Donnelly CA, et al. Transmission dynamics of the etiological agent of SARS in Hong Kong: impact of public health interventions. Science. 2003;300(5627):1961&#x2010;1966.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lipsitch M, Cohen T, Cooper B, et al. Transmission dynamics and control of severe acute respiratory syndrome. Science. 2003;300(5627):1966&#x2010;1970.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adam DC, Wu P, Wong JY, et al. Clustering and superspreading potential of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 infections in Hong Kong. Nat Med. 2020;26(11):1714&#x2010;1719. doi:10.1038/s41591&#x2010;020&#x2010;1092&#x2010;0</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bi Q, Wu Y, Mei S, et al. Epidemiology and transmission of COVID&#x2010;19 in 391 cases and 1286 of their close contacts in Shenzhen, China: a retrospective cohort study. Lancet Infect Dis. 2020;20(8):911&#x2010;919.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Endo A, Abbott S, Kucharski AJ, Funk S, et al. Estimating the overdispersion in COVID&#x2010;19 transmission using outbreak sizes outside China. Wellcome Open Res. 2020;5(67):67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hendrix MJ. Absence of apparent transmission of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 from two stylists after exposure at a hair salon with a universal face covering policy&#x2014;Springfield, Missouri. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2020;2020:69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khanh N, Thai P, Quach H, et al. Transmission of SARS&#x2010;CoV 2 during long&#x2010;haul flight. Emerg Infect Dis. 2020;26(11):2617&#x2010;2624.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sehra ST, Salciccioli JD, Wiebe DJ, Fundin S, Baker JF. Maximum daily temperature, precipitation, ultra&#x2010;violet light and rates of transmission of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 in the United States. Clin Infect Dis. 2020;71(9):2482&#x2010;2487.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Salje H, Kiem CT, Lefrancq N, et al. Estimating the burden of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 in France. Science. 2020;369(6500):208&#x2010;211.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chernozhukov V, Kasahara H, Schrimpf P. Causal impact of masks, policies, behavior on early Covid&#x2010;19 pandemic in the U.S. J Econ. 2020;220(1):23&#x2010;62. doi:10.1016/j.jeconom.2020.09.003</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang R, Li Y, Zhang AL, Wang Y, Molina MJ. Identifying airborne transmission as the dominant route for the spread of COVID&#x2010;19. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2020;117(26):14857&#x2010;14863. doi:10.1073/pnas.2009637117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitze T, Kosfeld R, Rode J, W&#xe4;lde K. Face masks considerably reduce COVID&#x2010;19 cases in Germany. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2020;117(51):32293&#x2010;32301. doi:10.1073/pnas.2015954117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Flaxman S, Mishra S, Gandy A, et al. Estimating the effects of non&#x2010;pharmaceutical interventions on COVID&#x2010;19 in Europe. Nature. 2020;584(7820):257&#x2010;261.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brauner JM, Mindermann S, Sharma M, et al. Inferring the effectiveness of government interventions against COVID&#x2010;19. Science. 2021;371(6531):eabd9338.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soltesz K, Gustafsson F, Timpka T, et al. The effect of interventions on COVID&#x2010;19. Nature. 2020;588(7839):E26&#x2010;E28. doi:10.1038/s41586&#x2010;020&#x2010;3025&#x2010;y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ng QX, De Deyn MLZQ, Yeo WS. Do face masks help? Is not the question. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2020;117(44):27078&#x2010;27079. doi:10.1073/pnas.2012241117</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bhatt S, Ferguson N, Flaxman S, Gandy A, Mishra S, Scott JA. Semi&#x2010;mechanistic Bayesian modeling of COVID&#x2010;19 with renewal processes. arXiv preprint arXiv:2012.00394. 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olney AM, Smith J, Sen S, Thomas F, Unwin HJT. Estimating the effect of social distancing interventions on COVID&#x2010;19 in the United States. Am J Epidemiol. 2021;190(8):1504&#x2010;1509.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wood SN, Inferring UK. COVID&#x2010;19 fatal infection trajectories from daily mortality data: were infections already in decline before the UK lockdowns? Biometrics. 2021;78(3):1127&#x2010;1140.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Monod M, Blenkinsop A, Xi X, et al. Age groups that sustain resurging COVID&#x2010;19 epidemics in the United States. Science. 2021;371(6536):eabe8372. doi:10.1126/science.abe8372</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cori A, Ferguson NM, Fraser C, Cauchemez S. A new framework and software to estimate time&#x2010;varying reproduction numbers during epidemics. Am J Epidemiol. 2013;178(9):1505&#x2010;1512.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>White LF, Moser CB, Thompson RN, Pagano M. Statistical estimation of the reproductive number from case notification data. Am J Epidemiol. 2021;190(4):611&#x2010;620.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vegvari C, Abbott S, Ball F, et al. Commentary on the use of the reproduction number R during the COVID&#x2010;19 pandemic. Stat Methods Med Res. 2022;31(9):1675&#x2010;1685.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mishra S, Scott JA, Laydon DJ, et al. A COVID&#x2010;19 model for local authorities of the United Kingdom. J R Stat Soc Ser A Stat Soc. 2022;185(Supplement_1):S86&#x2010;S95.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wallinga J, Teunis P. Different epidemic curves for severe acute respiratory syndrome reveal similar impacts of control measures. Am J Epidemiol. 2004;160(6):509&#x2010;516.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dehning J, Zierenberg J, Spitzner FP, et al. Inferring change points in the spread of COVID&#x2010;19 reveals the effectiveness of interventions. Science. 2020;369(6500):eabb9789.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Russell TW, Golding N, Hellewell J, et al. Reconstructing the early global dynamics of under&#x2010;ascertained COVID&#x2010;19 cases and infections. BMC Med. 2020;18(1):1&#x2010;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Levin AT, Hanage WP, Owusu&#x2010;Boaitey N, Cochran KB, Walsh SP, Meyerowitz&#x2010;Katz G. Assessing the age specificity of infection fatality rates for COVID&#x2010;19: systematic review, meta&#x2010;analysis, and public policy implications. Eur J Epidemiol. 2020;35(12):1123&#x2010;1138.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Robert Koch Institute. Corona&#x2010;monitoring lokal. 2020. https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/Gesundheitsmonitoring/Studien/cml&#x2010;studie/cml&#x2010;studie_node.html. Accessed October 10, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pitzer VE, Chitwood M, Havumaki J, et al. The impact of changes in diagnostic testing practices on estimates of COVID&#x2010;19 transmission in the United States. Am J Epidemiol. 2021;190(9):1908&#x2010;1917.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hsiang S, Allen D, Annan&#x2010;Phan S, et al. The effect of large&#x2010;scale anti&#x2010;contagion policies on the COVID&#x2010;19 pandemic. Nature. 2020;584(7820):262&#x2010;267.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies NG, Kucharski AJ, Eggo RM, et al. Effects of non&#x2010;pharmaceutical interventions on COVID&#x2010;19 cases, deaths, and demand for hospital services in the UK: a modelling study. Lancet Public Health. 2020;5(7):e375&#x2010;e385.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Parker D, Pianykh O. Mobility&#x2010;guided estimation of Covid&#x2010;19 transmission rates. Am J Epidemiol. 2021;190(6):1081&#x2010;1087.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xie S, Wang W, Wang Q, Wang Y, Zeng D. Evaluating effectiveness of public health intervention strategies for mitigating COVID&#x2010;19 pandemic. Stat Med. 2022;41(19):3820&#x2010;3836.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Agosto A, Campmas A, Giudici P, Renda A. Monitoring COVID&#x2010;19 contagion growth. Stat Med. 2021;40(18):4150&#x2010;4160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keller JP, Zhou T, Kaplan A, Anderson GB, Zhou W. Tracking the transmission dynamics of COVID&#x2010;19 with a time&#x2010;varying coefficient state&#x2010;space model. Stat Med. 2022;41(15):2745&#x2010;2767.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Held L, H&#xf6;hle M, Hofmann M. A statistical framework for the analysis of multivariate infectious disease surveillance counts. Stat Model. 2005;5(3):187&#x2010;199.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meyer S, Held L. Incorporating social contact data in spatio&#x2010;temporal models for infectious disease spread. Biostatistics. 2016;18(2):338&#x2010;351.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fisher LH, Wakefield J. Ecological inference for infectious disease data, with application to vaccination strategies. Stat Med. 2020;39(3):220&#x2010;238.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abbott S, Hellewell J, Thompson RN, et al. Estimating the time&#x2010;varying reproduction number of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 using national and subnational case counts. Wellcome Open Res. 2020;5(112):112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plummer M. rjags: Bayesian Graphical Models using MCMC. R package version 4&#x2010;10. 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffman MD, Gelman A. The no&#x2010;U&#x2010;turn sampler: adaptively setting path lengths in Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. J Mach Learn Res. 2014;15(1):1593&#x2010;1623.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Grinsztajn L, Semenova E, Margossian CC, Riou J. Bayesian workflow for disease transmission modeling in Stan. Stat Med. 2021;40(27):6209&#x2010;6234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>T&#xf6;nshoff B, M&#xfc;ller B, Elling R, et al. Prevalence of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 infection in children and their parents in Southwest Germany. JAMA Pediatr. 2021;175(6):586&#x2010;593.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rodiah I, Vanella P, Kuhlmann A, et al. Age&#x2010;specific contribution of contacts to transmission of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 in Germany. Eur J Epidemiol. 2023;38(1):39&#x2010;58.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Keeling MJ. The effects of local spatial structure on epidemiological invasions. Proc R Soc Lond Ser B Biol Sci. 1999;266(1421):859&#x2010;867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davis S, Trapman P, Leirs H, Begon M, Heesterbeek J. The abundance threshold for plague as a critical percolation phenomenon. Nature. 2008;454(7204):634&#x2010;637.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Korber B, Fischer WM, Gnanakaran S, et al. Tracking changes in SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 spike: evidence that D614G increases infectivity of the COVID&#x2010;19 virus. Cell. 2020;182(4):812&#x2010;827.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ali ST, Wang L, Lau EHY, et al. Serial interval of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 was shortened over time by nonpharmaceutical interventions. Science. 2020;369(6507):1106&#x2010;1109. doi:10.1126/science.abc9004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wieler L, Rexroth U, Gottschalk R. Emerging COVID&#x2010;19 success story: Germany's strong enabling environment. 2020. https://www.exemplars.health/emerging&#x2010;topics/epidemic&#x2010;preparedness&#x2010;and&#x2010;response/covid&#x2010;19/germany. Accessed November 7, 2020.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stang A, Standl F, Kowall B, et al. Excess mortality due to COVID&#x2010;19 in Germany. J Infect. 2020;81:797&#x2010;801.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Contreras S, Dehning J, Loidolt M, et al. The challenges of containing SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 via test&#x2010;trace&#x2010;and&#x2010;isolate. Nat Commun. 2021;12(1):1&#x2010;13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Furman E. On the convolution of the negative binomial random variables. Stat Prob Lett. 2007;77(2):169&#x2010;172.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Betsch C, Korn L, Sprengholz P, et al. Social and behavioral consequences of mask policies during the COVID&#x2010;19 pandemic. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2020;117(36):21851&#x2010;21853.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomori DV, R&#xfc;bsamen N, Berger T, et al. Individual social contact data and population mobility data as early markers of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 transmission dynamics during the first wave in Germany&#x2014;an analysis based on the COVIMOD study. BMC Med. 2021;19:1&#x2010;13.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laxminarayan R, Wahl B, Dudala SR, et al. Epidemiology and transmission dynamics of COVID&#x2010;19 in two Indian states. Science. 2020;370(6517):691&#x2010;697. doi:10.1126/science.abd7672</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>K&#xfc;chenhoff H, G&#xfc;nther F, H&#xf6;hle M, Bender A. Analysis of the early COVID&#x2010;19 epidemic curve in Germany by regression models with change points. Epidemiol Infect. 2021;149:e68. doi:10.1017/S0950268821000558</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferretti L, Wymant C, Kendall M, et al. Quantifying SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 transmission suggests epidemic control with digital contact tracing. Science. 2020;368(6491):eabb6936.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gurdasani D, Ziauddeen H. On the fallibility of simulation models in informing pandemic responses. Lancet Glob Health. 2020;8(6):e776&#x2010;e777. doi:10.1016/S2214&#x2010;109X(20)30219&#x2010;9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haug N, Geyrhofer L, Londei A, et al. Ranking the effectiveness of worldwide COVID&#x2010;19 government interventions. Nat Hum Behav. 2020;4(12):1303&#x2010;1312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toxvaerd F. Rational disinhibition and externalities in prevention. Int Econ Rev. 2019;60(4):1737&#x2010;1755.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toxvaerd F. Equilibrium social distancing. Covid. Economics. 2020;(15):110&#x2010;133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Baker RE, Yang W, Vecchi GA, Metcalf CJE, Grenfell BT. Susceptible supply limits the role of climate in the early SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 pandemic. Science. 2020;369(6501):315&#x2010;319.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Carlson CJ, Gomez AC, Bansal S, Ryan SJ. Misconceptions about weather and seasonality must not misguide COVID&#x2010;19 response. Nat Commun. 2020;11(1):1&#x2010;4.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaven&#x10d;iak T, Monrad JT, Leech G, et al. Seasonal variation in SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 transmission in temperate climates: a Bayesian modelling study in 143 European regions. PLoS Comput Biol. 2022;18(8):e1010435.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ledebur K, Kaleta M, Chen J, et al. Meteorological factors and non&#x2010;pharmaceutical interventions explain local differences in the spread of SARS&#x2010;CoV&#x2010;2 in Austria. PLoS Comput Biol. 2022;18(4):e1009973.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pei S, Yamana TK, Kandula S, Galanti M, Shaman J. Burden and characteristics of COVID&#x2010;19 in the United States during 2020. Nature. 2021;598(7880):338&#x2010;341.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Weidemann F, Dehnert M, Koch J, Wichmann O, H&#xf6;hle M. Bayesian parameter inference for dynamic infectious disease modelling: rotavirus in Germany. Stat Med. 2014;33(9):1580&#x2010;1599.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bj&#xf8;rnstad ON, Finkenst&#xe4;dt BF, Grenfell BT. Dynamics of measles epidemics: estimating scaling of transmission rates using a time series SIR model. Ecological Monographs. 2002;72(2):169&#x2010;184.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wakefield J, Dong TQ, Minin VN. Spatio&#x2010;temporal analysis of surveillance data. In: Held L, Hens N, O'Neill P, Wallinga J, eds. Handbook of Infectious Disease Data Analysis. London, UK: Chapman and Hall/CRC; 2019:455&#x2010;476.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Finkenst&#xe4;dt BF, Grenfell BT. Time series modelling of childhood diseases: a dynamical systems approach. J R Stat Soc Ser C Appl Stat. 2000;49(2):187&#x2010;205.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>