<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">28093542</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2017</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>31</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>27</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1476-1645</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>96</Volume><Issue>4</Issue><PubDate><Year>2017</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The American journal of tropical medicine and hygiene</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Am J Trop Med Hyg</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Disease Burden of Dengue in the Philippines: Adjusting for Underreporting by Comparing Active and Passive Dengue Surveillance in Punta Princesa, Cebu City.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>887</StartPage><EndPage>898</EndPage><MedlinePgn>887-898</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.4269/ajtmh.16-0488</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>AbstractDengue virus (DENV) is a serious threat to public health. Having reliable estimates of the burden of dengue is important to inform policy and research, but surveillance systems are not designed to capture all symptomatic DENV infections. We derived the rate of reporting of dengue by comparing active surveillance of symptomatic DENV infections in a prospective community-based seroepidemiological cohort study (<i>N</i> = 1008) of acute febrile illness in Punta Princesa, Cebu City, Philippines, with passive surveillance data from the Cebu City Health Department. Febrile episodes detected in a weekly follow-up of participants were tested for serotype-specific DENV by hemi-nested reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (nested RT-PCR) and acute/convalescent blood samples tested by dengue IgM/IgG enzyme immunoassay. We estimated the burden of dengue in the Philippines in disability-adjusted life years (DALYs), and conducted a probabilistic sensitivity analysis using Monte-Carlo simulations to address uncertainty. The results showed a 21% cumulative reporting rate of symptomatic DENV infections, equivalent to an expansion factor of 4.7 (95% certainty level [CL]: 2.2-15.1). Based on surveillance data in the Philippines for 2010-2014, we estimated 794,255 annual dengue episodes (95% CL: 463,000-2,076,000) and a disease burden of 535 (95% CL: 380-994) DALYs per million population using age weights and time discounting and 997 (95% CL: 681-1,871) DALYs per million population without age and time adjustments. Dengue imposes a substantial burden in the Philippines; almost 10 times higher than estimated for rabies, about twice the burden of intestinal fluke infections, and about 10% of the burden of tuberculosis. Our estimates should inform policy makers and raise awareness among the public.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Undurraga</LastName><ForeName>Eduardo A</ForeName><Initials>EA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Schneider Institutes for Health Policy, Heller School, Brandeis University, Waltham, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Edillo</LastName><ForeName>Frances E</ForeName><Initials>FE</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biology, University of San Carlos, Cebu City, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Erasmo</LastName><ForeName>Jonathan Neil V</ForeName><Initials>JNV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Health, Cebu City, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Alera</LastName><ForeName>Maria Theresa P</ForeName><Initials>MTP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Philippines-AFRIMS Virology Research Unit, Cebu City, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Yoon</LastName><ForeName>In-Kyu</ForeName><Initials>IK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dengue Vaccine Initiative, International Vaccine Institute, Seoul, Republic of Korea.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Armed Forces Research Institute of Medical Sciences, Bangkok, Thailand.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Largo</LastName><ForeName>Francisco M</ForeName><Initials>FM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics, University of San Carlos, Cebu City, Philippines.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Shepard</LastName><ForeName>Donald S</ForeName><Initials>DS</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Schneider Institutes for Health Policy, Heller School, Brandeis University, Waltham, Massachusetts.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2017</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>16</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Am J Trop Med Hyg</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0370507</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0002-9637</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000293" MajorTopicYN="N">Adolescent</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000328" MajorTopicYN="N">Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002648" MajorTopicYN="N">Child</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002675" MajorTopicYN="N">Child, Preschool</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D003715" MajorTopicYN="N">Dengue</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000191" MajorTopicYN="N">economics</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005260" MajorTopicYN="N">Female</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017048" MajorTopicYN="N">Health Care Costs</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015994" MajorTopicYN="N">Incidence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D007223" MajorTopicYN="N">Infant</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008297" MajorTopicYN="N">Male</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D008875" MajorTopicYN="N">Middle Aged</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D009010" MajorTopicYN="N">Monte Carlo Method</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010679" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Philippines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011159" MajorTopicYN="Y">Population Surveillance</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013997" MajorTopicYN="N">Time Factors</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014505" MajorTopicYN="N">Urban Population</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D055815" MajorTopicYN="N">Young Adult</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2017</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2017</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2017</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2017</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28093542</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5392638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.16-0488</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Bhatt S, Gething PW, Brady OJ, Messina JP, Farlow AW, Moyes CL, Drake JM, Brownstein JS, Hoen AG, Sankoh O, Myers MF, George DB, Jaenisch T, Wint GRW, Simmons CP, Scott TW, Farrar JJ, Hay SI. The global distribution and burden of dengue. Nature. 2013;496:504&#x2013;507.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3651993</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23563266</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanaway JD, Shepard DS, Undurraga EA, Halasa YA, Coffeng LE, Brady OJ, Hay SI, Bedi N, Bensenor IM, Casta&#xf1;eda-Orjuela CA, Chuang T-W, Gibney KB, Memish ZA, Rafay A, Ukwaja KN, Yonemoto N, Murray CJL. The global burden of dengue: a systematic analysis from the Global Burden of Disease Study 2013. Lancet Infect Dis. 2016;16:712&#x2013;723.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5012511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26874619</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepard DS, Halasa YA, Undurraga EA. Economic and disease burden of dengue. In: Gubler DJ, Ooi Ee, Vasudevan SG, Farrar J, editors. Dengue and Dengue Hemorrhagic Fever. Wallingford, UK: CAB International; 2014. pp. 50&#x2013;77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepard DS, Coudeville L, Halasa YA, Zambrano B, Dayan GH. Economic impact of dengue illness in the Americas. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2011;84:200&#x2013;207.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3029168</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21292885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepard DS, Undurraga EA, Halasa YA. Economic and disease burden of dengue in Southeast Asia. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2013;7:e2055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3578748</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23437406</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepard DS, Undurraga EA, Halasa YA, Stanaway JD. The global economic burden of dengue: a systematic analysis. Lancet Infect Dis. 2016;16:935&#x2013;941.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27091092</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  Dengue: Guidelines for Diagnosis, Treatment, Prevention and Control. New edition. 2009. http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/44188/1/9789241547871_eng.pdf Available at. Accessed September 8, 2016.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23762963</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simmons CP, Farrar JJ, Nguyen VVC, Wills B. Current concepts: dengue. N Engl J Med. 2012;366:1423&#x2013;1432.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22494122</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bravo L, Roque VG, Brett J, Dizon R, L'Azou M. Epidemiology of dengue disease in the Philippines (2000&#x2013;2011): a systematic literature review. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2014;8:e3027.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4222740</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25375119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edillo FE, Halasa YA, Largo FM, Erasmo JNV, Amoin NB, Alera MTP, Yoon I-K, Alcantara AC, Shepard DS. Economic cost and burden of dengue in the Philippines. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2015;92:360&#x2013;366.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4347342</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25510723</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edillo F, Madarieta S. Trends of dengue infections (1997&#x2013;2008) in Cebu Province, Philippines. Dengue Bull. 2012;36:37&#x2013;49.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Undurraga EA, Halasa YA, Shepard DS. Use of expansion factors to estimate the burden of dengue in Southeast Asia: a systematic analysis. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2013;7:e2056.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3578761</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23437407</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization, Western Pacific Region  Emerging Disease Surveillance and Response: Dengue Situation Updates. WPRO 2014. 2013. http://www.wpro.who.int/emerging_diseases/DengueSituationUpdates/en/ Available at. Accessed January 7, 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dominguez NN. Current DF/DHF prevention and control programme in the Philippines. Dengue Bull. 1997;21:41&#x2013;47.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Department of Health, Republic of the Philippines  Disease Surveillance, Dengue Morbidity. 2012. http://dev1.doh.gov.ph/disease-surveillance Available at. Accessed January 7, 2014.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding MR. Dengue Surveillance and Diagnostics in the Philippines; First Asian Dengue Vaccination Advocacy (ADVA) Group Regional Workshop; Bangkok, Thailand. September 21&#x2013;23, 2012.2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>National Epidemiology Center . Manual of Procedures for the Philippine Integrated Disease Surveillance and Response. Manila, Philippines: Department of Health Philippines; 2008.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edillo FE, Erasmo JN, Halasa YA, Amoin NB, Largo FM, Shepard DS. Dengue surveillance system in action in the Philippines. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2013;89:178.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Duarte HHP, Franca EB. Data quality of dengue epidemiological surveillance in Belo Horizonte, southeastern Brazil. Rev Saude Publica. 2006;40:134&#x2013;142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16410994</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tien NTK, Luxemburger C, Toan NT, Pollissard-Gadroy L, Houng VTQ, Be PV, Rang NN, Wartel TA, Lang J. A prospective cohort study of dengue infection in schoolchildren in Long Xuyen, Viet Nam. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2010;104:592&#x2013;600.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20630553</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wichmann O, Yoon IK, Vong S, Limkittikul K, Gibbons RV, Mammen MP, Ly S, Buchy P, Sirivichayakul C, Buathong R, Huy R, Letson GW, Sabchareon A. Dengue in Thailand and Cambodia: an assessment of the degree of underrecognized disease burden based on reported cases. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2011;5:e996.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3066139</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21468308</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepard DS, Undurraga EA, Lees RS, Halasa YA, Lum L, Ng CW. Use of multiple data sources to estimate the economic cost of dengue illness in Malaysia. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2012;87:796&#x2013;805.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3516253</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23033404</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Montoya M, Gresh L, Mercado JC, Williams KL, Vargas MJ, Gutierrez G, Kuan G, Gordon A, Balmaseda A, Harris E. Symptomatic versus inapparent outcome in repeat dengue virus infections is influenced by the time interval between infections and study year. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2013;7:e2357.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3738476</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23951377</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Torres JR, Torres CG. Dengue in Latin America. A unique situation. Dengue Bull. 2002;26:62&#x2013;69.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halstead SB. Dengue in the Americas and southeast Asia: do they differ? Rev Panam Salud Publica. 2006;20:407&#x2013;415.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17341332</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vaughn DW, Green S, Kalayanarooj S, Innis BL, Nimmannitya S, Suntayakorn S, Endy TP, Raengsakulrach B, Rothman AL, Ennis FA. Dengue viremia titer, antibody response pattern, and virus serotype correlate with disease severity. J Infect Dis. 2000;181:2&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10608744</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fried JR, Gibbons RV, Kalayanarooj S, Thomas SJ, Srikiatkhachorn A, Yoon IK, Jarman RG, Green S, Rothman AL, Cummings DAT. Serotype-specific differences in the risk of dengue hemorrhagic fever: an analysis of data collected in Bangkok, Thailand from 1994 to 2006. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2010;4:e617.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2830471</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20209155</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gibbons RV, Kalanarooj S, Jarman RG, Nisalak A, Vaughn DW, Endy TP, Mammen MP, Srikiatkhachorn A. Analysis of repeat hospital admissions for dengue to estimate the frequency of third or fourth dengue infections resulting in admissions and dengue hemorrhagic fever, and serotype sequences. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2007;77:910&#x2013;913.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17984352</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olkowski S, Forshey BM, Morrison AC, Rocha C, Vilcarromero S, Halsey ES, Kochel TJ, Scott TW, Stoddard ST. Reduced risk of disease during postsecondary dengue virus infections. J Infect Dis. 2013;208:1026&#x2013;1033.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3749012</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23776195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzman MG, Alvarez M, Halstead SB. Secondary infection as a risk factor for dengue hemorrhagic fever/dengue shock syndrome: an historical perspective and role of antibody-dependent enhancement of infection. Arch Virol. 2013;158:1445&#x2013;1459.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23471635</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sierra BDL, Kouri G, Guzman MG. Race: a risk factor for dengue hemorrhagic fever. Arch Virol. 2007;152:533&#x2013;542.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17106622</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halstead SB, Streit TG, Lafontant JG, Putvatana R, Russell K, Sun W, Kanesa-Thasan N, Hayes CG, Watts DM. Haiti: absence of dengue hemorrhagic fever despite hyperendemic dengue virus transmission. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2001;65:180&#x2013;183.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11561700</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sharp TM, Moreira R, Soares MJ, da Costa LM, Mann J, DeLorey M, Hunsperger E, Mu&#xf1;oz-Jord&#xe1;n JL, Col&#xf3;n C, Margolis HS. Underrecognition of dengue during 2013 epidemic in Luanda, Angola. Emerg Infect Dis. 2015;21:1311.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4517701</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26196224</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Senn N, Luang-Suarkia D, Manong D, Max Siba P, Hannan McBride WJ. Contribution of dengue fever to the burden of acute febrile illnesses in Papua New Guinea: an age-specific prospective study. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2011;85:132.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3122357</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21734138</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ellis EM, Neatherlin JC, Delorey M, Ochieng M, Mohamed AH, Mogeni DO, Hunsperger E, Patta S, Gikunju S, Waiboic L, Fields B, Ofula V, Konongoi SL, Torres-Velasquez B, Marano N, Sang R, Margolis HS, Montgomery JM, Tomashek KM. A household serosurvey to estimate the magnitude of a dengue outbreak in Mombasa, Kenya, 2013. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2015;9:e0003733.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4414477</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25923210</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stoler J, Delimini RK, Bonney JK, Oduro AR, Owusu-Agyei S, Fobil JN, Awandare GA. Evidence of recent dengue exposure among malaria parasite-positive children in three urban centers in Ghana. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2015;92:497&#x2013;500.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4350537</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25582693</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzman MG, Jaenisch T, Gaczkowski R, Vo TTH, Sekaran SD, Kroeger A, Vazquez S, Ruiz D, Martinez E, Mercado JC, Balmaseda A, Harris E, Dimano E, Leano PSA, Yoksan S, Villegas E, Benduzu H, Villalobos I, Farrar J, Simmons CP. Multi-country evaluation of the sensitivity and specificity of two commercially-available NS1 ELISA assays for dengue diagnosis. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2010;4:e811.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2930874</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20824173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guzm&#xe1;n MG, Kour&#x1d6a4;&#xec; G. Dengue diagnosis, advances and challenges. Int J Infect Dis. 2004;8:69&#x2013;80.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14732325</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shepard DS, Undurraga EA, Betancourt-Cravioto M, Guzm&#xe1;n MG, Halstead SB, Harris E, Mudin RN, Murray KO, Tapia-Conyer R, Gubler DJ. Approaches to refining estimates of global burden and economics of dengue. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2014;8:e3306.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4238988</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25412506</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toan NT, Rossi S, Prisco G, Nante N, Viviani S. Dengue epidemiology in selected endemic countries: factors influencing expansion factors as estimates of underreporting. Trop Med Int Health. 2015;20:840&#x2013;863.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25753454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarti E, L'Azou M, Mercado M, Kuri P, Siqueira JB, Jr, Solis E, Noriega F, Ochiai RL. A comparative study on active and passive epidemiological surveillance for dengue in five countries of Latin America. Int J Infect Dis. 2016;44:44&#x2013;49.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26836763</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tomashek KM, Gregory CJ, Rivera S&#xe1;nchez A, Bartek MA, Garcia Rivera EJ, Hunsperger E, Mu&#xf1;oz-Jord&#xe1;n JL, Sun W. Dengue deaths in Puerto Rico: lessons learned from the 2007 epidemic. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2012;6:e1614.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3328431</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22530072</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pamplona LG, de Melo Braga DN, da Silva LMA, Aguiar MG, Castiglioni M, Silva-Junior JU, de Carvalho Ara&#xfa;jo FM, da Costa Pereira RA, Malta DL, de Lima Pompeu MM. Postmortem diagnosis of dengue as an epidemiological surveillance tool. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2016;94:187&#x2013;192.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4710428</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26598561</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vong S, Goyet S, Ly S, Ngan C, Huy R, Duong V, Wichmann O, Letson GW, Margolis HS, Buchy P. Under-recognition and reporting of dengue in Cambodia: a capture-recapture analysis of the National Dengue Surveillance System. Epidemiol Infect. 2012;140:491&#x2013;499.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21733251</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olkowski S, Stoddard ST, Halsey ES, Morrison AC, Barker CM, Scott TW. Sentinel versus Passive Surveillance for Measuring Changes in Dengue Incidence: Evidence from Three Concurrent Surveillance Systems in Iquitos, Peru. 2016. http://biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2016/02/18/040220.full.pdf Available at. Accessed March 5, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>DeRoeck D, Deen J, Clemens JD. Policymakers' views on dengue fever/dengue haemorrhagic fever and the need for dengue vaccines in four southeast Asian countries. Vaccine. 2003;22:121&#x2013;129.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14604579</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Beatty ME, Stone A, Fitzsimons DW, Hanna JN, Lam SK, Vong S, Guzman MG, Mendez-Galvan JF, Halstead SB, Letson GW, Kuritsky J, Mahoney R, Margolis HS, Asia-Pacific Amer Dengue P. Best practices in dengue surveillance: a report from the Asia-Pacific and Americas Dengue Prevention Boards. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2010;4:e890.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2982842</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21103381</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Racloz V, Ramsey R, Tong SL, Hu WB. Surveillance of dengue fever virus: a review of epidemiological models and early warning systems. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2012;6:e1648.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3358322</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22629476</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Badurdeen S, Valladares DB, Farrar J, Gozzer E, Kroeger A, Kuswara N, Ranzinger SR, Tinh HT, Leite P, Mahendradhata Y, Skewes R, Verrall A. WHO/TDR working group Sharing experiences: towards an evidence based model of dengue surveillance and outbreak response in Latin America and Asia. BMC Public Health. 2013;13:607.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3697990</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23800243</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ooi EE, Gubler D, Nam V. Dengue Research Needs Related to Surveillance and Emergency Response; Geneva. October 1&#x2013;5, 2006; Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization (WHO); 2007. pp. 124&#x2013;133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray CJL. Quantifying the burden of disease: the technical basis for disability-adjusted life years. Bull World Health Organ. 1994;72:429&#x2013;445.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2486718</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8062401</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meltzer MI, Rigau-Perez JG, Clark GG, Reiter P, Gubler DJ. Using disability-adjusted life years to assess the economic impact of dengue in Puerto Rico: 1984&#x2013;1994. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 1998;59:265&#x2013;271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9715944</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philippines Statistics Authority  Philippine Standard Geographic Code. Municipality/City: Cebu City. 2015. http://www.nscb.gov.ph/activestats/psgc/municipality.asp?muncode=072217000&amp;regcode=07&amp;provcode=22 Available at. Accessed May, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cebu City Health Department CCHD . Dengue Surveillance Report. Cebu City, Philippines: CCHD; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cebu City Health Department CCHD . Dengue Surveillance Report. Cebu City, Philippines: CCHD; 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Catinding NT, Ni&#xf1;al MO, Roque VGJ. Manual of Procedures for the Philippines Integrated and Surveillance and Response. Manila, Philippines: Department of Health; 2008. p. 228.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  Dengue Haemorrhagic Fever: Diagnosis, Treatment, Prevention and Control. 1997. http://www.who.int/csr/resources/publications/dengue/Denguepublication/en/ Available at. Accessed September, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ona E. Revised Dengue Clinical Case Management Guidelines: Administrative Order Number 2012-0006. Manila, Philippines: Department of Health; 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philippines Statistics Authority - National Statistics Office  Population and Housing Census. 2012. http://www.web0.psa.gov.ph/statistics/census/population-and-housing Available at. Accessed December 11, 2013.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Alera MT, Srikiatkhachorn A, Velasco JM, Tac-An IA, Lago CB, Clapham HE, Fernandez S, Levy JW, Thaisomboonsuk B, Klungthong C, Macareo LR, Nisalak A, Hermann L, Villa D, Yoon I-K. Incidence of dengue virus infection in adults and children in a prospective longitudinal cohort in the Philippines. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2016;10:e0004337.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4742283</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26845762</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yoon I-K, Alera MT, Lago CB, Tac-An IA, Villa D, Fernandez S, Thaisomboonsuk B, Klungthong C, Levy JW, Velasco JM. High rate of subclinical chikungunya virus infection and association of neutralizing antibody with protection in a prospective cohort in the Philippines. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2015;9:e0003764.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4423927</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25951202</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lanciotti RS, Calisher CH, Gubler DJ, Chang G-J, Vorndam AV. Rapid detection and typing of dengue viruses from clinical samples by using reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction. J Clin Microbiol. 1992;30:545&#x2013;551.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC265106</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1372617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray CJL, Vos T, Lozano R, Naghavi M, Flaxman AD, Michaud C, Ezzati M, Shibuya K, Salomon JA, Abdalla S, Aboyans V, Abraham J, Ackerman I, Aggarwal R, Ahn SY, Ali MK, Alvarado M, Anderson HR, Anderson LM, Andrews KG, Atkinson C, Baddour LM, Bahalim AN, Barker-Collo S, Barrero LH, Bartels DH, Bas&#xe1;&#xf1;ez M-G, Baxter A, Bell ML, Benjamin EJ, Bennett D, Bernab&#xe9; E, Bhalla K, Bhandari B, Bikbov B, Abdulhak AB, Birbeck G, Black JA, Blencowe H, Blore JD, Blyth F, Bolliger I, Bonaventure A, Boufous S, Bourne R, Boussinesq M, Braithwaite T, Brayne C, Bridgett L, Brooker S, Brooks P, Brugha TS, Bryan-Hancock C, Bucello C, Buchbinder R, Buckle G, Budke CM, Burch M, Burney P, Burstein R, Calabria B, Campbell B, Canter CE, Carabin H, Carapetis J, Carmona L, Cella C, Charlson F, Chen H, Cheng AT-A, Chou D, Chugh SS, Coffeng LE, Colan SD, Colquhoun S, Colson KE, Condon J, Connor MD, Cooper LT, Corriere M, Cortinovis M, de Vaccaro KC, Couser W, Cowie BC, Criqui MH, Cross M, Dabhadkar KC, Dahiya M, Dahodwala N, Damsere-Derry J, Danaei G, Davis A, Leo DD, Degenhardt L, Dellavalle R, Delossantos A, Denenberg J, Derrett S, Des Jarlais DC, Dharmaratne SD, Dherani M, Diaz-Torne C, Dolk H, Dorsey ER, Driscoll T, Duber H, Ebel B, Edmond K, Elbaz A, Ali SE, Erskine H, Erwin PJ, Espindola P, Ewoigbokhan SE, Farzadfar F, Feigin V, Felson DT, Ferrari A, Ferri CP, F&#xe8;vre EM, Finucane MM, Flaxman S, Flood L, Foreman K, Forouzanfar MH, Fowkes FG, Fransen M, Freeman MK, Gabbe BJ, Gabriel SE, Gakidou E, Ganatra HA, Garcia B, Gaspari F, Gillum RF, Gmel G, Gonzalez-Medina D, Gosselin R, Grainger R, Grant B, Groeger J, Guillemin F, Gunnell D, Gupta R, Haagsma J, Hagan H, Halasa YA, Hall W, Haring D, Haro JM, Harrison JE, Havmoeller R, Hay RJ, Higashi H, Hill C, Hoen B, Hoffman H, Hotez PJ, Hoy D, Huang JJ, Ibeanusi SE, Jacobsen KH, James SL, Jarvis D, Jasrasaria R, Jayaraman S, Johns N, Jonas JB, Karthikeyan G, Kassebaum N, Kawakami N, Keren A, Khoo JP, King CH, Knowlton LM, Kobusingye O, Koranteng A, Krishnamurthi R, Laden F, Lalloo R, Laslett LL, Lathlean T, Leasher JL, Lee YY, Leigh J, Levinson D, Lim SS, Limb E, Lin JK, Lipnick M, Lipshultz SE, Liu W, Loane M, Ohno SL, Lyons R, Mabweijano J, MacIntyre MF, Malekzadeh R, Mallinger L, Manivannan S, Marcenes W, March L, Margolis DJ, Marks GB, Marks R, Matsumori A, Matzopoulos R, Mayosi BM, McAnulty JH, McDermott MM, McGill N, McGrath J, Medina-Mora ME, Meltzer M, Mensah GA, Merriman TR, Meyer AC, Miglioli V, Miller M, Miller TR, Mitchell PB, Mock C, Mocumbi AO, Moffitt TE, Mokdad AA, Monasta L, Montico M, Moradi-Lakeh M, Moran A, Morawska L, Mori R, Murdoch ME, Mwaniki MK, Naidoo K, Nair MN, Naldi L, Narayan KM, Nelson PK, Nelson RG, Nevitt MC, Newton CR, Nolte S, Norman P, Norman R, O'Donnell M, O'Hanlon S, Olives C, Omer SB, Ortblad K, Osborne R, Ozgediz D, Page A, Pahari B, Pandian JD, Rivero AP, Patten SB, Pearce N, Padilla RP, Perez-Ruiz F, Perico N, Pesudovs K, Phillips D, Phillips MR, Pierce K, Pion S, Polanczyk GV, Polinder S, Pope CA, 3rd, Popova S, Porrini E, Pourmalek F, Prince M, Pullan RL, Ramaiah KD, Ranganathan D, Razavi H, Regan M, Rehm JT, Rein DB, Remuzzi G, Richardson K, Rivara FP, Roberts T, Robinson C, De Le&#xf2;n FR, Ronfani L, Room R, Rosenfeld LC, Rushton L, Sacco RL, Saha S, Sampson U, Sanchez-Riera L, Sanman E, Schwebel DC, Scott JG, Segui-Gomez M, Shahraz S, Shepard DS, Shin H, Shivakoti R, Singh D, Singh GM, Singh JA, Singleton J, Sleet DA, Sliwa K, Smith E, Smith JL, Stapelberg NJ, Steer A, Steiner T, Stolk WA, Stovner LJ, Sudfeld C, Syed S, Tamburlini G, Tavakkoli M, Taylor HR, Taylor JA, Taylor WJ, Thomas B, Thomson WM, Thurston GD, Tleyjeh IM, Tonelli M, Towbin JA, Truelsen T, Tsilimbaris MK, Ubeda C, Undurraga EA, van der Werf MJ, van Os J, Vavilala MS, Venketasubramanian N, Wang M, Wang W, Watt K, Weatherall DJ, Weinstock MA, Weintraub R, Weisskopf MG, Weissman MM, White RA, Whiteford H, Wiebe N, Wiersma ST, Wilkinson JD, Williams HC, Williams SR, Witt E, Wolfe F, Woolf AD, Wulf S, Yeh PH, Zaidi AK, Zheng ZJ, Zonies D, Lopez AD, AlMazroa MA, Memish ZA. Disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) for 291 diseases and injuries in 21 regions, 1990&#x2013;2010: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010. Lancet. 2012;380:2197&#x2013;2223.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23245608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  The Global Burden of Disease: 2004 Update. 2008. http://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/2004_report_update/en/ Available at. Accessed April 4, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray CJ, Ezzati M, Flaxman AD, Lim S, Lozano R, Michaud C, Naghavi M, Salomon JA, Shibuya K, Vos T. GBD 2010: design, definitions, and metrics. Lancet. 2012;380:2063&#x2013;2066.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23245602</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray CJL, Barber RM, Foreman KJ, Ozgoren AA, Abd-Allah F, Abera SF, Aboyans V, Abraham JP, Abubakar I, Abu-Raddad LJ, Abu-Rmeileh NM, Achoki T, Ackerman IN, Ademi Z, Adou AK, Adsuar JC, Afshin A, Agardh EE, Alam SS, Alasfoor D, Albittar MI, Alegretti MA, Alemu ZA, Alfonso-Cristancho R, Alhabib S, Ali R, Alla F, Allebeck P, Almazroa MA, Alsharif U, Alvarez E, Alvis-Guzman N, Amare AT, Ameh EA, Amini H, Ammar W, Anderson HR, Anderson BO, Antonio CAT, Anwari P, Arnl&#xf6;v J, Arsenijevic VSA, Artaman A, Asghar RJ, Assadi R, Atkins LS, Avila MA, Awuah B, Bachman VF, Badawi A, Bahit MC, Balakrishnan K, Banerjee A, Barker-Collo SL, Barquera S, Barregard L, Barrero LH, Basu A, Basu S, Basulaiman MO, Beardsley J, Bedi N, Beghi E, Bekele T, Bell ML, Benjet C, Bennett DA, Bensenor IM, Benzian H, Bernab&#xe9; E, Bertozzi-Villa A, Beyene TJ, Bhala N, Bhalla A, Bhutta ZA, Bienhoff K, Bikbov B, Biryukov S, Blore JD, Blosser CD, Blyth FM, Bohensky MA, Bolliger IW, Ba&#x15f;ara BB, Bornstein NM, Bose D, Boufous S, Bourne RRA, Boyers LN, Brainin M, Brayne CE, Brazinova A, Breitborde NJK, Brenner H, Briggs AD, Brooks PM, Brown JC, Brugha TS, Buchbinder R, Buckle GC, Budke CM, Bulchis A, Bulloch AG, Campos-Nonato IR, Carabin H, Carapetis JR, C&#xe1;rdenas R, Carpenter DO, Caso V, Casta&#xf1;eda-Orjuela CA, Castro RE, Catal&#xe1;-L&#xf3;pez F, Cavalleri F, &#xc7;avlin A, Chadha VK, Chang JC, Charlson FJ, Chen H, Chen W, Chiang PP, Chimed-Ochir O, Chowdhury R, Christensen H, Christophi CA, Cirillo M, Coates MM, Coffeng LE, Coggeshall MS, Colistro V, Colquhoun SM, Cooke GS, Cooper C, Cooper LT, Coppola LM, Cortinovis M, Criqui MH, Crump JA, Cuevas-Nasu L, Danawi H, Dandona L, Dandona R, Dansereau E, Dargan PI, Davey G, Davis A, Davitoiu DV, Dayama A, De Leo D, Degenhardt L, Del Pozo-Cruz B, Dellavalle RP, Deribe K, Derrett S, Des Jarlais DC, Dessalegn M, Dharmaratne SD, Dherani MK, Diaz-Torn&#xe9; C, Dicker D, Ding EL, Dokova K, Dorsey ER, Driscoll TR, Duan L, Duber HC, Ebel BE, Edmond KM, Elshrek YM, Endres M, Ermakov SP, Erskine HE, Eshrati B, Esteghamati A, Estep K, Faraon EJ, Farzadfar F, Fay DF, Feigin VL, Felson DT, Fereshtehnejad SM, Fernandes JG, Ferrari AJ, Fitzmaurice C, Flaxman AD, Fleming TD, Foigt N, Forouzanfar MH, Fowkes FG, Paleo UF, Franklin RC, F&#xfc;rst T, Gabbe B, Gaffikin L, Gankp&#xe9; FG, Geleijnse JM, Gessner BD, Gething P, Gibney KB, Giroud M, Giussani G, Gomez Dantes H, Gona P, Gonz&#xe1;lez-Medina D, Gosselin RA, Gotay CC, Goto A, Gouda HN, Graetz N, Gugnani HC, Gupta R, Gupta R, Guti&#xe9;rrez RA, Haagsma J, Hafezi-Nejad N, Hagan H, Halasa YA, Hamadeh RR, Hamavid H, Hammami M, Hancock J, Hankey GJ, Hansen GM, Hao Y, Harb HL, Haro JM, Havmoeller R, Hay SI, Hay RJ, Heredia-Pi IB, Heuton KR, Heydarpour P, Higashi H, Hijar M, Hoek HW, Hoffman HJ, Hosgood HD, Hossain M, Hotez PJ, Hoy DG, Hsairi M, Hu G, Huang C, Huang JJ, Husseini A, Huynh C, Iannarone ML, Iburg KM, Innos K, Inoue M, Islami F, Jacobsen KH, Jarvis DL, Jassal SK, Jee SH, Jeemon P, Jensen PN, Jha V, Jiang G, Jiang Y, Jonas JB, Juel K, Kan H, Karch A, Karema CK, Karimkhani C, Karthikeyan G, Kassebaum NJ, Kaul A, Kawakami N, Kazanjan K, Kemp AH, Kengne AP, Keren A, Khader YS, Khalifa SE, Khan EA, Khan G, Khang YH, Kieling C, Kim D, Kim S, Kim Y, Kinfu Y, Kinge JM, Kivipelto M, Knibbs LD, Knudsen AK, Kokubo Y, Kosen S, Krishnaswami S, Kuate Defo B, Kucuk Bicer B, Kuipers EJ, Kulkarni C, Kulkarni VS, Kumar GA, Kyu HH, Lai T, Lalloo R, Lallukka T, Lam H, Lan Q, Lansingh VC, Larsson A, Lawrynowicz AE, Leasher JL, Leigh J, Leung R, Levitz CE, Li B, Li Y, Li Y, Lim SS, Lind M, Lipshultz SE, Liu S, Liu Y, Lloyd BK, Lofgren KT, Logroscino G, Looker KJ, Lortet-Tieulent J, Lotufo PA, Lozano R, Lucas RM, Lunevicius R, Lyons RA, Ma S, Macintyre MF, Mackay MT, Majdan M, Malekzadeh R, Marcenes W, Margolis DJ, Margono C, Marzan MB, Masci JR, Mashal MT, Matzopoulos R, Mayosi BM, Mazorodze TT, Mcgill NW, Mcgrath JJ, Mckee M, Mclain A, Meaney PA, Medina C, Mehndiratta MM, Mekonnen W, Melaku YA, Meltzer M, Memish ZA, Mensah GA, Meretoja A, Mhimbira FA, Micha R, Miller TR, Mills EJ, Mitchell PB, Mock CN, Mohamed Ibrahim N, Mohammad KA, Mokdad AH, Mola GL, Monasta L, Monta&#xf1;ez Hernandez JC, Montico M, Montine TJ, Mooney MD, Moore AR, Moradi-Lakeh M, Moran AE, Mori R, Moschandreas J, Moturi WN, Moyer ML, Mozaffarian D, Msemburi WT, Mueller UO, Mukaigawara M, Mullany EC, Murdoch ME, Murray J, Murthy KS, Naghavi M, Naheed A, Naidoo KS, Naldi L, Nand D, Nangia V, Narayan KM, Nejjari C, Neupane SP, Newton CR, Ng M, Ngalesoni FN, Nguyen G, Nisar MI, Nolte S, Norheim OF, Norman RE, Norrving B, Nyakarahuka L, Oh IH, Ohkubo T, Ohno SL, Olusanya BO, Opio JN, Ortblad K, Ortiz A, Pain AW, Pandian JD, Panelo CI, Papachristou C, Park EK, Park JH, Patten SB, Patton GC, Paul VK, Pavlin BI, Pearce N, Pereira DM, Perez-Padilla R, Perez-Ruiz F, Perico N, Pervaiz A, Pesudovs K, Peterson CB, Petzold M, Phillips MR, Phillips BK, Phillips DE, Piel FB, Plass D, Poenaru D, Polinder S, Pope D, Popova S, Poulton RG, Pourmalek F, Prabhakaran D, Prasad NM, Pullan RL, Qato DM, Quistberg DA, Rafay A, Rahimi K, Rahman SU, Raju M, Rana SM, Razavi H, Reddy KS, Refaat A, Remuzzi G, Resnikoff S, Ribeiro AL, Richardson L, Richardus JH, Roberts DA, Rojas-Rueda D, Ronfani L, Roth GA, Rothenbacher D, Rothstein DH, Rowley JT, Roy N, Ruhago GM, Saeedi MY, Saha S, Sahraian MA, Sampson UK, Sanabria JR, Sandar L, Santos IS, Satpathy M, Sawhney M, Scarborough P, Schneider IJ, Sch&#xf6;ttker B, Schumacher AE, Schwebel DC, Scott JG, Seedat S, Sepanlou SG, Serina PT, Servan-Mori EE, Shackelford KA, Shaheen A, Shahraz S, Shamah Levy T, Shangguan S, She J, Sheikhbahaei S, Shi P, Shibuya K, Shinohara Y, Shiri R, Shishani K, Shiue I, Shrime MG, Sigfusdottir ID, Silberberg DH, Simard EP, Sindi S, Singh A, Singh JA, Singh L, Skirbekk V, Slepak EL, Sliwa K, Soneji S, S&#xf8;reide K, Soshnikov S, Sposato LA, Sreeramareddy CT, Stanaway JD, Stathopoulou V, Stein DJ, Stein MB, Steiner C, Steiner TJ, Stevens A, Stewart A, Stovner LJ, Stroumpoulis K, Sunguya BF, Swaminathan S, Swaroop M, Sykes BL, Tabb KM, Takahashi K, Tandon N, Tanne D, Tanner M, Tavakkoli M, Taylor HR, Te Ao BJ, Tediosi F, Temesgen AM, Templin T, Ten Have M, Tenkorang EY, Terkawi AS, Thomson B, Thorne-Lyman AL, Thrift AG, Thurston GD, Tillmann T, Tonelli M, Topouzis F, Toyoshima H, Traebert J, Tran BX, Trillini M, Truelsen T, Tsilimbaris M, Tuzcu EM, Uchendu US, Ukwaja KN, Undurraga EA, Uzun SB, Van Brakel WH, Van De Vijver S, van Gool CH, Van Os J, Vasankari TJ, Venketasubramanian N, Violante FS, Vlassov VV, Vollset SE, Wagner GR, Wagner J, Waller SG, Wan X, Wang H, Wang J, Wang L, Warouw TS, Weichenthal S, Weiderpass E, Weintraub RG, Wenzhi W, Werdecker A, Westerman R, Whiteford HA, Wilkinson JD, Williams TN, Wolfe CD, Wolock TM, Woolf AD, Wulf S, Wurtz B, Xu G, Yan LL, Yano Y, Ye P, Yent&#xfc;r GK, Yip P, Yonemoto N, Yoon SJ, Younis MZ, Yu C, Zaki ME, Zhao Y, Zheng Y, Zonies D, Zou X, Salomon JA, Lopez AD, Vos T. Global, regional, and national disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) for 306 diseases and injuries and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 188 countries, 1990&#x2013;2013: quantifying the epidemiological transition. Lancet. 2015;386:2145&#x2013;2191.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4673910</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26321261</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization  Disability Weights, Discounting and Age Weighting of DALYs. 2016. http://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/daly_disability_weight/en/ Available at. Accessed September 26, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Undurraga EA, Betancourt-Cravioto M, Ramos-Casta&#xf1;eda J, Mart&#xed;nez-Vega R, M&#xe9;ndez-Galv&#xe1;n J, Gubler DJ, Guzm&#xe1;n MG, Halstead SB, Harris E, Kuri-Morales P, Tapia-Conyer R, Shepard DS. Economic and disease burden of dengue in Mexico. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2015;9:e3547.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4364886</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25786225</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luz PM, Grinsztejn B, Galvani AP. Disability adjusted life years lost to dengue in Brazil. Trop Med Int Health. 2009;14:237&#x2013;246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19171013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borja MP, Lorenzo FME, Tallo VL, Rivera PT, Tan AG. Final Report of the Burden of Dengue in the Philippines. Manila, Philippines: Department of Health Central Office; 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nealon J, Taurel A-F, Capeding MR, Tran NH, Hadinegoro SR, Chotpitayasunondh T, Chong CK, Wartel TA, Beucher S, Frago C. Symptomatic dengue disease in five southeast Asian countries: epidemiological evidence from a dengue vaccine trial. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2016;10:e0004918.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4988713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">27532617</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding RZ, Brion JD, Caponpon MM, Gibbons RV, Jarman RG, Yoon I-K, Libraty DH. The incidence, characteristics, and presentation of dengue virus infections during infancy. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2010;82:330&#x2013;336.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2813177</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20134013</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding MR, Chua MN, Hadinegoro SR, Hussain IIHM, Nallusamy R, Pitisuttithum P, Rusmil K, Thisyakorn U, Thomas SJ, Huu Tran N, Wirawan DN, Yoon I-K, Bouckenooghe A, Hutagalung Y, Laot T, Wartel TA. Dengue and other common causes of acute febrile illness in Asia: an active surveillance study in children. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2013;7:e2331.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3723539</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23936565</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Philippines AFRIMS Virology Research Unit (PAVRU)  PAVRU Research Laboratory. 2015. http://pavru.afrims.org/ Available at. Accessed October 29, 2016.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hampson K, Coudeville L, Lembo T, Sambo M, Kieffer A, Attlan M, Barrat J, Blanton JD, Briggs DJ, Cleaveland S. Estimating the global burden of endemic canine rabies. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2015;9:e0003709.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4400070</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25881058</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>F&#xfc;rst T, Keiser J, Utzinger J. Global burden of human food-borne trematodiasis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet Infect Dis. 2012;12:210&#x2013;221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22108757</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Peabody JW, Shimkhada R, Tan C, Luck J. The burden of disease, economic costs and clinical consequences of tuberculosis in the Philippines. Health Policy Plan. 2005;20:347&#x2013;353.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16155066</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tiga DC, Undurraga EA, Ramos-Casta&#xf1;eda J, Mart&#xed;nez-Vega R, Tschampl CA, Shepard D. Persistent symptoms of dengue: estimates of the incremental disease and economic burden in Mexico. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2016;94:1085&#x2013;1089.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4856607</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26976885</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wilder-Smith A. Dengue vaccines: dawning at last? Lancet. 2014;384:1327&#x2013;1329.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25018119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Capeding MR, Tran NH, Hadinegoro SRS, Ismail HIHJM, Chotpitayasunondh T, Chua MN, Luong CQ, Rusmil K, Wirawan DN, Nallusamy R, Pitisuttithum P, Thisyakorn U, Yoon I-K, van der Vliet D, Langevin E, Laot T, Hutagalung Y, Frago C, Boaz M, Wartel TA, Tornieporth NG, Saville M, Bouckenooghe A. Clinical efficacy and safety of a novel tetravalent dengue vaccine in healthy children in Asia: a phase 3, randomised, observer-masked, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2014;384:1358&#x2013;1365.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25018116</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Villar L, Dayan GH, Arredondo-Garc&#xed;a JL, Rivera DM, Cunha R, Deseda C, Reynales H, Costa MS, Morales-Ram&#xed;rez JO, Carrasquilla G, Rey LC, Dietze R, Luz K, Rivas E, Montoya MCM, Supelano MC, Zambrano B, Langevin E, Boaz M, Tornieporth N, Saville M, Noriega F. Efficacy of a tetravalent dengue vaccine in children in Latin America. N Engl J Med. 2015;372:113&#x2013;123.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25365753</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barrett AD. Short-course oral corticosteroid therapy is not effective in early dengue infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2012;55:1225&#x2013;1226.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22865873</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Halstead SB. Dengue vascular permeability syndrome: what, no T cells? Clin Infect Dis. 2013;56:900&#x2013;901.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">23243186</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dow G, Mora E. The maximum potential market for dengue drugs V 1.0. Antiviral Res. 2012;96:203&#x2013;212.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22982015</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Erlanger TE, Keiser J, Utzinger J. Effect of dengue vector control interventions on entomological parameters in developing countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Med Vet Entomol. 2008;22:203&#x2013;221.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18816269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luz PM, Vanni T, Medlock J, Paltiel AD, Galvani AP. Dengue vector control strategies in an urban setting: an economic modelling assessment. Lancet. 2011;377:1673&#x2013;1680.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3409589</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21546076</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoffmann AA, Montgomery BL, Popovici J, Iturbe-Ormaetxe I, Johnson PH, Muzzi F, Greenfield M, Durkan M, Leong YS, Dong Y, Cook H, Axford J, Callahan AG, Kenny N, Omodei C, McGraw EA, Ryan PA, Ritchie SA, Turelli M, O'Neill SL. Successful establishment of Wolbachia in Aedes populations to suppress dengue transmission. Nature. 2011;476:454&#x2013;457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21866160</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Atkinson MP, Su Z, Alphey N, Alphey LS, Coleman PG, Wein LM. Analyzing the control of mosquito-borne diseases by a dominant lethal genetic system. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2007;104:9540&#x2013;9545.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1876161</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17519336</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>HDT/Sunnex . Three Regions Selected to Get Free Dengue Vaccines. Manila, Philippines: Sun Star; 2016.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>