<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedBookArticle><BookDocument><PMID Version="1">41066608</PMID><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="bookaccession">NBK618662</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.25302/08.2023.ME.2017C39337</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><Book><Publisher><PublisherName>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute (PCORI)</PublisherName><PublisherLocation>Washington (DC)</PublisherLocation></Publisher><BookTitle book="pcori823me2017c39337">Using Visual Methods to Apply Results from COVID-19 Related Randomized Controlled Trials to Patients Receiving Care at Clinics and Hospitals</BookTitle><PubDate><Year>2023</Year><Month>08</Month></PubDate><AuthorList Type="authors" CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Lund</LastName><ForeName>Jennifer L.</ForeName><Initials>JL</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Gillings School of Global Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of North Carolina Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Webster-Clark</LastName><ForeName>Michael A.</ForeName><Initials>MA</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Gillings School of Global Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Westreich</LastName><ForeName>Daniel</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Gillings School of Global Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sanoff</LastName><ForeName>Hanna K.</ForeName><Initials>HK</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of North Carolina Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>St&#xfc;rmer</LastName><ForeName>Til</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Gillings School of Global Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University of North Carolina Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Keil</LastName><ForeName>Alexander P.</ForeName><Initials>AP</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Epidemiology, Gillings School of Global Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><CollectionTitle book="pcoricollect">PCORI Final Research Reports</CollectionTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi">10.25302/08.2023.ME.2017C39337</ELocationID><Medium>Internet</Medium></Book><Language>eng</Language><PublicationType UI="D016454">Review</PublicationType><Abstract><AbstractText Label="MAIN STUDY">BACKGROUND: Randomized controlled trials (RCTs) are the gold standard for assessing treatment efficacy because their design optimizes internal validity. Participants of these trials are often not representative of patients for whom treatment is delivered in practice, however, so external validity is reduced. Early implementation in patient-centered outcomes research (PCOR) and comparative-effectiveness research (CER) has largely ignored differences in the characteristics of the populations in trial and target population and how care is delivered in these settings. Hybrid studies use data from both trials and real-world practice. This design takes advantage of randomization, thus preserving internal validity, but incorporates real-world (or observational) data, thus enhancing external validity. In addition, little practical guidance exists for implementation by applied researchers. OBJECTIVES: Emerging epidemiologic and statistical methods can address some of these issues regarding external validity, but they have not been combined, and their dissemination and uptake in applied and clinical settings are limited. To further the dissemination of these methods, we developed PCOR/CER guidance for designing and analyzing hybrid studies to extend inferences from trials to target populations using data visualization and flexible analytic methods. METHODS: We used a motivating example evaluating the comparative effectiveness (on all-cause mortality) and safety (on treatment-related paresthesia&#x2014;or numbness in the extremities) of adjuvant chemotherapy options (oxaliplatin plus 5-fluorouracil [5-FU] and leucovorin [FOLFOX] vs 5-FU + leucovorin [5-FU+LV]) for stage II to III colon cancer using data from a phase 3 trial (Multicenter International Study of Oxaliplatin/5-Fluorouracil/Leucovorin in the Adjuvant Treatment of Colon Cancer [MOSAIC]) and electronic health records from community oncology practices (the US Oncology Network). We generated guidance for using visualization to characterize target populations (aim 1) and therapy adherence (aim 2) relative to a trial population. We also introduced an analytic approach to combine sampling weights with flexible outcome modeling (ie, parametric g-formula) to compare the effectiveness of adjuvant chemotherapy under various adherence scenarios (aim 3). RESULTS: In aim 1 (characterizing differences in trial and target population composition), we introduced 4 visualizations to guide the evaluation of variables to extend treatment effects from trials to real-world practice. We applied these in our motivating example of colon cancer treatment. The first visualization demonstrated that the treatment effect from the MOSAIC trial could be extended to the US Oncology Network population using a smaller variable set than specified in a directed acyclic graph. The second visualization showed that the US Oncology Network target populations had sufficient similarity to the MOSAIC trial with respect to measured covariates to enable an extension of treatment effects. The third and fourth visualizations highlighted considerations for sampling model misspecification and potentially influential observations. In aim 2, we developed longitudinal cumulative dose (LCD), a measure integrating chemotherapy dose reductions, missed doses, and dose delays over time. For patients in MOSAIC and the US Oncology Network, we calculated the LCD&#x2014;the fraction of the final standard dose a participant reached by a given day&#x2014;for each participant and compared oxaliplatin LCD over time and at 24 weeks between the trial and real-world populations. Delivery of oxaliplatin differed across populations. Although the median and IQRs of oxaliplatin LCD were similar through day 133, differences emerged after this point (&#x3b1; = .05). At day 250, the median LCD was 10.2% (95% CI, 7.7%-13.4%) lower among US Oncology Network patients than among MOSAIC participants, translating to an average of approximately 1.2 fewer cycles of oxaliplatin cumulatively. In aim 3, we demonstrated the use of the parametric g-formula for estimating effects of treatment in hybrid studies. We applied this approach for regimens included in the trial (ie, 12 cycles of FOLFOX vs 12 cycles of 5-FU+LV) and regimens that deviated from the trial (6 cycles of FOLFOX vs 12 cycles of 5-FU+LV). We reviewed the set of necessary assumptions for extending regimen effects that were and were not addressed in the trial. We balanced distributions of potential effect measure modifiers in the trial and target populations by using sampling weights. Treating patients with FOLFOX for 12 cycles was associated with the lowest overall mortality but the highest prevalence of treatment-related paresthesia, whereas a 6-cycle regimen was associated with slightly higher mortality but substantially lower paresthesia prevalence. CONCLUSIONS: This study provided guidance for designing and analyzing hybrid studies using individual-level data from both trials and observational settings to evaluate PCOR/CER questions. By generating internally and externally valid estimates of therapy effectiveness in real-world practice, these results will inform the evidence base for clinical and policy decision-making. LIMITATIONS: As in all observational analyses, the parametric g-formula approach (aim 3) assumes that all factors related to the outcome that also predict treatment continuation are captured and accurately measured (ie, an assumption of no unmeasured confounding). This study compared the effectiveness of cancer therapies; the approach outlined may require refinement for other disease settings.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="COVID-19 SUBSTUDY">BACKGROUND: Researchers worldwide have continued to search for ways to fight COVID-19. Although in vitro work, animal subjects research, and observational studies in humans can help identify interventions worthy of further inquiry, the gold standard for assessing treatment efficacy is the RCT. Unfortunately, enrolling participants in RCTs for treating pandemics such as COVID-19 is difficult and often leads to nonrepresentative study populations. OBJECTIVES: The objective of the COVID-19 substudy was to generate timely information about the representativeness and generalizability of COVID-19-related clinical trials. METHODS: We conducted a systematic literature review of COVID-19 trials, extracted patient characteristics, and summarized findings on the types of variables reported in published manuscripts (aim 1). After collecting these data, we also expanded visualizations developed in the main methods study to show differences among the sex, age, and race distributions of patients with COVID-19 in RCTs and a potential target population of North Carolina adults recorded by the North Carolina Department of Health and Human Services both over the entire pandemic and during specific times (early vs late pandemic) (aim 2). RESULTS: We identified 137 manuscripts covering 149 trials investigating COVID-19 interventions. The regions most often included in the 137 studies were Asia (n = 42), North America (n = 26), and the Middle East (n = 26). Most of the 149 trials studied potential treatments (n = 113), and fewer studied vaccines (n = 29), prophylaxis (n = 5), or transmission (n = 1). Study populations ranged from 10 to 38 206 participants. Age (n = 149) and sex (n = 147) were consistently reported for trials but not race (n = 50), comorbidities (n = 97 for diabetes, n = 80 for hypertension, n = 31 for asthma), or nonracial markers of socioeconomic status (n = 2). When using visualizations to contrast the trial populations to North Carolina patients diagnosed with COVID-19, the trials appeared to systematically underrepresent women and Black people; differences in age were more complex. CONCLUSIONS: During the first 15 months of the COVID-19 pandemic, RCTs focused primarily on treating patients with COVID-19. Although age and sex were commonly documented in trial population, race and several comorbidities were rarely reported, and information about socioeconomic status was extremely rare; with information this limited, strong assumptions about uniform treatment effects across racial groups would be required to generalize or transport the results. Within the studies that reported information about age, sex, and race, the usual issues with underenrollment of ethnic minority and less advantaged populations recognized in other RCTs appeared to persist. LIMITATIONS: Despite our efforts to include as many COVID-19-related trials as possible, we were able to document only the results of studies that published their findings in academic journals or on ClinicalTrials.gov; it is likely that many other trials were conducted that failed to reach the reporting step because of futility or procedural problems, and it is unlikely that the published trials represent a completely random sample of all trials. The limited reporting of race information within the trials also made it difficult to draw final conclusions about the representativeness of the trials as a whole, even if we limit ourselves to studies occurring within the United States or North America, locations that are most likely to include information about race.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>Copyright &#xa9; 2023. The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. All Rights Reserved.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract></BookDocument><PubmedBookData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2023</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">41066608</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></PubmedBookData></PubmedBookArticle></PubmedArticleSet>