<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="PubMed-not-MEDLINE" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">31984365</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>24</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic-eCollection"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">2574-2531</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>2</Volume><Issue>3</Issue><PubDate><Year>2019</Year><Month>Oct</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>JAMIA open</Title><ISOAbbreviation>JAMIA Open</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Detecting reports of unsafe foods in consumer product reviews.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>330</StartPage><EndPage>338</EndPage><MedlinePgn>330-338</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1093/jamiaopen/ooz030</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Access to safe and nutritious food is essential for good health. However, food can become unsafe due to contamination with pathogens, chemicals or toxins, or mislabeling of allergens. Illness resulting from the consumption of unsafe foods is a global health problem. Here, we develop a machine learning approach for detecting reports of unsafe food products in consumer product reviews from Amazon.com.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="MATERIALS AND METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">We linked Amazon.com food product reviews to Food and Drug Administration (FDA) food recalls from 2012 to 2014 using text matching approaches in a PostGres relational database. We applied machine learning methods and over- and under-sampling methods to the linked data to automate the detection of reports of unsafe food products.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">Our data consisted of 1 297 156 product reviews from Amazon.com. Only 5149 (0.4%) were linked to recalled food products. Bidirectional Encoder Representation from Transformations performed best in identifying unsafe food reviews, achieving an F1 score, precision and recall of 0.74, 0.78, and 0.71, respectively. We also identified synonyms for terms associated with FDA recalls in more than 20 000 reviews, most of which were associated with nonrecalled products. This might suggest that many more products should have been recalled or investigated.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Challenges to improving food safety include, urbanization which has led to a longer food chain, underreporting of illness and difficulty in linking contaminated food to illness. Our approach can improve food safety by enabling early identification of unsafe foods which can lead to timely recall thereby limiting the health and economic impact on the public.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the American Medical Informatics Association.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Maharana</LastName><ForeName>Adyasha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biomedical Informatics and Medical Education, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Cai</LastName><ForeName>Kunlin</ForeName><Initials>K</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, Boston University, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hellerstein</LastName><ForeName>Joseph</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>eScience Institute, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hswen</LastName><ForeName>Yulin</ForeName><Initials>Y</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Computational Epidemiology Lab, Harvard Medical School, Boston MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Innovation Program, Boston Children's Hospital, Boston MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Social and Behavioral Sciences, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Boston MA, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Munsell</LastName><ForeName>Michael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Economics, Brandeis University, Waltham, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Staneva</LastName><ForeName>Valentina</ForeName><Initials>V</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>eScience Institute, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Verma</LastName><ForeName>Miki</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Applied and Computational Mathematical Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vint</LastName><ForeName>Cynthia</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Computer and Information Systems, Boston University, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Wijaya</LastName><ForeName>Derry</ForeName><Initials>D</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Computer Science, Boston University, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nsoesie</LastName><ForeName>Elaine O</ForeName><Initials>EO</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Global Health, Boston University School of Public Health, Boston, Massachusetts, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2019</Year><Month>08</Month><Day>05</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>JAMIA Open</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101730643</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>2574-2531</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">artificial intelligence</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">consumer product safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food and drug administration</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">food safety</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">machine learning</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2019</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2019</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>27</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2019</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2020</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2020</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2020</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>28</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>1</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2019</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>5</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31984365</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6951857</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1093/jamiaopen/ooz030</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">ooz030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Zhang P, Penner K, Johnston J.. Prevalence of selected unsafe food&#x2010;consumption practices and their associated factors in kansas. J Food Saf 1999; 194: 289&#x2013;97.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Story L. Lead paint prompts Mattel to recall 967, 000 toys. <i>The New York Times.</i>2007: 2.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>
Story L, Barboza D. Mattel recalls 19 million toys sent from China. <i>The New York Times.</i>2007: 15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teagarden MB, Hinrichs MA.. Learning from toys: reflections on the 2007 recall crisis. Thunderbird Int Bus Rev 2009; 511: 5&#x2013;17.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vierk KA, Koehler KM, Fein SB, et al. Prevalence of self-reported food allergy in American adults and use of food labels. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2007; 1196: 1504&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17451802</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>FARE. <i>Food Labeling Issues</i>
2018. 
https://www.foodallergy.org/life-with-food-allergies/newly-diagnosed/food-labeling-issues. Accessed December 14, 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malyukova I, Gendel S, Luccioli S.. Milk is the predominant undeclared allergen in US food product recalls. J Allergy Clin Immunol 2012; 1292: AB234.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gendel SM, Zhu J.. Analysis of US Food and Drug Administration food allergen recalls after implementation of the food allergen labeling and consumer protection act. J Food Prot 2013; 7611: 1933&#x2013;8.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24215698</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Teratanavat R, Hooker NH.. Understanding the characteristics of US meat and poultry recalls: 1994&#x2013;2002. Food Control 2004; 155: 359&#x2013;67.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gorton A, Stasiewicz MJ.. Twenty-two years of US meat and poultry product recalls: implications for food safety and food waste. J Food Prot 2017; 804: 674&#x2013;84.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28294687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bennett SD, Sodha SV, Ayers TL, et al. Produce-associated foodborne disease outbreaks, USA, 1998&#x2013;2013. Epidemiol Infect 2018; 146: 1397&#x2013;406.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9133681</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29923474</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Multistate Outbreak of E. coli O157:H7 Infections Linked to Romaine Lettuce (FINAL UPDATE). March 23, 2012. https://www.cdc.gov/ecoli/2011/romaine-lettace-3-23-12.html (Accessed: July 17, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Todd ECD, Harris CK, Knight AJ.. Spinach and the media: how we learn about a major outbreak. Food Prot Trends 2007; 27: 314&#x2013;21.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lang S. Effects of food recalls on retailers&#xe3; stock price. 2018. Cornell University (Thesis). https://ecommons.cornell.edu/handle/1813/60163. (Accessed July 17, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavallaro E, Date K, Medus C, et al. Salmonella typhimurium infections associated with peanut products. N Engl J Med 2011; 3657: 601&#x2013;10.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">21848461</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Powell DA, Jacob CJ, Chapman BJ.. Enhancing food safety culture to reduce rates of foodborne illness. Food Control 2011; 226: 817&#x2013;22.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Multistate Outbreak of Human Salmonella Enteritidis Infections Associated with Shell Eggs. August 27, 2010. https://www.cdc.gov/salmonella/enteritidis/archive/082710.html (Accessed July 17, 2019).</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuehn BM. Salmonella cases traced to egg producers. JAMA 2010; 30412: 1316..</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20858872</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laestadius LI, Lagasse LP, Smith KC, et al. Print news coverage of the 2010 Iowa egg recall: addressing bad eggs and poor oversight. Food Policy 2012; 376: 751&#x2013;9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nyachuba DG. Foodborne illness: is it on the rise? Nutr Rev 2010; 685: 257&#x2013;69.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20500787</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scharff RL. Economic burden from health losses due to foodborne illness in the United States. J Food Prot 2012; 751: 123&#x2013;31.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22221364</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Doyle MP, Erickson MC, Alali W, et al. The food industry&#x2019;s current and future role in preventing microbial foodborne illness within the United States. Clin Infect Dis 2015; 61: 252&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25824814</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kramer MN, Coto D, Weidner JD.. The science of recalls. Meat Sci 2005; 711: 158&#x2013;63.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22064061</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA). Responding to a Food Recall Procedures for Recalls of USDA Foods. 06/24/2014. https://www.fns.usda.gov/responding-food-recall-procedures-recalls-usda-foods (Accessed July 17, 2019)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amazon data source. http://jmcauley.ucsd.edu/data/amazon/links.html. (Accessed July 17, 2019)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McAuley J, Pandey R, Leskovec J. Inferring networks of substitutable and complementary products. In: Proceedings of the 21th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining; 2015; ACM: 785&#x2013;94.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mining Online Data for Early Identification of Unsafe Food Products. GitHub Repository. https://github.com/uwescience/DSSG2016-UnsafeFoods. (Accessed July 17, 2019)</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ding C, Li T, Peng W. Nonnegative matrix factorization and probabilistic latent semantic indexing: equivalence chi-square statistic, and a hybrid method. In: AAAI. 2006;42:137&#x2013;43.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Friedman J, Hastie T, Tibshirani R, 2001. The elements of statistical learning (Vol. 1, No. 10). New York: Springer series in statistics.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chawla NV, Bowyer KW, Hall LO, et al. SMOTE: synthetic minority over-sampling technique. J Artif Intell Res 2002; 16: 321&#x2013;57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Devlin J, Chang M-W, Lee K, et al. Bert: pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers for language understanding. arXiv preprint arXiv: 181004805; 2018.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. WHO estimates of the global burden of foodborne diseases: foodborne disease burden epidemiology reference group 2007&#x2013;2015 [cited 2016 Feb 8]. World Health Organization, 2015.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO. <i>WHO Food Safety. World Health Organization</i> https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/food-safety. Accessed February 6, 2019.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kirk MD, Pires SM, Black RE, et al. World Health Organization estimates of the global and regional disease burden of 22 foodborne bacterial, protozoal, and viral diseases, 2010: a data synthesis. PLoS Med 2015; 12: 1&#x2013;21.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4668831</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">26633831</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harris JK, Mansour R, Choucair B, et al. Health department use of social media to identify foodborne illness-Chicago, Illinois, 2013-2014. Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2014; 63: 681&#x2013;685.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4584908</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25121710</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jenine K, Harris JBH, Nguyen L, et al. Using twitter to identify and respond to food poisoning: The Food Safety STL Project. J Public Health Manag Pract 2017; 23: 577&#x2013;580.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5540821</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28166175</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Harrison C, Jorder M, Stern H, et al. Using online reviews by restaurant patrons to identify unreported cases of foodborne illness-New York City, 2012-2013. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep 2014; 63: 441&#x2013;445.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4584915</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">24848215</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Henly S, Tuli G, Kluberg SA, et al. Disparities in digital reporting of illness: a demographic and socioeconomic assessment. Prev Med 2017; 101: 18&#x2013;22.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5553633</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28528170</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cesare N, Grant C, Hawkins JB, et al. demographics in social media data for public health research: does it matter? arXiv preprint arXiv: 171011048; 2017.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nsoesie EO, Kluberg SA, Brownstein JS.. Online reports of foodborne illness capture foods implicated in official foodborne outbreak reports. Prev Med 2014; 67: 264&#x2013;9.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC4167574</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25124281</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Quade P, Nsoesie EO.. A platform for crowdsourced foodborne illness surveillance: description of users and reports. JMIR Public Health Surveill 2017; 33: e42.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC5517822</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">28679492</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sadilek A, Caty S, DiPrete L, et al. Machine-learned epidemiology: real-time detection of foodborne illness at scale. Npj Digital Med 2018; 11: 36.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC6550174</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">31304318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>