<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">20098724</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2010</Year><Month>03</Month><Day>01</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2026</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>21</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1549-1676</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>7</Volume><Issue>1</Issue><PubDate><Year>2010</Year><Month>Jan</Month><Day>19</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>PLoS medicine</Title><ISOAbbreviation>PLoS Med</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>The relationship between anti-merozoite antibodies and incidence of Plasmodium falciparum malaria: A systematic review and meta-analysis.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e1000218</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e1000218</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">e1000218</ELocationID><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000218</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND" NlmCategory="BACKGROUND">One of the criteria to objectively prioritize merozoite antigens for malaria vaccine development is the demonstration that naturally acquired antibodies are associated with protection from malaria. However, published evidence of the protective effect of these antibodies is conflicting.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS AND FINDINGS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">We performed a systematic review with meta-analysis of prospective cohort studies examining the association between anti-merozoite immunoglobin (Ig) G responses and incidence of Plasmodium falciparum malaria. Two independent researchers searched six databases and identified 33 studies that met predefined inclusion and quality criteria, including a rigorous definition of symptomatic malaria. We found that only five studies were performed outside sub-Saharan Africa and that there was a deficiency in studies investigating antibodies to leading vaccine candidates merozoite surface protein (MSP)-1(42) and erythrocyte binding antigen (EBA)-175. Meta-analyses of most-studied antigens were conducted to obtain summary estimates of the association between antibodies and incidence of P. falciparum malaria. The largest effect was observed with IgG to MSP-3 C terminus and MSP-1(19) (responders versus nonresponders, 54%, 95% confidence interval [CI] [33%-68%] and 18% [4%-30%] relative reduction in risk, respectively) and there was evidence of a dose-response relationship. A tendency towards protective risk ratios (RR&lt;1) was also observed for individual study estimates for apical membrane antigen (AMA)-1 and glutamate-rich protein (GLURP)-R0. Pooled estimates showed limited evidence of a protective effect for antibodies to MSP-1 N-terminal regions or MSP-1-EGF (epidermal growth factor-like modules). There was no significant evidence for the protective effect for MSP-2 (responders versus nonresponders pooled RR, MSP-2(FC27) 0.82, 95% CI 0.62-1.08, p = 0.16 and MSP-2(3D7) 0.92, 95% CI 0.75-1.13, p = 0.43). Heterogeneity, in terms of clinical and methodological diversity between studies, was an important issue in the meta-analysis of IgG responses to merozoite antigens.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">These findings are valuable for advancing vaccine development by providing evidence supporting merozoite antigens as targets of protective immunity in humans, and to help identify antigens that confer protection from malaria. Further prospective cohort studies that include a larger number of lead antigens and populations outside Africa are greatly needed to ensure generalizability of results. The reporting of results needs to be standardized to maximize comparability of studies. We therefore propose a set of guidelines to facilitate the uniform reporting of malaria immuno-epidemiology observational studies. Please see later in the article for the Editors' Summary.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fowkes</LastName><ForeName>Freya J I</ForeName><Initials>FJ</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>The Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research, Parkville, Victoria, Australia.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Richards</LastName><ForeName>Jack S</ForeName><Initials>JS</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Simpson</LastName><ForeName>Julie A</ForeName><Initials>JA</Initials></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Beeson</LastName><ForeName>James G</ForeName><Initials>JG</Initials></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D017418">Meta-Analysis</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D013485">Research Support, Non-U.S. Gov't</PublicationType><PublicationType UI="D000078182">Systematic Review</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2010</Year><Month>01</Month><Day>19</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>PLoS Med</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>101231360</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>1549-1277</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000913">Antibodies, Protozoan</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D000953">Antigens, Protozoan</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D017780">Malaria Vaccines</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D015800">Protozoan Proteins</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000913" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Protozoan</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000097" MajorTopicYN="Y">blood</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000953" MajorTopicYN="N">Antigens, Protozoan</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015195" MajorTopicYN="N">Drug Design</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D019317" MajorTopicYN="N">Evidence-Based Medicine</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015994" MajorTopicYN="N">Incidence</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D017780" MajorTopicYN="N">Malaria Vaccines</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016778" MajorTopicYN="N">Malaria, Falciparum</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000175" MajorTopicYN="N">diagnosis</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="N">immunology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000517" MajorTopicYN="N">prevention &amp; control</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D052940" MajorTopicYN="N">Merozoites</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D010963" MajorTopicYN="N">Plasmodium falciparum</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D015800" MajorTopicYN="N">Protozoan Proteins</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000276" MajorTopicYN="Y">immunology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><CoiStatement>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2009</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2009</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>11</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>26</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2010</Year><Month>3</Month><Day>2</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2010</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>19</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>epublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20098724</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2808214</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000218</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Marsh K, Kinyanjui S. Immune effector mechanisms in malaria. Parasite Immunol. 2006;28:51&#x2013;60.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16438676</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen S, Mc GI, Carrington S. Gamma-globulin and acquired immunity to human malaria. Nature. 1961;192:733&#x2013;737.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">13880318</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sabchareon A, Burnouf T, Ouattara D, Attanath P, Bouharoun-Tayoun H, et al. Parasitologic and clinical human response to immunoglobulin administration in falciparum malaria. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 1991;45:297&#x2013;308.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">1928564</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cohen S, Butcher GA, Crandall RB. Action of malarial antibody in vitro. Nature. 1969;223:368&#x2013;371.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4980851</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Brown GV, Anders RF, Mitchell GF, Heywood PF. Target antigens of purified human immunoglobulins which inhibit growth of Plasmodium falciparum in vitro. Nature. 1982;297:591&#x2013;593.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7045680</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>McCallum FJ, Persson KE, Mugyenyi CK, Fowkes FJ, Simpson JA, et al.  Acquisition of growth-inhibitory antibodies against blood-stage Plasmodium falciparum. PLoS One. 2008;3:e3571. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0003571.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003571</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2570221</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18958278</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bouharoun-Tayoun H, Attanath P, Sabchareon A, Chongsuphajaisiddhi T, Druilhe P. Antibodies that protect humans against Plasmodium falciparum blood stages do not on their own inhibit parasite growth and invasion in vitro, but act in cooperation with monocytes. J Exp Med. 1990;172:1633&#x2013;1641.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2188756</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2258697</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hodder AN, Crewther PE, Anders RF. Specificity of the protective antibody response to apical membrane antigen 1. Infect Immun. 2001;69:3286&#x2013;3294.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC98287</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11292751</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaur D, Mayer DC, Miller LH. Parasite ligand-host receptor interactions during invasion of erythrocytes by Plasmodium merozoites. Int J Parasitol. 2004;34:1413&#x2013;1429.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15582519</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>O'Donnell RA, de Koning-Ward TF, Burt RA, Bockarie M, Reeder JC, et al. Antibodies against merozoite surface protein (MSP)-1(19) are a major component of the invasion-inhibitory response in individuals immune to malaria. J Exp Med. 2001;193:1403&#x2013;1412.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2193299</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11413195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Clark JT, Donachie S, Anand R, Wilson CF, Heidrich HG, et al. 46&#x2013;53 kilodalton glycoprotein from the surface of Plasmodium falciparum merozoites. Mol Biochem Parasitol. 1989;32:15&#x2013;24.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2643035</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Oeuvray C, Bouharoun-Tayoun H, Gras-Masse H, Bottius E, Kaidoh T, et al. Merozoite surface protein-3: a malaria protein inducing antibodies that promote Plasmodium falciparum killing by cooperation with blood monocytes. Blood. 1994;84:1594&#x2013;1602.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8068948</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Theisen M, Soe S, Oeuvray C, Thomas AW, Vuust J, et al. The glutamate-rich protein (GLURP) of Plasmodium falciparum is a target for antibody-dependent monocyte-mediated inhibition of parasite growth in vitro. Infect Immun. 1998;66:11&#x2013;17.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC107852</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9423833</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dutta S, Haynes JD, Moch JK, Barbosa A, Lanar DE. Invasion-inhibitory antibodies inhibit proteolytic processing of apical membrane antigen 1 of Plasmodium falciparum merozoites. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2003;100:12295&#x2013;12300.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC218752</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14526103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Persson KE, McCallum FJ, Reiling L, Lister NA, Stubbs J, et al. Variation in use of erythrocyte invasion pathways by Plasmodium falciparum mediates evasion of human inhibitory antibodies. J Clin Invest. 2008;118:342&#x2013;351.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2117763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18064303</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cowman AF, Crabb BS. Invasion of red blood cells by malaria parasites. Cell. 2006;124:755&#x2013;766.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16497586</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Richards JS, Beeson JG. The future for blood-stage vaccines against malaria. Immunol Cell Biol. 2009;87:377&#x2013;390.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19417768</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gupta S, Snow RW, Donnelly CA, Marsh K, Newbold C. Immunity to non-cerebral severe malaria is acquired after one or two infections. Nat Med. 1999;5:340&#x2013;343.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10086393</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stroup DF, Berlin JA, Morton SC, Olkin I, Williamson GD, et al. Meta-analysis of observational studies in epidemiology: a proposal for reporting. Meta-analysis Of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (MOOSE) group. JAMA. 2000;283:2008&#x2013;2012.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10789670</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Severe and complicated malaria. World Health Organization, Division of Control of Tropical Diseases. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 1990;84(Suppl 2):1&#x2013;65.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">2219249</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. Severe falciparum malaria. World Health Organization, Communicable Diseases Cluster. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 2000;94(Suppl 1):S1&#x2013;S90.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11103309</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egger M, Smith GD, Phillips AN. Meta-analysis: principles and procedures. BMJ. 1997;315:1533&#x2013;1537.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2127925</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9432252</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang J, Yu KF. What's the relative risk? A method of correcting the odds ratio in cohort studies of common outcomes. JAMA. 1998;280:1690&#x2013;1691.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9832001</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Higgins JP, Thompson SG, Deeks JJ, Altman DG. Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses. BMJ. 2003;327:557&#x2013;560.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC192859</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12958120</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ioannidis JP, Patsopoulos NA, Evangelou E. Uncertainty in heterogeneity estimates in meta-analyses. BMJ. 2007;335:914&#x2013;916.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2048840</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17974687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sterne JA, Egger M. Funnel plots for detecting bias in meta-analysis: guidelines on choice of axis. J Clin Epidemiol. 2001;54:1046&#x2013;1055.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11576817</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egger M, Davey Smith G, Schneider M, Minder C. Bias in meta-analysis detected by a simple, graphical test. BMJ. 1997;315:629&#x2013;634.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2127453</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9310563</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Meraldi V, Nebie I, Tiono AB, Diallo D, Sanogo E, et al. Natural antibody response to Plasmodium falciparum Exp-1, MSP-3 and GLURP long synthetic peptides and association with protection. Parasite Immunol. 2004;26:265&#x2013;272.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15541030</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nebie I, Diarra A, Ouedraogo A, Soulama I, Bougouma EC, et al. Humoral responses to Plasmodium falciparum blood-stage antigens and association with incidence of clinical malaria in children living in an area of seasonal malaria transmission in Burkina Faso, West Africa. Infect Immun. 2008;76:759&#x2013;766.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2223475</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18070896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Nebie I, Tiono AB, Diallo DA, Samandoulougou S, Diarra A, et al. Do antibody responses to malaria vaccine candidates influenced by the level of malaria transmission protect from malaria? Trop Med Int Health. 2008;13:229&#x2013;237.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18304269</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Conway DJ, Cavanagh DR, Tanabe K, Roper C, Mikes ZS, et al. A principal target of human immunity to malaria identified by molecular population genetic and immunological analyses. Nat Med. 2000;6:689&#x2013;692.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10835687</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polley SD, Tetteh KK, Cavanagh DR, Pearce RJ, Lloyd JM, et al. Repeat sequences in block 2 of Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 are targets of antibodies associated with protection from malaria. Infect Immun. 2003;71:1833&#x2013;1842.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC152097</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">12654798</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Metzger WG, Okenu DM, Cavanagh DR, Robinson JV, Bojang KA, et al. Serum IgG3 to the Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 2 is strongly associated with a reduced prospective risk of malaria. Parasite Immunol. 2003;25:307&#x2013;312.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14507328</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polley SD, Tetteh KK, Lloyd JM, Akpogheneta OJ, Greenwood BM, et al. Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 3 is a target of allele-specific immunity and alleles are maintained by natural selection. J Infect Dis. 2007;195:279&#x2013;287.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17191173</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dziegiel M, Rowe P, Bennett S, Allen SJ, Olerup O, et al. Immunoglobulin M and G antibody responses to Plasmodium falciparum glutamate-rich protein: correlation with clinical immunity in Gambian children. Infect Immun. 1993;61:103&#x2013;108.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC302693</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8418032</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egan AF, Morris J, Barnish G, Allen S, Greenwood BM, et al. Clinical immunity to Plasmodium falciparum malaria is associated with serum antibodies to the 19-kDa C-terminal fragment of the merozoite surface antigen, PfMSP-1. J Infect Dis. 1996;173:765&#x2013;769.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8627050</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Taylor RR, Allen SJ, Greenwood BM, Riley EM. IgG3 antibodies to Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 2 (MSP2): increasing prevalence with age and association with clinical immunity to malaria. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 1998;58:406&#x2013;413.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9574783</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okenu DM, Riley EM, Bickle QD, Agomo PU, Barbosa A, et al. Analysis of human antibodies to erythrocyte binding antigen 175 of Plasmodium falciparum. Infect Immun. 2000;68:5559&#x2013;5566.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC101506</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10992454</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Okech BA, Corran PH, Todd J, Joynson-Hicks A, Uthaipibull C, et al. Fine specificity of serum antibodies to Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein, PfMSP-1(19), predicts protection from malaria infection and high-density parasitemia. Infect Immun. 2004;72:1557&#x2013;1567.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC356041</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14977962</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gray JC, Corran PH, Mangia E, Gaunt MW, Li Q, et al. Profiling the antibody immune response against blood stage malaria vaccine candidates. Clin Chem. 2007;53:1244&#x2013;1253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17510307</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodoo D, Theander TG, Kurtzhals JA, Koram K, Riley E, et al. Levels of antibody to conserved parts of Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 in Ghanaian children are not associated with protection from clinical malaria. Infect Immun. 1999;67:2131&#x2013;2137.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC115948</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10225865</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodoo D, Theisen M, Kurtzhals JA, Akanmori BD, Koram KA, et al. Naturally acquired antibodies to the glutamate-rich protein are associated with protection against Plasmodium falciparum malaria. J Infect Dis. 2000;181:1202&#x2013;1205.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10720556</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cavanagh DR, Dodoo D, Hviid L, Kurtzhals JA, Theander TG, et al. Antibodies to the N-terminal block 2 of Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 are associated with protection against clinical malaria. Infect Immun. 2004;72:6492&#x2013;6502.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC522997</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15501780</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dodoo D, Aikins A, Asamoah Kusi K, Lamptey H, Remarque E, et al. Cohort study of the association of antibody levels to AMA1, MSP119, MSP3 and GLURP with protection from clinical malaria in Ghanaian children. Malar J. 2008;7:142.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2529305</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18664257</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polley SD, Mwangi T, Kocken CH, Thomas AW, Dutta S, et al. Human antibodies to recombinant protein constructs of Plasmodium falciparum Apical Membrane Antigen 1 (AMA1) and their associations with protection from malaria. Vaccine. 2004;23:718&#x2013;728.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15542195</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Polley SD, Conway DJ, Cavanagh DR, McBride JS, Lowe BS, et al. High levels of serum antibodies to merozoite surface protein 2 of Plasmodium falciparum are associated with reduced risk of clinical malaria in coastal Kenya. Vaccine. 2006;24:4233&#x2013;4246.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16111789</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osier FH, Polley SD, Mwangi T, Lowe B, Conway DJ, et al. Naturally acquired antibodies to polymorphic and conserved epitopes of Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 3. Parasite Immunol. 2007;29:387&#x2013;394.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1976398</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17650180</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Yaman F, Genton B, Anders R, Taraika J, Ginny M, et al. Assessment of the role of the humoral response to Plasmodium falciparum MSP2 compared to RESA and SPf66 in protecting Papua New Guinean children from clinical malaria. Parasite Immunol. 1995;17:493&#x2013;501.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8552419</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Al-Yaman F, Genton B, Kramer K, Chang S, Hui G, et al. Assessment of the role of naturally acquired antibody levels to Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein-1 in protecting Papa New Guinean children from malaria morbidity. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 1996;54:443&#x2013;448.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8644896</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perraut R, Marrama L, Diouf B, Sokhna C, Tall A, et al. Antibodies to the conserved C-terminal domain of the Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 and to the merozoite extract and their relationship with in vitro inhibitory antibodies and protection against clinical malaria in a Senegalese village. J Infect Dis. 2005;191:264&#x2013;271.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15609237</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lusingu JP, Vestergaard LS, Alifrangis M, Mmbando BP, Theisen M, et al. Cytophilic antibodies to Plasmodium falciparum glutamate rich protein are associated with malaria protection in an area of holoendemic transmission. Malar J. 2005;4:48.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC1262760</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16194274</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John CC, O'Donnell RA, Sumba PO, Moormann AM, de Koning-Ward TF, et al. Evidence that invasion-inhibitory antibodies specific for the 19-kDa fragment of merozoite surface protein-1 (MSP-1 19) can play a protective role against blood-stage Plasmodium falciparum infection in individuals in a malaria endemic area of Africa. J Immunol. 2004;173:666&#x2013;672.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15210830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>John CC, Moormann AM, Pregibon DC, Sumba PO, McHugh MM, et al. Correlation of high levels of antibodies to multiple pre-erythrocytic Plasmodium falciparum antigens and protection from infection. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2005;73:222&#x2013;228.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16014863</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tolle R, Fruh K, Doumbo O, Koita O, N'Diaye M, et al. A prospective study of the association between the human humoral immune response to Plasmodium falciparum blood stage antigen gp190 and control of malarial infections. Infect Immun. 1993;61:40&#x2013;47.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC302685</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8418064</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stanisic DI, Richards JS, McCallum FJ, Michon P, King CL, et al. IgG subclass-specific responses against Plasmodium falciparum merozoite antigens are associated with control of parasitemia and protection from symptomatic illness. Infect Immun. 2009;77:1165&#x2013;1174.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2643653</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19139189</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Perraut R, Marrama L, Diouf B, Fontenille D, Tall A, et al. Distinct surrogate markers for protection against Plasmodium falciparum infection and clinical malaria identified in a Senegalese community after radical drug cure. J Infect Dis. 2003;188:1940&#x2013;1950.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">14673775</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Richie TL, Stowers A, Nhan DH, Coppel RL. Naturally acquired antibody responses to Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 4 in a population living in an area of endemicity in Vietnam. Infect Immun. 2001;69:4390&#x2013;4397.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC98511</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">11401978</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scopel KK, da Silva-Nunes M, Malafronte RS, Braga EM, Ferreira MU. Variant-specific antibodies to merozoite surface protein 2 and clinical expression of Plasmodium falciparum malaria in rural Amazonians. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2007;76:1084&#x2013;1091.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17556615</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Osier FH, Fegan G, Polley SD, Murungi L, Verra F, et al. Breadth and magnitude of antibody responses to multiple Plasmodium falciparum merozoite antigens are associated with protection from clinical malaria. Infect Immun. 2008;76:2240&#x2013;2248.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2346713</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18316390</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sarr JB, Pelleau S, Toly C, Guitard J, Konate L, et al. Impact of red blood cell polymorphisms on the antibody response to Plasmodium falciparum in Senegal. Microbes Infect. 2006;8:1260&#x2013;1268.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">16679042</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Koussis K, Withers-Martinez C, Yeoh S, Child M, Hackett F, et al. A multifunctional serine protease primes the malaria parasite for red blood cell invasion. Embo J. 2009;28:725&#x2013;735.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2647770</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19214190</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huber W, Felger I, Matile H, Lipps HJ, Steiger S, et al. Limited sequence polymorphism in the Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 3. Mol Biochem Parasitol. 1997;87:231&#x2013;234.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">9247935</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hu J, Chen Z, Gu J, Wan M, Shen Q, et al.  Safety and immunogenicity of a malaria vaccine, Plasmodium falciparum AMA-1/MSP-1 chimeric protein formulated in montanide ISA 720 in healthy adults. PLoS One. 2008;3:e1952. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0001952.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0001952</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2276862</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18398475</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malkin E, Hu J, Li Z, Chen Z, Bi X, et al. A phase 1 trial of PfCP2.9: an AMA1/MSP1 chimeric recombinant protein vaccine for Plasmodium falciparum malaria. Vaccine. 2008;26:6864&#x2013;6873.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18930094</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ogutu BR, Apollo OJ, McKinney D, Okoth W, Siangla J, et al.  Blood stage malaria vaccine eliciting high antigen-specific antibody concentrations confers no protection to young children in Western Kenya. PLoS ONE. 2009;4:e4708. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0004708.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004708</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2650803</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19262754</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moher D, Fortin P, Jadad AR, Juni P, Klassen T, et al. Completeness of reporting of trials published in languages other than English: implications for conduct and reporting of systematic reviews. Lancet. 1996;347:363&#x2013;366.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">8598702</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roussilhon C, Oeuvray C, Muller-Graf C, Tall A, Rogier C, et al.  Long-term clinical protection from falciparum malaria is strongly associated with IgG3 antibodies to merozoite surface protein 3. PLoS Med. 2007;4:e320. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.0040320.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0040320</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2071934</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18001147</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mabunda S, Aponte JJ, Tiago A, Alonso P. A country-wide malaria survey in Mozambique. II. Malaria attributable proportion of fever and establishment of malaria case definition in children across different epidemiological settings. Malar J. 2009;8:74.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2678146</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19383126</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mwangi TW, Ross A, Snow RW, Marsh K. Case definitions of clinical malaria under different transmission conditions in Kilifi District, Kenya. J Infect Dis. 2005;191:1932&#x2013;1939.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC3545188</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15871128</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smith T, Schellenberg JA, Hayes R. Attributable fraction estimates and case definitions for malaria in endemic areas. Stat Med. 1994;13:2345&#x2013;2358.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">7855468</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bejon P, Warimwe G, Mackintosh CL, Mackinnon MJ, Kinyanjui SM, et al. Analysis of immunity to febrile malaria in children that distinguishes immunity from lack of exposure. Infect Immun. 2009;77:1917&#x2013;1923.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2681775</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19223480</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Egan AF, Burghaus P, Druilhe P, Holder AA, Riley EM. Human antibodies to the 19kDa C-terminal fragment of Plasmodium falciparum merozoite surface protein 1 inhibit parasite growth in vitro. Parasite Immunol. 1999;21:133&#x2013;139.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10205793</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vandenbroucke JP, von Elm E, Altman DG, Gotzsche PC, Mulrow CD, et al. Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE): explanation and elaboration. Ann Intern Med. 2007;147:W163&#x2013;194.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">17938389</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>von Elm E, Altman DG, Egger M, Pocock SJ, Gotzsche PC, et al. The Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement: guidelines for reporting observational studies. Lancet. 2007;370:1453&#x2013;1457.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18064739</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>