<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Manual"><PMID Version="1">25023449</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2015</Year><Month>05</Month><Day>05</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>04</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1469-4409</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>143</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2015</Year><Month>Apr</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>Epidemiology and infection</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Epidemiol Infect</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Using surveillance and monitoring data of different origins in a Salmonella source attribution model: a European Union example with challenges and proposed solutions.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1148</StartPage><EndPage>1165</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1148-65</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1017/S0950268814000429</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Microbial subtyping approaches are commonly used for source attribution of human salmonellosis. Such methods require data on Salmonella in animals and humans, outbreaks, infection abroad and amounts of food available for consumption. A source attribution model was applied to 24 European countries, requiring special data management to produce a standardized dataset. Salmonellosis data on animals and humans were obtained from datasets provided by the European Food Safety Authority. The amount of food available for consumption was calculated based on production and trade data. Limitations included different types of underreporting, non-participation in prevalence studies, and non-availability of trade data. Cases without travel information were assumed to be domestic; non-subtyped human or animal records were re-identified according to proportions observed in reference datasets; missing trade information was estimated based on previous years. The resulting dataset included data on 24 serovars in humans, broilers, laying hens, pigs and turkeys in 24 countries.</AbstractText></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>DE Knegt</LastName><ForeName>L V</ForeName><Initials>LV</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Division of Epidemiology and Microbial Genomics,Technical University of Denmark,Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pires</LastName><ForeName>S M</ForeName><Initials>SM</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Division of Epidemiology and Microbial Genomics,Technical University of Denmark,Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hald</LastName><ForeName>T</ForeName><Initials>T</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>National Food Institute, Division of Epidemiology and Microbial Genomics,Technical University of Denmark,Denmark.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2014</Year><Month>07</Month><Day>15</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Epidemiol Infect</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8703737</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0950-2688</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000818" MajorTopicYN="N">Animals</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D002645" MajorTopicYN="N">Chickens</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D004196" MajorTopicYN="N">Disease Outbreaks</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005060" MajorTopicYN="N" Type="Geographic">Europe</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005062" MajorTopicYN="N">European Union</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="Y">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D005516" MajorTopicYN="N">Food Microbiology</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000706" MajorTopicYN="N">statistics &amp; numerical data</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D058751" MajorTopicYN="N">Livestock</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D011159" MajorTopicYN="N">Population Surveillance</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000379" MajorTopicYN="N">methods</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012475" MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000145" MajorTopicYN="N">classification</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012478" MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella Food Poisoning</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012480" MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella Infections</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="Y">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012481" MajorTopicYN="N">Salmonella Infections, Animal</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000453" MajorTopicYN="N">epidemiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000209" MajorTopicYN="N">etiology</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012703" MajorTopicYN="N">Serotyping</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D013552" MajorTopicYN="N">Swine</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D014422" MajorTopicYN="N">Turkeys</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000382" MajorTopicYN="N">microbiology</QualifierName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">surveillance</Keyword></KeywordList><CoiStatement>The initial version of the EU model was developed with partial funding from contract CT/EFSA/Zoonoses/2010/02 (contract value 45000 Euros) between EFSA and the DTU National Food Institute, in relation to Question no. EFSA-Q-2010-00685.</CoiStatement></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2014</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2014</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>16</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2015</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>6</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pmc-release"><Year>2014</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">25023449</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9507159</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1017/S0950268814000429</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pii">S0950268814000429</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Reference><Citation>Greger M. The human/animal interface: emergence and resurgence of zoonotic infectious diseases. Critical Reviews in Microbiology 2007; 33: 243&#x2013;299.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">18033595</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization. The world health report 2007 (http://www.who.int/whr/2007/en/index.html). Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization. Accessed 7 July 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. The European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2009. EFSA Journal 2011; 9: 2090.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kuchenm&#xfc;ller T, et al. Estimating the global burden of foodborne diseases&#xa0;&#x2013;&#xa0;a collaborative effort. Eurosurveillance 2009; 14: 1&#x2013;4.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19422776</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires SM, et al. Attributing the human disease burden of foodborne infections to specific sources. Foodborne Pathogens and Disease 2009; 6: 417&#x2013;424.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19415971</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. EFSA Panel on biological hazards (BIOHAZ). Scientific opinion on a request from EFSA on overview of methods for source attribution for human illness from food borne microbiological hazards. EFSA Journal 2008; 764: 1&#x2013;43.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC10193638</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">37213830</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hald T, et al. A Bayesian approach to quantify the contribution of animal-food sources to human salmonellosis. Risk Analysis 2004; 24: 255&#x2013;269.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">15028016</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. Report on the analysis of the baseline study on the prevalence of <i>Salmonella</i> in holdings of laying hen flocks of <i>Gallus gallus</i>. EFSA Journal
2007; 97: 1&#x2013;84.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. Report of the task force on zoonoses data collection on the analysis of the baseline survey on the prevalence of <i>Salmonella</i> in slaughter pigs in the EU, 2006&#x2013;2007. Part A: <i>Salmonella</i> prevalence estimates. EFSA Journal
2008; 135: 1&#x2013;111.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. Report of the task force on zoonoses data collection on the analysis of the baseline survey on the prevalence of <i>Salmonella</i> in turkey flocks, in the EU, 2006&#x2013;2007. Part A: <i>Salmonella</i> prevalence estimates. EFSA Journal
2008; 134: 1&#x2013;224.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. Report of the task force on zoonoses data collection on the analysis of the baseline survey on the prevalence of <i>Salmonella</i> in broiler flocks of <i>Gallus gallus</i> in the EU, 2005&#x2013;2006. Part A: <i>Salmonella</i> prevalence estimates. EFSA Journal
2007; 98: 1&#x2013;85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. EFSA Panel of Biological Hazards (BIOHAZ). Scientific Opinion on a request from European Commission on quantitative estimation of the impact of setting a new target for the reduction of <i>Salmonella</i> in breeding hens of <i>Gallus gallus</i>. EFSA Journal
2009; 1036: 1&#x2013;68.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. EFSA Panel of Biological Hazards (BIOHAZ). Scientific Opinion on a quantitative estimation of the public health impact of setting a new target for the reduction of <i>Salmonella</i> in broilers. EFSA Journal
2011; 9: 2106.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. EFSA Panel of Biological Hazards (BIOHAZ). Scientific Opinion on an estimation of the public health impact of setting a new target for the reduction of <i>Salmonella</i> in turkeys. EFSA Journal
2012; 10: 2616.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires SM, Hald T. Assessing the differences in public-health impact of <i>Salmonella</i> subtypes using a Bayesian microbial subtyping approach for source attribution. Foodborne Pathogens and Diseases
2010; 7: 143&#x2013;151.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19877767</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wahlstr&#xf6;m H, et al. 
Source attribution of human <i>Salmonella</i> cases in Sweden. Epidemiology and Infection
2011; 139: 1246&#x2013;1253.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20943003</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pires SM, <i>Attributing human salmonellosis and campylobacteriosis to food, animal and environmental sources</i> (thesis). Copenhagen, University of Copenhagen, 2009, 157 pp.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Knegt LV, <i>A multi-country approach for attributing human salmonellosis to animal reservoirs: global perspectives and application of surveillance data from the European Union</i> (thesis). Kongens Lyngby, Denmark: Technical University of Denmark, 2013, 109 pp.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control. Surveillance of communicable diseases in the European Union: a long-term strategy 2008&#x2013;2013 (http://ecdc.europa.eu/en/aboutus/Key%20Documents/08-13_KD_Surveillance_of_CD.pdf). Solna, Sweden: European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control, 2007. Acessed 2 November 2012.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. Analysis of the baseline survey on the prevalence of <i>Campylobacter</i> in broiler batches and of <i>Campylobacter</i> and <i>Salmonella</i> on broiler carcasses in the EU, 2008&#xa0;&#x2013;&#xa0;Part A: <i>Campylobacter</i> and <i>Salmonella</i> prevalence estimates. EFSA Journal
2010; 8: 1503.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. Analysis of the baseline survey on the prevalence of <i>Salmonella</i> in holdings with breeding pigs in the EU, 2008&#xa0;&#x2013;&#xa0;Part A: <i>Salmonella</i> prevalence estimates. EFSA Journal
2009; 7: 1377.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Statistical Office of the European Union (EUROSTAT). (epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/portal/page/portal/statistics/search_database). Accessed 25 March 2011.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wheeler JG, et al. Study of infectious intestinal disease in England: rates in the community, presenting to general practice, and reported to national surveillance. British Medical Journal 1999; 318: 1046&#x2013;1050.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC27838</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">10205103</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Havelaar AH, et al. Estimating the true incidence of campylobacteriosis and salmonellosis in the European Union, 2013. Epidemiology and Infection 2012; 141: 293&#x2013;302.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC9152072</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">22717051</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Collaborating Center for Reference and Research on <i>Salmonella</i>. Antigenic Formulae of the <i>Salmonella</i> Serovars, 9th edn. Paris, France: Institut Pasteur, 2007.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Global Foodborne Infections Network Country Databank (WHO/GFN CDB). (http://thor.dfvf.dk/gss). Accessed 15 November 2010.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. The community summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in the European Union in 2007. EFSA Journal 2009; 223: 312.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. The community summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in the European Union in 2008. EFSA Journal 2010; 8: 1496.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Association of Poultry Processors and Poultry Trade in the EU Countries. Annual Report 2009. Brussels, Belgium: Association of Poultry Processors and Poultry Trade in the EU Countries.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. Collection and routine analysis of import surveillance data with a view to identification of emerging risks. EFSA Journal 2010; 8: 1531.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>World Health Organization Global Environment Monitoring System Food Consumption Cluster Diets. GEMS/Food regional diets: regional per capita consumption of raw and semi-processed agricultural commodities, prepared by the Global Environment Monitoring System/Food Contamination Monitoring and Assessment Programme (GEMS/Food). Geneva, Switzerland: World Health Organization; 2006.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosef O, et al. 
Serotyping of <i>Campylobacter jejuni, Campylobacter coli</i> and <i>Campylobacter laridis</i> from domestic and wild animals. Applied Environmental Microbiology
1985; 49: 1507&#x2013;1510.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC241755</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">4015088</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Feinsinger P, Spears EE, Poole RW. A simple measure of niche breadth. Ecology 1981; 62: 27&#x2013;32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullner P, et al. Source attribution of food-borne zoonoses in New Zealand: a modified Hald model. Risk Analysis 2009; 29: 970&#x2013;984.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">19486473</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mullner P, et al. 
Molecular epidemiology of <i>Campylobacter jejuni</i> in a geographically isolated country with a uniquely structured poultry industry. Applied Environmental Microbiology
2010; 76: 2145&#x2013;2154.</Citation><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pmc">PMC2849254</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">20154115</ArticleId></ArticleIdList></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. EFSA Panel on biological hazards (BIOHAZ). Scientific Opinion on monitoring and assessment of the public health risk of &#x2018;<i>Salmonella</i> Typhimurium-like&#x2019; strains. EFSA Journal
2010; 8: 1826.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>European Food Safety Authority. The community summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in the European Union in 2006. EFSA Journal 2007; 130: 352.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>David J, Attribution of human cases of salmonellosis to different species of production animals in France: adaptability and robustness of the microbial subtyping source attribution Bayesian model (thesis). Vannes, France: Universit&#xe9; Europ&#xe9;enne de Bretagne, 2009, 217 pp.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>